<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- The Bernmeister's New Testament, Abridged Edition -->
<!-- Copyright © 2024 Bernard M. Woodland -->
<!-- Version 1 -->
<!-- Public domain -->
<!-- The Bernmeister's NT Version 1 -->
<usx version="3.0">
  <!--   *******************   -->
  <!--   Titles and TOC Info   -->
  <!--   *******************   -->
  <book code="1CO" style="id">The Bernmeister's NT</book>
  <para style="h">1 Corinthians</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Epistle of 1 Corinthians</para>
  <para style="toc2">1 Corinthians</para>
  <para style="toc3">1 Cor.</para>
  <para style="mt2">THE EPISTLE OF</para>
  <para style="mt1">1 CORINTHIANS</para>
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  1   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="1CO 1" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 1:1" />From Paul, who has the calling of an apostle (a missionary) of Christ Jesus through the will of God,
        and his comrade Sosthenes—<verse eid="1CO 1:1" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 1:2" />To God’s church which exists in Corinth, those set apart by Christ Jesus from the unbelievers in this
        world, those called to be holy in unison with those everywhere who are calling upon the name of our Lord
        Jesus Christ (i.e., those invoking Jesus’s promises, his authority, and his favorable disposition)—<verse eid="1CO 1:2" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 1:3" />Grace and peace to you from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.<verse eid="1CO 1:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 1:4" />When it comes to you, I’m always thanking my God for the grace He’s given you in Christ Jesus, <verse eid="1CO 1:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 1:5" />because in him you’ve been enriched in all things, in every concept imaginable and in all sorts of knowledge
        and understanding, <verse eid="1CO 1:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 1:6" />just as the testimony of Christ (i.e., the official statement about Christ) has been both made firm and
        has been confirmed in you, <verse eid="1CO 1:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 1:7" />so that you’re not lacking in any Holy Spirit-generated gift, ministry, or manifestation of the Holy
        Spirit, eagerly awaiting the revelation of Christ Jesus our Lord, <verse eid="1CO 1:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 1:8" />who will also establish us until the end of time so that we’re blameless in the day of our Lord Jesus
        Christ. <verse eid="1CO 1:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 1:9" />Faithful is the God through whom we’ve been called into the fellowship of His son Jesus Christ our Lord.<verse eid="1CO 1:9" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 1:10" />I appeal to you, comrades, through the name (i.e., the authority) of our Lord Jesus Christ, pleading
        to you that you would always be on the same page and that there not be divisions among you, but that
        you’d be fitted and mended together with the same mind and with the same knowledge and understanding.<verse eid="1CO 1:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 1:11" />In this regard and concerning you, it’s been made clear to me by Chloe’s family and her servants, my
        dear comrades, that there’s strife going on between you. <verse eid="1CO 1:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 1:12" />I’ll say this: some of you say “I’m Paul’s devotee exclusively” while others say “I’m Apollos’s devotee
        exclusively” or “I’m Peter’s devotee exclusively”, or “I’m Christ’s devotee exclusively.” <verse eid="1CO 1:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 1:13" />Has Christ been divided up into pieces? Paul wasn’t crucified on your behalf, was he? Or, were you baptized
        (i.e., initiated into the Christian faith) on Paul’s sole authority to be a member of Paul’s camp? <verse eid="1CO 1:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 1:14" />Thank God I didn’t baptize any of you except Crispus and Gaius, <verse eid="1CO 1:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 1:15" />lest anyone say that they were baptized on my sole authority to be a member of my camp. <verse eid="1CO 1:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 1:16" />Now I did baptize Stephanas’s family and servants, but as far as the rest of you, I’m not absolutely
        sure if I baptized anyone else. <verse eid="1CO 1:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 1:17" />You see, Christ didn’t send me to go about baptizing in order to build a camp of my own followers but
        to go about evangelizing instead, not in wisdom which comes out of a message, so that the cross of Christ
        wouldn’t be rendered ineffectual.<verse eid="1CO 1:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 1:18" />The message of the cross, you see, is stupidity to those who are lost and dying on the one hand, but
        to those who are being saved (i.e., being rescued from spiritual, moral, and physical calamity), it’s
        the power of God. <verse eid="1CO 1:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 1:19" />For it’s written in the Old Testament:
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 1:19"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 1:19">I’ll destroy the wisdom of the wise,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 1:19">And I’ll annul the understanding of those who understand<verse eid="1CO 1:19"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 1:20" />Where’s the wise man? Where’s the scholar? Where’s this generation’s premier debater? Hasn’t God turned
        this world’s wisdom into stupidity?<verse eid="1CO 1:20" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 1:21" />You see, by the wisdom of God, since the world through its wisdom didn’t come to recognize, discern,
        understand, or know God, God was more than happy through the stupidity of what was preached to save those
        who made the decision to believe. <verse eid="1CO 1:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 1:22" />Forasmuch as Jews chase after stupendous miracles and Westerners chase after wisdom, <verse eid="1CO 1:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 1:23" />we, on the other hand, preach a crucified-Christ; for Jews it’s the root-cause of the failure caused
        by disobedience on the one end of the stick, on the other end of the stick, for Westerners it’s stupidity,<verse eid="1CO 1:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 1:24" />but to them who are “the Called” (i.e., those whom God has summoned to be His people and who have heeded
        the summons), Jews and Westerners alike, Christ is God’s power and God’s wisdom, <verse eid="1CO 1:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 1:25" />since the “stupidity” of God is wiser than the wisdom to be found in mankind, and the “weakness” of God
        is stronger than the strength to be found in mankind.<verse eid="1CO 1:25" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 1:26" />To this point, consider your group “the Called”: if one looks at their backgrounds only, not very many
        of them are wise, not many powerful, not many from high-society families or nobility. <verse eid="1CO 1:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 1:27" />No, God’s chosen the stupid things of the world to put to shame the wise things, and the weak things
        of the world to put to shame the strong, <verse eid="1CO 1:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 1:28" />and God’s chosen the lowly born and those things which are contemptuous—He’s chosen the things that don’t
        exist to abolish what does, <verse eid="1CO 1:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 1:29" />so that any and every human endeavor or accomplishment apart from God can’t be presented proudly before
        Him in the statement, “See—look what I did!” <verse eid="1CO 1:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 1:30" />But what’s come out of Him is that you’re melded with Christ Jesus, who became to us wisdom from God,
        righteousness, and likewise holiness and redemption (i.e., the recovery of what you once had), <verse eid="1CO 1:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 1:31" />so it’d turn out just like it’s written in the Old Testament, “Let the one who brags about his accomplishments
        brag in the Lord.”<verse eid="1CO 1:31" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="1CO 1" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  2   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="1CO 2" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 2:1" />When I went and visited you, comrades, I didn’t go there and use heady, intellectual language and sublime
        speech while telling you about the mystery of God. <verse eid="1CO 2:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 2:2" />You see, I decided that when among you I’d appear as though I knew no other facts whatsoever except things
        about Jesus Christ and the fact that this fellow was crucified. <verse eid="1CO 2:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 2:3" />I appeared to you as one lacking vigor and strength and as downright fearful, and was frequently trembling,<verse eid="1CO 2:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 2:4" />and my message and my preaching weren’t in words that were wise and persuasive but were accompanied by
        a powerful demonstration of the Spirit that’s difficult to describe if you’ve never experienced it, <verse eid="1CO 2:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 2:5" />so that your faith wouldn’t be a faith grounded in human wisdom but would be in the power of God instead.<verse eid="1CO 2:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 2:6" />Now we speak words of wisdom among those who are mature, a wisdom, however, not of this age nor of the
        rulers of this age (i.e., the demon spirits which have controlling influence over this world), rulers
        who are being rendered ineffective and brought to nothing— <verse eid="1CO 2:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 2:7" />instead we speak words of God’s wisdom in a mystery, a wisdom which has been hidden up to this point,
        a wisdom which God knew beforehand in eternity past and intended for our glory, <verse eid="1CO 2:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 2:8" />a wisdom which none of the rulers of this age knew, understood, or recognized, for if they had, they
        wouldn’t have crucified the Lord of Glory. <verse eid="1CO 2:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 2:9" />No, the wisdom isn’t like that, it’s like it’s written instead:
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 2:9"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 2:9">That which eye hasn’t seen and ear hasn’t heard</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 2:9">And hasn’t arisen and come to rest upon any human heart—</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 2:9">That which God prepared for those who love Him<verse eid="1CO 2:9"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 2:10" />God revealed it to us through the Spirit: for the Spirit thoroughly searches and investigates everything,
        even the deep things of God. <verse eid="1CO 2:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 2:11" />For what person knows firsthand the intimate details and intentions of a given person except for that
        person’s spirit that’s in him? In the same way, no one has known, understood, or recognized the intimate
        details and intentions of God except the Spirit of God.<verse eid="1CO 2:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 2:12" />Now we have not received the spirit of the world but rather the Spirit who proceeds out of God, so that
        we would know firsthand what God has given to us as an expression of His grace— <verse eid="1CO 2:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 2:13" />and what was given to us is also that which we speak, not speaking in human teachings consisting of words
        of wisdom but rather in teachings of the Spirit consisting of the fitting together nicely of Holy Spirit-related
        content with other Holy Spirit-related content. <verse eid="1CO 2:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 2:14" />A person who’s dominated by his mind, intellect, or emotions instead of by his spirit won’t receive the
        things of the Spirit of God; in fact, to him such things are stupid, and he cannot know, understand,
        or recognize them because such things are spiritually examined and decided as a result. <verse eid="1CO 2:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 2:15" />But the spiritual person examines and decides all things, but he himself isn’t examined and his life
        decided by anyone.<verse eid="1CO 2:15" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 2:16" />Who has known, understood, or recognized the Lord’s mind?
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 2:16">Who mentors Him?</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 2:16"></para>
    <para style="m" vid="1CO 2:16">We, however, have a mind which is of Christ.<verse eid="1CO 2:16"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="1CO 2" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  3   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="1CO 3" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 3:1" />But I, comrades, wasn’t able to speak to you like I would to people attuned to and dominated by spiritual
        things but rather like I would to people attuned to and dominated by fleshly things (i.e., things that
        have to do with our lives in the natural, even touching our carnal appetites), same as I would to those
        who are babies in Christ. <verse eid="1CO 3:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 3:2" />I fed you milk, not solid food, as you were not yet able to digest solid food, having not been weaned
        off milk—but even now you still can’t handle solid food; <verse eid="1CO 3:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 3:3" />You’re still fleshly, you see: where there’s jealousy and strife still found among you, are you not fleshly,
        and do you not leads lives dictated by the undesirable human tendencies?<verse eid="1CO 3:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 3:4" />For example, when one of you says, “I’m Paul’s devotee exclusively,” and another of you says, “I’m Apollos’s
        devotee exclusively,” are you not being dominated by your undesirable human tendencies? <verse eid="1CO 3:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 3:5" />So who is Apollos? Who is Paul—they’re ministers, and you came to believe in Christ through their ministries,
        and all the steps involved and the ministries that were a part of leading you to Christ happened to each
        person as the Lord granted that it happen. <verse eid="1CO 3:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 3:6" />I planted the seed, Apollos watered it, but it was God who made it grow, <verse eid="1CO 3:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 3:7" />so that neither the one doing the planting nor the one doing the watering is the most important part
        of the process, but God who makes things grow is the most important. <verse eid="1CO 3:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 3:8" />The one who does the planting and the one who does the watering are on the same team, and each will receive
        an individual-specific wage according to his own individual labor.<verse eid="1CO 3:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 3:9" />We’re God’s coworkers, you see, laboring together in God’s field, whereas you’re the building-project
        which God’s constructing, <verse eid="1CO 3:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 3:10" />being constructed according to the grace of God which was given to me as a judicious chief architect
        and principal contractor. Accordingly, I laid the foundation, and another subcontractor came after me
        and built the structure on top of the foundation, but let each subcontractor look over what he built,
        to ensure that it was done correctly. <verse eid="1CO 3:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 3:11" />The fact of the matter is that no one can lay any other foundation other than the one which has been
        laid, which foundation is Jesus Christ. <verse eid="1CO 3:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 3:12" />Now if some subcontractor builds upon the foundation by putting in place gold, silver, gemstones (i.e.,
        the subcontractor did a high-quality job), wood, hay, or straw (i.e., the subcontractor did a low-quality
        job) structures upon that foundation, <verse eid="1CO 3:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 3:13" />the quality of the work that that particular subcontractor did will become apparent to everyone, since
        some cataclysmic event will eventually occur that is enormously stressful to the structure, making its
        true strengths and deficiencies abundantly clear to everyone, since these true strengths and weaknesses
        are revealed by fire (i.e., intense stress), and the fire will determine what kind of job was done by
        putting it through the wringer. <verse eid="1CO 3:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 3:14" />If any of the built-up construction remains, the subcontractor will get paid; <verse eid="1CO 3:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 3:15" />if any of the built-up construction is burned up, he’ll lose money on the project, but he’ll be spared
        of personal ruin, but he’ll lose his entire investment through the ordeal.<verse eid="1CO 3:15" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 3:16" />Don’t you know that you are a temple of God and that the Spirit of God has taken up residence in you?<verse eid="1CO 3:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 3:17" />If someone trashes, ruins, or destroys the temple of God, God will trash that guy. The temple of God—the
        very thing that you are—is holy, you see.<verse eid="1CO 3:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 3:18" />Let no one fool himself utterly in this regard: if any of you considers himself to be wise in this age,
        let him become stupid, so that he would become wise; <verse eid="1CO 3:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 3:19" />for the wisdom of this world is stupidity to God. In fact, it’s written in the Old Testament:
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 3:19"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 3:19">He’s catching the wise in their subtle trickery<verse eid="1CO 3:19"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 3:20" />And another verse says,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 3:20"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 3:20">The Lord understands the arguments of the wise—</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 3:20">He knows that they’re futile<verse eid="1CO 3:20"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 3:21" />So then, let no one be charged up and beam with pride over people that they’re devotees of. The fact
        of the matter is, all of you— <verse eid="1CO 3:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 3:22" />whether we’re referring to Paul, Apollos, or Peter—or whether we’re talking about life, death, the past,
        or the future— <verse eid="1CO 3:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 3:23" />are Christ’s devotees, and Christ is a devotee of God.<verse eid="1CO 3:23" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="1CO 3" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  4   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="1CO 4" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 4:1" />Let a person frame his perception of us this way: that we’re attendants of Christ and stewards of the
        mystery of God. <verse eid="1CO 4:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 4:2" />In regard to stewardship, it’s a minimum requirement that a person who’s a steward be found faithful.<verse eid="1CO 4:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 4:3" />But it’s not a big deal for me to be examined and then judged by you or by any human tribunal for that
        matter, nor do I judge myself in self-examination. <verse eid="1CO 4:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 4:4" />In fact, I’m not self-conscious about anything I might’ve done wrong, but—no—I haven’t been exonerated
        of all wrong-doing in this stewardship of mine, but the Lord is the one who examines and judges me, <verse eid="1CO 4:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 4:5" />so that you won’t judge me before the timeframe set aside for judgment, that is until the Lord happens
        to come, who in the course of judging will also will illuminate the hidden things of darkness and will
        put the plans, strategies, intentions, and collaborations of the hearts out in the open, and at that
        time the praise from God to each person for what he did right will appear.<verse eid="1CO 4:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 4:6" />But because of you, comrades, I made the change and applied these things to Apollos and me, so that through
        our example you would learn the meaning of “Don’t be so high-and-mighty that the stuff that’s written
        in the Bible somehow doesn’t apply to you,” so that your egos don’t become overly-inflated, with one
        person thinking himself to be superior in understanding something to the one who explained that something
        to him in the first place, both opposed to someone who has a different opinion. <verse eid="1CO 4:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 4:7" />Furthermore, who determines what all the different points of view are among you and sorts you into categories
        based on viewpoint?</para>
    <para style="p" vid="1CO 4:7">What do you have that you didn’t go out and get? And if you got the things you decided to get, why do
        you carry on like you never got them? <verse eid="1CO 4:7"/>
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 4:8" />You’ve already gotten plenty enough—you’re already rich—you live like kings when you’re apart from us—it
        sure would be great if you actually became kings, so that we could live like kings together with you.<verse eid="1CO 4:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 4:9" />You see, I’m thinking that God made an exhibit out of us—the apostles, the lowliest of people—putting
        us on display, making us appear to everyone as though we’re men who’re condemned to death, since we became
        a spectacle to the world, to angels, and to all of mankind. <verse eid="1CO 4:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 4:10" />We are idiots on account of Christ, but you are logical and sensible in Christ; we are weak, you are
        strong; we are glorious, you are dishonored. <verse eid="1CO 4:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 4:11" />Up until this very moment in time, we went hungry and thirsty, had no clothes to wear, were beaten, were
        homeless, <verse eid="1CO 4:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 4:12" />and toiled doing hard manual labor. While being abused, we bless; while being persecuted, we endure;<verse eid="1CO 4:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 4:13" />while being slandered, we speak softly. Up until now, we’ve been treated like we’re the scum of the world;
        like we’re everyone’s garbage.<verse eid="1CO 4:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 4:14" />I’m not writing these things to shame you or to put you on a guilt trip, rather I’m writing to you as
        though you’re my children, ones who are dear to me, and I’m admonishing, warning, and instructing you
        as such. <verse eid="1CO 4:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 4:15" />You see, even if you had a million tutors in Christ, you still wouldn’t have many fathers (i.e., those
        who were instrumental in your conversion) in Christ, seeing that I begot you in Christ Jesus through
        the Gospel. <verse eid="1CO 4:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 4:16" />So I’m pleading with you: get to where you imitate me. <verse eid="1CO 4:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 4:17" />Because of this desire on my part, I sent you Timothy, who is my dear child in Christ and who’s faithful
        in the Lord, who’ll remind you to imitate the way I do things in Christ Jesus, just like I teach everyone
        in churches everywhere.<verse eid="1CO 4:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 4:18" />As I’m not heading in your direction to visit you at the moment, some of you have acquired inflated egos.<verse eid="1CO 4:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 4:19" />But if it was the Lord’s will, I’d leave immediately and travel as quickly as possible to visit you,
        and I’ll recognize and discern not the message of those who’ve reached the point where their egos are
        inflated but rather their power; <verse eid="1CO 4:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 4:20" />for the kingdom of God (i.e., God’s interaction with mankind) is not in a message but in power. <verse eid="1CO 4:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 4:21" />Which would you rather have? That I’d take a staff with me to correct you with when I go visit you, or
        that I’d visit you in a love-spirit and with soft-spoken gentleness?<verse eid="1CO 4:21" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="1CO 4" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  5   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="1CO 5" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 5:1" />News is going around that there’s actually fornication (i.e., sexual immorality) among you, the sort
        of fornication that you don’t even find among the heathens, to the effect that someone’s having sex with
        his stepmother. <verse eid="1CO 5:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 5:2" />You’ve become smug over this and what’s the more haven’t mourned (i.e., prayed deep, heart-felt prayers
        of grieving and sorrow) in order that the one who’s committed this atrocity be removed from your midst.<verse eid="1CO 5:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 5:3" />To address this topic, although away physically-speaking but present spiritually-speaking, I have already
        judged the one who’s doing this as if I was present <verse eid="1CO 5:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 5:4" />by the authority vested in me by our Lord Jesus Christ, my spirit having gathered together with you all
        in the power of the our Lord Jesus <verse eid="1CO 5:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 5:5" />to hand a person such as him over to Satan (and to hand him over once and be done with it) for the destruction
        of the flesh, so that the spirit will avoid utter calamity when the Lord “settles all Family business”
        so-to-speak.<verse eid="1CO 5:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 5:6" />You talking a big talk doesn’t make you look good—Don’t you know that a tiny pinch of yeast when placed
        in a batch of dough will spread to the entire batch, causing every last bit of it to ferment? <verse eid="1CO 5:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 5:7" />Scrub every bowl and utensil that came in contact with the old yeast thoroughly, so that you’d be a fresh
        batch of dough the way that you really are: yeast-free dough. Add to this the fact that Christ was slaughtered
        and offered as our Passover lamb sacrifice, <verse eid="1CO 5:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 5:8" />so that we would not partake of the Passover meal with bread contaminated by yeast from the previous
        batch nor contaminated by the yeast of unfathomably-wicked evil, but with the yeast-free bread of sincerity
        and truth instead.<verse eid="1CO 5:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 5:9" />In the previous letter I wrote that you shouldn’t associate with fornicators, <verse eid="1CO 5:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 5:10" />but I didn’t mean not to associate with any fornicator who’s a part of this corrupt society we live in,
        or with the greedy and rapacious or with idolaters; otherwise, if that were the case, you’d have to leave
        this corrupt society and shun it forever. <verse eid="1CO 5:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 5:11" />I wrote to you just now not to associate with someone if that someone who goes by the name “comrade”
        were to be a fornicator, or someone who’s greedy, or an idolater, or someone who cusses or uses abusive
        language, or a drunkard, or someone who’s rapacious—don’t share a meal with them either. <verse eid="1CO 5:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 5:12" />Furthermore, why should I care about judging those on the outside? Aren’t you the ones who judge those
        on the inside? <verse eid="1CO 5:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 5:13" />God judges those on the outside. The Old Testament says, “Get rid of your evil person.”<verse eid="1CO 5:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="1CO 5" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  6   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="1CO 6" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 6:1" />Does any one of you have the audacity to have a civil dispute which you’re having with another comrade
        arbitrated by those who are unrighteous, and not by the saints (i.e., your fellow-believers)? <verse eid="1CO 6:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 6:2" />Or are you simply unaware of the fact that the saints will judge the world? If the world is to be judged
        by you, you’re capable of forming arbitration panels for settling petty disputes. <verse eid="1CO 6:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 6:3" />Don’t you know that we’ll judge angels?—We’re that much more capable then of judging day-to-day affairs.<verse eid="1CO 6:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 6:4" />So when you do happen to form a panel for arbitrating day-to-day affairs, you put those in the church
        who are despised and lowly-esteemed on the panel. <verse eid="1CO 6:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 6:5" />Shame on you—Isn’t there even one of you who has wisdom when it comes to this sort of thing, someone
        who can straighten out a situation his comrade is in? <verse eid="1CO 6:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 6:6" />Instead, a comrade takes another comrade to court, and the court consists of unbelievers. <verse eid="1CO 6:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 6:7" />You’re already undergoing a complete moral breakdown indeed by taking each other to court: why don’t
        you just be wronged? Why don’t you just be cheated? <verse eid="1CO 6:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 6:8" />Instead of enduring being wronged, you’re wronging and cheating others, and you’re doing this to fellow
        comrades. <verse eid="1CO 6:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 6:9" />Don’t you know that those who wrong others won’t inherit the kingdom of God (i.e., won’t have a relationship
        with God; have Him involved with their lives)? Don’t be fooled: neither fornicators nor idolaters nor
        adulterers nor catamites nor homosexuals <verse eid="1CO 6:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 6:10" />nor thieves nor the greedy—there’ll be no drunkards, none of those who cuss and use abusive language,
        none of those who are rapacious—these people won’t inherit the kingdom of God. <verse eid="1CO 6:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 6:11" />And that’s what some of you were—but no more: you were washed, you were sanctified (i.e., separated,
        set apart, and declared holy), you were justified (i.e. examined by a judge and cleared of any charges)
        by the authority of our Lord Jesus Christ and in the Spirit of our God.<verse eid="1CO 6:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 6:12" />To me, everything is permissible but not everything is beneficial. To me, everything’s permissible, but
        I’ll not be put under the control of anything. <verse eid="1CO 6:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 6:13" />Food is meant for the stomach, and the stomach is meant for food, but God will do away with food and
        stomach both. The body’s not meant for fornication but for the Lord, and the Lord is meant for the body.<verse eid="1CO 6:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 6:14" />God both raised the Lord from the dead and will raise us from the dead through His power.<verse eid="1CO 6:14" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 6:15" />Don’t you know that our bodies are a piece of Christ’s body? Shall I take these things—shall I take a
        piece of Christ’s body and make it a piece which is a part of a prostitute?—Don’t even think about it.<verse eid="1CO 6:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 6:16" />Don’t you know that he who unites with a prostitute or a woman who’s a fornicator becomes a single body
        with her through the bond of sex? “For,” He says, “the two will be made into one flesh.” <verse eid="1CO 6:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 6:17" />The one who unites with the Lord becomes a single spirit with him. <verse eid="1CO 6:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 6:18" />Run as fast as you can away from fornication (i.e., sexual acts which are immoral): all sins that a person
        happens to commit are done outside the body, but the fornicator commits a sin which is done to (or even
        into) his own body. <verse eid="1CO 6:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 6:19" />Don’t you know that our collective-body is a temple which is a dwelling-place for the Holy Spirit to
        dwell in, thereby living among us, the Spirit which you have from God, and that you don’t own yourselves?<verse eid="1CO 6:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 6:20" />You’ve been bought at a high price; therefore, glorify God with your collective-body.<verse eid="1CO 6:20" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="1CO 6" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  7   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="1CO 7" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 7:1" />To elaborate on what I wrote to you in the previous letter, it’s good for a man not to go about touching
        a woman for the purpose of instigating sexual arousal. <verse eid="1CO 7:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 7:2" />But because of the variety and volume of the fornications (i.e., sexual acts which are immoral) taking
        place around you, let each man have his own woman to be his wife, and likewise let each woman have her
        own man to be her husband. <verse eid="1CO 7:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 7:3" />Let the husband fulfill his obligation of having sex with his wife; likewise, let the wife do the same
        with her husband. <verse eid="1CO 7:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 7:4" />The wife doesn’t get to dictate what goes on with her own body, but the husband does; likewise, the husband
        doesn’t get to dictate what goes on with his own body, but the wife does. <verse eid="1CO 7:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 7:5" />Don’t deprive each other of sex, unless it’s for an agreed-upon time in order to devote yourselves to
        prayer, and get back at it (i.e., back to having sex) so that Satan not tempt you because of your lack
        of self-control. <verse eid="1CO 7:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 7:6" />In saying this, I’m offering you a concession and not giving you a command. <verse eid="1CO 7:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 7:7" />I want all men to be like me, but each has his own gift from God instead, one person this way, the other
        person that way.<verse eid="1CO 7:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 7:8" />I’m telling those who aren’t married or who are widows that it would be good if they would stay the way
        I am. <verse eid="1CO 7:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 7:9" />But if they can’t control themselves, have them get married; it’s better to marry than to burn with sexual
        desire, you see. <verse eid="1CO 7:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 7:10" />To those who are already married, I’m having the wives take a command (not me giving the command but
        the Lord) for them not to leave their husbands. <verse eid="1CO 7:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 7:11" />Now if she happens to leave him anyways, have her remain single or be reconciled with her husband. And
        I’m having the husbands take a command to not divorce their wives. <verse eid="1CO 7:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 7:12" />I’m telling the rest of you (me talking, not the Lord) this: if some man has a wife who’s an unbeliever,
        and she consents to live with him, don’t have him divorce her; <verse eid="1CO 7:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 7:13" />if some wife has a husband who’s an unbeliever, and this fellow consents to live with her, don’t have
        her divorce him. <verse eid="1CO 7:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 7:14" />You see, the unbelieving-husband is set apart to God as holy and specially protected by Him by the believing
        wife, and the unbelieving-wife is set apart as holy and specially protected by the comrade who is her
        husband; if that were not the case, their children would be unholy, spiritually contaminated, and not
        set apart to God, but now that there’s a believing spouse in the picture, they’re holy and specially
        protected. <verse eid="1CO 7:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 7:15" />Now if an unbelieving husband or wife leaves his believing spouse, let him or her part ways: the comrade,
        whether man or woman, isn’t under any obligation in such case. God has called us to live in peace (i.e.,
        live free of the conflict, duress, or affliction that many unbelieving spouse brings) whatever our situation
        might be; <verse eid="1CO 7:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 7:16" />in this regard, how do you know, wives, if you’ll succeed in rescuing your unbelieving husbands from
        spiritual and moral calamity? Or how do you know, husbands, if you’ll succeed in rescuing your unbelieving
        wives from spiritual and moral calamity?<verse eid="1CO 7:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 7:17" />Moving on to topics relevant to every person…Have each person lead his life in the way that the Lord
        deems appropriate for the particular situation he was in when he became a believer. I’m giving the same
        command to all the churches which I started. <verse eid="1CO 7:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 7:18" />Had you already been circumcised when called (i.e., had you made a vow to obey the Law of Moses prior
        to becoming a believer )?—Don’t obliterate the effects of circumcision (i.e., don’t obliterate the effects
        of this vow). Was anyone called when they were uncircumcised (i.e., did anyone become a believer but
        at no time ever made a vow to obey the Law of Moses)?—Don’t get circumcised (i.e., don’t make such a
        vow). <verse eid="1CO 7:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 7:19" />The circumcision in the case of the believer who was circumcised already is irrelevant and not an issue
        whatsoever, and the uncircumcision in the case of the believer who wasn’t circumcised already is irrelevant
        and not an issue whatsoever, but the keeping of God’s commandments is the real issue instead. <verse eid="1CO 7:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 7:20" />Whatever situation or set of circumstances a person was in when he was called (i.e., when he became a
        believer), he should stay in that situation or set of circumstances. <verse eid="1CO 7:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 7:21" />Were you called when you were a slave?—Don’t worry about it; instead, if you get the chance to gain your
        freedom, by all means take advantage of the opportunity. <verse eid="1CO 7:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 7:22" />Furthermore, the person who was called by the Lord (i.e., became a believer) while a slave is the Lord’s
        freeman; in the same way, he who was called while free is Christ’s slave. <verse eid="1CO 7:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 7:23" />You’ve been bought at a high price: don’t become other peoples’ slaves. <verse eid="1CO 7:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 7:24" />Whatever situation and circumstances each person was in when he was called, comrades, have him remain
        in this situation when he gets with God.<verse eid="1CO 7:24" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 7:25" />About the young ladies who have never been married: I don’t have a command from the Lord, but I’ll give
        an opinion as one who’s been shown mercy by the Lord enabling me to be reliable. <verse eid="1CO 7:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 7:26" />These are my thoughts about living through the difficulties of the present time, namely that it’s good
        for a person to live the following way: <verse eid="1CO 7:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 7:27" />Are you bound by commitment to a wife?—Don’t try to separate from her. Separated from a wife?—Don’t go
        looking for another woman. <verse eid="1CO 7:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 7:28" />But if you do happen to get married, you haven’t sinned. And if the typical young lady in the church
        happens to get married, she hasn’t sinned. Folks such as these will face hard times in their natural
        lives; I’m trying to spare you this grief.<verse eid="1CO 7:28" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 7:29" />Let me tell you what, comrades, a compressed window of time is all that remains of our lives, so that
        those who have wives should live as though they don’t have wives, <verse eid="1CO 7:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 7:30" />and those who weep as though they don’t weep, and those who rejoice as though they don’t rejoice, and
        those who deal in business as though they’ve halted trading, <verse eid="1CO 7:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 7:31" />and those using the world as though they don’t use it; when you get right down to it, the world we live
        in in its present form is passing away. <verse eid="1CO 7:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CO 7:32" />I don’t want you to be consumed by or worry about the trivial day-to-day affairs of life. He who’s not
        married is consumed by and worries about the things of the Lord, how he might be pleasing to him, <verse eid="1CO 7:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CO 7:33" />but he who’s married is consumed by and worries about things of the world we live in and the people we
        live around, how he might use these things to be pleasing to the wife he has, <verse eid="1CO 7:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CO 7:34" />and he reaches the point where he’s constantly consumed by these and worries about them continually.
        Both the woman who’s single and the young lady who’s never been married are consumed by and worry about
        the things of the Lord, so they would be holy both in body and in spirit. But she who’s married is consumed
        by and worries about the things of the world, how she’s going to please her husband. <verse eid="1CO 7:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CO 7:35" />I’m telling you this for your own benefit—not so I can put you on a leash, but so it would result in
        a seemly, undistracted devotion to the Lord.<verse eid="1CO 7:35" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CO 7:36" />Now if someone’s behaving inappropriately towards the young lady he’s in a relationship with, and he
        thinks she might be “overly-ripe” in such a way that he’s obliged to make something happen (i.e., she’s
        pregnant, he thinks it might be too hard to hide anymore, and he’ll have to do something about it), let
        him do what he wants to do—he’s not committing a sin in doing so—let them get married. <verse eid="1CO 7:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CO 7:37" />But he who has taken a firm stand in his heart, not having to act out of necessity but has the upper-hand
        over his individual sexual desire, and has decided in his own heart to stay a virgin rather than sleep
        with his girlfriend or fiancée, does well, <verse eid="1CO 7:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CO 7:38" />with the result that both he who waits until marriage handles his virginity well, but he who remains
        single will do better, as he’ll be spared the difficulties I wrote about here.<verse eid="1CO 7:38" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CO 7:39" />The wife is morally bound to her husband as long as her husband lives, but if her husband were to pass
        away, she’s free to marry whom she wants, only she must marry in the Lord (i.e., marry in such a way
        that’s pleasing to the Lord; marry another believer). <verse eid="1CO 7:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CO 7:40" />But in my opinion she’d be happier if she were to stay the way she is (i.e., stay unmarried after becoming
        a widow), and I think I have the agreement of the Spirit of God too.<verse eid="1CO 7:40" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="1CO 7" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  8   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="1CO 8" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 8:1" />Now about the issue of eating meat sacrificed to idols, every one of us has our own understanding of
        how this ought to be handled. The understanding a person has on a given issue makes him rather full of
        himself, but the love shown in the handling of said issue edifies. <verse eid="1CO 8:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 8:2" />If any given person thinks he’s reached the point where he’s acquired some level of understanding, he
        has not yet understood the matter as it must be understood. <verse eid="1CO 8:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 8:3" />If someone loves God, this individual has been known and understood by Him.<verse eid="1CO 8:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 8:4" />So now, about the consumption of food offered to idols: we know for a fact that the idols in the world
        don’t amount to a hill of beans, and no person or thing is God except for One being only. <verse eid="1CO 8:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 8:5" />Now, granted, there are those who claim there are gods, whether they be in the sky, in the atmosphere,
        among the stars, in a spiritual world beyond that, or on the earth, so that there’re many gods and many
        lords, <verse eid="1CO 8:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 8:6" />but from our point of view there’s one God the Father, out of Whom are all things, and we are returned
        to Him and to the Lord Jesus Christ, through whom are all things, and we are through him.<verse eid="1CO 8:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 8:7" />That aside, we are not on the same level in every aspect of understanding. Up until now some people have
        been in the habit of eating food sacrificed to idols, and since their consciences are weak (i.e., their
        consciences prod them with pangs of guilt over matters they have a deficient understanding of, in this
        case in regard to food sacrificed to idols), they violate their consciences. <verse eid="1CO 8:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 8:8" />Eating or not eating this food doesn’t get us anywhere with God: we’re neither worse off if we were to
        not eat it nor are we better off if we were to eat it.<verse eid="1CO 8:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 8:9" />See to it that the right you have to eat such food doesn’t somehow in and of itself become a stumbling
        block (i.e., an influence for causing sin) for those who have a weak conscience. <verse eid="1CO 8:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 8:10" />You see, if someone with a weak conscience were to watch you, a person who has the correct understanding
        on this issue, sitting at the dinner table with food sacrificed to idols lying on the plate in front
        of you, wouldn’t his conscience, because it’s in a state of weakness, being built up in regard to the
        eating of foods sacrificed to idols (i.e., because of an incorrect understanding in regard to this issue
        of food sacrificed to idols, his conscience has been conditioned to respond with guilt when it ought
        not)? <verse eid="1CO 8:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 8:11" />You see, he who’s weak—the comrade whom Christ died for—is being destroyed by your correct understanding.<verse eid="1CO 8:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 8:12" />In the way that you sin against the comrades and beat on their weak consciences, you sin against Christ.<verse eid="1CO 8:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 8:13" />That’s why if food causes my comrade to stumble, there’s no way whatsoever that I’ll ever eat sacrificial
        meat again, so that I won’t be a stumbling block to my brother.<verse eid="1CO 8:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="1CO 8" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  9   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="1CO 9" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 9:1" />Am I not a freeman? Am I not an apostle (i.e., have I not been sent by God to pioneer the spread of Christianity)?
        Have I not seen our Lord Jesus with my own eyes? Are you not my accomplishment in the Lord? <verse eid="1CO 9:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 9:2" />If I’m not an apostle sent to root others in Christianity, at least I’m an apostle sent to root you;
        in fact, you’re my certificate of authenticity of my having been sent by the Lord. <verse eid="1CO 9:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 9:3" />My rebuttal to those examining me for the purpose of judging and condemning me is the same.<verse eid="1CO 9:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 9:4" />Do we not have the right to be hosted in such a way that we eat and drink for free? <verse eid="1CO 9:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 9:5" />Do we not have the right to have a fellow-comrade-wife accompany us as she follows our lead on our journeys
        and have her hosted as well, as all the other apostles of the Lord and Peter do?— <verse eid="1CO 9:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 9:6" />Or is it just Barnabas and I who don’t have the right to not have to work to support ourselves? <verse eid="1CO 9:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 9:7" />When did any soldier ever serve in the army and have to pay for his own rations? Who plants a vineyard
        and doesn’t feed off what it produces? Or who cares for a ewe and doesn’t feed off the sheep’s milk?<verse eid="1CO 9:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 9:8" />I’m not talking from a human perspective, or talking about concepts that the Law does not also talk about.<verse eid="1CO 9:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 9:9" />The fact of the matter is, in the Law of Moses it’s written, “Don’t put a muzzle on an oxen while it’s
        threshing wheat.” You don’t think God cares about the welfare of the oxen when it’s threshing, do you?<verse eid="1CO 9:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 9:10" />Or is it that the Law’s addressing this topic for our benefit? Furthermore, it’s written in the Law for
        our benefit that the sower ought to sow and the thresher to thresh with the hope of getting a percentage
        of the harvest. <verse eid="1CO 9:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 9:11" />If we sowed into you the Holy Spirit-related things which are the backbone of your spiritual lives, is
        it a big deal if we reap the physical things we need to live by from you? <verse eid="1CO 9:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 9:12" />If others have the right of taking a percentage from you, don’t we all the more so?
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="1CO 9:12">No, we’re not asserting this right; instead we put up with all kinds of things so that nothing would
        hinder the Gospel, the good-news message of Christ. <verse eid="1CO 9:12"/>
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 9:13" />Don’t you know that they who work the sacred duties in the temple feed on the sacrifices offered at the
        temple; that they who attend to the altar divide the spoils of the altar among themselves? <verse eid="1CO 9:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 9:14" />In the same way the Lord planned for and commanded those who proclaim the Gospel to make their living
        from the Gospel. <verse eid="1CO 9:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 9:15" />I have not used any of these mandates. I didn’t write about these things to make them happen to me; in
        fact, I’d rather die than have someone invalidate the proud assertions which I openly pride myself in.<verse eid="1CO 9:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 9:16" />Should I proclaim the Gospel, it’s not my place to make proud assertions, you see: by necessity they’re
        imposed on me. I’ll be in deep trouble, you see, should I not proclaim the Gospel. <verse eid="1CO 9:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 9:17" />If I put this into practice voluntarily, you see, I’ll earn my pay. If I do this voluntarily, I’ve reached
        the point where I can be entrusted with a managerial position. <verse eid="1CO 9:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 9:18" />So what’s my pay rate? I’m not getting paid a penny so that I can present the Gospel free of charge with
        a view towards me not exercising my right to receive financial support as one who proclaims the Gospel.<verse eid="1CO 9:18" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 9:19" />Being a freeman, freed from all things, in all things I made myself a slave, so that I’d win over the
        many. <verse eid="1CO 9:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 9:20" />I became a Jew to the Jews so that I would win over Jews: to those who live under the Law of Moses, I
        let myself be under the Law (though as far as my own personal life is concerned, I’m not under the Law),
        so that I would win over those under the Law. <verse eid="1CO 9:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 9:21" />I became lawless (i.e., not living under the Law of Moses or under any God-based set of rules for that
        matter) to the lawless (though not living lawlessly apart from God, but being law-bound as a part of
        Christ) in order to win over the lawless. <verse eid="1CO 9:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 9:22" />I became powerless to control my own circumstances to those who are powerless over their circumstances
        so that I would win over the powerless. I became all things to all people so I’d save (i.e., rescue from
        calamity, spiritual, moral, and otherwise) some. <verse eid="1CO 9:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 9:23" />But everything I do, I do for the sake of the proclamation of the Gospel so I’d become a workman who
        specializes in it.<verse eid="1CO 9:23" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 9:24" />Don’t you know that those who compete in track &amp; field run races but only one of them gets the first-place
        trophy? Play to win—that’s the way you compete. <verse eid="1CO 9:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 9:25" />Everyone who competes in athletics trains, and those folks do so in order to get a trophy which can and
        undoubtedly will lose its prestige over time, but we train to win a trophy which will always remain prestigious;<verse eid="1CO 9:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 9:26" />hence, as far as I’m concerned, I don’t train for the race without setting any specific personal goals
        to meet. I train to box in such a way that in the ring I’ll land punches and not wind up with fistfuls
        of air. <verse eid="1CO 9:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 9:27" />Uh-uh—I apply strict, punishing disciple to my body (i.e., to my carnal nature in particular), treating
        it roughly and wearing it down; I subdue it and make it my slave, lest I, having proclaimed the Gospel
        to others, should somehow or someway fail to live up to the standard it sets.<verse eid="1CO 9:27" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="1CO 9" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 10   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="1CO 10" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 10:1" />I don’t want you to fail to understand this, comrades, the fact that our forefathers—all of them—were
        always under the cloud which they followed after leaving Egypt, and all of them passed through the Red
        Sea, <verse eid="1CO 10:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 10:2" />and every one of them was initiated into and joined up with Moses in totality by virtue of the cloud
        and the sea, <verse eid="1CO 10:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 10:3" />and every one of them was fed from the same spiritual food, <verse eid="1CO 10:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 10:4" />and every one of them drank from the same spiritual source: they drank out of the Spiritual Trailing
        Rock (and the rock was Christ).<verse eid="1CO 10:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 10:5" />But God was not pleased with many of them; their dead bodies were strewn about the wilderness as we see.<verse eid="1CO 10:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 10:6" />Now the lives these people led is an example, a pattern, a parallel of our own lives, so that we not
        have strong yearnings bordering on sensual passions for evil, just as some of them had. <verse eid="1CO 10:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 10:7" />Neither become idolaters, just as some of them did, as it’s written in the Old Testament,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 10:7"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 10:7">The folk-people sat down to eat and drink</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 10:7">And when they were done got up to play<verse eid="1CO 10:7"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 10:8" />Nor commit fornication (i.e., behave in a sexually immoral way), just as some of them committed fornication,
        and as a result twenty-three thousand dropped dead in one day. <verse eid="1CO 10:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 10:9" />Nor test Christ (i.e., use a circumstance as a test to see if Christ will pass from your point of view),
        just as some of them tested him and as a result were destroyed by serpents. <verse eid="1CO 10:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 10:10" />Nor grumble, murmur, or complain just as some of them grumbled and as a result were destroyed by the
        Destroyer.<verse eid="1CO 10:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 10:11" />Now those things that happened to them turned out to be an example, a pattern, a parallel of our own
        lives, and it was recorded in the Bible to make us aware that this applies to us, whom the ends of the
        ages have arrived at and are staring us in the face, <verse eid="1CO 10:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 10:12" />so that the one who thinks he stands (i.e., the one who thinks he’s immune to sin) should see to it that
        he doesn’t fall (i.e., fall to sin). <verse eid="1CO 10:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 10:13" />No temptation has been taken hold of by the person being tempted if it were not for the fact that humans
        are susceptible to it. But God is faithful, Who won’t permit us to be tempted beyond what we’re capable
        of. No, He’ll make an exit strategy consisting of the ability to bear the temptation while under the
        weight of it.<verse eid="1CO 10:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 10:14" />Therefore, my dear comrades, get as far away from the idolatry you’re surrounded with as fast as you
        can. <verse eid="1CO 10:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 10:15" />I’m talking to you as though I’m speaking to sensible people. You decide the sensibility of what I’m
        saying. <verse eid="1CO 10:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 10:16" />The cup of blessing (i.e., the cup of communion wine) which we pronounce a blessing with, is it not an
        intimate association with the blood of Christ? The loaf of bread which we break during communion, is
        it not an intimate association with the body of Christ? <verse eid="1CO 10:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 10:17" />Because the loaf is a single entity, we the many are one body; we all partake of pieces which come out
        of the one loaf, you see. <verse eid="1CO 10:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 10:18" />Take a look at Israel, physically speaking: don’t they who feed themselves with the meat of the sacrificial
        animals have an intimate association with the altar and share in the work which goes on there? <verse eid="1CO 10:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 10:19" />So what exactly am I trying to tell you? That idolatry is something which needs to be taken seriously?
        Or that food sacrificed to an idol is something which needs to be taken seriously? <verse eid="1CO 10:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 10:20" />Uh-uh—What they sacrifice they sacrifice to demons and not to God; I don’t want an intimate association
        between you and demons to form. <verse eid="1CO 10:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 10:21" />You can’t be drinking from the Lord’s cup (i.e., following the Lord’s plan for your lives) and from demons’
        cup; you can’t be partaking of the Lord’s table (i.e., receiving the Lord’s provision for your nourishment,
        and for all of your needs for that matter) and of the demons’ table. <verse eid="1CO 10:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 10:22" />Or do you intend to provoke the Lord to wrath? We aren’t more powerful than he, are we?<verse eid="1CO 10:22" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 10:23" />Everything is permissible, but not everything is beneficial. Everything is permissible, but not everything
        edifies. <verse eid="1CO 10:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 10:24" />Let no one pursue his own interests exclusively but the next person’s as well. <verse eid="1CO 10:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 10:25" />Eat any sort of meat which is sold at the marketplace without any qualms; the Bible says, <verse eid="1CO 10:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 10:26" />“The abundant, splendid variety of things that the earth contains was put there by the Lord’s doing,”
        you see. <verse eid="1CO 10:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 10:27" />If someone who’s an unbeliever invites you over to his house and you want to go, eat everything that’s
        laid out on the table or put on your plate without having any qualms about eating any of it. <verse eid="1CO 10:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 10:28" />If someone were to tell you, “This is meat which was sacrificed in a pagan ritual,” don’t eat it on account
        of that person who pointed it out and because of the misgivings surrounding it—<verse eid="1CO 10:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 10:29" />I don’t mean because of your own misgivings but because of the other person’s. Now just why is what I’m
        free to do or not do decided by another person’s misgivings? <verse eid="1CO 10:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 10:30" />If I partake in the eating of certain foods by means of grace (i.e., using the license I’ve been given),
        why are terrible things said about me in connection with He Whom I offer up thanksgiving to? <verse eid="1CO 10:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 10:31" />So whether you eat or don’t eat something or whether you drink or don’t drink something or whether you
        do or don’t do anything else, everything you end up doing, do to God’s glory. <verse eid="1CO 10:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CO 10:32" />Get to where you’re not inadvertently causing a Jew or Westerner or anyone in God’s church to get offended
        or to fall to temptation, <verse eid="1CO 10:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CO 10:33" />just as I too try to fit in with everyone by not offending them or causing alarm among them, not pursuing
        my own interests but rather the interests of the majority, so that they might be saved.<verse eid="1CO 10:33" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="1CO 10" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 11   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="1CO 11" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 11:1" />Imitate me, just as I too imitate Christ.<verse eid="1CO 11:1" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 11:2" />I applaud you since you keep in the front of your mind my entire collection of teaching and you firmly
        adhere to the instruction as I presented and entrusted it to you. <verse eid="1CO 11:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 11:3" />I want you to know for certain that Christ is the head of every man; the man which God created is the
        head of woman; God is the head of Christ. <verse eid="1CO 11:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 11:4" />Any man who has something down over his head while praying or prophesying disgraces his head. <verse eid="1CO 11:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 11:5" />Any woman who’s praying or prophesying with her head unveiled disgraces her head: it’s the same thing
        as having her hair cut off, in fact; <verse eid="1CO 11:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 11:6" />for if a woman isn’t veiled, have her cut her hair off too. If it’s disgraceful for a woman to have her
        hair cut off or her head shaved, have her put a veil on.<verse eid="1CO 11:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 11:7" />In regard to this topic, a man certainly doesn’t have to put a veil over his head, as his very existence
        is as God’s image and glory (i.e., His crowning achievement in creation; His pride and joy; what He treasures
        the most; His complement), but the woman is man’s glory (i.e., man’s pride and joy; what he treasures
        above all else; the reflection of the finest in him; his complement). <verse eid="1CO 11:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 11:8" />You see, man isn’t derived from woman, but the other way around: woman is derived from man. <verse eid="1CO 11:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 11:9" />Also, taking a closer look at this, man wasn’t created because of the woman, but rather woman was created
        because of the man. <verse eid="1CO 11:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 11:10" />Because of this the woman ought to have control over her head because of the angels. <verse eid="1CO 11:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 11:11" />Nevertheless in the Lord neither does woman exist apart from man nor does man exist apart from woman;<verse eid="1CO 11:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 11:12" />for just as the woman was created out of the man, in the same way as that the man too is birthed through
        the woman, and all the things we see in creation come out of God.<verse eid="1CO 11:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 11:13" />Decide among yourselves: is it fitting for a woman to pray to God while unveiled? <verse eid="1CO 11:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 11:14" />Doesn’t even nature itself teach you that if a man were to wear his hair long, it would surely be dishonorable
        for him to do so? <verse eid="1CO 11:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 11:15" />But if a woman were to wear her hair long, it would be glory to her (i.e., it would magnify her, highlighting
        and complementing her; it would be a point of pride for her)? Because the long hair has been given to
        her as a substitute for an article of clothing she would wrap around herself. <verse eid="1CO 11:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 11:16" />But in case someone’s thinking about starting an argument over this, we don’t have such a custom, nor
        do any one of the other of God’s churches.<verse eid="1CO 11:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 11:17" />While preparing the command I’m about to give you, I didn’t have anything good to say about you, since
        your getting together as a group is not for the better but for the worse. <verse eid="1CO 11:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 11:18" />More to the point, at the head of the list is the reports that I hear that there are divisions which
        constantly exist among you when you get together as a church, and I believe that at least some of it
        is true. <verse eid="1CO 11:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 11:19" />Furthermore, there has got to be factions among you, where each faction consists of the people who share
        the same opinion about something, so that it’s become evident that those who decide what does or doesn’t
        fly have come to the forefront among you.<verse eid="1CO 11:19" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 11:20" />So your coming together at the same gatherings isn’t to partake of the Lord’s meal, is it? <verse eid="1CO 11:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 11:21" />At the meal served at the gathering, each person in fact gets a head-start on his eating with the idea
        of getting more than the next guy, and as a result one fellow goes hungry on the one hand, while one
        fellow gets drunk on the other. <verse eid="1CO 11:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 11:22" />Furthermore, don’t you have pubs and restaurants for eating and drinking at? Or do you have contempt
        for the church of God and humiliate those who don’t have enough to get by on? What was I supposed to
        tell you? Was I supposed to applaud you for doing this? I don’t have any applause in this particular
        case.<verse eid="1CO 11:22" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 11:23" />Delving into this topic more deeply, I received from the Lord and took to heart that which I also presented
        and entrusted to you, that the night the Lord Jesus was betrayed and arrested, he took a loaf, <verse eid="1CO 11:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 11:24" />prayed, broke it, and said,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 11:24"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 11:24"><char style="wj">This is my body which is</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 11:24"><char style="wj">Lifted up, broken, and distributed for your sakes.</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 11:24"><char style="wj">Do this for the purpose of refreshing your memories of me.</char><verse eid="1CO 11:24"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 11:25" />In the same fashion he also took the cup while dining, saying,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 11:25"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 11:25"><char style="wj">This cup is the new covenant ratified by means of my blood.</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 11:25"><char style="wj">As often as you choose to or happen to drink from the cup,</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 11:25"><char style="wj">Do this for the purpose of refreshing your memories of me.</char><verse eid="1CO 11:25"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 11:26" />For as often as you happen to or choose to eat this bread and drink this cup, you proclaim the death
        of the Lord until whatever time he ends up coming, <verse eid="1CO 11:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 11:27" />so that he who perchance eats the bread or drinks the cup of the Lord unworthily will be culpable of
        the body and the blood of the Lord. <verse eid="1CO 11:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 11:28" />Have a person examine and test himself and prove to himself and approve of himself, and have him eat
        from the loaf and drink from the cup in this manner; <verse eid="1CO 11:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 11:29" />you see, he who eats and drinks the communion meal unworthily eats and drinks judgment (i.e., a guilty
        verdict) upon himself by not evaluating the body. <verse eid="1CO 11:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 11:30" />For this reason many of you are weak and frail (i.e., are run down with a long-running illness or have
        maladies), and a good number of you are in the process of dying. <verse eid="1CO 11:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 11:31" />If we were to examine and judge ourselves (i.e., examine ourselves and acknowledge our own guilt), we
        would not be judged and pronounced guilty. <verse eid="1CO 11:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CO 11:32" />Being judged by the Lord, you are disciplined, trained, and corrected, so that you won’t be condemned
        together with the world (i.e., with the unbelievers and the entire ungodly system they created). <verse eid="1CO 11:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CO 11:33" />Rember this, my comrades, so that when gathering together for the purpose of eating, wait for one another
        rather than getting a head-start on eating. <verse eid="1CO 11:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CO 11:34" />If someone’s famished, have him eat in a pub or restaurant, so that he won’t join in on one of your meal
        gatherings in such a way that it results in him being judged and pronounced guilty.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="1CO 11:34">Now as far as the other issues I mean to address, I’ll settle these whenever I happen to come visit.<verse eid="1CO 11:34"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="1CO 11" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 12   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="1CO 12" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 12:1" />Concerning spirituals (things which are of nature related to the Holy Spirit: i.e., spiritual gifts,
        ministries, and extraordinary manifestations of the Holy Spirit), comrades, I don’t want you to fail
        to understand this. <verse eid="1CO 12:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 12:2" />You know for a fact that when you were pagans in close contact with the mute and dumb idols, as long
        as you kept on being led by the evil spirits those idols attracted, you were being led astray. <verse eid="1CO 12:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 12:3" />This is why I’m making you understand that no one while speaking by means of the Spirit of God says “Jesus
        is accursed,” and no one when speaking by the influence of a spirit can say “Jesus is Lord” except if
        the influence is by the Holy Spirit.<verse eid="1CO 12:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 12:4" />Now there’s a variety of gifts, gifts which are freely given by God as an act of grace and not as something
        which have been earned by the recipient, but the same Spirit. <verse eid="1CO 12:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 12:5" />And there are a variety of ministries, but the same Spirit still. <verse eid="1CO 12:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 12:6" />And there are a variety of effects produced by the Holy Spirit, but the same God Who works every little
        piece of everything. <verse eid="1CO 12:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 12:7" />To each is given the manifestation of the Spirit for the common good. <verse eid="1CO 12:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 12:8" />In this regard, through the Spirit is given to one person the word of wisdom, but on the other hand to
        another person the word of knowledge according to the same Spirit, <verse eid="1CO 12:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 12:9" />to another special faith by the same Spirit, but to another gifts of healings by the same Spirit, <verse eid="1CO 12:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 12:10" />but to another the working of miracles, but to another prophecy, but to another the discerning of spirits,
        but to another a different kind of tongue, to another the interpretation of tongues. <verse eid="1CO 12:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 12:11" />The one-in-the-same Spirit works all of these gifts, ministries, and effects, divvying them up and parceling
        them out to each individual just the way He wants.<verse eid="1CO 12:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 12:12" />In fact, just as the body is a single unit and has many parts, and all the parts, even though there’s
        many of them, comprise one body, it’s the same way with Christ. <verse eid="1CO 12:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 12:13" />You see, every one of us was inducted into one body by one Spirit, whether a given person was Jewish,
        was a Westerner, whether a slave or freeman—all of us have been made to drink of the water of life from
        one Spirit; <verse eid="1CO 12:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 12:14" />for the body does not consist of one part only but of many parts. <verse eid="1CO 12:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 12:15" />If the foot were to say, “I’m not a hand—I’m not one of the parts the body has,” then because of this
        claim it’s not a constituent body part? <verse eid="1CO 12:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 12:16" />And if the ear were to say, “I’m not an eye, I’m not part of the body,” because of saying this, it’s
        not part of the body? <verse eid="1CO 12:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 12:17" />If the entire body was just one giant eye, how would you hear? If the entire body was just one giant
        ear, how could you smell anything?<verse eid="1CO 12:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 12:18" />So as it turns out God put every one of the parts into position just the way He wanted. <verse eid="1CO 12:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 12:19" />If every little piece was one type of part only, where would that leave the body? <verse eid="1CO 12:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 12:20" />It turns out that while there’re many parts indeed, there’s but one body. <verse eid="1CO 12:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 12:21" />The eye can’t get away with telling the hand “I don’t need you”; furthermore, the head can’t tell the
        feet “I don’t need you” either. <verse eid="1CO 12:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 12:22" />No—the parts of the body which seem to be weaker are more necessary than they appear to be. <verse eid="1CO 12:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 12:23" />We assign a greater value to the parts of the body we deem to be of little value, and we put a greater
        amount of clothing over our private parts to ensure that they’re well-hidden, <verse eid="1CO 12:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 12:24" />but the valuable parts have no need of that. No—God composed—He blended together and mixed—the body by
        having given more value to those parts lacking it <verse eid="1CO 12:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 12:25" />so there wouldn’t be division in the body, but that the members would care for each other treating each
        other the same way. <verse eid="1CO 12:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 12:26" />If a single member happens to suffer, all the members suffer along with it. If a single member is glorified,
        all the members are glorified along with it.<verse eid="1CO 12:26" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 12:27" />Now you all are Christ’s body, and you as the individual members populate the various body parts. <verse eid="1CO 12:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 12:28" />God has indeed placed in the church first apostles (i.e., missionaries sent out to pioneer new Christian
        works), second prophets, third teachers, those who perform miracles, gifts of healings, those who help
        in any of a multitude of ways, administrations (i.e., guidance, governorship: literally the one who steers
        the ship), various tongues. <verse eid="1CO 12:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 12:29" />Not everyone’s an apostle, are they? Not everyone’s a prophet, are they? Not everyone’s a teacher, are
        they? Not everyone performs miracles, do they? <verse eid="1CO 12:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 12:30" />Not everyone has one of the various gifts of healings, do they? Not everyone speaks in tongues, do they?
        Not everyone interprets messages in tongues, do they? <verse eid="1CO 12:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 12:31" />But maintain a burning desire for the greater gifts.
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="1CO 12:31">Yet I’ll show you a road to take which is superior to this…<verse eid="1CO 12:31"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="1CO 12" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 13   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="1CO 13" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 13:1" />If I were to speak in tongues of men and of angels but not have love, I will have become a blaring brass
        instrument or clanging cymbal. <verse eid="1CO 13:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 13:2" />If I were to have a prophecy and that prophecy would give me the answers to life’s questions so I would
        know for certain all the mysteries and all the knowledge and understanding, or if I were to have all
        the faith so as to move mountains from place to place, but not have love, I am nothing. <verse eid="1CO 13:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 13:3" />And if I were to sell everything I own and tender my body to be burned, but not have love, it is helping
        me nothing.<verse eid="1CO 13:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 13:4" />The love of which I speak is patient, the love is kind, isn’t jealous and doesn’t cause rivalry, doesn’t
        vaunt itself and act as a show-off, isn’t full of itself, <verse eid="1CO 13:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 13:5" />doesn’t act unseemly or indecently, doesn’t seek its self-interest, doesn’t gaslight others, doesn’t
        keep a mental scorecard of the bad things done to it, <verse eid="1CO 13:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 13:6" />doesn’t rejoice at the wrongdoing of others but joins in the rejoicing in the truth; <verse eid="1CO 13:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 13:7" />it endures all things, believes all things, hopes all things, endures all things.<verse eid="1CO 13:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 13:8" />The love of which we speak never breaks down. Should there be prophecies, they’ll be done away with;
        should there be tongues, they’ll cease; should there be knowledge and understanding, it’ll be done away
        with. <verse eid="1CO 13:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 13:9" />The fact of the matter is that we know and understand from the perspective of a part of the whole and
        we prophecy from the perspective of a part, <verse eid="1CO 13:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 13:10" />but when the Complete comes, the Partial will be done away with. <verse eid="1CO 13:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 13:11" />When I was a child, I was talking like a child, was thinking like a child, was reasoning like a child—when
        I became a man, I did away with the things of childhood. <verse eid="1CO 13:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 13:12" />Furthermore, at the moment we’re seeing life as though we’re looking at the vague reflection cast by
        a mirror, but some time in the future we’ll look at life as though we’re looking at it face-to-face;
        at the moment my knowing and understanding comes out of a single part of the whole, but some time in
        the future I’ll know and understand life exactly just as I have been known and understood by God exactly.<verse eid="1CO 13:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 13:13" />At the present time faith, hope, and love remain—these three—but the greatest of them is love.<verse eid="1CO 13:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="1CO 13" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 14   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="1CO 14" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 14:1" />Pursue love and have a burning desire for the spirituals (i.e., spiritual gifts and manifestations of
        the Holy Spirit), but more so that you would prophesy than speak in tongues. <verse eid="1CO 14:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 14:2" />You see, the one who speaks in tongues isn’t talking to people when he’s speaking in tongues but is talking
        to God instead. In fact no one hears him speak intelligibly: he speaks mysteries by his spirit. <verse eid="1CO 14:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 14:3" />Converseley, the one who prophesies speaks edification; exhortation, encouragement, comfort, advice;
        and consolation to people. <verse eid="1CO 14:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 14:4" />The one who speaks in tongues edifies himself (i.e., builds himself up); the one who prophesies edifies
        the church. <verse eid="1CO 14:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 14:5" />I want all of you to speak in tongues and speak in tongues, but more so that you would prophesy and prophesy.
        The one who prophesies is more important than the one who speaks in tongues, unless he were to interpret
        what was spoken in tongues, so that the church would receive edification.<verse eid="1CO 14:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 14:6" />So now, comrades, if I were to go up to you and proceed to speak in tongues, how would it benefit you,
        except if I were to convey a revelation, an understanding, a prophecy, or a teaching? <verse eid="1CO 14:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 14:7" />Nevertheless the inanimate objects which are designed to produce specific, coherent sound patterns, whether
        we’re talking about a flute or a harp—if one of them were to not put out distinct musical notes, how
        will the flute-playing or harp-playing be comprehensible? <verse eid="1CO 14:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 14:8" />Furthermore, if a bugle were to play an indistinguishable tune, who would get into position for battle?<verse eid="1CO 14:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 14:9" />Similarly, if you were to not form intelligible words in whatever language you speak in, how would what’s
        spoken be comprehensible? The fact of the matter is that you would just be wasting your breath. <verse eid="1CO 14:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 14:10" />Who knows just how many different languages there are worldwide, and none of them consists of a set of
        incomprehensible sounds. <verse eid="1CO 14:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 14:11" />So if I were to not have the voice-control to utter words correctly in a given language, from the perspective
        of the person I’m speaking to, I’ll appear to whomever I’m speaking to as though I’m a person from another
        country who can’t speak the native language, and he’ll appear the same way to me. <verse eid="1CO 14:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 14:12" />Likewise, you too, since you are zealous of spirituals (i.e., manifestations of the Holy Spirit), seek
        that which furthers the edification of the church.<verse eid="1CO 14:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 14:13" />In light of this, let the one speaking in tongues pray that he would interpret what he’s speaking. <verse eid="1CO 14:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 14:14" />You see, if I were to pray in tongues, my spirit would be praying but my mind wouldn’t be involved in
        the production of the words. <verse eid="1CO 14:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 14:15" />So what’s the conclusion? I will pray in the Spirit, but I will pray also with the mind. I will sing
        a song of praise to the Lord in the Spirit, but I will also sing a song with the mind. <verse eid="1CO 14:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 14:16" />Otherwise, if you were to give a praise, blessing, or consecration with the spirit, a person who isn’t
        versed in the things of the Spirit and doesn’t speak in tongues—how will he say “amen” (i.e., speak a
        verbal affirmation) upon hearing Your Blessing, since he doesn’t know what you’re saying? <verse eid="1CO 14:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 14:17" />For you certainly give a blessing well, but the other person who’s not versed in the things of the Spirit
        doesn’t get anything out of it. <verse eid="1CO 14:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 14:18" />I give God thanks that I speak in tongues more than you all, <verse eid="1CO 14:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 14:19" />but putting that to the side, when I’m in a church I want to speak five words or so using my mind so
        that I would pass on instruction to others, rather than a million words in an unknown language.<verse eid="1CO 14:19" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 14:20" />Comrades, don’t become children in your thought processes, but instead, act like toddlers with the evil
        you’re inundated with and become adults in your thought processes. <verse eid="1CO 14:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 14:21" />It’s written in the Old Testament:
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 14:21"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 14:21">“In different tongues</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 14:21">And by the lips of different people</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 14:21">I will speak to this folk,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 14:21">And they won’t even hear and obey Me</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 14:21">As I speak in this way,” says the Lord<verse eid="1CO 14:21"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 14:22" />This is the case so much so that the tongues referred to by this Old Testament passage are intended to
        be a sign (i.e., a miracle God performed, done in such a way to demonstrate beyond any doubt that He
        did it) not to those who believe but rather to those who refuse to believe. <verse eid="1CO 14:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 14:23" />So if the entire church were to gather together in one place and everyone were to speak in tongues and
        a person who isn’t versed in the things of the Spirit or speak in tongues or an unbeliever were to enter,
        they’d come to the conclusion that you all are insane, wouldn’t they? <verse eid="1CO 14:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 14:24" />But if everyone were to prophecy and some unbeliever or someone who’s not versed in the Spirit were to
        enter, everything inside of him will be exposed by everyone, he’ll be examined by everyone, <verse eid="1CO 14:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 14:25" />the secrets of his heart will get to where they’re out in the open for everyone to see, so that he’ll
        worship God as he falls on his face, telling everyone that God really is among you.<verse eid="1CO 14:25" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 14:26" />What’s the bottom line, comrades? When you get together as a group, each has a hymn, each has a teaching,
        each has a revelation, each has a message in tongues, each has an interpretation of a message in tongues.
        Let everything that happens serve the purpose of edification— <verse eid="1CO 14:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 14:27" />Should someone speak in tongues, let there be two or at the most three messages given at a time one after
        the other and let one person interpret each message. <verse eid="1CO 14:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 14:28" />Now if there’s no interpreter, have him remain silent in church, but let him speak in tongues to himself
        and to God.<verse eid="1CO 14:28" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 14:29" />Let a handful of prophets speak, and let the others go through what they prophesy and judge it piece
        by piece. <verse eid="1CO 14:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 14:30" />Now if something were to be revealed to another person seated nearby or in the congregation, have the
        first one silence himself. <verse eid="1CO 14:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 14:31" />The fact is all of you can prophecy one after another, so that everyone would learn and be exhorted,
        comforted, counseled, and advised; <verse eid="1CO 14:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CO 14:32" />the spirits of prophets are subordinate to and take directions from prophets. <verse eid="1CO 14:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CO 14:33" />You see, God is not a product of confusion but of peace.
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="1CO 14:33">As in all the congregations of those who believe in Christ, <verse eid="1CO 14:33"/>
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CO 14:34" />have the women in the churches keep silent. The fact of the matter is, I don’t allow them to speak aloud
        addressing the entire congregation, but have them submit instead, just as the Old Testament concurs.<verse eid="1CO 14:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CO 14:35" />If they want to learn something in particular, let them ask their husbands at home; it’s disgraceful
        for a woman to speak aloud in a disrupting way in church you see— <verse eid="1CO 14:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CO 14:36" />Or did the word of God issue forth from you? Or are you the only ones it came down and met?<verse eid="1CO 14:36" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CO 14:37" />If someone is considered to be a prophet or spiritual (i.e., the Holy Spirit manifests spiritual gifts
        through him), let him come to recognize and understand that what I’m writing to you is a commandment
        from the Lord. <verse eid="1CO 14:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CO 14:38" />But if someone will not understand, let him remain without understanding. <verse eid="1CO 14:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CO 14:39" />So then, my comrades, seek to prophesy and prophesy and to speak and speak in tongues, not preventing
        speaking in tongues— <verse eid="1CO 14:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CO 14:40" />But let everything be done properly and orderly.<verse eid="1CO 14:40" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="1CO 14" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 15   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="1CO 15" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 15:1" />I’m making you understand, comrades, the Gospel (i.e., the good-news message) which was evangelized to
        you, which in addition you received (i.e., took hold of in your hearts and applied to your own selves),
        and in which you stand (i.e., in this you are established, you remain stable and steadfast, and in this
        you withstand the pressures of life), <verse eid="1CO 15:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 15:2" />and through which you are being saved (i.e., time after time being rescued from life’s calamities) by
        some concept evangelized to you if you keep a tight grip on what you received, unless of course you weren’t
        serious when you made the decision to believe (i.e., you frivolously, heedlessly, inconsiderately, without
        purpose, without just cause, without careful thought, without due consideration, or haphazardly made
        the decision).<verse eid="1CO 15:2" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 15:3" />You see, I gave the highest priority to putting into you what I too received, namely that Christ died
        on behalf of us sinners according to the Scriptures, <verse eid="1CO 15:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 15:4" />that he was buried, that he rose on the Third Day, <verse eid="1CO 15:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 15:5" />and that he was seen by Peter, and then after that by the twelve disciples. <verse eid="1CO 15:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 15:6" />After that he was seen by over five-hundred people at the same time, the majority of whom have stayed
        alive until now, but some of them have passed away. <verse eid="1CO 15:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 15:7" />After that, he was seen by James and then by all of the apostles. <verse eid="1CO 15:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 15:8" />Last of all he was seen by me too, the bastard-stepchild sort of.<verse eid="1CO 15:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 15:9" />You see, I am the most insignificant of the apostles, one who is not worthy enough to be called an apostle
        because I persecuted God’s church. <verse eid="1CO 15:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 15:10" />By the grace of God I am what I am, but His grace wasn’t wasted on me; instead I worked harder than all
        of them, not me personally but rather the grace of God in conjunction with me. <verse eid="1CO 15:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 15:11" />So whether I’m the one doing the preaching or those other apostles are the ones doing it, we preach this
        same message in the same fashion, and you believed this same message in the same fashion.<verse eid="1CO 15:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 15:12" />Now if the belief that Christ was raised from the dead is being preached, how is it that certain individuals
        among you claim that there is no resurrection from the dead (i.e., once a person dies, his total existence
        ceases; there is no life after death, nor can a person return from the dead since the moment he dies
        he ceases to exist)? <verse eid="1CO 15:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 15:13" />If there’s no resurrection from the dead, not even Christ has been raised from the dead. <verse eid="1CO 15:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 15:14" />If Christ hasn’t been raised, then our preaching of Christ is a waste of time and your faith is a waste
        of time— <verse eid="1CO 15:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 15:15" />And it’ll be obvious to everyone that we lie under oath, since we swore by God under oath that He raised
        Christ—whom He didn’t raise—from the dead, since the dead supposedly aren’t raised. <verse eid="1CO 15:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 15:16" />You see, if the dead aren’t raised, not even Christ has been raised. <verse eid="1CO 15:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 15:17" />But if Christ hasn’t been raised, your faith is pointless; you are still trapped in your sins— <verse eid="1CO 15:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 15:18" />and those who’ve passed away in Christ have perished too. <verse eid="1CO 15:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 15:19" />If we who in this life have hoped in Christ have been stranded, we are the most pathetic people of all.<verse eid="1CO 15:19" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 15:20" />But it turns out that Christ has been raised from the dead, a premier of those who’ve passed away. <verse eid="1CO 15:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 15:21" />You see, since death came through a single, specific person, resurrection from the dead (i.e., hope of
        existing after death; life after death; blissful existence in the afterlife) also came through a single,
        specific person. <verse eid="1CO 15:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 15:22" />To this point, just as everyone died (i.e., died spiritually: underwent a stagnation of waste, joylessness,
        futility, and destruction; eventually died physically) by means of Adam, likewise everyone in Christ
        shall be made alive by means of Christ too. <verse eid="1CO 15:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 15:23" />But the resurrection will occur by each person’s ranking: Christ the premier first, then after him those
        who are affiliated with Christ will be resurrected at his coming, <verse eid="1CO 15:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 15:24" />then comes the End, when the kingdom of God the Father will be transferred into his hands, entrusted
        to him for him to do as he wills, when He’ll abolish every ruler, every authority, and every power; <verse eid="1CO 15:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 15:25" />you see, it’s absolutely necessary that he reign and reign until such a time that all of his enemies
        be put under his feet (i.e., all his enemies be subjected to him: totally subdued and under his absolute
        control). <verse eid="1CO 15:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 15:26" />Death will be the last enemy to be destroyed; <verse eid="1CO 15:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 15:27" />you see, it’s written, “He put all things under his feet.” When the circumstances arise in which He happens
        to say “all things have been subjected,” it goes without saying that the Father’s not included in the
        “all things.” <verse eid="1CO 15:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 15:28" />But when those circumstances arise when He subjects all things to him, then in addition the son himself
        will be subjected to the One Who subjected all things to him, so that God would become every little piece
        of everything.<verse eid="1CO 15:28" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 15:29" />But if all this is not the case, what are they going to do, they who are getting themselves baptized
        as a symbol of their resurrection from the dead? If the dead are definitely not resurrected, why are
        they being baptized as a symbol of them not being dead? <verse eid="1CO 15:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 15:30" />Why do we take risks with our lives every moment? <verse eid="1CO 15:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 15:31" />Day after day I die by the lofty oath sworn to look after you, comrades, which I keep in Christ Jesus
        our Lord. <verse eid="1CO 15:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CO 15:32" />That I had my back against the wall and was fighting for my life in Ephesus, what’s the point of doing
        it all if the dead aren’t resurrected. Wouldn’t we be better off doing what Isaiah said?—</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:32"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:32">Let us eat and drink and live it up,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:32">For tomorrow we shall die<verse eid="1CO 15:32"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CO 15:33" />Don’t be fooled into believing that; realize this instead:
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:33"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:33">The wrong crowd corrupts good conduct<verse eid="1CO 15:33"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CO 15:34" />Snap out of it and don’t continue in sin. In fact, some of you don’t have a knowing, recognition, or
        understanding of God. Shame on you.<verse eid="1CO 15:34" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CO 15:35" />Moving on though, someone’s bound to say, “How will the dead be resurrected (i.e., how’s it possible
        for a dead person to obtain a new body)?” What kind of body will they get in the afterlife? <verse eid="1CO 15:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CO 15:36" />How brainless you are! What someone sows doesn’t spring to life unless it happens to die, <verse eid="1CO 15:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CO 15:37" />and what one sows isn’t the body (i.e., the same biological form) of what it will become. No—you sow
        a bare seed…perhaps it’s wheat…perhaps it’s some other grain… <verse eid="1CO 15:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CO 15:38" />But God gives it a body (i.e., a plant form) the way He wanted and gives a unique, peculiar body to each
        type of seed sown. <verse eid="1CO 15:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CO 15:39" />Not all flesh (i.e., cell and tissue composition) is the same flesh (i.e., consists of the same kind
        of tissues, skeleton, muscle, skin, etc.). No—there’s one type of flesh which corresponds to humans,
        another type of flesh which corresponds to farm animals, another type of flesh to birds, another type
        of flesh to fish. <verse eid="1CO 15:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CO 15:40" />There are bodies (i.e., unique physical entities) in outer-space and bodies on Earth, but no, they’re
        not the same: there’s one type of glory (i.e., wonder, splendor, awe, something spectacular) for the
        entities in space vs. another type of glory for the entities on Earth; <verse eid="1CO 15:40" />
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="1CO 15:41" />the uniqueness of glory that the sun has is a different glory than the type that the moon has, and there’s
        a different, unique type for the stars too: in fact one star differs in its glory from that of another
        star.<verse eid="1CO 15:41" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="42" style="v" sid="1CO 15:42" />The resurrection from the dead works the same way. The body which is sown is a mortal, decaying body
        tainted with moral corruption; it’s resurrected an immortal, non-decayable body untainted by moral corruption.<verse eid="1CO 15:42" />
      <verse number="43" style="v" sid="1CO 15:43" />It’s sown in dishonor, it’s resurrected in glory; sown in weakness, raised in power; <verse eid="1CO 15:43" />
      <verse number="44" style="v" sid="1CO 15:44" />sown a soul-body (i.e., a body having all the quintessential human elements: one that has a thirst for
        the things of this life, that thinks and feels as humans do, has human frailties), raised a spiritual-body.
        If it is a soul-body, it is also a spiritual-body: <verse eid="1CO 15:44" />
      <verse number="45" style="v" sid="1CO 15:45" />this is also the way it’s written in the Old Testament,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:45"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:45">The first man Adam became a living-soul</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:45"></para>
    <para style="m" vid="1CO 15:45">…The Last Adam became a sprung-to-life-spirit. <verse eid="1CO 15:45"/>
      <verse number="46" style="v" sid="1CO 15:46" />No, the first Adam wasn’t the spiritual-body prototype-man rather the soul-body prototype-man, then came
        the spiritual-body prototype-man. <verse eid="1CO 15:46" />
      <verse number="47" style="v" sid="1CO 15:47" />The first man came out of the earth’s dirt, the second man came out of the spiritual world. <verse eid="1CO 15:47" />
      <verse number="48" style="v" sid="1CO 15:48" />As the dirt is, so too are the dirt-creations; as the spiritual world is, so too are the spiritual-creations.<verse eid="1CO 15:48" />
      <verse number="49" style="v" sid="1CO 15:49" />And just as we bore the image of the dirt, let us bear the image of the spiritual as well.<verse eid="1CO 15:49" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="50" style="v" sid="1CO 15:50" />I’ll say this, comrades, that flesh and blood (i.e., the best that human ability can muster) cannot inherit
        the kingdom of God (i.e., cannot put you in a place where you have a relationship with God; where God
        works in and through your life); neither does decayable mortality tainted with moral corruption inherit
        non-decayable immortality untainted by moral corruption.<verse eid="1CO 15:50" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="51" style="v" sid="1CO 15:51" />Hey—I’ll tell you a mystery: we all shall not sleep (i.e., stay dead forever), but we all shall be changed<verse eid="1CO 15:51" />
      <verse number="52" style="v" sid="1CO 15:52" />in a split-second, in the time it takes to blink an eye, at the last bugle call: the bugle shall sound
        off, and the dead will be raised and become non-decayable immortals untainted by moral corruption. Yes,
        we ourselves shall be changed. <verse eid="1CO 15:52" />
      <verse number="53" style="v" sid="1CO 15:53" />You see, this decayable mortality must put on non-decayable immortality, and this mortal nature must
        put on an immortal nature. <verse eid="1CO 15:53" />
      <verse number="54" style="v" sid="1CO 15:54" />When this decayable mortality shall have put on non-decayable immortality, and this mortal nature shall
        have put on an immortal nature, then the verses will come to pass which say,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:54"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:54">Death is engulfed by victory.<verse eid="1CO 15:54"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="55" style="v" sid="1CO 15:55" />Death, where is your victory?
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:55">Death, where is your sting?<verse eid="1CO 15:55"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="56" style="v" sid="1CO 15:56" />The sting of death is sin, and the power of sin is the Law (i.e., the Law of Moses; the set of commandments
        given by God)— <verse eid="1CO 15:56" />
      <verse number="57" style="v" sid="1CO 15:57" />But thank-you God, Who gives us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.<verse eid="1CO 15:57" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="58" style="v" sid="1CO 15:58" />So then, my dear comrades, get to where you’re unshakeable, un-moveable, and un-perturbable, abounding
        and proliferating in the Lord’s work at all times, knowing for certain that your work in the Lord is
        not for nothing, is not going to waste.<verse eid="1CO 15:58" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="1CO 15" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 16   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="1CO 16" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 16:1" />Concerning the matter of taking up a collection for the poor and sending it to God’s people in Jerusalem,
        do the same thing that I commanded the churches in Galatia to do: <verse eid="1CO 16:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 16:2" />Let each of you in private stash away a bit of your money every Sunday—whatever you can afford—so that
        when I come, there won’t be any collection-taking going on then. <verse eid="1CO 16:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 16:3" />When I make it over to your place, whomever you happen to decide upon to write letters of recommendation
        for, I’ll dispatch as couriers to take your gift to Jerusalem. <verse eid="1CO 16:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 16:4" />If there happens to be an issue of respect, they’ll come with me when I depart.<verse eid="1CO 16:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 16:5" />I’ll come your way when I pass through Macedonia; I’ll be passing through Macedonia, you see. <verse eid="1CO 16:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 16:6" />Perhaps I’ll stay with you a while or even spend the winter, so that you’ll send me on my way refreshed
        and prepared for the journey wherever I happen to go; <verse eid="1CO 16:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 16:7" />you see, at the moment I don’t want to just stop by for a short visit while passing through the area;
        you see, I hope to stay a while with you, if the Lord permits. <verse eid="1CO 16:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 16:8" />I’ll stay in Ephesus until Pentecost (i.e., until late May to early June). <verse eid="1CO 16:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 16:9" />In fact, a great door (i.e., a tremendous opportunity) has been opened for me and it looks promising,
        but I’ll have to face many adversaries.<verse eid="1CO 16:9" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 16:10" />If Timothy happens to show up, see to it that he doesn’t get to where he’s intimidated by you; he’s doing
        the Lord’s work like I’m doing, you see, <verse eid="1CO 16:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 16:11" />so don’t let anyone treat him disrespectfully or despise him. Send him forth to his next destination
        in peace (i.e., take care of him, treat him well, and send him out prepared for the journey), so that
        he manages to come to me, for I expect him with the group of comrades who’ll be coming.<verse eid="1CO 16:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 16:12" />Concerning Comrade Apollos…I’ve encouraged him an awful lot to pay you a visit, doing so by travelling
        with the comrades who’ll be coming, and it wasn’t his desire altogether to go at this time, but he’ll
        go in good time.<verse eid="1CO 16:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 16:13" />Stay focused, take a firm stand in the faith, man up, seize control and hold on tightly. <verse eid="1CO 16:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 16:14" />Let everything you do manifest itself in love.<verse eid="1CO 16:14" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 16:15" />I appeal to you, comrades…you know first-hand Stephanas’s household, since they’re the crème de la crème
        of the converts of Achaia and have been put in positions of deacons for God’s people, the saints…<verse eid="1CO 16:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 16:16" />I appeal to you that you too would submit to such fine individuals as these and to all the fellow-workers
        and laborers. <verse eid="1CO 16:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 16:17" />I’m so glad that Stephanas, Fortunatus, and Achaicus showed up, that these fellows filled in the pieces
        that you’re missing: <verse eid="1CO 16:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 16:18" />they gave rest to my spirit and to yours, so recognize the character and contribution of men such as
        these.<verse eid="1CO 16:18" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 16:19" />The churches in the Roman province of Asia send their greetings to you. Aquila and Priscilla send many
        greetings to you in the Lord and are joined in their greetings with the group of Christians who meet
        in their house. <verse eid="1CO 16:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 16:20" />All the comrades greet you. Give each other a hearty handshake and an affectionate hug—holy ones—for
        me.<verse eid="1CO 16:20" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 16:21" />The greeting written here is in my own handwriting, that of Paul’s. <verse eid="1CO 16:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 16:22" />If anyone doesn’t like the Lord a lot, let him be accursed. Maranatha (Do come Lord).<verse eid="1CO 16:22" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 16:23" />The grace of the Lord Jesus be with you all. <verse eid="1CO 16:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 16:24" />May my love be with all of you in Christ Jesus.<verse eid="1CO 16:24" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="1CO 16" />
</usx>
