<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- The Bernmeister's New Testament, Abridged Edition -->
<!-- Copyright © 2024 Bernard M. Woodland -->
<!-- Version 2 -->
<!-- Public domain -->
<!-- The Bernmeister's NT Version 2 -->
<usx version="3.0">
  <!--   *******************   -->
  <!--   Titles and TOC Info   -->
  <!--   *******************   -->
  <book code="ACT" style="id">The Bernmeister's NT</book>
  <para style="h">Acts</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Book of Acts</para>
  <para style="toc2">Acts</para>
  <para style="toc3">Acts</para>
  <para style="mt2">THE BOOK OF</para>
  <para style="mt1">ACTS</para>
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  1   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="ACT 1" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 1:1" />Indeed now—the previous composition which I drafted about everything, oh Theophilus, about what Jesus
        proceeded to do and do and teach and teach <verse eid="ACT 1:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 1:2" />up until the day he was taken up into heaven, having left orders with the apostles through the Holy Spirit—apostles
        whom he had personally hand-picked. <verse eid="ACT 1:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 1:3" />After his suffering, he also appeared to them alive using many demonstrations and proofs, making himself
        visible to them over the course of forty days and discussing matters related to God’s kingdom. <verse eid="ACT 1:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 1:4" />While they were assembled, he commanded them not to leave Jerusalem for a while, but instead to wait
        for the Father’s promise (quoting Jesus),</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 1:4"><char style="wj">“…Which you’ve heard about from me. </char><verse eid="ACT 1:4"/>
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 1:5" /><char style="wj">While—yes—John baptized </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">people by immersing
        them </char></char><char style="wj">in water, but you, though, will be baptized in the Holy Spirit not
        many days from now.”</char><verse eid="ACT 1:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 1:6" />Indeed now—when they were gathered together, they kept asking him over and over, “Lord, is this the moment
        in time you’re going to reinstate Israel as its own sovereign nation?”<verse eid="ACT 1:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 1:7" />He told them, <char style="wj">“It’s not been granted for you to know the exact dates or the windows
        of time</char><char style="wj"> which the Father has established using His own authority. </char><verse eid="ACT 1:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 1:8" /><char style="wj">But never mind that—you will receive </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">miracle-working
        </char></char><char style="wj">power when the Holy Spirit has gone to you and come upon you, and you
        will attest to my truthfulness</char><char style="wj"> in Jerusalem, in all of Judea and Samaria, and
        elsewhere—even as far as the furthest reaches of the planet.”</char><verse eid="ACT 1:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 1:9" />After he said these things, while they were still looking at him he was taken up: a cloud took him away
        out of their sight. <verse eid="ACT 1:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 1:10" />As they were staring up into the sky while he was travelling upwards, two men dressed in white appeared
        out of nowhere and stood next to them, <verse eid="ACT 1:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 1:11" />and they said, “Gentlemen, fellow Galileans, why are you just standing there looking up into the sky?
        This Jesus who was taken away from you up into the sky will come in the same manner which you’ve observed
        him travelling into the sky.”<verse eid="ACT 1:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 1:12" />They then returned to Jerusalem from what’s known as the Mount of Olives, which is near Jerusalem, about
        a half-mile/1 km down the road. <verse eid="ACT 1:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 1:13" />When they entered the city, they went to the top floor of where they were staying, they being Peter,
        John, James, Andrew, Philip, Thomas, Bartholomew, Matthew, James son of Alphaeus, Simon the Zealot, and
        Judas son of James. <verse eid="ACT 1:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 1:14" />All of these fellows were in one accord and single-mindedly sticking to it—not getting side-tracked—in
        prayer, accompanied by women and by Mary the mother of Jesus and his brothers.<verse eid="ACT 1:14" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 1:15" />During the span of time they were up there, Peter stood up in the midst of the comrades (and there was
        a group consisting of 120 grown men, the figure not including the women, teens, and children) and said,<verse eid="ACT 1:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 1:16" />”Gentlemen, fellow comrades, the verses in the Bible had to be fulfilled which the Holy Spirit spoke
        beforehand through David’s mouth about Judas, who became ringleader to those who apprehended Jesus, <verse eid="ACT 1:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 1:17" />that he was considered to be one of us and that he wound up being the unfortunate one who performed this
        duty.”<verse eid="ACT 1:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 1:18" />To recap, that guy used some or all of the payment he received for his wrong-doing and acquired a plot
        of property with it, and got himself in a head-first direction and killed himself in such a way that
        his torso ruptured and all of his intestines spilled out. <verse eid="ACT 1:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 1:19" />This became known to all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, resulting in that plot of land being called Akeldama
        in their language, which is translated “Plot of Blood,” <verse eid="ACT 1:19" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 1:20" />Returning to what Peter said, ”Seeing that the Book of Psalms has recorded in it,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 1:20"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 1:20">“Let his domicile go from occupied to unoccupied,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 1:20">And from there on out </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 1:20">Let there be no one who occupies it</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 1:20"></para>
    <para style="m" vid="ACT 1:20">“And,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 1:20"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 1:20">“Let someone else assume his leadership position<verse eid="ACT 1:20"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 1:21" />”So it has to be one of the men who accompanied us the entire time that the Lord Jesus was acquainted
        with us, <verse eid="ACT 1:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 1:22" />starting from John’s baptism up until the day which he was taken from us (namely that he was a witness
        of his resurrection), in order for one of these men to become one of us.”<verse eid="ACT 1:22" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 1:23" />Two candidates were put forward, Joseph who’s called Barsabbas, who’s also known as Justus, and Matthias.<verse eid="ACT 1:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 1:24" />They prayed and said, “You, Lord, are intimately familiar with the hearts of everyone; point out the
        one you’ve selected from among these two <verse eid="ACT 1:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 1:25" />to assume the position of this ministry and apostleship, which Judas usurped for his own purpose.” <verse eid="ACT 1:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 1:26" />They flipped a coin, and Matthias won the toss, and he was henceforth considered to be an apostle along
        with the eleven others.<verse eid="ACT 1:26" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 1" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  2   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="ACT 2" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 2:1" />When all the days had been checked off until fifty were reached—the Day of Pentecost—everyone was together
        and on the same page. <verse eid="ACT 2:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 2:2" />From out of the sky a noise suddenly occurred, one which seemed like a violent wind was being swept in,
        and it filled the entire building in which they were sitting. <verse eid="ACT 2:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 2:3" />Tongues like the tongues of the flames from a fire were seen being distributed to them, and a tongue
        sat upon each and every one of them, <verse eid="ACT 2:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 2:4" />and every one of them was filled with the Holy Spirit and began to speak in various tongues (other languages)
        as the Spirit kept on giving them the unction to be uttering in tongues.<verse eid="ACT 2:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 2:5" />Now there were Jews staying in Jerusalem, devout men, who were from every nation across the globe. <verse eid="ACT 2:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 2:6" />So when this sound happened, a bunch of them, confused, gathered together, because each person kept hearing
        them speaking in his own dialect of his own language. <verse eid="ACT 2:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 2:7" />They were non-stop confused and kept on wondering saying, “Don’t look now—but aren’t all of these folks
        who are speaking Galileans? <verse eid="ACT 2:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 2:8" />And how is it that each of us can hear what’s being spoken in his own native dialect of his own native
        language?— <verse eid="ACT 2:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 2:9" />Parthians, Medes, Elamites; those who live in Mesopotamia, Judea and not only there but in Cappadocia,
        Pontus, the province of Asia, <verse eid="ACT 2:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 2:10" />Phrygia, and not only there but Pamphylia, Egypt and the parts of Libya around Cyrene; visitors from
        Rome, <verse eid="ACT 2:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 2:11" />both Jews and Gentiles who’ve converted to Judaism; Cretans and Arabs—we all hear them in our own languages
        saying things which magnify God.” <verse eid="ACT 2:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 2:12" />Now everyone kept on being amazed, confused and perplexed, telling one another, “What in the world’s
        going on?” <verse eid="ACT 2:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 2:13" />But others, jeering, kept on saying something to the effect, “They went off and got drunk on sweet wine,
        the stuff the winos are always drinking.”<verse eid="ACT 2:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 2:14" />Peter along with the eleven others stood to address the crowd, raised his voice, and announced, “Men,
        Judeans, and everyone who’s staying in Jerusalem: may you listen to what I have to say and may this become
        understood to you. <verse eid="ACT 2:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 2:15" />The fact of the matter is, it’s not what you think, that is that these people are drinking, seeing that
        it’s only nine in the morning, <verse eid="ACT 2:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 2:16" />but instead this is what’s spoken through the prophet Joel,<verse eid="ACT 2:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 2:17" />”’In the Last Days, things will turn out this way,’</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:17">God says:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:17">‘I’ll pour out My Spirit onto all flesh.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:17">Your sons and daughters will prophesy,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:17">Your young men will see visions,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:17">Your elderly men will dream dreams.<verse eid="ACT 2:17"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 2:18" />In those days I will pour out My Spirit</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:18">Upon My male and female servants—</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:18">Indeed I will—</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:18">And they will prophesy.<verse eid="ACT 2:18"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 2:19" />I will grant that wonders occur in the sky above</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:19">And signs upon the earth below:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:19">Blood, fire, and smoke trails.<verse eid="ACT 2:19"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 2:20" />The sun will change into darkness</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:20">And the moon into blood</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:20">Prior to the coming</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:20">Of the Great and Marvelous Day of the Lord.<verse eid="ACT 2:20"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 2:21" />And things will turn out this way:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:21">All who choose to call for the Lord to act on his behalf</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:21">In the way He is reputed to act</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:21">Will be spared calamity.’<verse eid="ACT 2:21"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 2:22" />”Men, Israelites, listen to what I’m telling you. Jesus of Nazareth was a man who had been appointed
        by God to act on our behalf, and God performed miracles, wonders, and signs for us through him in your
        midst, as you all know. <verse eid="ACT 2:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 2:23" />By the specific determination of God, one which He decided ahead of time, this man was apprehended and
        taken into custody by bad, out-of-control men, fastened to a cross, and the cross was hoisted up as a
        form of execution. <verse eid="ACT 2:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 2:24" />God resurrected this man, having broken the travail of death, on account of the fact that it wasn’t possible
        for him to be overpowered and constrained by death, <verse eid="ACT 2:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 2:25" />seeing that in the Scriptures David told him,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:25"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:25">“Throughout it all, I kept on seeing the Lord ahead of time</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:25">In the area that I was most concerned about</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:25">Because He is right where I need Him</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:25">So that I don’t get rattled.<verse eid="ACT 2:25"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 2:26" />Because of this, I rejoiced in heart and uttered exultations,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:26">And, what’s more, my physical well-being</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:26">Will occupy the spot where hope exists,<verse eid="ACT 2:26"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 2:27" />Because You have not left the essence of my life-being</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:27">In the graveyard,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:27">Nor will You allow your Holy One to undergo decay.<verse eid="ACT 2:27"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 2:28" />Having familiarized me with the way of life,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:28">You will fill me with gladness</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:28">With Your undivided attention.<verse eid="ACT 2:28"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 2:29" />”Men, comrades, it’s appropriate to address you with confidence concerning our patriarch David, to say
        that he too passed away and was buried, and that his tomb has been right nearby from the day he died
        up until the present time. <verse eid="ACT 2:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 2:30" />So being a prophet and knowing that God made an oath and ‘swore to him that from out of the collection
        of those whom he would sire and their offspring, one of them would sit on his throne,’ <verse eid="ACT 2:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 2:31" />while seeing into the future, he spoke about the resurrection of Jesus; the fact is,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:31"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:31">“He has neither been left to the graveyard,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:31">Nor has his flesh undergone decay<verse eid="ACT 2:31"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 2:32" />”God resurrected this Jesus-fellow, of which we all are witnesses, <verse eid="ACT 2:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 2:33" />and thereupon promoted him to the position of God’s Chief Executive—not only that but having received
        the promise of the Holy Spirit from the Father, he’s poured out all of this that you see and hear. <verse eid="ACT 2:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 2:34" />You see, David didn’t ascend into heaven, but it was he specifically who said,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:34"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:34">“The Lord said to my Lord,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:34">‘Assume the role of being My right-hand man<verse eid="ACT 2:34"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 2:35" />Until such time I choose</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 2:35">To subjugate your enemies in obeisance to you’<verse eid="ACT 2:35"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 2:36" />”Let it be known with certainty to the entire Israeli ethnicity-nation that God made him both Lord and
        Messiah (Christ), this Jesus-fellow whom you crucified.”<verse eid="ACT 2:36" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 2:37" />Now, after they heard this, it caused their hearts to melt, and they told Peter and the rest of the apostles,
        “What should we do about it, men, comrades?” <verse eid="ACT 2:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 2:38" />Peter told them, “Have a change of heart and of ways and go ahead and have each of you be baptized by
        the authority of Jesus Christ for the forgiveness of your sins, and you will receive the gift of the
        Holy Spirit. <verse eid="ACT 2:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 2:39" />You see, the promise is for you, for your children and for everyone who’s far away—it is just as much
        given to the one as to the other; in other words, it is for all those whom the Lord God happens to or
        chooses to summon.” <verse eid="ACT 2:39" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 2:40" />He kept on stating a lot of other declarations, and kept on appealing to them summarized by saying, “May
        you escape from this twisted contemporary Zeitgeist.” <verse eid="ACT 2:40" />
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="ACT 2:41" />So those who took to heart and acted upon his message were baptized, and on that day around three-thousand
        individuals were added. <verse eid="ACT 2:41" />
      <verse number="42" style="v" sid="ACT 2:42" />They were faithful to keep listening to the apostles’ instruction, to keep having fellowship-dinners
        together, dinners culminating in a communion memorial, and to keep attending the prayer meetings.<verse eid="ACT 2:42" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="43" style="v" sid="ACT 2:43" />Now a deep reverence was continually maintained, and many signs and wonders kept on occurring through
        the apostles. <verse eid="ACT 2:43" />
      <verse number="44" style="v" sid="ACT 2:44" />Now all of those believing were on the same page in regard to the previously mentioned things and shared
        everything, <verse eid="ACT 2:44" />
      <verse number="45" style="v" sid="ACT 2:45" />and properties and possessions kept on being sold, and that which was sold kept on being distributed
        to every person according to whoever happened to have a need. <verse eid="ACT 2:45" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="46" style="v" sid="ACT 2:46" />Not only that but day by day they continued to be faithful to be in one accord in the temple, and furthermore
        they continued to attend the dinners mentioned previously from house to house, sharing food with great
        joy and simplicity of heart, <verse eid="ACT 2:46" />
      <verse number="47" style="v" sid="ACT 2:47" />praising God and having favor with the entirety of the folk-people—and the Lord kept adding those being
        saved day by day while the previously mentioned things were going on.<verse eid="ACT 2:47" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 2" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  3   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="ACT 3" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 3:1" />Now Peter and John went over to the temple at the Three-in-the-Afternoon-Prayer-Time, <verse eid="ACT 3:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 3:2" />and a certain man who was lame from the time he was born, having to be carried around all time, was there,
        whom some people day after day kept on placing at the temple gate known as the Beautiful Gate, so that
        he could beg for handouts from those entering the temple complex. <verse eid="ACT 3:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 3:3" />Seeing that Peter and John were about to go into the temple complex, he asked for a handout. <verse eid="ACT 3:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 3:4" />Peter stared at him, and John joined in with him, and Peter said, “Look at us!” <verse eid="ACT 3:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 3:5" />He proceeded to give heed to them, looking at them and paying attention to them, waiting to—expecting
        to—get something from them. <verse eid="ACT 3:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 3:6" />Peter said, “I don’t have any cash on me, but I’ll give you what I’ve got: by the authority vested in
        me by Jesus Christ of Nazareth, get up and walk around!”— <verse eid="ACT 3:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 3:7" />And he grabbed him by his right hand and pulled him up—And immediately his feet and ankles were strengthened
        and made sturdy— <verse eid="ACT 3:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 3:8" />And with a leap he stood up and started walking around and entered the temple complex together with them,
        walking around, jumping, and praising God. <verse eid="ACT 3:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 3:9" />All the folk-people saw him walking around and praising God, <verse eid="ACT 3:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 3:10" />and they recognized him as the same beggar who used to sit where the beggars sit at the temple’s Beautiful
        Gate, and they were filled with amazement and exhilaration at how things had turned out for him.<verse eid="ACT 3:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 3:11" />While the lame man was clutching Peter and John, folks everywhere at the colonnade known as Solomon’s
        Colonnade ran towards them, utterly amazed. <verse eid="ACT 3:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 3:12" />Seeing this, Peter responded to the crowd, “Men, Israelites, why are you amazed at this? Why are you
        staring at us as though we enabled him to walk by our own power or piety? <verse eid="ACT 3:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 3:13" />The God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob—the God of our patriarchal ancestors—glorified
        His servant Jesus, whom you all had arrested and whom you all rejected in the very presence of Pilate,
        after that guy delivered a verdict that would have set him free. <verse eid="ACT 3:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 3:14" />You rejected the holy and righteous one and asked for a homicidal man—a murderer—to be let off the hook
        and given back to you. <verse eid="ACT 3:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 3:15" />You killed the Prince of Life, whom God raised from the dead, of which we are witnesses. <verse eid="ACT 3:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 3:16" />And based on the faith which is derived from Jesus’s authorization to act, this person whom you see and
        know first-hand—Jesus’s authorization to act strengthened him and made him sturdy, and right in front
        of you all, the through-him-faith gave him this perfect health which you see. <verse eid="ACT 3:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 3:17" />Yes indeed comrades, I know that you conducted your lives in a way which is consistent with ignorance,
        just like your predecessors and ancestors did, <verse eid="ACT 3:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 3:18" />but the God that made the suffering of His Messiah known ahead of time through the mouth of all the prophets
        caused these things be fulfilled in this manner.<verse eid="ACT 3:18" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 3:19" />”So now, have a change of ways and turn your hearts to the obliteration of your sins, <verse eid="ACT 3:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 3:20" />in order that episodes of refreshing would issue forth from the Lord’s totally-focused attention, and
        He would send you the one who’s already been appointed to a position of authority, Christ Jesus, <verse eid="ACT 3:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 3:21" />whom the spiritual world will most definitely embrace up to the times of the establishment of everything
        that God has spoken through the mouth of His saints—namely the prophets—from day-one. <verse eid="ACT 3:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 3:22" />Yes, in the Old Testament Moses said that,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 3:22"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 3:22">“The Lord our God will bring to prominence a prophet</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 3:22">And send him your way,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 3:22">A prophet from among our fellow men—</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 3:22">One who is like me.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 3:22">You shall listen to what comes out of him</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 3:22">And you shall act in accordance to everything</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 3:22">That he happens to say to you.<verse eid="ACT 3:22"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 3:23" />What will happen to any individual</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 3:23">Who chooses not to listen to that prophet</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 3:23">Is that he will be absolutely annihilated,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 3:23">Never seen or heard from again.<verse eid="ACT 3:23"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 3:24" />”Indeed, all the prophets starting with Samuel, including those who came afterwards, talked about and
        announced these days that we’re living in. <verse eid="ACT 3:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 3:25" />You all are the beneficiaries of the prophets and of the covenant which God entered into with our ancestors,
        saying to Abraham, ‘All of the nationalities of the earth will be blessed by one of your descendants.’<verse eid="ACT 3:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 3:26" />God first and foremost brought to prominence his servant and sent him your way blessing you when each
        person turns away from your evil ways.”<verse eid="ACT 3:26" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 3" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  4   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="ACT 4" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 4:1" />While they were talking to the folk-people, the priests, the temple guards, and the Sadducees showed
        up, <verse eid="ACT 4:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 4:2" />exasperated because of them teaching the people and proclaiming Jesus’s resurrection from the dead, <verse eid="ACT 4:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 4:3" />and they arrested them and put them in jail until the next day; you see, it was evening already. <verse eid="ACT 4:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 4:4" />Many of those who heard the message became believers, and the number of men (not including women and
        children) who believe in Jesus reached five thousand.<verse eid="ACT 4:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 4:5" />Now what happened the next day is that the rulers, the councilmen, and the designated teachers convened
        in Jerusalem— <verse eid="ACT 4:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 4:6" />and Annas the High Priest was among them, and Caiaphas, John, and Alexander, and any person at all who
        was born into and, as a result, belonged to the high priests’ caste. <verse eid="ACT 4:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 4:7" />They made them stand in the center for questioning,</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 4:7">“By what governmental power have you done this, or who authorized you to do this in their agency?”<verse eid="ACT 4:7"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 4:8" />Then Peter, filled with the Holy Spirit, told them, “Rulers of the people and councilmen: <verse eid="ACT 4:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 4:9" />If we’re being questioned in court today in reference to a good deed done to a feeble man, namely as
        to just how exactly this fellow has been pulled out of his miserable condition: <verse eid="ACT 4:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 4:10" />Let it be known to every one of you and to all of the folk-people of Israel that at the behest of and
        by the authority of Jesus of Nazareth, whom you all crucified, whom God raised from the dead—by using
        this delegated authority, this fellow stands before you completely well. <verse eid="ACT 4:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 4:11" />That is,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 4:11"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 4:11">“The stone treated with contempt by you, the builders</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 4:11">Has become the principal cornerstone<verse eid="ACT 4:11"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 4:12" />”There is no security and protection for our natural and spiritual lives in anyone else; the fact of
        the matter is, there is no other person of impeccable reputation and of authority among the breadth of
        the varieties of peoples everywhere that the human race has ever produced and put forward as a candidate
        of such in whom it is absolutely necessary to be rescued from our deplorable spiritual, mental, and physical
        condition.”<verse eid="ACT 4:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 4:13" />Gawking at the boldness and confidence with which Peter and John were speaking, and floored by the fact
        that the men were uneducated and untrained, they were flabbergasted and began to notice that they had
        a close connection with Jesus, having been a part of his life and ministry. <verse eid="ACT 4:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 4:14" />Furthermore, seeing the man standing there in unison with them—the one who had been healed—they couldn’t
        come up with anything to say against the whole affair. <verse eid="ACT 4:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 4:15" />Ordering them to leave the council chamber, they huddled together <verse eid="ACT 4:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 4:16" />saying,</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 4:16">“What should we do about these people, since it certainly has become apparent to everyone who’s visiting
        or living in Jerusalem that a recognizable miracle has occurred through them, and we can’t deny it? <verse eid="ACT 4:16"/>
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 4:17" />We can’t let this go on; instead, so that this won’t continue to spread more and more among the folk-people,
        we’ll threaten them telling them to no longer speak to any person using this authority as the basis for
        their speaking.”<verse eid="ACT 4:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 4:18" />They summoned them and ordered them not to teach—not even to utter a peep—acting on the basis of Jesus’s
        authority. <verse eid="ACT 4:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 4:19" />Responding to that order Peter and John told them, “You make the call whether God considers heeding you
        more than heeding Him the right thing to do; <verse eid="ACT 4:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 4:20" />you see, as far as we’re concerned, we can’t NOT talk about what we’ve seen and heard.”<verse eid="ACT 4:20" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 4:21" />After they were threatened, they released them, not being able to figure out a way they could punish
        them on account of the folk-people, because everyone glorified God over what had happened; <verse eid="ACT 4:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 4:22" />you see, the man whom this miraculous healing happened to was more than forty years old.<verse eid="ACT 4:22" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 4:23" />After they were released, they went to their own particular group of people and reported what the chief
        priests and the councilmen told them. <verse eid="ACT 4:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 4:24" />After they heard this, everyone single-mindedly and in unison raised their voices and directed their
        words towards God and said, “Master, You who made the sky, the earth, the sea, and everything in it,<verse eid="ACT 4:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 4:25" />who, by means of the Holy Spirit, spoke from the mouth of our ancestor, Your servant David,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 4:25"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 4:25">“Just why, now, did the people</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 4:25">In all the various nations become insolent?</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 4:25">The folk-people carefully planned</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 4:25">Things which are useless, <verse eid="ACT 4:25"/>
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 4:26" />for which</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 4:26">The kings of the land stood nearby in support,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 4:26">And the rulers were assembled for the same purpose:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 4:26">To oppose the Lord and to oppose His Messiah (Christ).<verse eid="ACT 4:26"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 4:27" />”The fact is, they actually were assembled in this city for the purpose of opposing Your holy servant
        Jesus, whom You singled out to be specially chosen and to be given special, supernatural abilities—they
        being Herod and Pontius Pilate joined by the Gentiles and the Israeli people— <verse eid="ACT 4:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 4:28" />to do what Your situational control and Your well-thought-through plan decided ahead of time would happen.<verse eid="ACT 4:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 4:29" />And now, Lord, take a good, hard look at their threats and grant that Your servant speak Your message
        time after time with total boldness and confidence, <verse eid="ACT 4:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 4:30" />while at the same time You supernaturally intervene, the intervention resulting in healings, miracles,
        and supernatural portents occurring through the authority placed in your holy servant Jesus.”<verse eid="ACT 4:30" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 4:31" />After they were done praying, the place they were gathered was shaken, and everyone there was filled
        with the Holy Spirit and then began to speak God’s message with boldness and confidence once they left
        and got on with their daily business.<verse eid="ACT 4:31" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 4:32" />Now the sizable group of believers was of one heart, mind, and soul, and not a single person was saying
        that anything that he owned belonged to him exclusively, but instead everything was kept in common between
        them. <verse eid="ACT 4:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 4:33" />The apostles kept on putting the account of the resurrection of the Lord Jesus out there by means of
        tremendous miracles, and tremendous grace (i.e., God’s favor and His willingness to act in their behalf
        and to act through them) was upon them. <verse eid="ACT 4:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 4:34" />In fact, not a person among them was in need. You see, those who owned properties or houses and other
        buildings kept on selling them and selling them and bringing the proceeds of the sales <verse eid="ACT 4:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 4:35" />to the apostles, placing the proceeds in under their care and ownership. Money, goods, and the like were
        continuously being distributed to each person in proportion to what a given person happened to need.<verse eid="ACT 4:35" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 4:36" />Joseph, whom the apostles called Barnabas (which translated means “the epitome of one who fills the role
        of assistant, advocate, counselor, and encourager”), a clergyman, Cyprian by birth, <verse eid="ACT 4:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 4:37" />being the owner of a field, sold it and gave the money to the apostles, putting it in their custody.<verse eid="ACT 4:37" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 4" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  5   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="ACT 5" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 5:1" />Now a certain man named Ananias sold a piece of property in conjunction with his wife Sapphira <verse eid="ACT 5:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 5:2" />and withheld—appropriated—part of the proceeds, keeping the money for himself (his wife was in on it
        too) and gave a certain amount to the apostles, placing it under their care and ownership. <verse eid="ACT 5:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 5:3" />Peter told him,</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 5:3">“Ananias, how is it that Satan filled your heart causing you to lie in the presence of the Holy Spirit
        and appropriate some of the sales price from the sale of the property? <verse eid="ACT 5:3"/>
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 5:4" />While you still had it, wasn’t it yours to keep, and after it was sold, didn’t you have the right to
        retain control over the proceeds? How did this whole affair get lodged in your heart? You didn’t lie
        to human beings but to God.”<verse eid="ACT 5:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 5:5" />While Ananias was listening to these words, he dropped dead. An enormous sense of awe and reverence—downright
        fear—came over all those who were listening. <verse eid="ACT 5:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 5:6" />The older teens and younger men wrapped his body up, carried him out, and buried him.<verse eid="ACT 5:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 5:7" />About three hours went by and his wife came in, unaware of what had happened. <verse eid="ACT 5:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 5:8" />Peter reacted to her entrance,</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 5:8">“Tell me: did you sell the property for X amount of dollars?”</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 5:8">She said, “Yes, for X dollars.”<verse eid="ACT 5:8"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 5:9" />Peter said to her, “Why did you two conspire to try to pull a fast one on the Spirit of the Lord? Take
        a look at the feet of those who buried your husband at the door—and they’re going to carry you out as
        well.”<verse eid="ACT 5:9" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 5:10" />She immediately dropped dead alongside his feet. The older teens and younger men came in, checked that
        she was dead, and took her and buried her next to her husband. <verse eid="ACT 5:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 5:11" />A sense of awe and reverence—downright fear—came upon the entire community of believers and upon those
        who heard what happened. <verse eid="ACT 5:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 5:12" />Lots of miracles, all kinds of them, occurred among the folk-people. Everyone was on the same page, sharing
        the same heartfelt passion, meeting in the part of the temple complex called Solomon’s Colonnade. <verse eid="ACT 5:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 5:13" />As far as everyone else was concerned, no one was daring enough to join them, but apart from that, the
        people thought they were awesome. <verse eid="ACT 5:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 5:14" />More and more kept being added to their party, those who believe in the Lord that is, and not only men
        but women too, <verse eid="ACT 5:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 5:15" />to the point that they were even bringing out into the streets those with maladies of one sort or another,
        physical problems that were dragging them down, and placing them upon single-person dining couches and
        cots, so that when Peter came through he might possibly peer down and check in on any one of them and
        offer assistance in the form of healing. <verse eid="ACT 5:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 5:16" />Swaths of people in the vicinity of Jerusalem began to gather, bringing those with maladies and those
        inflicted by dirty, disgusting spirits, all of whom kept on getting healed or otherwise treated for whatever
        was wrong with them.<verse eid="ACT 5:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 5:17" />The High Priest and all those associated with him (those who belong to the Sadducees sect) were stirred
        to action by a competitive, passionate zeal, <verse eid="ACT 5:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 5:18" />and they apprehended the apostles and put them in the city jail. <verse eid="ACT 5:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 5:19" />But some time during the night, an angel unlocked the cell door and lead them out, and said, <verse eid="ACT 5:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 5:20" />”Go stand in the temple complex and tell all the short messages—the accounts, stories, sayings, and anecdotes—of
        this new life in Christ, and do this over and over again.” <verse eid="ACT 5:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 5:21" />Once they heard this, they entered the temple at the crack of dawn and proceeded to teach.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 5:21">Now the chief priest came over while leading his entourage of associates—the Council with all of the
        councilmen—and they sent word to the city jail to retrieve them. <verse eid="ACT 5:21"/>
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 5:22" />But when the attendants got there, they didn’t find that they were in the jail, so they turned around,
        went back, and reported it, <verse eid="ACT 5:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 5:23" />saying, “We found that the city jail was firmly locked down and found the prison guards standing at all
        of their posts at all of the doors. After they opened the door and let us in, we discovered that no one
        was there.” <verse eid="ACT 5:23" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 5:24" />As they heard these words, both the commander of the temple guard and the high priests were perplexed
        over how this could’ve happened. <verse eid="ACT 5:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 5:25" />Someone showed up and reported to them, “Check this out—the men whom you put in jail are standing in
        the temple complex teaching the folk-people.” <verse eid="ACT 5:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 5:26" />Then the commander with a party of attendants attached to him proceeded to get them again and take them
        away—but not by employing violent force, since they were wary and fearful of the people, lest they be
        pelted with stones.<verse eid="ACT 5:26" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 5:27" />After they brought them into the council chamber, they were made to stand before the Council. The High
        Priest questioned them, <verse eid="ACT 5:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 5:28" />”Didn’t I absolutely and emphatically command you not to teach basing your authority to speak on this
        person? See here now—Jerusalem’s been filled with your teaching, and you want to blame us and have us
        assume the guilt and consequences for this man’s death.”<verse eid="ACT 5:28" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 5:29" />Peter and the apostles replied, “We must obey God over obeying people. <verse eid="ACT 5:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 5:30" />God our Father resurrected Jesus, whom you got your grubby hands on and killed, having hung him on a
        wooden cross-beam. <verse eid="ACT 5:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 5:31" />God exalted this person, this number-one leader and savior, to the position of chief executive officer,
        to be His right-hand man, to grant a change of heart and of ways to Israel and a forgiveness of sins.<verse eid="ACT 5:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 5:32" />You personally are first-hand witnesses of these affairs and of the Holy Spirit whom God gave to those
        who obey Him.”<verse eid="ACT 5:32" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 5:33" />This hit a real sore spot with those who heard this, and they became infuriated and were wanting to kill
        them. <verse eid="ACT 5:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 5:34" />A Pharisee named Gamaliel, a teacher of the Law of Moses who was well-respected by all the folk-people,
        got up in the council and ordered the men out for a short while <verse eid="ACT 5:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 5:35" />and said to them, “Men, Israelites, stop, take a look at yourselves, and think for a moment about what
        you’re about to do to these men. <verse eid="ACT 5:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 5:36" />The fact is, a good while ago, Theudas came to prominence, claiming to be someone special, and four hundred
        men joined up with him. Everyone who believed in his cause disbanded, and his cause amounted to nothing.<verse eid="ACT 5:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 5:37" />After this, Judas the Galilean came to prominence during the time that the census was being taken, and
        he led a group of people away in apostasy. And that guy perished too, and everyone who believed in his
        cause dispersed.<verse eid="ACT 5:37" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 5:38" />”With that in mind, at this point in time I’m telling you to walk away from these men and leave them
        alone, because if either the intentions themselves or this cause as a whole happens to be man-made, it
        will be demolished. <verse eid="ACT 5:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 5:39" />But if it originates from God, you won’t be able to wipe them out—lest it become self-evident that you’re
        fighting against God.”</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 5:39">They were persuaded by him, <verse eid="ACT 5:39"/>
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 5:40" />and they summoned the men, beat them, and commanded them not to speak based on Jesus’s authority and
        set them free. <verse eid="ACT 5:40" />
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="ACT 5:41" />They therefore proceeded to go their way rejoicing after facing the Council because they had been deemed
        worthy to be dishonored on behalf of Jesus’s authority <verse eid="ACT 5:41" />
      <verse number="42" style="v" sid="ACT 5:42" />and didn’t stop meeting in the temple complex and from house to house every day, teaching and proclaiming
        the good news—the Gospel—of Christ Jesus.<verse eid="ACT 5:42" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 5" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  6   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="ACT 6" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 6:1" />Now during this timeframe when the number of disciples was expanding, a complaint originated from the
        Greek-speaking Jews against the native Israeli Jews, that their widows were being overlooked in the Daily
        Meal Service. <verse eid="ACT 6:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 6:2" />So the twelve summoned the bulk of the disciples and said, “We’re not happy about neglecting the teaching
        of God’s word by being restaurant waiters. <verse eid="ACT 6:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 6:3" />Look into the matter, comrades, and come up with seven men from among you that it’s been observed and
        generally agreed are full of spirit and wisdom, whom we might put in charge of this matter. <verse eid="ACT 6:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 6:4" />We, though, will devote ourselves to prayer and to the ministry of the word of God.”<verse eid="ACT 6:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 6:5" />The reasoning put forth was agreeable in the view of the large group assembled, and Stephen, a man full
        of faith and the Holy Spirit, Philip, Procorus, Nicanor, Timon, Parmenas, and Nicolas, who was a convert
        to Judaism from Antioch, were chosen. <verse eid="ACT 6:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 6:6" />They stood these men before the apostles, and after they prayed for them, they laid their hands on them.<verse eid="ACT 6:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 6:7" />And the word of God kept on being proclaimed, being received, and producing results, and the number of
        disciples in Jerusalem continued to grow at a high rate, and a bunch of the priests began to obey by
        believing in the faith.<verse eid="ACT 6:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 6:8" />Now Stephen, full of grace—God’s favor and His willingness to work through him—and miracle-working capability,
        began to perform tremendous miracles among the people. <verse eid="ACT 6:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 6:9" />Some people from the synagogue of those who are said to be Freedmen, Cyrenians, Alexandrians, and those
        from Cilicia and the Roman Province of Asia asserted themselves, arguing with Stephen, <verse eid="ACT 6:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 6:10" />and didn’t have the strength of words to withstand the wisdom and the spirit with which he continuously
        spoke. <verse eid="ACT 6:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 6:11" />Then they got men to claim that, “While he was speaking, we definitely heard him make a blasphemous remark
        against the Bible and God,” <verse eid="ACT 6:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 6:12" />and stirred up the folk-people, the councilmen, and the designated teachers and descended on him all
        of a sudden, apprehended him, and brought him into the Council chamber. <verse eid="ACT 6:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 6:13" />From there, the phony witnesses produced testimony saying, “This man won’t stop uttering remarks against
        this Holy Place and the Bible. <verse eid="ACT 6:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 6:14" />The fact is, we definitely heard him saying that this Jesus-of-Nazareth-guy will destroy this place and
        alter the traditions which Moses passed down to us.” <verse eid="ACT 6:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 6:15" />The panel of councilmen fixed their eyes upon him and looked at his face and saw that his countenance
        was like the countenance of an angel.<verse eid="ACT 6:15" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 6" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  7   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="ACT 7" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 7:1" />So the high priest said, “Is this so?”<verse eid="ACT 7:1" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 7:2" />He began to speak and said, “Men, comrades, and patriarchs: listen to me. The God of Glory appeared to
        our ancestral patriarch Abraham while he was living in Mesopotamia, prior to him getting settled in Harran,<verse eid="ACT 7:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 7:3" />and told him, ‘Leave your homeland and your relatives and go to a country which I will point out to you
        at some point.’ <verse eid="ACT 7:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 7:4" />He then left the country of Chaldea and settled in Harran. After his father died, from there he relocated
        to this country, to where we live now, <verse eid="ACT 7:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 7:5" />and he wasn’t given a tract of land in this country, one that he and his descendants would own in perpetuity—not
        even a tiny plot that would’ve been barely big enough to get by on—And he had been promised that, ‘This
        country be granted to him, given to him for him to own, he and his descendants—his progeny—after him,’
        while not having a son at the time. <verse eid="ACT 7:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 7:6" />Here’s what God had to say to him: ‘This is what’s going to happen: his descendants—his progeny—will
        be foreigners and outsiders in another country, and those in the other country will enslave them and
        mistreat them for four hundred years. <verse eid="ACT 7:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 7:7" />And I will judge the nation (i.e. personally intervene and put an end to the evil that they’re doing)
        who made the decision to enslave you…,’ God said, ‘…and after these things have occurred, they will leave
        and come back to this place here and continuously offer up worship by attending to an ongoing service
        of rituals.’<verse eid="ACT 7:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 7:8" />”And He imparted to him a covenant comprised of circumcision. According to this set of instructions,
        he sired Isaac and circumcised him on the eighth day after his birth, and Isaac did this to Jacob, and
        Jacob to the twelve patriarchs, the ancestral founders of what would be the twelve tribes of Israel.<verse eid="ACT 7:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 7:9" />”But the patriarchs were jealous of Joseph and handed him over to be put in the custody of some Egyptians;
        but God was with him, <verse eid="ACT 7:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 7:10" />and delivered him out of all of his tribulations and gave him favor and wisdom in the presence of the
        king of Egypt, that is Pharaoh, and he was put in charge over Egypt and over his (Pharoah’s) entire ruling
        clan and staff. <verse eid="ACT 7:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 7:11" />Now a famine came out of nowhere and oppressed Egypt and Canaan causing a terrible ordeal, and our eleven
        patriarchal ancestors weren’t able to find enough food to eat. <verse eid="ACT 7:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 7:12" />Jacob heard that there was wheat in Egypt and sent out our ancestors as envoys to make the initial contact.<verse eid="ACT 7:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 7:13" />Second time around Joseph made himself known to his brothers, and Joseph’s birth, lineage, and ethnicity
        were made apparent to Pharaoh. <verse eid="ACT 7:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 7:14" />Joseph sent a message and summoned Jacob his father to his side and all the relatives, a total of seventy-five
        individuals, <verse eid="ACT 7:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 7:15" />and Jacob went down to Egypt. He died and so did our twelve ancestors, <verse eid="ACT 7:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 7:16" />they relocated to Shechem, and he was placed in the tomb which Abraham bought (paying in cash) from the
        sons of Hamor in Shechem.<verse eid="ACT 7:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 7:17" />”Just as the time for the fulfillment of the promise which God promised to Abraham got closer, the Israeli
        people grew and multiplied in Egypt, <verse eid="ACT 7:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 7:18" />until ‘…Another king ascended to power over Egypt, one who wasn’t affiliated with the Israeli people.’<verse eid="ACT 7:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 7:19" />This fellow used cunning, Machiavellian techniques against our people and mistreated our ancestors going
        so far as to expose their babies to the raw elements to where they wouldn’t survive. <verse eid="ACT 7:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 7:20" />That was the timeframe in which Moses was born, and he was polished, charming, courteous, polite, witty,
        and elegant to the highest degree—he who had spent three months being raised in momma’s house. <verse eid="ACT 7:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 7:21" />While he was exposed to the raw elements in order to die, Pharaoh’s daughter adopted him as her own son<verse eid="ACT 7:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 7:22" />and trained and disciplined Moses in every sort of Egyptian wisdom and sophistication; he was formidable
        in speech, ability, and actions.<verse eid="ACT 7:22" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 7:23" />”Now as he reached the age of forty, he felt an urging to visit his kinsmen, the Israelites. <verse eid="ACT 7:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 7:24" />While seeing someone being ill-treated, he came to his defense and took vengeance on the one being oppressed
        and struck down the Egyptian oppressor. <verse eid="ACT 7:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 7:25" />Now he was assuming that his brethren would understand that, through his abilities and actions, God was
        coming to their rescue, but they didn’t understand, <verse eid="ACT 7:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 7:26" />and the following day he appeared to some men as they were fighting and tried to get them to reconcile
        with one another and said, ‘Men, you’re kinsmen, why are you hurting each other?’ <verse eid="ACT 7:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 7:27" />But one who was harming his acquaintance spurned him and said, ‘Who appointed you to be a ruler and a
        judge over us? <verse eid="ACT 7:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 7:28" />I hope you don’t want to eliminate me the same way you eliminated the Egyptian yesterday.’ <verse eid="ACT 7:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 7:29" />Moses fled at this remark, and became a stranger and a foreigner in the land of Midian, where he gave
        birth to a couple of sons.<verse eid="ACT 7:29" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 7:30" />”When forty years were completed, ‘…An angel appeared to him in the Mt. Sinai wilderness in the flame
        of a burning bush.’ <verse eid="ACT 7:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 7:31" />Seeing this, Moses was captivated by such a sight. While approaching it, a commanding voice appeared,<verse eid="ACT 7:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 7:32" />’I am the God of your forefathers, the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob.’ Moses became terrified and
        dared not try to wrap his head around the whole thing. <verse eid="ACT 7:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 7:33" />’The Lord said to him, “Take your sandals off; the place on which you’ve come to stand is holy ground.<verse eid="ACT 7:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 7:34" />I’ve seen the mistreatment of My people in Egypt and have heeded their groaning and have come down to
        deliver them. Go now: I’m sending you to Egypt.”’<verse eid="ACT 7:34" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 7:35" />“This Moses whom they spurned by saying, ‘Who appointed you ruler and judge?’—this is the ruler and deliverer
        God sent with the assistance of an angel that was seen by him in the bush. <verse eid="ACT 7:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 7:36" />This person led them out of Egypt and performed spectacular miracles for forty years in the country of
        Egypt, in the Red Sea, and in the wilderness. <verse eid="ACT 7:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 7:37" />This person is Moses who said to the Israelites, ‘God will bring to prominence in your midst a prophet
        like me from among your kinsmen.’<verse eid="ACT 7:37" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 7:38" />”This is the fellow who was present in the gathering in the wilderness, along with the angel which spoke
        to him on Mt. Sinai and with our ancestors, and is the person who was shown living words to give to us,<verse eid="ACT 7:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 7:39" />whom our ancestors didn’t want to become subordinate to, but instead rejected and in their hearts turned
        back to Egypt, <verse eid="ACT 7:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 7:40" />having told Aaron, ‘Make us gods that will be our banner on the march and in battle, ensuring success
        at every turn. The fact is, this Moses-fellow who led us out of Egypt—we don’t know what’s become of
        him.’ <verse eid="ACT 7:40" />
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="ACT 7:41" />During that timeframe they did the calf-making-thing and proceeded to offer up sacrifices to the idol
        and to rejoice in what their hands had wrought. <verse eid="ACT 7:41" />
      <verse number="42" style="v" sid="ACT 7:42" />So God turned His head from them and let them have their own way in enacting worship to the vast array
        of planets and stars in the sky, just like it’s written in the prophet-section of the Old Testament,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 7:42"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 7:42">“‘You didn’t bring Me offerings and sacrifices</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 7:42">When you were in the wilderness for forty years,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 7:42">Now did you house of Israel?<verse eid="ACT 7:42"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="43" style="v" sid="ACT 7:43" />But you applied yourselves to Molok’s house of worship</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 7:43">And to your star-god Rephan</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 7:43">And to the idols which you created</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 7:43">For the purpose of worshipping them.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 7:43">Because of this I will exile you</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 7:43">To a place which is somewhere out beyond Babylon.’<verse eid="ACT 7:43"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="44" style="v" sid="ACT 7:44" />”The tabernacle of the ark of the covenant existed with our ancestors in the wilderness just the way
        the end-to-end specifications were dictated to Moses to be built according to the blueprint he got to
        see; <verse eid="ACT 7:44" />
      <verse number="45" style="v" sid="ACT 7:45" />the tabernacle which our ancestors took turns entering while Joshua was taking possession of the lands
        owned by foreign nations, nations which God drove out by the onslaughtof our ancestors up until the timeframe
        of David, <verse eid="ACT 7:45" />
      <verse number="46" style="v" sid="ACT 7:46" />who found favor in the eyes of God, and he begged God that he would be allowed to come up with a plan
        to build a permanent tabernacle for the lineage of Jacob. <verse eid="ACT 7:46" />
      <verse number="47" style="v" sid="ACT 7:47" />But instead Solomon built Him a building—a home— <verse eid="ACT 7:47" />
      <verse number="48" style="v" sid="ACT 7:48" />but no—the Most High doesn’t reside in man-made structures, just like the prophet says,<verse eid="ACT 7:48" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="49" style="v" sid="ACT 7:49" />“’To Me, the heavens are a throne</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 7:49">And the earth is a stool that I use to rest My feet on.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 7:49">What sort of house will you make for me,’ says the Lord,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 7:49">‘Or what would be the place which I rest?<verse eid="ACT 7:49"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="50" style="v" sid="ACT 7:50" />Has not My hand made all of these things?’<verse eid="ACT 7:50" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="51" style="v" sid="ACT 7:51" />”Unyielding and unchanged in hearts and ears, you always resist the Holy Spirit; you’re just like your
        ancestors. <verse eid="ACT 7:51" />
      <verse number="52" style="v" sid="ACT 7:52" />Tell me—which prophet did your ancestors not persecute? Which one? They killed those who announced ahead
        of time things associated with the coming of the Righteous Man, whom you’ve become traitors to and murderers
        of— <verse eid="ACT 7:52" />
      <verse number="53" style="v" sid="ACT 7:53" />you the very people who received the Law of Moses, taking it to be an angelic ordinance, but didn’t keep
        it.”<verse eid="ACT 7:53" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="54" style="v" sid="ACT 7:54" />Having heard these things, they were piqued and went into a rage of fury and proceeded to grit their
        teeth, biting down hard, gnashing them against him. <verse eid="ACT 7:54" />
      <verse number="55" style="v" sid="ACT 7:55" />Being full of the Holy Spirit, he gazed up into the sky, to where heaven is, and saw God’s glorious magnificence
        and Jesus standing at God’s right hand (signifying that he’s completely vested in all executive powers)<verse eid="ACT 7:55" />
      <verse number="56" style="v" sid="ACT 7:56" />and said, “Check this out—I see the sky up to heaven opened up and the Man standing at God’s right hand.”<verse eid="ACT 7:56" />
      <verse number="57" style="v" sid="ACT 7:57" />They screamed with their ears covered tightly, rushed him in unison, <verse eid="ACT 7:57" />
      <verse number="58" style="v" sid="ACT 7:58" />took him out of the city and proceeded to stone him to death. And the witnesses (who according to the
        Law of Moses must be the first to cast stones) took their jackets off and set them next to an aspiring
        young man named Saul. <verse eid="ACT 7:58" />
      <verse number="59" style="v" sid="ACT 7:59" />As they were stoning Stephen he invokes heaven saying,</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 7:59">“Lord Jesus, receive my spirit.”<verse eid="ACT 7:59"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="60" style="v" sid="ACT 7:60" />He dropped to his knees and loudly shouted out, “Lord, may you not hold them accountable for this sin.”</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 7:60">Having said this, he went to sleep (i.e. he died as a believer).<verse eid="ACT 7:60"/>
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 7" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  8   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="ACT 8" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 8:1" />Now Saul whole-heartedly agreed with eliminating Stephen.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 8:1">On that day a terrible persecution broke out against the church—the gathering of believers—in Jerusalem.
        Everyone scattered over the Judean and Samarian countryside except for the apostles. <verse eid="ACT 8:1"/>
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 8:2" />Devout men buried Stephen and mourned greatly for him during the period of mourning held for him. <verse eid="ACT 8:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 8:3" />Saul proceeded to go from house to house ravaging the church, barging in and dragging off men and women,
        arresting them and putting them in jail.<verse eid="ACT 8:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 8:4" />Those who were scattering throughout the countryside were announcing the good news message—proclaiming
        the Gospel, the good news of the Word. <verse eid="ACT 8:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 8:5" />Philip went over to a Samaritan city and proceeded to preach Christ to them. <verse eid="ACT 8:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 8:6" />The crowds eagerly took in the various statements made by Philip, united in one heart and mind in their
        listening and in their watching miracles that he performed. <verse eid="ACT 8:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 8:7" />The fact is, many filthy, disgusting spirits were being cast out one after another, crying out in a loud
        voice as they left. Many paralyzed and lame were being healed. <verse eid="ACT 8:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 8:8" />Much joy took place in that city.<verse eid="ACT 8:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 8:9" />Now a certain man named Simon used to awe the Samaritans in the city by practicing magic, claiming to
        be someone special, <verse eid="ACT 8:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 8:10" />a person who captivated everyone’s attention, from the insignificant to the important, what they were
        describing as, “God’s miracle-working power: the Bomb.” <verse eid="ACT 8:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 8:11" />They kept paying attention to him for a long time, dazzled by the works of magic. <verse eid="ACT 8:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 8:12" />But when they believed Philip proclaiming the good news of God’s kingdom and proclaiming the authority
        vested in Jesus Christ and what he’s all about, they proceeded to be baptized, men and women both. <verse eid="ACT 8:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 8:13" />Simon himself also believed and, once baptized, while sticking like glue to Philip and seeing spectacular
        miracles and tremendous miracle-working abilities, kept on becoming more and more enchanted by having
        been dazzled over and over again.<verse eid="ACT 8:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 8:14" />Now once the apostles in Jerusalem heard that Samaria had whole-heartedly embraced and acted upon God’s
        word, they sent them Peter and John, <verse eid="ACT 8:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 8:15" />such individuals who would go over and pray for them so that they would receive the Holy Spirit: <verse eid="ACT 8:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 8:16" />for he (the Holy Spirit) had not yet fallen upon any one of them, but they only existed in a state where
        they had been baptized into all that the Lord Jesus stands for. <verse eid="ACT 8:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 8:17" />Then they laid hands on them and they began receiving the Holy Spirit. <verse eid="ACT 8:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 8:18" />Simon, seeing the Spirit given through the apostles’ laying on of hands, offered them money <verse eid="ACT 8:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 8:19" />saying,</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 8:19">“Give me this ability too, so that the person I lay my hands on would receive the Holy Spirit.”<verse eid="ACT 8:19"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 8:20" />But Peter said to him, “Get lost—I hope you die—you and your money along with you—since you assumed you
        could acquire God’s offering to mankind through cash. <verse eid="ACT 8:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 8:21" />You don’t get to participate in this business—not even a bit, seeing that your heart is not right in
        God’s sight. <verse eid="ACT 8:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 8:22" />So abandon this wickedness and beg the Lord if he would somehow possibly forgive your heart’s intention;<verse eid="ACT 8:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 8:23" />the fact is, I see that you’re coughing up bitterness and are handcuffed by unrighteousness.”<verse eid="ACT 8:23" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 8:24" />In response, Simon said, “You all pray to the Lord on my behalf, so that I won’t be afflicted by what
        you’ve said.”<verse eid="ACT 8:24" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 8:25" />So then they thoroughly presented and spoke about the concept of the Lord and returned to Jerusalem,
        and many Samaritan towns began to have the good news proclaimed in them.<verse eid="ACT 8:25" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 8:26" />Now an angel spoke to Philip, “Head on out south on the road which runs from Jerusalem to Gaza, the one
        that nobody uses.” <verse eid="ACT 8:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 8:27" />He got going. Out of nowhere an Ethiopian man appeared, a eunuch who had control over the Queen of Ethiopia’s
        entire treasury, one who had gone to Jerusalem to worship <verse eid="ACT 8:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 8:28" />and was on the return trip sitting on his chariot and reading out of the prophet Isaiah. <verse eid="ACT 8:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 8:29" />The Spirit said to Philip, “Go up to him and join his chariot.” <verse eid="ACT 8:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 8:30" />Philip ran over to him and heard him reading out of the prophet Isaiah, and said, “Hmm…do you really
        understand what you’re reading?” <verse eid="ACT 8:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 8:31" />He said, “Ya, about that. How would I be able to unless someone walks me through it?”, and he asked Philip
        to climb aboard the chariot, sit down together with him, and help him out. <verse eid="ACT 8:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 8:32" />The passage of Scripture which he was in the middle of reading was this:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 8:32"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 8:32">Like a sheep led to slaughter</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 8:32">And like a lamb speechless before the shearer:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 8:32">In the same way he won’t open his mouth.<verse eid="ACT 8:32"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 8:33" />In his self-abasement his justice has been stripped from him.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 8:33">How can anyone possibly describe</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 8:33">The prevailing Zeitgeist of his time,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 8:33">Since his life has been wiped off the face of the Earth?<verse eid="ACT 8:33"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 8:34" />Upon reflection the eunuch said to Philip, “Can I ask you whom the prophet’s talking about here? Is he
        talking about himself or about someone else?” <verse eid="ACT 8:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 8:35" />Philip opened his mouth and, from this passage of Scripture, began to tell him all about the good news
        of Jesus. <verse eid="ACT 8:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 8:36" />As they were going down the road, they stumbled across some water, and the eunuch said, “Look—water:
        what’s stopping me from getting baptized?” <verse eid="ACT 8:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 8:37" /> <verse eid="ACT 8:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 8:38" />He ordered his chariot to come to a halt, and both of them—Philip and the eunuch—got off the chariot
        and went into the water, and Philip baptized him. <verse eid="ACT 8:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 8:39" />When they got out of the water, the Spirit of the Lord took hold of Philip and redirected him, and the
        eunuch didn’t see him anymore; you see, he was going his way rejoicing. <verse eid="ACT 8:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 8:40" />Philip wound up in Azotus, and while travelling through there kept on proclaiming the good news to all
        of the cities all the way to Caesarea.<verse eid="ACT 8:40" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 8" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  9   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="ACT 9" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 9:1" />Saul, still huffing murderous threats at the Lord’s disciples, went to the high priest <verse eid="ACT 9:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 9:2" />and asked—begged—for letters of authorization from him to present to the synagogues in Damascus, so that
        if he were to find anyone belonging to “the Way”, either man or woman, once they’re caught and tied with
        rope, he would lead them to Jerusalem. <verse eid="ACT 9:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 9:3" />While travelling he was nearing Damascus and suddenly a light from up in the sky—from out of heaven—flashed
        around him, <verse eid="ACT 9:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 9:4" />and he fell to the ground and heard a voice saying to him,</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 9:4"><char style="wj">“Saul, Saul, why are you persecuting me?”</char><verse eid="ACT 9:4"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 9:5" />He said, “Who are you, sir?”</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 9:5"><char style="wj">“This is Jesus, the one you’re persecuting. </char><verse eid="ACT 9:5"/>
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 9:6" /><char style="wj">But enough—get up and go into the city, and you’ll be told what you must go about doing.”</char><verse eid="ACT 9:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 9:7" />His fellow travellers stood speechless, without doubt hearing the voice but not seeing anyone. <verse eid="ACT 9:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 9:8" />Saul got up off the ground, and when his eyes were opened, he couldn’t see a thing; he entered Damascus
        being led by the hand. <verse eid="ACT 9:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 9:9" />For three days he had no sight and didn’t eat or drink anything.<verse eid="ACT 9:9" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 9:10" />Now there was a certain disciple in Damascus named Ananias. The Lord spoke to him in a dream,</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 9:10"><char style="wj">“Ananias.”</char></para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 9:10">He said, “I’m here, Lord.”<verse eid="ACT 9:10"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 9:11" />The Lord told him, <char style="wj">“Get yourself ready and go down Straight Street and look in Judas’s
        house for a man named Saul who’s from Tarsus; you see, he’s praying </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">for
        help</char></char><char style="wj"> </char><verse eid="ACT 9:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 9:12" /><char style="wj">and saw</char><char style="wj"> a man named Ananias come in and lay his hands on him
        in order to recover his sight.”</char><verse eid="ACT 9:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 9:13" />Ananias replied, “Lord, a lot of people have told me about this man, about how much harm he’s done to
        the set-apart-people in Jerusalem— <verse eid="ACT 9:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 9:14" />and he has the backing of the high priest to catch and tie up anyone in this location who’s inviting
        you into his life.”<verse eid="ACT 9:14" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 9:15" />The Lord said to him, <char style="wj">“Get going, since he’s a specially-chosen instrument of mine—this
        fellow </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">is</char></char><char style="wj">—to take what I stand
        for</char><char style="wj"> and </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">with pains</char></char><char
        style="wj"> bring it to the attention of </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">foreign</char></char><char
        style="wj"> nations, and not just </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">foreign </char></char><char
        style="wj">nations but kings and Israeli descendants </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">scattered
        all around</char></char><char style="it"><char style="wj">.</char></char><char style="wj"> </char><verse eid="ACT 9:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 9:16" /><char style="wj">In fact, I’ll show him how much he’ll have to suffer on behalf of acting as my representative</char><char
        style="wj">.”</char><verse eid="ACT 9:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 9:17" />So Ananias left and entered the house, laid his hands upon him, and said, “Saul, fellow comrade, the
        Lord sent me—Jesus, the one who appeared to you while you were on the way here—in order that you would
        regain your sight would be filled with the Holy Spirit.” <verse eid="ACT 9:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 9:18" />And without delay something akin to fish scales fell away from his eyes, and he regained his sight. He
        took the initiative and was baptized. <verse eid="ACT 9:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 9:19" />Once he got something to eat, he was invigorated.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 9:19">He spent several days with the Damascus disciples. <verse eid="ACT 9:19"/>
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 9:20" />He straightaway proceeded to preach Jesus—that this person is the Son of God—in the synagogues. <verse eid="ACT 9:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 9:21" />Again and again everyone who heard him was amazed, and they started saying, “Isn’t this the guy who’s
        wreaking havoc on those in Jerusalem who’ve invited Jesus into their lives? Hasn’t he come here for the
        same reason, so that he could take the ones he’s caught, tie them up, and bring them right to the high
        priest?” <verse eid="ACT 9:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 9:22" />But Saul proceeded to become all the more forceful and confounded the Jews living in Damascus, demonstrating
        through proofs that this very person Jesus is the Messiah, the Christ.<verse eid="ACT 9:22" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 9:23" />As a good many days had gone by and things were coming to a head, the Jews conspired to eliminate him,<verse eid="ACT 9:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 9:24" />but their plot became known to Saul. They even started monitoring the gates closely, not just by day
        but by night too, so that they could eliminate him, <verse eid="ACT 9:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 9:25" />but in spite of this disciples took him one night and put him all the way through the city wall and lowered
        him down in a large basket.<verse eid="ACT 9:25" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 9:26" />After arriving in Jerusalem, he kept attempting to join up with the disciples, but a lot of them kept
        on being afraid of him, not believing that he actually was a disciple. <verse eid="ACT 9:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 9:27" />So Barnabas got ahold of him and brought him to the apostles and told them all about him: how he was
        on the road and saw the Lord, and that the Lord spoke to him…how in Damascus he was speaking out on behalf
        of Jesus and all that he stands for. <verse eid="ACT 9:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 9:28" />He accompanied them while entering and leaving Jerusalem, accompanying them the entire time while in
        Jerusalem, speaking out on behalf of the Lord and all that he stands for, <verse eid="ACT 9:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 9:29" />and he proceeded to speak to and to have discussions—to the point of arguing—with the Greek-speaking
        Jews, but they tried to apprehend him in order to eliminate him. <verse eid="ACT 9:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 9:30" />The comrades recognized that this was a problem and brought him over to Caesarea and sent him away to
        Tarsus.<verse eid="ACT 9:30" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 9:31" />So now the church up and down the entire stretch of Judea, Galilee, and Samaria experienced peace, being
        edified and conducting their lives in the deep reverence—the fear—of the Lord, and with the assistance
        and comfort of the Holy Spirit, they were growing and growing.<verse eid="ACT 9:31" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 9:32" />While Peter happened to be travelling all throughout the area, he also went over to the-set-apart-ones
        living in Lydda. <verse eid="ACT 9:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 9:33" />He found a man there, a certain person named Aeneas, who had been bedfast for the last eight years, a
        person who had become paralyzed. <verse eid="ACT 9:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 9:34" />Peter told him, “Aeneas, Jesus Christ is healing you: get up and make your bed.” Immediately he got up.<verse eid="ACT 9:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 9:35" />Everyone living in Lydda and Sharon saw him; those very people turned to the Lord.<verse eid="ACT 9:35" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 9:36" />Now in Joppa there was a certain disciple named Tabitha, which translated means “Dorcas.” She was teeming
        in good works and in donations to the poor, which she was constantly contributing. <verse eid="ACT 9:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 9:37" />During that timeframe she happened to get run-down with an illness, becoming sick to the point of death
        and eventually dying. They bathed her and put her in the top floor of a building. <verse eid="ACT 9:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 9:38" />Lydda being close to Joppa, the disciples heard that Peter was over there and sent two men to him asking
        him earnestly—begging him, “Hurry up! Come over to our place!” <verse eid="ACT 9:38" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 9:39" />Peter got up and went with them and, once he arrived, was ushered up to the upper floor. All the widows
        stood next to him crying and showing the oh-so-many tunics and cloaks which she was in the habit of making
        while she was with them. <verse eid="ACT 9:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 9:40" />Peter pushed everyone out of the room, and got on his knees and prayed and turned to the body and said,
        “Tabitha, get up!” She opened her eyes and, seeing Peter, sat up. <verse eid="ACT 9:40" />
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="ACT 9:41" />He gave her a hand and got her up. He called for the set-apart-people and presented her alive from the
        dead. <verse eid="ACT 9:41" />
      <verse number="42" style="v" sid="ACT 9:42" />What happened became known up and down the entire Joppa stretch, and many believed in the Lord. <verse eid="ACT 9:42" />
      <verse number="43" style="v" sid="ACT 9:43" />As it turned out, he remained a good amount of time in Joppa with one Simon Tanner.<verse eid="ACT 9:43" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 9" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 10   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="ACT 10" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 10:1" />In Caesarea a certain man named Cornelius, a centurion in a battalion named “From (the Roman province
        of) Italia,” <verse eid="ACT 10:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 10:2" />a devout Gentile who, together with his entire household, was a sympathizer and near-convert to Judaism,
        often giving contributions to the poor-folk and constantly praying to God, <verse eid="ACT 10:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 10:3" />around three o’clock in the afternoon distinctly saw an angel in a vision enter this world and go to
        him and say, </para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 10:3">“Cornelius.”<verse eid="ACT 10:3"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 10:4" />Once he stared at him, he became afraid and said, “What is it, sir?”</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 10:4">He told him, “Your prayers and donations have percolated upwards to where they’ve garnered God’s attention,
        and He’s quite pleased by what He sees. <verse eid="ACT 10:4"/>
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 10:5" />Send a few men to Joppa right now and summon Simon, who goes by ‘Peter.’ <verse eid="ACT 10:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 10:6" />This fellow’s being boarded by one Simon Tanner, whose house is next to the sea.” <verse eid="ACT 10:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 10:7" />As the angel who was speaking to him left, he called for two men from his household staff and a pious
        soldier from among those who waited on him. <verse eid="ACT 10:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 10:8" />He explained everything to them and dispatched them to Joppa.<verse eid="ACT 10:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 10:9" />During the next day, while those men were on the road and getting near to the city, Peter went out on
        the back deck around noon to pray. <verse eid="ACT 10:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 10:10" />He got hungry and had a hankering to eat. While they were getting the noon meal ready, what happened
        is that he fell into a trance <verse eid="ACT 10:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 10:11" />and sees that the sky had been opened up and sees an object something like a huge, four-cornered cloth
        sheet coming down, being lowered to the ground, <verse eid="ACT 10:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 10:12" />on top of which was every type of four-footed animal, were reptiles, and were birds from the sky—In other
        words, all sorts of animals which, according to Jewish kosher laws, Jews are forbidden to eat. <verse eid="ACT 10:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 10:13" />Out of nowhere a voice addressed him, “Get to it, Peter: slaughter and eat them.” <verse eid="ACT 10:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 10:14" />But Peter said, “No way, sir, since I’ve never eaten anything which isn’t kosher.” <verse eid="ACT 10:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 10:15" />Again a second time a voice from the sky spoke to him, “The item which God has purged of its non-kosher-ness
        is permissible for you to eat.” <verse eid="ACT 10:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 10:16" />This happened a third time and immediately after that the object was taken up into the sky.<verse eid="ACT 10:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 10:17" />While Peter was turning things over in his head, being stumped at what the vision he’d witnessed could
        possibly mean, out of nowhere the men who were sent by Cornelius stopped at the gate asking around about
        Simon’s house, <verse eid="ACT 10:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 10:18" />and in their conversation proceeded to inquire if Simon who goes by Peter was staying at this place.<verse eid="ACT 10:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 10:19" />While Peter was thinking over the vision, the Spirit told him, “Take a look—three men are looking for
        you. <verse eid="ACT 10:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 10:20" />Enough said—go down, go over, and introduce yourself to them; I’ve sent them, no doubt.” <verse eid="ACT 10:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 10:21" />So Peter went over to the men and said, “Hey, I’m the one you’re looking for. What’s the reason you’ve
        come?” <verse eid="ACT 10:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 10:22" />They said, “Cornelius, a centurion, a righteous man and a Jewish-sympathizer—plus well-spoken-of and
        respected by the whole Jewish race—was divinely instructed by an angel to have you sent to his house
        and to listen to a message by you.” <verse eid="ACT 10:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 10:23" />As a result he invited them in and entertained them, letting them stay at his place.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 10:23">The next day, he got ready and departed with them, and some of the comrades from Joppa came with him.<verse eid="ACT 10:23"/>
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 10:24" />The following day, they arrived in Caesarea; Cornelius was waiting for them to arrive and gathered together
        his close friends and relatives. <verse eid="ACT 10:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 10:25" />Now just as Peter arrived, Cornelius went up to him and prostrated himself before him in worship. <verse eid="ACT 10:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 10:26" />Peter got him up by saying, “Get up: me—I’m just a human being.” <verse eid="ACT 10:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 10:27" />Conversing with him, he entered the house and discovered that a lot of people had gathered there <verse eid="ACT 10:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 10:28" />and said to them, “You understand that it’s forbidden for a Jewish man to associate with or visit someone
        of another race. But God showed me that the item which has been purged of its non-kosher-ness (talking
        about a person in this case) is to be permitted. <verse eid="ACT 10:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 10:29" />Therefore, I had no objection to coming when you sent for me. So let me ask: what reason have you summoned
        me?”<verse eid="ACT 10:29" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 10:30" />Cornelius said, “Starting four days ago up until this very moment we were praying just like we pray during
        the Three-in-the-Afternoon-Prayer-Time in my house, and—just like that—a man dressed in white appeared
        out of nowhere and stood in front of me <verse eid="ACT 10:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 10:31" />and said, ‘Cornelius, your prayers and donations have percolated upwards to where they’ve garnered God’s
        attention, and He’s quite pleased by what He sees. <verse eid="ACT 10:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 10:32" />So now, send some men to Joppa and send for Simon who goes by Peter. This fellow’s being boarded in Simon
        Tanner’s house next to the sea.’ <verse eid="ACT 10:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 10:33" />So without delay I dispatched some men your way, and you’ve kindly acquiesced to being brought here.
        So at this time all of us are on the edge of our seats waiting to hear and to obey everything that you’ve
        been directed and commanded by the Lord.”<verse eid="ACT 10:33" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 10:34" />Peter opened his mouth and said, “I’m really, really floored by the fact that God doesn’t show partiality,<verse eid="ACT 10:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 10:35" />but instead those in every race, culture, and nationality who reverence Him and go about doing right
        are acceptable to Him. <verse eid="ACT 10:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 10:36" />He sent the word out to the Israeli descendants issuing a good-news proclamation of peace through Jesus
        Christ—this person is everyone’s Lord— <verse eid="ACT 10:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 10:37" />you know about it: the affair that happened all throughout Judea, starting in Galilee after the baptism
        that John preached: <verse eid="ACT 10:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 10:38" />That God singled out and specially chose Jesus of Nazareth and put on him an oh-so-powerful-dose of the
        miracle-working power of the Holy Spirit, who then, since God was with him, went throughout the confines
        of Israel doing good works and healing all who were being oppressed by the devil. <verse eid="ACT 10:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 10:39" />We ourselves are eyewitnesses to all that he did in the country occupied by the Jews and in Jerusalem—he
        that they hung on a wooden cross-beam and killed. <verse eid="ACT 10:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 10:40" />God resurrected this fellow on the third day and caused him to be seen by the naked eye and appear before
        people, <verse eid="ACT 10:40" />
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="ACT 10:41" />but not to be seen by any-old person but instead to provide evidence to those hand-picked beforehand
        by God—that is us—the very people who ate and drank together with him after his resurrection from the
        dead. <verse eid="ACT 10:41" />
      <verse number="42" style="v" sid="ACT 10:42" />He commanded us to preach to the folk-people and to solemnly testify that this fellow is the one who’s
        been promised by God; this fellow is a judge of the living and the dead. <verse eid="ACT 10:42" />
      <verse number="43" style="v" sid="ACT 10:43" />To this end, all of the prophets affirm the receiving of forgiveness of sins through his authority and
        what he stands for…”<verse eid="ACT 10:43" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="44" style="v" sid="ACT 10:44" />While Peter was still in the middle of saying this, the Holy Spirit fell (i.e. they were baptized in
        the Holy Spirit by the Spirit manifesting Himself in a strong, sudden way inside of them, to the point
        of having trouble keeping control of themselves) on everyone who was listening to the message. <verse eid="ACT 10:44" />
      <verse number="45" style="v" sid="ACT 10:45" />The believers who were dedicated to a strict form of Judaism who accompanied Peter were flabbergasted
        because the offering—the gift—of the baptism in the Holy Spirit was poured out on the Gentiles, those
        who are not Jewish by birth or by conversion: <verse eid="ACT 10:45" />
      <verse number="46" style="v" sid="ACT 10:46" />for they heard them speaking in tongues and magnifying God. Then Peter reacted to what had happened,<verse eid="ACT 10:46" />
      <verse number="47" style="v" sid="ACT 10:47" />“Surely water for someone to be baptized in can’t be denied to these people, particularly those who received
        the Holy Spirit just like we did?” <verse eid="ACT 10:47" />
      <verse number="48" style="v" sid="ACT 10:48" />He commanded that they be baptized by the authority of Jesus Christ. After that, they asked him to stay
        for several days.<verse eid="ACT 10:48" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 10" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 11   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="ACT 11" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 11:1" />Now the apostles and comrades over in Judea heard that the Gentiles too and not just the Jews had whole-heartedly
        embraced and acted upon God&apos;s word, God’s system of logic. <verse eid="ACT 11:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 11:2" />When Peter went over to Jerusalem, the believers who adhered to Judaism strictly proceeded to show that
        they had misgivings about what he did and questioned what he did: <verse eid="ACT 11:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 11:3" />“You went into a house that has those outside of Judaism in it and shared a meal with them.”<verse eid="ACT 11:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 11:4" />Peter proceeded to explain to them what happened, explaining it in sequential order: <verse eid="ACT 11:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 11:5" />“I was in Joppa praying and had a vision while in a trance: the vision was of an object something like
        a huge, four-cornered cloth sheet descending out of the sky, and it came as far as me and stopped. <verse eid="ACT 11:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 11:6" />I stared at it and started to notice what was there: I saw the gamut of four-footed animals, wild beasts,
        reptiles, and birds from the sky. <verse eid="ACT 11:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 11:7" />Along with it, I heard a voice telling me, ‘Get to it, Peter: slaughter and eat them.’ <verse eid="ACT 11:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 11:8" />But I said, ‘No way, sir, since nothing which isn’t kosher has ever entered my mouth.’ <verse eid="ACT 11:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 11:9" />A second time a voice from the sky spoke in reply, ‘That which God has purged of its non-kosher-ness
        is permissible for you to eat.’ <verse eid="ACT 11:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 11:10" />This happened a third time, and the objects in the vision were taken back up into the sky again. <verse eid="ACT 11:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 11:11" />Just like that, three men stopped at the house which I was staying, men sent as messengers from Cornelius
        to me. <verse eid="ACT 11:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 11:12" />The Spirit told me to have no doubts or reservations and go introduce myself to them. Some of the comrades—these
        fellows here—also accompanied me, and we entered the man’s house.<verse eid="ACT 11:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 11:13" />”He reported how he saw an angel in his house, and the angel stood there and said, ‘Send messengers to
        Joppa and send for Simon who goes by Peter, <verse eid="ACT 11:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 11:14" />who’ll speak to you and tell you things by which you will be rescued from your spiritual malaise, you
        and your entire household.’ <verse eid="ACT 11:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 11:15" />While I was just getting started talking, the baptism in the Holy Spirit fell on them just like it did
        on us too way-back-when. <verse eid="ACT 11:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 11:16" />But I remembered the Lord’s sayings, as he kept on telling us, <char style="wj">‘Sure, John baptized
        with water, but you all will be baptized with the Holy Spirit.’</char> <verse eid="ACT 11:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 11:17" />So now, if God gave the same exact offering—gift—to them as He gave to us too, to believe in the Lord
        Jesus Christ, who was I to stand in God’s way?” <verse eid="ACT 11:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 11:18" />After hearing this, they fell silent and glorified God saying, “Then that means that God also granted
        the Gentiles the Complete-Changeover which leads to that special fullness of life.”<verse eid="ACT 11:18" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 11:19" />So now, those who were scattered because of the pressure due to the persecution that occurred upon Stephen’s
        stoning spread out as far as Phoenicia, Cyprus, and Antioch telling the Concept to Jews alone. <verse eid="ACT 11:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 11:20" />Among them were some men from Cyprus and Cyrene, men in particular who went to Antioch and were talking
        and talking to the Greek-speaking Jews, telling them the good news—the Gospel—of the Lord Jesus. <verse eid="ACT 11:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 11:21" />The Lord was supernaturally and spectacularly working behind the scenes in conjunction with them, and
        consequently there were many people who believed and turned to the Lord.<verse eid="ACT 11:21" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 11:22" />The whole story was heard by the ears of the church in Jerusalem, and they dispatched Barnabas, who passed
        through the region until he got to Antioch. <verse eid="ACT 11:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 11:23" />Once he got there and got to see the manifestation of God’s grace, rejoiced. Because he was a good man,
        full of the Holy Spirit, and faithful, he advised, encouraged, and in every way helped them all with
        a heartfelt determination to stick with it until the Lord comes back. <verse eid="ACT 11:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 11:24" /> —And a good-many people were added to the Lord. <verse eid="ACT 11:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 11:25" />He left for Tarsus to hunt Saul down, <verse eid="ACT 11:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 11:26" />and once he found him brought him to Antioch. As things turned out in their case, they got together in
        the church for a whole year and taught a good number of people, and as a result the disciples were first
        referred to as “Christians” in Antioch.<verse eid="ACT 11:26" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 11:27" />During this timeframe, prophets went from Jerusalem to Antioch. <verse eid="ACT 11:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 11:28" />One of them by the name of Agabus stood up and through the Spirit portended that a huge famine over the
        entire civilized worldwas going to occur, which happened during the Roman Emperor Claudius’s reign. <verse eid="ACT 11:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 11:29" />The disciples reacted in such a way that what came out of them was that each one of them, as far as he
        had the means to do so, determined to send a ministry-gift to the comrades living in Judea. <verse eid="ACT 11:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 11:30" />They did just that and sent the money they collected to the presiding board, the leaders of the church
        in Jerusalem, using Barnabas and Saul as couriers.<verse eid="ACT 11:30" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 11" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 12   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="ACT 12" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 12:1" />About that time, King Herod seized a few people who belonged to the church in order to mistreat them
        badly. <verse eid="ACT 12:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 12:2" />He killed John’s brother James with a sword. <verse eid="ACT 12:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 12:3" />Seeing how pleasing this was to the Judeans, he proceeded to take it a step further and apprehend Peter
        too (it was around Passover), <verse eid="ACT 12:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 12:4" />whom he arrested and put in jail, putting him in the custody of four squads (a squad consisting of four
        men) of soldiers who would guard him, intending to haul him up before the folk-people after the Passover.<verse eid="ACT 12:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 12:5" />So now, Peter was being kept in jail; the church continued praying fervently to God for him.<verse eid="ACT 12:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 12:6" />When Herod was about to lead him forth to his death, Peter was sleeping that night between two soldiers,
        chained up with two chains. In addition to that, two soldiers were guarding the door. <verse eid="ACT 12:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 12:7" />Out of nowhere, an angel went up to him and a light shined in the cell. He tapped Peter’s chest and woke
        him up saying,</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 12:7">“Get up—quickly now!”</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 12:7">His chains fell from his arms.<verse eid="ACT 12:7"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 12:8" />The angel told him, “Put your shirt and pants on and put your sandals on.” He did just that.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 12:8">He then says to him, “Put your jacket on and follow me.”<verse eid="ACT 12:8"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 12:9" />Once he left the prison, he followed him, but because of the angel he didn’t know that what was happening
        was for real; he kept on thinking that he was having a dream. <verse eid="ACT 12:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 12:10" />After passing through the night watchmen’s first checkpoint and through the second, they went to the
        Iron Gate, the gate people use when carrying things into the city. That very gate opened automatically
        itself for them, and after they left the city, they went down one narrow street and immediately the angel
        left him. <verse eid="ACT 12:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 12:11" />Peter came to his senses and said, “Now I know for certain that the Lord sent one of his angels and delivered
        me from Herod’s clutches and from all that awaited me from the Judean folk-people.” <verse eid="ACT 12:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 12:12" />Realising where he was, he went to Mary’s house (Mary the mother of John, who goes by “Mark”), where
        a good number of people were gathered praying.<verse eid="ACT 12:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 12:13" />He knocked on the outer courtyard door and a girl named Rhoda went to answer it. <verse eid="ACT 12:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 12:14" />Recognizing Peter’s voice, out of joy she didn’t open the door but ran in and announced that Peter’s
        standing at the door. <verse eid="ACT 12:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 12:15" />They told her, “You’re crazy,” but she kept on insisting that it’s so. They kept on telling her, “It’s
        his messenger,” <verse eid="ACT 12:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 12:16" />but Peter stayed there knocking, so they opened the door, saw him, and just lost it. <verse eid="ACT 12:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 12:17" />He motioned with his hand to get them to quiet down and began to explain how the Lord led him out of
        the prison; in addition, he told them, “Go out and tell these things to James and his brothers.” He left
        and went to some other place.<verse eid="ACT 12:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 12:18" />When daylight came, no small amount of commotion took place among the soldiers: what exactly happened
        to Peter? <verse eid="ACT 12:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 12:19" />Herod looked for him and upon not finding him interrogated the guards and ordered that they be taken
        away and executed and left Judea for Caesarea and proceeded to spend time there.<verse eid="ACT 12:19" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 12:20" />Now he was furious with Tyre and Sidon; but in the solidarity of a unified front, they approached him
        and, once they won the king’s chamberlain Blastus over to their side, kept begging for peace on account
        of their country being fed out of the king’s grain silos. <verse eid="ACT 12:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 12:21" />On a prearranged date, Herod, fully clothed in his regal apparel and presiding in his official capacity
        as judge, proceeded to address them. <verse eid="ACT 12:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 12:22" />The populace kept shouting out, “We’re hearing a god’s voice and not a human voice!” <verse eid="ACT 12:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 12:23" />Immediately an angel struck him in retaliation for not coming clean and telling the truthby letting that
        remark slide, and he wound up being eaten by worms and breathed his last.<verse eid="ACT 12:23" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 12:24" />The Word of God kept on growing and multiplying. <verse eid="ACT 12:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 12:25" />Having fulfilled their mission, Barnabas and Saul returned from Jerusalem and took along with them John
        who goes by Mark. <verse eid="ACT 12:25" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 12" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 13   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="ACT 13" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 13:1" />Now there were prophets and teachers interspersed throughout the church in Antioch: Barnabas, Simeon
        who goes by Niger, and Lucius the Cyrenian; Manaen a close, boyhood friend (might’ve even been a foster
        brother) of the tetrarch Herod, and Saul. <verse eid="ACT 13:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 13:2" />While worshipping the Lord in worship services and while fasting, the Holy Spirit told them, “Consecrate
        Barnabas and Saul to the work that I have called them.” <verse eid="ACT 13:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 13:3" />Then, after fasting, praying, and laying hands on them, they turned them loose.<verse eid="ACT 13:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 13:4" />So then they, having been dispatched by the Holy Spirit, went over to Seleucia, and from there sailed
        out to Cyprus. <verse eid="ACT 13:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 13:5" />When they wound up in Salamis, they proclaimed God’s word in the Jews’ synagogues. Now he had Mark around
        to run errands for him and to help with odds-and-ends.<verse eid="ACT 13:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 13:6" />After they went through the entire island all the way to Paphos, they ran across a particular man, a
        sorcerer/false-prophet Jew who adopted the name “Joshua-2.0,” <verse eid="ACT 13:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 13:7" />an associate of the intelligent, quick-witted Roman proconsul Sergius Paulus. This fellow Sergius Paulus
        summoned Barnabas and Saul, seeking to hear all about God’s word. <verse eid="ACT 13:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 13:8" />The sorcerer Elymas (that’s the way his name—Joshua-2.0’s name, that is—is translated), though, opposed
        them, trying to distort the message, steering the proconsul away from the faith. <verse eid="ACT 13:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 13:9" />But Saul (which is also “Paul”), being full of the Holy Spirit, glared at him <verse eid="ACT 13:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 13:10" />and said, “Oh, aren’t you full of all kinds of deception, trickery, and unscrupulousness, you spitting
        image of the devil, you enemy of any shape or form of righteousness?—You won’t pause for a moment in
        your turning people away by your distortion of the Lord’s Straightforward Ways. <verse eid="ACT 13:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 13:11" />See here: a supernatural working of the Lord’s power will assail you right this moment, and you’ll become
        blind—not even able to see the sun—for a duration of time”—and immediately a total loss of sight to where
        everything went completely dark was imposed upon him, and he began to go around trying to find a blind-man’s
        guide to lead him about by the hand. <verse eid="ACT 13:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 13:12" />Upon seeing what had happened, the proconsul then believed, astonished at the lesson that the Lord taught
        Elymas.<verse eid="ACT 13:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 13:13" />Paul and the band which surrounded him put out to sea at Paphos and went to Perga, Pamphylia. Mark, however,
        left them and returned to Jerusalem. <verse eid="ACT 13:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 13:14" />For their part, though, starting at Perga, they cut across and arrived in Antioch-Pasidia, and attended
        a synagogue meeting on the Sabbath, introduced themselves, and took a seat. <verse eid="ACT 13:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 13:15" />After the bringing-out of the Old Testament scrolls, the synagogue heads sent them a message, “Men, comrades,
        if any one of you has an encouraging word for the folk-people, speak up.” <verse eid="ACT 13:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 13:16" />Paul stood up, gestured with his hand, and said:</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 13:16">“Men, Israelites, and Gentile sympathizers to Judaism, listen to what I have to say. <verse eid="ACT 13:16"/>
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 13:17" />The God of this people Israel chose our ancestors and brought them to prominence in the temporary stay
        in Egypt, and by a supernatural intervention in the affairs of mankind brought them out of there <verse eid="ACT 13:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 13:18" />and tolerated them for about forty years in the wilderness. <verse eid="ACT 13:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 13:19" />After destroying seven nations in Canaan, he took possession of their land, <verse eid="ACT 13:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 13:20" />occupying it for about 450 years. After this, He designated ad-hoc rulers until the prophet Samuel came
        on the scene. <verse eid="ACT 13:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 13:21" />And then they asked for a king, and God gave them Saul son of Kish, a man from the clan of Benjamin,
        for forty years. <verse eid="ACT 13:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 13:22" />Once he was removed, He brought David to prominence, making him their king. He went on record and said
        about him, ‘I found David son of Jesse, a man after My heart, one who does everything I ever wanted.’<verse eid="ACT 13:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 13:23" />From out of this fellow’s lineal descendants God brought Israel to a savior named Jesus, according to
        what had been promised, <verse eid="ACT 13:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 13:24" />John having preached ahead of time, before Jesus came on the scene, a baptism, an initiation ceremony
        of a change of heart and of ways, to all the people of Israel. <verse eid="ACT 13:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 13:25" />But as John crossed the finish line and his ministry was waning, he kept on saying, ‘What do you all
        suppose that I am? I am not the One—No—get ahold of this: he who comes after me—I am not worthy to take
        his sandal off.’<verse eid="ACT 13:25" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 13:26" />”Men, comrades, descendants of Abraham’s line, and those Gentiles among you who are Jewish sympathizers:
        the message of this rescue-plan rescuing you from your spiritual malaise has been sent out to you. <verse eid="ACT 13:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 13:27" />The fact is, those who live in Jerusalem along with their rulers, not acknowledging this and the voices
        of the prophets which are read aloud every Sabbath, finished coming to a verdict, <verse eid="ACT 13:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 13:28" />and—without a single one of them finding a reason for the death penalty—asked Pilate to kill Jesus. <verse eid="ACT 13:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 13:29" />Just as all the things noted about him in the Scriptures were fulfilled, they took him down off the wooden
        cross-beam and put him in a tomb— <verse eid="ACT 13:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 13:30" />But God resurrected him from the dead, <verse eid="ACT 13:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 13:31" />the one who for many days was seen by those who accompanied him from Galilee to Jerusalem, by the very
        people who are declaring to the folk-people that this is indeed factual. <verse eid="ACT 13:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 13:32" />And we are delivering the good news to you all, that what was promised to the forefathers has occurred,<verse eid="ACT 13:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 13:33" />because God has fulfilled this among us the descendants, having resurrected Jesus, as there is also a
        verse in the second Psalms which reads:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 13:33"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 13:33">“You are My son:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 13:33">I have begotten you today<verse eid="ACT 13:33"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 13:34" />”Since He resurrected him from the dead, he’s not going to be returning to bodily decomposition ever
        again. This has resulted in the following being the case:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 13:34"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 13:34">“I will give you David’s holy things, his guaranteed things<verse eid="ACT 13:34"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 13:35" />”Consequently, there’s another place where it says:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 13:35"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 13:35">“You will not destine Your Holy-One</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 13:35">To undergo bodily decomposition<verse eid="ACT 13:35"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 13:36" />”Indeed, when his own generation was alive, David attended to the will of God and expired and went to
        be with his ancestors and underwent decomposition, <verse eid="ACT 13:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 13:37" />but the one whom God raised from the dead didn’t undergo decomposition. <verse eid="ACT 13:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 13:38" />So now, let it be known, men, comrades, that through this resurrection forgiveness of sins is being proclaimed
        to you—forgiveness of everything which you have not been justified in doing by the Law of Moses. <verse eid="ACT 13:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 13:39" />By this resurrection, everyone who believes is justified. <verse eid="ACT 13:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 13:40" />So see to it that what’s been spoken by the Old Testament prophets not get the better of you:<verse eid="ACT 13:40" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="ACT 13:41" />”Here they are, the cynics and the scoffers:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 13:41">Gape at them for a moment and then vanish,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 13:41">Because I’m doing something special in your lifetime.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 13:41">There’s no way at all that you would believe what I’m up to,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 13:41">Even if someone were to describe it to you.”<verse eid="ACT 13:41"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="42" style="v" sid="ACT 13:42" />While they were saying goodbye, they kept pleading with him to speak to them on the following Sabbath,
        to talk some more about what was said. <verse eid="ACT 13:42" />
      <verse number="43" style="v" sid="ACT 13:43" />Once they were dismissed from the synagogue service, many of the Jews and the devout proselytes to Judaism
        followed Paul and Barnabas. While certain ones of them in particular were speaking face-to-face with
        them, Paul and Barnabas kept on persuading them to continue in the grace of God.<verse eid="ACT 13:43" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="44" style="v" sid="ACT 13:44" />On the following Sabbath, almost the entire city gathered together to hear the Word of the Lord. <verse eid="ACT 13:44" />
      <verse number="45" style="v" sid="ACT 13:45" />Seeing how many were in the crowd, the Jews were filled with envy and proceeded to say things in opposition
        to what was spoken by Paul, contradicting him and blaspheming him, <verse eid="ACT 13:45" />
      <verse number="46" style="v" sid="ACT 13:46" />and so Paul and Barnabas, speaking to the wider audience, said, “It was necessary to speak the Word of
        God to you first, but since you reject it and render yourselves unworthy of that special fullness of
        life (eternal life), take note: I’m turning to the Gentiles. <verse eid="ACT 13:46" />
      <verse number="47" style="v" sid="ACT 13:47" />You see, the Lord has given you commands to follow like this:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 13:47"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 13:47">“I have positioned you Jews</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 13:47">To be a light for Gentile nations,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 13:47">In order that you be a means of rescue and refuge</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 13:47">To the furthest reaches of the planet.”<verse eid="ACT 13:47"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="48" style="v" sid="ACT 13:48" />Hearing this, the Gentiles proceeded to rejoice and to glorify the Word of the Lord, and the very ones
        who were appointed to eternal life believed.<verse eid="ACT 13:48" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="49" style="v" sid="ACT 13:49" />Now the Word of the Lord kept on being spread throughout the whole country. <verse eid="ACT 13:49" />
      <verse number="50" style="v" sid="ACT 13:50" />The Jews incited the pious women, the ones who were prominent and who were leaders in the city, fomented
        a persecution against Paul and Barnabas, and kicked them out of their district. <verse eid="ACT 13:50" />
      <verse number="51" style="v" sid="ACT 13:51" />They wiped their hands of it and went to Iconium, <verse eid="ACT 13:51" />
      <verse number="52" style="v" sid="ACT 13:52" />and the disciples kept on being filled with a Holy-Spirit-fueled-joy.<verse eid="ACT 13:52" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 13" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 14   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="ACT 14" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 14:1" />In Iconium events occurred along the same lines: they introduced themselves to the members of the synagogue
        and affiliated themselves with it in order to speak before the synagogue so that a great many Jews, and
        not only they but Greek-speaking Jews, would become believers. <verse eid="ACT 14:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 14:2" />The Jews who weren’t converted to the faith went on the offensive against them and polluted the minds
        of the Gentiles, pitting them against the comrades. <verse eid="ACT 14:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 14:3" />So then they stayed a good deal of time speaking openly about the Lord, testifying about the message
        of his grace, allowing miracles to take place through their hands. <verse eid="ACT 14:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 14:4" />The majority of the population was divided: on the one hand there were those of the Jews’ camp; on the
        other hand there were those of the apostles’ camp. <verse eid="ACT 14:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 14:5" />Spontaneously and impulsively, both the Gentiles and the Jews were joined by their rulers and decided
        to attack them and stone them. <verse eid="ACT 14:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 14:6" />Realizing what was going on, they got out of there and fled to the cities of Lycaonian, Lystra and Derbe
        specifically and to the surrounding area. <verse eid="ACT 14:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 14:7" />There they continually shared the good news, the good news of the Gospel.<verse eid="ACT 14:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 14:8" />There was a certain helpless man in Lystra—unable to use his legs—who kept on sitting on the ground all
        the time, lame from the time he was born, one who hadn’t walked around even once. <verse eid="ACT 14:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 14:9" />This fellow heard Paul speaking; after Paul stared at him, and while staring sees that he has the faith
        to escape his affliction, <verse eid="ACT 14:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 14:10" />he said in a loud voice, “Get up on your feet and stand straight up!”—and he proceeded to do just that:
        he sprung up and walked around, <verse eid="ACT 14:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 14:11" />and seeing what Paul did the crowd raised their voices in the Lycaonian language saying, “The gods came
        down to us in the form of these men!”— <verse eid="ACT 14:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 14:12" />and they proceeded to call Barnabas “Zeus” and Paul “Hermes,” since Paul did most of the talking— <verse eid="ACT 14:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 14:13" />and the priest of Zeus, whose temple is situated right before you get to the city, brought bulls and
        the garlands that sacrificial animals are adorned with to the city gates and, joined by the crowds, was
        itching to perform sacrifices.<verse eid="ACT 14:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 14:14" />When the apostles Barnabas and Paul heard this, they tore their garments to show how upset they were
        and rushed out into the crowd yelling, <verse eid="ACT 14:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 14:15" />“Men, why are you doing this? We too are men who experience passion and pain the same way you do, while
        at the same time telling you the good news of turning away from these worthless things to a living God,
        who made the sky, the earth, the sea, and everything along with them, <verse eid="ACT 14:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 14:16" />who in the bygone generations permitted people everywhere to go their own way and do their own thing—<verse eid="ACT 14:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 14:17" />and yet He didn’t leave them void of evidence pointing to Him being up in heaven doing good things and
        being kind, giving you that sweet rain which makes for productive growing seasons, the food injecting
        gladness into your hearts until your hearts are filled to the brim.” <verse eid="ACT 14:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 14:18" />Saying these things just barely caused the crowd to stop performing sacrifices.<verse eid="ACT 14:18" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 14:19" />Now Jews from Antioch and Iconium arrived, talked the crowd into stoning Paul, did just that, and dragged
        him and dragged him until they got outside the city, thinking he was dead. <verse eid="ACT 14:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 14:20" />While his disciples were standing around him in a circle, he got up and went back into the city. The
        next day he left for Derbe accompanied by Barnabas, <verse eid="ACT 14:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 14:21" />and after he proclaimed the good news of the Gospel to that city and made a decent number of disciples
        there, returned to Lystra, then to Iconium, and then to Antioch, <verse eid="ACT 14:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 14:22" />getting the life-being of the disciples to rely on the Lord, encouraging them to stick with the faith
        and advising them by saying that a lot of difficulties and intense pressure will occur and must be endured
        in order to succeed in their life of faith (enter God’s kingdom).<verse eid="ACT 14:22" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 14:23" />Now having prayed, combining fasting with the prayer, he went church by church and appointed presiding
        boards, and the Lord kept on adding more people to those who had already come to believe. <verse eid="ACT 14:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 14:24" />They passed through Pisidia and came to Pamphylia, <verse eid="ACT 14:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 14:25" />and after speaking the Word of God in Perga, they went down to Attalia. <verse eid="ACT 14:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 14:26" />From there they sailed to Antioch, from where they started the trip, and were commended for the mission
        they accomplished by the grace of God. <verse eid="ACT 14:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 14:27" />After getting there and gathering the church together, they proceeded to report what God did, as He was
        with them on the trip, and to report that He opened a door of faith for the Gentiles (i.e. He created
        an opportunity for the Gentiles to join the faith). <verse eid="ACT 14:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 14:28" />They continued to spend time—and no small amount of it—with the disciples.<verse eid="ACT 14:28" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 14" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 15   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="ACT 15" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 15:1" />A few key people came over from Judea and proceeded to tell them how things ought to be done, instructing
        the comrades that you’ve got to be circumcised in Moses (i.e. become Jewish and commit to obeying the
        commandments in the Law of Moses), or else you can’t be saved (i.e. receive Christ and walk with him).<verse eid="ACT 15:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 15:2" />No small disagreement and debate occurred between Paul and Barnabas on one side and them on the other,
        and they arranged for Paul, Barnabas, and certain others from among them to go to the apostles and the
        presiding board in Jerusalem in regard to this debate. <verse eid="ACT 15:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 15:3" />So then those sent forth by the church kept creating tremendous joy among the comrades as they were passing
        through Phoenicia and Samaria recounting the Gentiles’ conversion. <verse eid="ACT 15:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 15:4" />Arriving in Jerusalem, they were welcomed by the church, the apostles, and the presiding board, and reported
        what God was doing in conjunction with them.<verse eid="ACT 15:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 15:5" />Now a few who belonged to the Pharisee-sect and who had become believers stood up to speak and said that
        the Gentile believers must be circumcised (and thus convert to Judaism) and be ordered to adhere to the
        Law of Moses, <verse eid="ACT 15:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 15:6" />and the apostles and the presiding board got together to look into this matter. <verse eid="ACT 15:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 15:7" />After much debate took place, Peter stood up and told them:</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 15:7">“Men, comrades: you understand that from the very start (our start that is), God chose that the Gentiles
        hear the Gospel through my mouth and become believers. <verse eid="ACT 15:7"/>
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 15:8" />God, the Knower-Of-The-Heart, went on record and told them that He would give them the baptism of the
        Holy Spirit just like He gave it to us. <verse eid="ACT 15:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 15:9" />After their hearts were cleansed by faith, no one discriminated against them. <verse eid="ACT 15:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 15:10" />So at this point in time, you’re trying God’s patience (testing God) by placing an unnecessary burden
        on the disciples (putting a yoke on the disciples’ necks), one which neither our ancestors nor we were
        strong enough to bear. <verse eid="ACT 15:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 15:11" />No—it’s through the grace of the Lord Jesus that one exercises faith to be saved from their sin following
        the same pattern as those people did.”<verse eid="ACT 15:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 15:12" />The whole lot of them fell silent and began to listen to Barnabas and Paul explain the miracles that
        God did among the Gentiles through them. <verse eid="ACT 15:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 15:13" />After their silence, James responded, “Men, comrades, listen to me. <verse eid="ACT 15:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 15:14" />Simon explained the way that, for the first time, God paid a visit—a caring, helping type of visit—in
        order to form a unique group of people from out of the Gentiles, a people consecrated to everything He
        represents. <verse eid="ACT 15:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 15:15" />The words of the prophets agree with this, as it’s written:<verse eid="ACT 15:15" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 15:16" />”’After this occurs, I will return</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 15:16">And rebuild David’s fallen condo</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 15:16">And rebuild what remains of it</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 15:16">And restore it,<verse eid="ACT 15:16"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 15:17" />So that what’s left of the people</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 15:17">Just might seek out the Lord,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 15:17">Plus all of the Gentiles upon whom</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 15:17">My mark of ownership was assigned to,’</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 15:17">Says the Lord who’s doing this<verse eid="ACT 15:17"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 15:18" />and Who’s been making this known from eternity past.<verse eid="ACT 15:18" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 15:19" />”Therefore I decided not to bother those who are of Gentile origin who are turning to God, <verse eid="ACT 15:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 15:20" />but instead to write them letters which tell them to abstain from the detestable things forbidden by
        of the Law of Moses: from things polluted by idols, from bizarre sexual immorality, and from drinking
        the blood remaining in the body of an animal after it’s been killed by having its neck broken. <verse eid="ACT 15:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 15:21" />You see, going back to ancient times, the Law of Moses has always had those who preach it, as it’s being
        read aloud in the synagogues in city after city, Sabbath after Sabbath.”<verse eid="ACT 15:21" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 15:22" />Then the apostles and the presiding board in conjunction with the entire church decided what was best
        to do and chose men from among them to send with Paul and Barnabas to Antioch, namely Judas, who goes
        by Barsabbas, and Silas, men who were leaders among their comrades, <verse eid="ACT 15:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 15:23" />and wrote a certified letter so there would be no doubt of its authenticity,</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 15:23">“The apostles and the presiding board, comrades: to the comrades up and down Antioch, Syria, and Cilicia,
        those who are of Gentile origin. Greetings! <verse eid="ACT 15:23"/>
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 15:24" />Because we heard that some of our own people have of their own initiative ventured out and troubled you
        with remarks unsettling to your mind, people who have not been issued instructions to do so, <verse eid="ACT 15:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 15:25" />all of us were in agreement in deciding what was best to do and chose comrades to send you who will accompany
        our beloved Barnabas and Paul, <verse eid="ACT 15:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 15:26" />men who have dedicated their lives to to all that our Lord Jesus Christ stands for. <verse eid="ACT 15:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 15:27" />So we have sent Judas and Silas, and they will report the same as what is written here through word-of-mouth.<verse eid="ACT 15:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 15:28" />The fact is, the Holy Spirit and we thought it best not to make you shoulder any more burden than these
        items which we’re listing here, which are absolutely necessary: <verse eid="ACT 15:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 15:29" />abstain from food sacrificed to idols, from slaughtering an animal with the intent of drinking its blood,
        and from bizarre sexual immorality.”<verse eid="ACT 15:29" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 15:30" />So then, once they were released, they went up to Antioch, gathered the community of believers together,
        and gave them the letter. <verse eid="ACT 15:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 15:31" />After it was read they rejoiced at the advice, exhortation, and encouragement. <verse eid="ACT 15:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 15:32" />Judas and Silas as well exhorted and encouraged the comrades by means of many short prophetic messages
        (they being prophets in their own right) and put them on a firm footing. <verse eid="ACT 15:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 15:33" />After putting in time there, they were released in good standing from the comrades back to the ones who
        sent them.<verse eid="ACT 15:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 15:34" /> <verse eid="ACT 15:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 15:35" />Paul and Barnabas continued on in Antioch teaching and evangelizing the Word of the Lord, and many others
        did too.<verse eid="ACT 15:35" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 15:36" />After some days Paul said to Barnabas, “Let’s return to the cities in which we proclaimed the word of
        the Lord and go from city to city visiting the comrades there and see how they’re getting on in their
        faith.” <verse eid="ACT 15:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 15:37" />Now Barnabas was wanting to take Mark (i.e. John who goes by Mark) along with them too, <verse eid="ACT 15:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 15:38" />but Paul was thinking it fitting not to take Mark along, the guy who deserted them, leaving them at Pamphylia
        and ceasing to accompany them on their mission. <verse eid="ACT 15:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 15:39" />A sharp disagreement took place to the point where they parted ways from each other, and Barnabas took
        Mark and sailed for Cyprus. <verse eid="ACT 15:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 15:40" />Paul called on Silas to accompany him and left, after being handed over to the Lord’s grace for safe
        keeping by the comrades. <verse eid="ACT 15:40" />
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="ACT 15:41" />He went on and on passing through Syria putting the churches on a firm footing.<verse eid="ACT 15:41" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 15" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 16   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="ACT 16" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 16:1" />Paul arrived in Derbe and then in Lystra and stumbled across a particular disciple there named Timothy,
        the son of a Jewish woman who was a believer in Christ but whose father was a Greek-speaking westerner,<verse eid="ACT 16:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 16:2" />whose good reputation was attested to by the comrades in Lystra and Iconium. <verse eid="ACT 16:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 16:3" />Paul wanted this fellow to leave with him, and took him to get circumcised (symbolizing his conversion
        to Judaism and the beginning of his obeying the Law of Moses) because of the Jews that were in that locale.
        You see, they all knew that he had a father who was a westerner. <verse eid="ACT 16:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 16:4" />As they were travelling through the cities, they committed themselves to keeping an eye on the issues
        that had been decided by the apostles and the presiding board in Jerusalem. <verse eid="ACT 16:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 16:5" />So then the churches were being strengthened in the faith and were increasing in number day by day.<verse eid="ACT 16:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 16:6" />After passing through Phrygia and the province of Galatia, they were prevented from speaking the Word
        by the Holy Spirit in the Roman province of Asia, in which Phrygia is located and which borders Galatia.<verse eid="ACT 16:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 16:7" />After they went over to Mysia, they kept on trying to go to Bithynia, but the Spirit of Jesus didn’t
        allow them to. <verse eid="ACT 16:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 16:8" />After making an appearance in Mysia, they went over to Troas. <verse eid="ACT 16:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 16:9" />A vision was seen by Paul over the course of a night: some Macedonian man stood planted in one place
        begging him, “Cut across the Aegean Sea to Macedonia and help us out.” <verse eid="ACT 16:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 16:10" />Like he saw in the vision, we immediately sought to depart for Macedonia surmising that God had summoned
        us there to evangelize them.<verse eid="ACT 16:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 16:11" />They sailed from Troas straight to Samothrace, and the next day to Neapolis, <verse eid="ACT 16:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 16:12" />and from there to Philippi, which is a leading colony-city in that part of Macedonia. We were keeping
        at it in this city for a number of days, <verse eid="ACT 16:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 16:13" />and on the Sabbath we went out the city gates and down by the river, figuring it would be a good place
        to pray. We sat down and proceeded to speak to the women who had formed a group there. <verse eid="ACT 16:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 16:14" />A particular woman named Lydia, a dealer in luxurious cloth, a Thyatirian sympathizer and near-convert
        to Judaism, was listening and listening, as the Lord opened her heart to heed what was being spoken by
        Paul. <verse eid="ACT 16:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 16:15" />As she was baptized (and her household was too), she asked earnestly, “If you’ve come to the conclusion
        that I’m faithful to the Lord, come stay at my house,” and she wouldn’t take “no” for an answer.<verse eid="ACT 16:15" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 16:16" />Now it so happened as they were going to a prayer meeting, that some teenage servant-girl who had a spirit
        of divination accosted them, one who brought her bosses a hefty sum of money by telling fortunes. <verse eid="ACT 16:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 16:17" />She followed Paul around and kept on yelling, “These men are servants of the Most High God, ones who
        are proclaiming what you need to do to set things right with God,” about them, <verse eid="ACT 16:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 16:18" />and she kept this up for several days. Paul, exasperated, turned to the spirit and said, “By the authority
        vested in me by Jesus Christ, I command you to leave her!”—and it left her that moment. <verse eid="ACT 16:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 16:19" />Seeing that any hope of generating income departed when the spirit departed, her bosses seized Paul and
        Silas and dragged them to the main town square to where the rulers were. <verse eid="ACT 16:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 16:20" />They brought them to the magistrates and said, “These here men are agitating our city, seeing that they’re
        Jews. <verse eid="ACT 16:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 16:21" />They proclaim—impose upon us—sets of rules which are impermissible for us to embrace, seeing that we’re
        Romans.” <verse eid="ACT 16:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 16:22" />The crowd joined in on attacking them. The magistrates flew off the handle and ordered them to be beaten
        with rods, <verse eid="ACT 16:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 16:23" />and after wounding them with many blows threw them in jail and ordered the jail keeper to lock them up
        tightly, <verse eid="ACT 16:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 16:24" />who, once he received such a stern order, shuttled them deep inside the jail and put their legs in stocks.<verse eid="ACT 16:24" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 16:25" />Towards the middle of the night while Paul and Silas were praying, they kept on singing praises to God
        (and the prisoners kept hearing from them). <verse eid="ACT 16:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 16:26" />A severe earthquake took place suddenly, one of such a magnitude that it shook the foundation of the
        jailhouse, and immediately all the doors were opened, and all of the stocks, chains, and fetters were
        unfastened. <verse eid="ACT 16:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 16:27" />The jail keeper was awakened, and seeing all the jail’s doors opened, drew his sword and was about to
        kill himself, thinking that all the prisoners had escaped, <verse eid="ACT 16:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 16:28" />but Paul called out to him in a loud voice, “Don’t hurt yourself; we’re all still here, you see.” <verse eid="ACT 16:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 16:29" />He called for a torch, ran in, and, trembling, fell before Paul and Silas. <verse eid="ACT 16:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 16:30" />He brought them out and said, “Sirs, what must I do to be saved from my wretched spiritual and moral
        condition?” <verse eid="ACT 16:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 16:31" />They said, “Believe in the Lord Jesus, and you and your household will be saved,” <verse eid="ACT 16:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 16:32" />and he told him the Word of the Lord, him together with his entire household. <verse eid="ACT 16:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 16:33" />At that moment in the middle of the night he took them into his personal care and dressed their wounds.
        With no further delay he was baptized, he and all who were under his authority, <verse eid="ACT 16:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 16:34" />and he brought them upstairs to his apartment and sat them down at his table and put out a spread of
        food. He rejoiced with his entire household, as they all arrived at the point where they had faith in
        God.<verse eid="ACT 16:34" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 16:35" />Now days went by and the magistrates sent the constables saying, “Let those men out now.” <verse eid="ACT 16:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 16:36" />The jail keeper informed Paul, “The magistrates have sent word so that you can go free. So at this time,
        leave and go in peace (i.e., go your way free of conflict, duress, or affliction).” <verse eid="ACT 16:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 16:37" />Paul said to the jail keeper, “They beat us in public without a decision handed down from a court proceeding—men
        who are Roman citizens—threw us in jail—and now they want to kick us out of jail in secret? No—not a
        chance—have them personally come over and bring us out themselves.” <verse eid="ACT 16:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 16:38" />The constables told the magistrates these remarks; those who heard this became afraid that they’re indeed
        Roman citizens. <verse eid="ACT 16:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 16:39" />They came and pleaded with them, brought them out, and kept on asking them to leave the city. <verse eid="ACT 16:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 16:40" />After leaving the jail, they went to Lidia’s house and were hosted there, and once they saw comrades,
        they comforted them, and they finally departed.<verse eid="ACT 16:40" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 16" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 17   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="ACT 17" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 17:1" />After travelling through Amphipolis and Apollonis, they came to Thessalonica, where there was a synagogue.<verse eid="ACT 17:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 17:2" />For three Sabbaths Paul went to the synagogue and approached those who meet in the synagogue, as he was
        his habit of doing, and reasoned with them from the Scriptures, <verse eid="ACT 17:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 17:3" />going through detail after detail, example after example presenting to them that the Messiah, the Christ,
        had to suffer and be raised from the dead and that this person Jesus is the Messiah…”The one I’m making
        known to you.” <verse eid="ACT 17:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 17:4" />Some of them were persuaded and joined in with Paul and Silas, including a great many of the devout,
        God-fearing westerners (i.e., Greek-speaking near-Jewish converts), and no small number of the leading
        women.<verse eid="ACT 17:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 17:5" />Overtaken by the passions of jealousy, the Jews went so far as to recruit some hooligans from the hangouts
        in the middle of town, formed a mob out of them, and proceeded to cause a commotion. After attacking
        Jason’s house, they started to try to parade them over to the rabble. <verse eid="ACT 17:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 17:6" />Not finding them there, they proceeded to drag Jason and some of the comrades over to the city officials,
        all the while shouting, “Those guys who’ve ripped through the civilized world like a tornado have arrived
        here, <verse eid="ACT 17:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 17:7" />the ones Jason has taken in as guests. All these guys engage in activities that violate Caesar’s ordinances,
        claiming that there’s a different king named Jesus.” <verse eid="ACT 17:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 17:8" />Hearing this disturbed the crowd and the city officials, <verse eid="ACT 17:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 17:9" />and they collected the fine commensurate for the crime from Jason and from the rest of them and released
        them.<verse eid="ACT 17:9" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 17:10" />Wasting no time, the comrades immediately sent both Paul and Silas away to Berea during the night, who,
        after arriving and while being away, went to the synagogue. <verse eid="ACT 17:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 17:11" />Now these people were more open-minded, better educated, and had more sophisticated thought processes
        than the Thessalonians, being individuals in particular who were totally gung-ho to embrace the Word,
        who day after day examined the Scriptures to see if all these things which Paul preached were in fact
        true. <verse eid="ACT 17:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 17:12" />So then, many of them believed, including many of the prominent westerner-women and men—no small number
        in total. <verse eid="ACT 17:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 17:13" />Now as the Jews from Thessalonica became aware that the Word of God was being proclaimed in Berea, they
        went there as well to shake up the crowds and to cause them to feel disturbed. <verse eid="ACT 17:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 17:14" />Immediately then the comrades sent Paul away, having him walk until he reached the ocean, while Silas
        and Timothy remained there. <verse eid="ACT 17:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 17:15" />Those who escorted Paul escorted him until they got to Athens and received an order from Paul destined
        for Silas and Timothy that they should leave and come to him as quickly as possible.<verse eid="ACT 17:15" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 17:16" />While Paul was waiting for them to arrive, his spirit was provoked and enraged seeing the city overrun
        with idols; <verse eid="ACT 17:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 17:17" />so then he kept on reasoning with and disputing with the Jews and the devout sympathizers of Judaism
        in the synagogue and day in, day out with whoever happened to be in the city square.<verse eid="ACT 17:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 17:18" />Now some of the Epicurean and Stoic philosophers engaged him in a discussion; some proceeded to say,
        “What point is this dilettante-intellectual here trying to make?”, but others said, “He seems to be a
        preacher who preaches about weird imps.” They were saying this because he was spreading the word about
        Jesus and his resurrection, <verse eid="ACT 17:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 17:19" />and they took him and brought him to a meeting of the Areopagus council on Mars Hill, saying, “May we
        get up to speed on what the new-fangled teaching taught by you is all about? <verse eid="ACT 17:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 17:20" />You see, what you’re filling our heads with is strange, so we wish to understand how this fits into the
        big picture.” <verse eid="ACT 17:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 17:21" />(Now all Athenians and foreigners who reside in Athens have no time for anything other than talking about
        or hearing about something novel.)<verse eid="ACT 17:21" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 17:22" />Paul stood in center-stage before everyone at the Areopagus and said, “Men, Athenians, what I observe
        of you is that you’re exceptionally devout in every regard; <verse eid="ACT 17:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 17:23" />you see, looking up at your objects of veneration while passing through, I ran across an elevated-altar
        on which is inscribed, ‘To an unknown God.’ You offer up religious devotion to that which is unknown
        to you, so I’ll have you know this: <verse eid="ACT 17:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 17:24" />The God who made the world and everything in it—this sky and earth that you see all around you—is a lord
        who does not dwell in man-made temples, <verse eid="ACT 17:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 17:25" />nor needs the hands-on attendance of healing treatments, as He Himself gives life and breath and everything
        to everyone and everything, <verse eid="ACT 17:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 17:26" />and in addition made all the nations, races, and ethnic groups that you see living all over the planet
        out of one person, after delineating arranged seasons and the extent to which they linger, <verse eid="ACT 17:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 17:27" />and made all the nations to seek after God if perchance they might reach out to touch and handle Him
        and in so doing find Him. <verse eid="ACT 17:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 17:28" />You see, in Him we live and are set in motion and have our existence, as some of your own poets have
        stated too,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 17:28"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 17:28">“For we are God’s offspring indeed<verse eid="ACT 17:28"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 17:29" />”So an offspring which gets its existence from God ought not consider the Divine Deity to be comparable
        to a figure of some sort made with gold, silver, or stone, a craftsman’s sculpture and the reflection
        of a person’s conceptualization. <verse eid="ACT 17:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 17:30" />So then, having overlooked the epochs of ignorance, at this time God is ordering all people everywhere
        to go about having a change of heart and of ways, <verse eid="ACT 17:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 17:31" />because a day has been marked on the calendar in which He’s going to judge the civilized world from the
        perspective of Him being always right and of Him expecting people to do right— judge the world by a man
        whom He designated, offering assurance to everyone that this is indeed the case by having resurrected
        him from the dead.”<verse eid="ACT 17:31" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 17:32" />Once they heard “life-after-death” (i.e. the resurrection of the dead), some began to sneer, but others
        said, “We’d like to hear from you on this subject again, for sure.” <verse eid="ACT 17:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 17:33" />And with that, Paul left center-stage. <verse eid="ACT 17:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 17:34" />Now some of the men joined up with him and became believers, among whom were Dionysius, a member of the
        Areopagite, and a woman named Damaris, and others with them. <verse eid="ACT 17:34" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 17" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 18   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="ACT 18" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 18:1" />After this Paul got himself away from Athens and went to Corinth. <verse eid="ACT 18:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 18:2" />He found a certain Jew by the name of Aquila, who grew up in Pontus but had recently come from Italy,
        and Priscilla his wife, who had both come because of Claudius’s order to expel all the Jews from Rome,
        and went to them. <verse eid="ACT 18:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 18:3" />Being of the same trade, he proceeded to take up residence near them and to start working. In this regard
        they were tent makers by trade. <verse eid="ACT 18:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 18:4" />He kept on reasoning and trying to win over those in the synagogue every Sabbath, Sabbath after Sabbath,
        and was persuading Jews and westerners time and again.<verse eid="ACT 18:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 18:5" />As they (Silas and Timothy) came over from Macedonia, Paul continued to devote himself to the preaching
        of the Word, solemnly declaring to the Jews that Jesus is the Messiah. <verse eid="ACT 18:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 18:6" />As they were deployed against him hurling abuses, he shook out his clothing signaling his having nothing
        to do with them and said, “You’re to blame for your own destruction! I’m wiping my hands of it! From
        now on, I’m going to the Gentiles.” <verse eid="ACT 18:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 18:7" />He left there and was taken into the home of someone named Titius Justus, a pious God-worshipper, whose
        house was next-door to the synagogue.<verse eid="ACT 18:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 18:8" />Now the synagogue head Crispus came to have faith in the Lord together with his entire household, and
        hearing this, many of the Corinthians started to have faith in the Lord and were being baptized. <verse eid="ACT 18:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 18:9" />The Lord spoke to Paul at night in a dream, “Don’t fall into fear—no—keep on talking and don’t fall silent,<verse eid="ACT 18:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 18:10" />because I am with you and no one can lay a hand on you to harm you, because a dedicated group of people
        are with me—a great many of them—in this city.” <verse eid="ACT 18:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 18:11" />So for a year and a half he filled the role of teacher among them, teaching them the Word of God.<verse eid="ACT 18:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 18:12" />While Gallio was the Roman proconsul of Achaia, the Jews, united in heart, mind, and purpose, jumped
        Paul and brought him to the courtroom where Gallio sat as judge, <verse eid="ACT 18:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 18:13" />saying “This guy uses the Law of Moses to convince people to not be piously devoted to God and to not
        worship Him.” <verse eid="ACT 18:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 18:14" />Just as Paul was about to open his mouth to speak, Gallio said to the Jews, “Oh you Jews! If this really
        was some wrong-doing or nefarious crime, I would’ve put up with this from you while complying with the
        methodology of a court proceeding. <verse eid="ACT 18:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 18:15" />But issues concerning concepts, authority, reputations, law, etc. that are specific to you are to be
        monitored by you; I do not wish to be a judge who decides these matters,” <verse eid="ACT 18:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 18:16" />and dismissed their case. <verse eid="ACT 18:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 18:17" />Everyone got ahold of the synagogue head Sosthenes and began to beat him right there in the courtroom,
        and Gallio had no intention of doing anything about it.<verse eid="ACT 18:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 18:18" />Paul continued to stay with the comrades for a good number of days more, said goodbye to them, and proceeded
        to sail to Syria, accompanied by Priscilla and Aquila, after shaving his head in Cenchreae, since, you
        see, he was holding fast to the restrictions that come with an Old Testament pledge called a Nazirite
        vow. <verse eid="ACT 18:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 18:19" />They arrived in Ephesus, and he left those others there, but he for his part went to the synagogue and
        proceeded to reason with the Jews. <verse eid="ACT 18:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 18:20" />When they asked him to stay for an even longer time, he wouldn’t acquiesce, <verse eid="ACT 18:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 18:21" />but said goodbye instead, “If it’s God’s will, I’ll come back and visit you again” and put out to sea
        from Ephesus. <verse eid="ACT 18:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 18:22" />After he went down to Caesarea and went over and greeted the church, he went down to Antioch. <verse eid="ACT 18:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 18:23" />After spending some time there, he left and went through one part of Galatia after another and Phrygia
        too, putting the disciples on a firm footing.<verse eid="ACT 18:23" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 18:24" />Now a certain Jew who grew up in Alexandrian named Apollos, a man who was quite the scholar, arrived
        in Ephesus, being proficient and capable in the Scriptures. <verse eid="ACT 18:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 18:25" />This fellow was schooled in the Way of the Lord, and as he was fervent—boiling-over really—in the Spirit,
        he went about speaking and kept meticulously teaching on the subject of Jesus, understanding John’s baptism
        only. <verse eid="ACT 18:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 18:26" />In addition this fellow began to speak boldly and freely in the synagogue. Once Priscilla and Aquila
        heard him, they took him aside and correctly explained to him the Way of the Lord. <verse eid="ACT 18:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 18:27" />As he was wanting to tour in Achaia, prompted to do so the comrades wrote a letter of recommendation
        to the disciples there to receive him, who when he arrived was joined in tight unison with those who
        had become believers through the grace of God. <verse eid="ACT 18:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 18:28" />The fact is, he kept on overwhelming the Jews in public with refutations, vehemently showing with specifics
        through the Scriptures that Jesus is the Messiah.<verse eid="ACT 18:28" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 18" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 19   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="ACT 19" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 19:1" />Now what happened when Apollos was in Corinth was that Paul passed through the highland districts and
        came to Ephesus. He found some disciples off to the side there <verse eid="ACT 19:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 19:2" />and said,</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 19:2">“Did you get the baptism in the Holy Spirit now that you’ve become believers?”</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 19:2">They replied, “Not only did we not receive it, but we’ve not heard of there being a baptism in the Holy
        Spirit.”<verse eid="ACT 19:2"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 19:3" />And to that Paul said, “What have you been baptized into (i.e., into what covenant have you been initiated)?”</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 19:3">They said, “Into John the Baptist’s baptism.”<verse eid="ACT 19:3"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 19:4" />Paul said, “John’s baptism was an initiation into a covenant of a change of heart and of ways, while
        at the same time he was baptizing he was telling the people to look to the Coming-One who comes later
        so that they would believe in him. This person is Jesus.”<verse eid="ACT 19:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 19:5" />After hearing this, they were baptized by the authority of the Lord Jesus. <verse eid="ACT 19:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 19:6" />When Paul laid his hands on them, the Holy Spirit came upon them as they were baptized in the Holy Spirit,
        and along with that they began speaking in tongues and speaking Holy-Spirit-inspired words. <verse eid="ACT 19:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 19:7" />All told, there were about twelve men (not including women and children) there.<verse eid="ACT 19:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 19:8" />After he introduced himself to the synagogue and became affiliated with the people there, for three months
        he proceeded to openly and freely reason with and attempt to convince the members about things pertaining
        to God’s involvement with mankind. <verse eid="ACT 19:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 19:9" />As some kept on getting more and more resistant and turned-off, bad-mouthing the Way in front of the
        majority, he parted ways with them and pulled the disciples away, while day by day reasoning in the lecture
        forum in Tyrannus. <verse eid="ACT 19:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 19:10" />Now this occurred for two years, to the extent that everyone living in the Roman province of Asia heard
        the Word of the Lord, both Jews and westerners, <verse eid="ACT 19:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 19:11" />and God kept performing miracles through the hands of Paul, <verse eid="ACT 19:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 19:12" />even to the extent that cloths, handkerchiefs, and tradesman’s aprons which he had bare-skin, physical
        contact with which were taken from him, and when laid over those who were run-down from an illness or
        whatnot, the diseases left them, and the Evil Spirits went out of them.<verse eid="ACT 19:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 19:13" />There were these roaming Jewish exorcists who attempted to invoke the delegated authority of the Lord
        Jesus Christ over people who have Evil Spirits by saying, “I exorcise you all by the authority of Jesus
        whom Paul preaches!” <verse eid="ACT 19:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 19:14" />Now there were seven sons of a certain Jewish chief priest named Sceva doing this to an Evil Spirit one
        day, <verse eid="ACT 19:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 19:15" />and the Evil Spirit replied to them, “I’m familiar with Jesus and I know about Paul, but who are you?”,<verse eid="ACT 19:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 19:16" />and the man who had the Evil Spirit in him assaulted them and dominated and overpowered them to the extent
        that they fled the building half-naked, bruised, and beaten.<verse eid="ACT 19:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 19:17" />This became known to all the Jews who were living in Ephesus and to the westerners as well, and fear
        fell upon all of them, and what the Lord Jesus is all about began to be magnified, <verse eid="ACT 19:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 19:18" />and many of those who had become believers began confessing out loud what their sinful habits are, telling
        everyone about them. <verse eid="ACT 19:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 19:19" />A sizeable number of those involved in the occult gathered their books together and burned them up in
        front of everyone. When they added up the cost of the books, they arrived at a figure of $6.25 million.<verse eid="ACT 19:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 19:20" />In this way—according to the Lord’s awesome power—the Word kept on growing and getting stronger.<verse eid="ACT 19:20" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 19:21" />As these things ran their course, Paul determined by the Spirit to go through Macedonia and the Roman
        province of Asia in the course of going to Jerusalem, having said, “After I’ve been there, I’ve got to
        see Rome too.” <verse eid="ACT 19:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 19:22" />He sent two of his helping-assistants, Timothy and Erastus, on ahead, while he, on the other hand, stayed
        back for a period of time in Asia.<verse eid="ACT 19:22" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 19:23" />Meanwhile, no trivial disturbance took place with regard to the Way. <verse eid="ACT 19:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 19:24" />You see, a certain fellow by the name of Demetrius, a silversmith by trade who made silver shrines of
        the Greek goddess Artemis which generated a not-so-insubstantial income for the guild, <verse eid="ACT 19:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 19:25" />gathered everyone connected with this line of work together and said, “Gentlemen, you know that our well-being
        comes from this trade, <verse eid="ACT 19:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 19:26" />and you see for yourself that this Paul-guy is talking a good number of people in Ephesus—and in nearly
        all of Asia—into disregarding and shunning our handiwork, claiming that man-made objects are not gods.<verse eid="ACT 19:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 19:27" />Not only does this threaten that our profession will become disreputable, but it also threatens that
        the temple of the great goddess Artemis will lose all of its prestige and all this will wind up destroying
        her magnificence, she whom the entire province of Asia and the civilized world worships.”<verse eid="ACT 19:27" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 19:28" />Once they heard this, they were filled with rage and shouted, “The Ephesians’ Artemis is awesome!” <verse eid="ACT 19:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 19:29" />The city was filled with turmoil, and, once they caught Paul’s Macedonian travelling companions Gaius
        and Aristarchus, they all together rushed to the theater. <verse eid="ACT 19:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 19:30" />Paul was wanting to engage the mob, but the disciples wouldn’t let him. <verse eid="ACT 19:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 19:31" />Some of the public officials, being his friends, sent word to him begging him not to venture into the
        theater. <verse eid="ACT 19:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 19:32" />Some kept shouting one thing, some another thing. The fact is, the throng was confused; most of them
        didn’t know why they’d gathered together. <verse eid="ACT 19:32" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 19:33" />The crowd pinned the blame on Alexander, who was pushed to the front by the Jews. Alexander motioned
        to the mob with his hand so that he could begin talking his way out of the situation. <verse eid="ACT 19:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 19:34" />Recognizing that he’s a Jew, for about two hours they shouted a singular chant, “The Ephesians’ Artemis
        is awesome!” <verse eid="ACT 19:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 19:35" />After hushing the crowd, the city clerk said, “Gentlemen, fellow Ephesians, show me one person who doesn’t
        know that the Ephesians’ city is home to and protector and custodian of Artemis the Awesome, the image
        which fell down from Zeus. <verse eid="ACT 19:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 19:36" />Since this is absolutely the case, we’ve got to settle down and not do anything rash. <verse eid="ACT 19:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 19:37" />You see, you brought these men who are neither temple-robbers nor blasphemers of our goddess here against
        their wills. <verse eid="ACT 19:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 19:38" />Now if Demetrius along with his fellow tradesmen really have a complaint to levy against anyone, there’s
        such a person called a ‘proconsul’—let them take it before him. <verse eid="ACT 19:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 19:39" />But if that’s not good enough for you, whatever it is you’re wanting to have done will have to be resolved
        through the court system. <verse eid="ACT 19:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 19:40" />The fact is, based on what’s taken place today, we’re in jeopardy of being accused of rioting, since
        we have no good excuse for what we’ve done.”<verse eid="ACT 19:40" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="ACT 19:41" />After he said this, he dismissed the throng.<verse eid="ACT 19:41" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 19" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 20   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="ACT 20" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 20:1" />After the riot stopped Paul sent for the disciples, and once he encouraged them and after a going-away
        get-together, he left for Macedonia. <verse eid="ACT 20:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 20:2" />After passing through those parts and encouraging them with many a message, he went to Greece, <verse eid="ACT 20:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 20:3" />and after he’d put in three months there, a plot by the Jews against him materialized while he was about
        to set sail for Syria; he wound up making the decision to return via Macedonia.<verse eid="ACT 20:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 20:4" />Now accompanying him were Pyrrhus’s son Sopater from Berea, Aristarchus and Secundus from Thessalonica,
        Gaius from Derbe, Timothy, and Tychicus and Trophimus from the Roman province of Asia. <verse eid="ACT 20:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 20:5" />These fellows went out ahead and waited for us in Troas. <verse eid="ACT 20:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 20:6" />We set sail from Philippi after the multi-day Feast of Unleavened Bread ended, and by the time five days
        or so went by met up with those in Troas, where we stayed on for seven days.<verse eid="ACT 20:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 20:7" />On a Sunday when we gathered to break bread (i.e., have a communion meal while enjoying each other’s
        company), Paul kept on explaining to them in depth the logic behind what he taught, pointing out to them
        the logical fallacies of the opposing points of view, and in general covering a given subject with them
        from top to bottom. Because he was planning on leaving the next day, he was lengthening the lesson until
        midnight.<verse eid="ACT 20:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 20:8" />Now in the upstairs room in which they were gathered, there were enough lamps to provide a sufficient
        amount of lighting, <verse eid="ACT 20:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 20:9" />and there was a teenager there named Eutychus sitting on the window sill who fell deep asleep while Paul
        was going into more and more explanations, and who, when he was woken up, fell out of the third floor
        and was pronounced dead on the spot. <verse eid="ACT 20:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 20:10" />Paul went down, vigorously attended to him, took him in his arms, and said, “Don’t make a commotion—he’s
        alive, you see.” <verse eid="ACT 20:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 20:11" />He went back up, prayed over the meal, ate to his heart’s content, and spoke until dawn: That’s the manner
        in which he departed. <verse eid="ACT 20:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 20:12" />They took the lad away—and he was alive when they did—and were relieved in no small way.<verse eid="ACT 20:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 20:13" />We went on ahead and got on the ship and sailed to Assos, intending to take on Paul there as a passenger;
        you see, he had arranged for things to be done that way, while he himself planned to travel by foot.<verse eid="ACT 20:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 20:14" />When he met us in Assos, he boarded, and we went to Mitylene, <verse eid="ACT 20:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 20:15" />and from there caught an outbound wind the following day and arrived at a place across from Chios. The
        following day we cut across to Samos, and the day after that arrived in Miletus. <verse eid="ACT 20:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 20:16" />You see, Paul had weighed the options and decided to sail past Ephesus, in order to not waste time in
        Asia; the fact is, he was in a hurry to get to Jerusalem in time for the Pentecost holiday, if possible.<verse eid="ACT 20:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 20:17" />From Miletus Paul sent a message to Ephesus and summoned the church governing board together to meet
        with him when he got there. <verse eid="ACT 20:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 20:18" />When they met up with him, he told them, “Starting with the first day I set foot in Asia, you know how
        I’ve spent the entire time with you, <verse eid="ACT 20:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 20:19" />serving the Lord in total humility and self-abasement and in tears and during the hard times of the plots
        fomented against me by the Jews, <verse eid="ACT 20:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 20:20" />as I did not shirk a bit in telling you the things which are a benefit to you, teaching you in public
        and indoors privately, <verse eid="ACT 20:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 20:21" />solemnly declaring to both the Jews and the Gentiles a change of heart and of ways in relation to God
        and declaring faith in our Lord Jesus. <verse eid="ACT 20:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 20:22" />Take note of this: I’ve been compelled by the Spirit to go to Jerusalem; what I’ll be confronted with
        there, I do not know. <verse eid="ACT 20:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 20:23" />Nevertheless, in city after city the Holy Spirit solemnly goes on record to tell me that bonds and afflictions
        await me. <verse eid="ACT 20:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 20:24" />But—no—I have not uttered a peep about how precious my life is to me as I finish my race and complete
        the ministry which I received from the Lord Jesus, to thoroughly declare the good-news-message of the
        grace of God.<verse eid="ACT 20:24" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 20:25" />”Take note of this: I know that all of you—you whom I was preaching the Kingdom of God to while passing
        through the area—will never set eyes on me again. <verse eid="ACT 20:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 20:26" />Therefore I’m going on record this very day to say that I can’t be blamed for the destruction of the
        lives of anyone, <verse eid="ACT 20:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 20:27" />for I have not shirked in telling anyone the will of our God. <verse eid="ACT 20:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 20:28" />Be mindful of yourselves and of the entire flock of Christians whom the Holy Spirit put you as overseers
        (or bishops) over, leading God’s church, a church which he acquired through his very-own blood. <verse eid="ACT 20:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 20:29" />I know that monstrous wolves will join up with you after my departure, penetrating your inner-circle,
        not sparing the flock, <verse eid="ACT 20:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 20:30" />and men will arise from among you who speak distorted, perverted, and corrupted things, causing some
        of the disciples to commit apostasy by becoming their followers. <verse eid="ACT 20:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 20:31" />Therefore be continuously and vigilantly on the lookout, remembering that day and night for three years
        I did not take a break from warning every last one of you—warning you in tears.<verse eid="ACT 20:31" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 20:32" />”At this time I commit you to God and to the concept of His grace, to be edified by the Power (the miracle-working
        power in fact) and for God’s end-goal plan for your lives to be granted among those who’ve been set apart
        and have been made holy. <verse eid="ACT 20:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 20:33" />Any kind of cash, checks, or clothing I desired from no one. <verse eid="ACT 20:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 20:34" />You’re personally acquainted with the fact that my own hands attended to my needs and subsistence. <verse eid="ACT 20:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 20:35" />I’ve pointed all this out to you so that you participate in like manner in the toil of helping those
        who are weak (perhaps weak because of a sickness of some sort) and to remember the words of the Lord
        Jesus that he himself said, ‘It is more blessed to go about giving than to go about receiving.’”<verse eid="ACT 20:35" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 20:36" />After he said these things, he dropped to his knees to pray with all of them. <verse eid="ACT 20:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 20:37" />A good amount of crying by everyone took place, and they wrapped their arms forcefully around Paul’s
        neck and kept on kissing him, <verse eid="ACT 20:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 20:38" />in agony most of all because of the message which he spoke that they would never set eyes on him again.
        They then proceeded to put him on the ship and send him off.<verse eid="ACT 20:38" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 20" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 21   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="ACT 21" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 21:1" />When it came time to set sail, once we were torn away from them, we set a straight course and came to
        Cos, and the next day to Rhodes, and from there to Patara. <verse eid="ACT 21:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 21:2" />Finding a ship that was making the run straight to Phoenicia, not hugging the coast, we boarded and sailed
        off. <verse eid="ACT 21:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 21:3" />When Cyprus appeared over the horizon, we kept it on our port side and kept on sailing to Syria and docked
        at Tyre, seeing that the ship was destined to unload its cargo there. <verse eid="ACT 21:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 21:4" />Seeking out and finding disciples, we stayed there for seven days. Those disciples in particular kept
        on telling Paul through the Spirit to not go down to Jerusalem.<verse eid="ACT 21:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 21:5" />When those days were up, we left there and started walking, with everyone having a send-out for us, joined
        by their wives and children, until they got outside the city walls. At the shore we dropped to our knees
        and prayed. <verse eid="ACT 21:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 21:6" />We tore ourselves away from each other and boarded the ship, and those good people returned to their
        kinfolk and fellow citizens.<verse eid="ACT 21:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 21:7" />For our part, we finished taking the ship from Tyre and arrived in Ptolemais, greeted the comrades and
        spent a day with them. <verse eid="ACT 21:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 21:8" />The next day we left and went to Caesarea, and were invited to stay at Philip the Evangelist’s house
        (Philip being one of the original seven directors chosen in the early days), and stayed with him as his
        guests. <verse eid="ACT 21:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 21:9" />This fellow had four unmarried daughters who prophesied on a regular basis. <verse eid="ACT 21:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 21:10" />While staying put there for plenty of days, a certain-someone from the Judean church—a prophet named
        Agabus—came over from Jerusalem, <verse eid="ACT 21:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 21:11" />approached them, took Paul’s belt off, tied his own hands and feet with it, and said, “Thus says the
        Holy Spirits: The Jews in Jerusalem will tie up the man who owns this belt the same way as this and hand
        him over to the Gentiles to be put in custody by them.”<verse eid="ACT 21:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 21:12" />When we heard this, we and the locals as well advised him—begged him—not to go to Jerusalem. <verse eid="ACT 21:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 21:13" />Paul then replied, “What are you all doing crying and breaking my heart? Fact is, I’m ready to not only
        be bound but also to be killed in Jerusalem, on behalf of all that the Lord Jesus stands for.” <verse eid="ACT 21:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 21:14" />Not making any progress in talking him out of it, they quieted down and said, “May the Lord’s will come
        to pass.”<verse eid="ACT 21:14" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 21:15" />After this stretch of time was over, we made preparations and proceeded to go to Jerusalem. <verse eid="ACT 21:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 21:16" />Some of the disciples from Caesarea accompanied us as well, bringing us to a certain Cyprian named Mnason,
        whom we were to stay with, a disciple who had been around for a long time.<verse eid="ACT 21:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 21:17" />When we showed up in Jerusalem, the comrades gladly received us. <verse eid="ACT 21:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 21:18" />The next day Paul—we—met up with James and the entire church governing board. <verse eid="ACT 21:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 21:19" />Once greetings were exchanged, he explained down to the last detail what God had accomplished among the
        Gentiles through his ministry. <verse eid="ACT 21:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 21:20" />Those who heard this glorified God and told him, “You see, comrade, how many tens of thousands there
        are within the Jewish community who have become believers, and all of them are zealous to be in compliance
        with the Law of Moses. <verse eid="ACT 21:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 21:21" />The word’s going around about you that you’re instructing all the Jews to abandon the Law of Moses and
        live like Gentiles, telling them not to circumcise their boys and in refusing to do so, not enrolling
        them into Judaism nor to live a lifestyle of keeping the ancient traditions that go hand-in-hand with
        following the Law of Moses. <verse eid="ACT 21:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 21:22" />So what’s the story here? Everyone’s going to hear that you’ve come to town and will be sifting through
        every statement you make which they hear through the grapevine.<verse eid="ACT 21:22" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 21:23" />”So this is what you should do: There are four men who have voluntarily taken the Old Testament pledge
        called the Nazirite vow and are partway through it. <verse eid="ACT 21:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 21:24" />Befriend them, perform Jewish purification rituals with them as a group and pay their expenses until
        they reach the end of their vow when they’ll shave their heads, and everyone will know that the word-on-the-street
        about you is baloney, and you live uprightly instead and keep the Law of Moses for your own self. <verse eid="ACT 21:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 21:25" />Now about the Gentiles who’ve become believers: we disseminated the decision to obey the following list
        of rules: to abstain from food sacrificed to idols, from slaughtering an animal with the intent of drinking
        its blood, and from bizarre sexual immorality.”<verse eid="ACT 21:25" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 21:26" />Paul then befriended the four men, and on the following day, once he was ritualistically purified, entered
        the temple complex with them, letting everyone know the days of ritualistic purification had been checked
        off, until such a time that the prescribed offering was offered by each one of them.<verse eid="ACT 21:26" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 21:27" />As the seven days were about to come to an end, the Jews from the Roman province of Asia saw him in the
        temple and proceeded to stir up everyone in the crowd, and they grabbed ahold of him, <verse eid="ACT 21:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 21:28" />while shouting, “Men, fellow Israelites, help: this is the man who’s teaching everyone everywhere a teaching
        which is in opposition to what the folk-people believe and is against the Law of Moses and this very
        place. What’s more, he brought Gentiles into the temple and defiled this holy place.” <verse eid="ACT 21:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 21:29" />You see, they had seen the Ephesian named Trophimus in the city with him beforehand, and they assumed
        that Paul had brought him into the temple at some point.<verse eid="ACT 21:29" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 21:30" />The entire city was perturbed, and the folk people formed a stampede, and forcibly taking hold of Paul,
        they proceeded to drag him outside the temple complex, and the temple gates were immediately shut behind
        them. <verse eid="ACT 21:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 21:31" />And while trying to kill him, a report was dispatched to the colonel of the Roman garrison posted in
        the city that the entire city of Jerusalem was on the move. <verse eid="ACT 21:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 21:32" />He immediately gathered soldiers and junior officers to his side, chased them down, and cornered them.
        Seeing the colonel and the soldiers, they stopped beating Paul. <verse eid="ACT 21:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 21:33" />Next, the colonel drew near, took custody of him, spoke out an order that he be tied up with two chains,
        and inquired who he might be and what it is that he had done. <verse eid="ACT 21:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 21:34" />Some of the people in the crowd were shouting one thing at them, some were shouting another. Unable to
        understand what was going on because of the riot, he ordered that he be brought to the garrison’s base.<verse eid="ACT 21:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 21:35" />But when they got to the stairs, they found that he was being carried by the soldiers on account of them
        being pressured by the crowd. <verse eid="ACT 21:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 21:36" />You see, a multitude of the folk-people were shouting, “Get rid of him!”<verse eid="ACT 21:36" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 21:37" />And while they were about to enter the base, Paul said to the colonel, “May I say something to you?”
        He said, “You know Greek? <verse eid="ACT 21:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 21:38" />So that means that you’re not the Egyptian who a few months ago stirred up a rebellion and lead the 4,000
        men from the terrorist organization out into the desert.” <verse eid="ACT 21:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 21:39" />Paul said, “I certainly am a Jew, from Tarsus, Cilicia, a citizen of a not-so-insignificant city. I’m
        asking you to return me to the folk-people and speak to them.” <verse eid="ACT 21:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 21:40" />Paul turned around, went back, stood on the stairs, and motioned with his hand for the crowd to be silent.
        Once the crowd was quiet, he addressed them in Aramaic…<verse eid="ACT 21:40" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 21" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 22   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="ACT 22" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 22:1" />…”Men, fellow comrades, and patriarchs: listen to my side of the story now.” <verse eid="ACT 22:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 22:2" />Once they heard him addressing them in Aramaic, they gave him their attention all the more. He then goes
        on to say, <verse eid="ACT 22:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 22:3" />“I am a Jew, born in Tarsus, Cilicia, raised in this city as an understudy of Gamaliel, having received
        tutelage down to the minutest detail from the foremost expert in the Law of Moses, being zealous of God
        in the same way that you all are today. <verse eid="ACT 22:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 22:4" />I kept on persecuting those in the movement called This Way to the point of death, subduing them and
        putting them in jail, both men and women alike. <verse eid="ACT 22:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 22:5" />As the high priest vouched for me (and every one of the councilmen too), and along with that I also received
        letters of authorization addressed to the comrades in Damascus, I proceeded to go bring those who lived
        up there too to Jerusalem, all tied up, so that they would be forced into submission, thoroughly crushing
        their will to resist.<verse eid="ACT 22:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 22:6" />”What happened to me sometime around midday while walking and approaching Damascus is that a light from
        out of the sky suddenly shined around me, a light like a spotlight consisting of a continuous lightning
        flash. <verse eid="ACT 22:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 22:7" />I fell to the ground and heard a voice saying to me,</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 22:7"><char style="wj">“‘Saul, Saul, why are you persecuting me?’</char><verse eid="ACT 22:7"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 22:8" />”I replied, ‘Who are you, sir?’</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 22:8">“He told me, <char style="wj">‘I’m Jesus of Nazareth, whom you’re persecuting.’</char><verse eid="ACT 22:8"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 22:9" />”Now those who were accompanying me saw the light indeed, but didn’t hear the voice which was speaking
        to me.<verse eid="ACT 22:9" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 22:10" />”I said, ‘What do you want me to do, sir?’</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 22:10"><char style="wj">“The Lord said to me, ‘Get up and go to Damascus; everything that I’ve arranged for
        you to do will be explained to you there.’</char><verse eid="ACT 22:10"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 22:11" />”As I had lost my sight due to the glory of that magnificent light, I was led about by the hand the way
        blind men are by my colleagues and arrived in Damascus.<verse eid="ACT 22:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 22:12" />”Now someone named Ananias, a devout man according to what the Law of Moses prescribes, his devoutness
        affirmed by all the Jews living there, <verse eid="ACT 22:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 22:13" />went up to me, stood over me, and said, ‘Comrade Saul, regain your sight,’ and that very moment I looked
        up at him and was able to see again. <verse eid="ACT 22:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 22:14" />He said, ‘God of our ancestors appointed you to know His will and to see the One Who’s Right and to hear
        the sound of words coming from His mouth, <verse eid="ACT 22:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 22:15" />because you will give an official account to all sorts of people all over the place about what you’ve
        seen and heard. <verse eid="ACT 22:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 22:16" />And what are you going to do now? You’re going to get up and get ready to be baptized and have your sins
        washed away, after you’ve asked him to do for you what he’s best known for.’<verse eid="ACT 22:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 22:17" />”What happened to me after returning to Jerusalem and was praying in the temple is that I found myself
        in a trance. <verse eid="ACT 22:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 22:18" />I saw him telling me, <char style="wj">‘Hurry up and get out of Jerusalem—quickly now—because they are
        not having anything to do with what you’re saying about me.’</char> <verse eid="ACT 22:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 22:19" />I said, ‘Lord, they know that I was going from synagogue to synagogue imprisoning and beating those who
        believe in you. <verse eid="ACT 22:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 22:20" />And when the blood of your advocate and representative Stephen started to be shed, I was right there
        too off to the side, heartily approving and keeping an eye on the jackets that the ones who were killing
        him had taken off.’ <verse eid="ACT 22:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 22:21" />He said to me, <char style="wj">‘Get going, because I’m sending you to a far-away nation…’</char>”<verse eid="ACT 22:21" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 22:22" />Now they were listening to him attentively up to the previous statement, and they then raised their voice
        singularly and said, “Wipe him off the face of the earth—a guy like this doesn’t deserve to live!”, <verse eid="ACT 22:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 22:23" />and screamed and went absolutely ballistic. <verse eid="ACT 22:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 22:24" />The colonel ordered that he be brought into the base, and said a few words for him to be whipped as part
        of an interrogation, in order to ascertain the reason he was being shouted at like this. <verse eid="ACT 22:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 22:25" />As he stretched him out with the leather straps positioning him for the scourging, Paul said to the centurion
        standing there,</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 22:25">“Is it legal for you all to whip a Roman citizen who hasn’t been convicted in a court of law?”<verse eid="ACT 22:25"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 22:26" />Upon hearing this, the centurion went over to the colonel and reported it, “What in the world are you
        about to do? This here man’s a Roman citizen.”<verse eid="ACT 22:26" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 22:27" />The colonel came over and said, “Tell me—are you a Roman citizen?”</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 22:27">Paul said, “Yes.”<verse eid="ACT 22:27"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 22:28" />The Centurion answered, “I acquired this citizenship of mine with a large sum of money.”</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 22:28">Paul said, “But as for me—I was born into mine.” <verse eid="ACT 22:28"/>
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 22:29" />As a result, those who were about to interrogate him immediately backed away. The centurion became frightened
        knowing beyond a shadow of doubt that he’s a Roman citizen and that he had been tied up illegally.<verse eid="ACT 22:29" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 22:30" />A council was convened the following day to ascertain the facts of what he was being accused of by the
        Jews. He let him out, summoned the high priest and the councilmen to attendance, brought Paul down from
        the base, and had him stand before them.<verse eid="ACT 22:30" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 22" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 23   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="ACT 23" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 23:1" />Paul looked intently at the council and said, “Men, comrades, with a good conscience in every respect
        I have lived my life for God up to this day.” <verse eid="ACT 23:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 23:2" />The high priest Ananias had the ones standing next to him hit him in the mouth. <verse eid="ACT 23:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 23:3" />Paul then said to him, “God’s going to hit you back, you bogus judge. And to think that you presume to
        sit in judgment over me according to the Law of Moses, but you hit me illegally.” <verse eid="ACT 23:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 23:4" />The attendants who were standing nearby said, “You’re insulting God’s high priest,” <verse eid="ACT 23:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 23:5" />and so Paul goes on to say, “I didn’t know, comrades, that he’s a high priest. You see, it’s written
        in Scripture, ‘You shall refrain from speaking ill of a ruler of the people.’”<verse eid="ACT 23:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 23:6" />Realizing that one part of the council consisted of Pharisees but the other part consisted of Sadducees,
        Paul shouted to the council, “Men, comrades, I myself am a Pharisee, the very product of Pharisees—I’m
        on trial for the hope that life after death offers!” <verse eid="ACT 23:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 23:7" />Once he said this, a disagreement broke out between the Pharisees and the Sadducees, and the majority
        were split over the issue. <verse eid="ACT 23:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 23:8" />(On the one side of the dispute, Sadducees assert that there is no life after death, nor are there angels
        or spirits; whereas Pharisees profess the opposite.) <verse eid="ACT 23:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 23:9" />Heavy back-and-forth shouting took place, and so some of the designated teachers who were on the Pharisees’
        side stood up and said in hot contention, “We find that this man has done no wrong. If a spirit spoke
        to him, or perhaps an angel, …” <verse eid="ACT 23:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 23:10" />With quite a quarrel breaking out, the colonel was growing anxious over Paul’s safety lest Paul be torn
        to pieces by them and ordered a company of soldiers to come down out of the base and snatch him from
        their midst and bring him to the base.<verse eid="ACT 23:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 23:11" />That night the Lord stood over Paul as he was lying in bed and said, <char style="wj">“Don’t sweat it.
        You see, just as I kept on telling you in all seriousness about </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">what
        would happen to you</char></char><char style="wj"> in Jerusalem in relation to me, the same thing has
        to happen to you in Rome.”</char><verse eid="ACT 23:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 23:12" />When day came, the Judeans formed a cabal and swore an oath amongst themselves promising not to eat or
        drink until they killed Paul. <verse eid="ACT 23:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 23:13" />There were more than forty who took this oath as part of the cabal, <verse eid="ACT 23:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 23:14" />and these men approached the high priest and the council and said, “We took an oath amongst ourselves,
        swearing that we would be cursed if we break it, not to enjoy even a morsel of food until we kill Paul.<verse eid="ACT 23:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 23:15" />So have an audience before the colonel now, you and the council with you, and petition him to bring Paul
        down acting as though you’ll be investigating his case in detail. We’ll be ready to bump him off before
        he ever gets close to you.”<verse eid="ACT 23:15" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 23:16" />Paul’s nephew (his sister’s son) heard about the ambush, was escorted to the base, was granted access,
        and informed Paul. <verse eid="ACT 23:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 23:17" />Paul called one of the centurions over and said, “Send this young man to the colonel, as he has something
        to tell him.” <verse eid="ACT 23:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 23:18" />He did indeed take the young man into his custody and brought him to the colonel and said, “The prisoner
        Paul called me over and asked me to bring this young man who has something to tell you.”<verse eid="ACT 23:18" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 23:19" />The colonel clasped his hand and took him aside so that they could talk in private, and proceeded to
        inquire, “What is it that you have to tell me?” <verse eid="ACT 23:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 23:20" />He said, “The Judeans concocted a plot to ask that you bring Paul down tomorrow to appear before the
        council as though some detail about his case is being examined. <verse eid="ACT 23:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 23:21" />So then don’t let them talk you into this, as more than forty of their men are in on the plot ready to
        jump him, and these men swore amongst themselves to not eat or drink until they bump him off, and they’re
        ready to go as of this moment, waiting for you to give the word.” <verse eid="ACT 23:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 23:22" />So the colonel released the young man and ordered him not to tell anyone that he had an audience with
        him.<verse eid="ACT 23:22" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 23:23" />He summoned two of his centurions and said, “Get two hundred soldiers ready to march all the way to Caesarea,
        plus seventy cavalrymen and two hundred javelin-throwers, with a departure time of nine in the evening,<verse eid="ACT 23:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 23:24" />and saddle up a mule so that Paul will be delivered safely to Governor Felix, since he’ll be mounted.”<verse eid="ACT 23:24" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 23:25" />He dictated a letter which reads,<verse eid="ACT 23:25" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 23:26" />From Claudius Lysias, to his excellency Governor Felix: Greetings!<verse eid="ACT 23:26" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 23:27" />The Jews got ahold of this man and were about to kill him, but I came to the rescue with my soldiers.
        Having learned he was a Roman citizen <verse eid="ACT 23:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 23:28" />and wanting to get to know the grounds on which they were accusing him, I took him to their council.<verse eid="ACT 23:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 23:29" />I discovered that he was being charged for an issue involving their law, but nothing that he was being
        charged with was worthy of death or imprisonment. <verse eid="ACT 23:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 23:30" />Now after I received a report that a conspiracy to take this man’s life was about to be hatched, I immediately
        sent him to you, commanding his accusers to present their case before you.<verse eid="ACT 23:30" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 23:31" />So then the soldiers, following the orders they were given, took Paul and brought him to Antipatris over
        the course of the night. <verse eid="ACT 23:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 23:32" />The next day the infantry allowed the cavalrymen to part ways and continue on with him to Caesarea, while
        they returned to base. <verse eid="ACT 23:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 23:33" />Those cavalrymen entered Caesarea and delivered the letter to the governor and presented Paul to him.<verse eid="ACT 23:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 23:34" />He read it, asked what province he’s from, and found out that he’s from Cilicia. <verse eid="ACT 23:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 23:35" />”I’ll give you a hearing,” he said, “when your accusers show up.” He ordered that he be placed under
        guard in Herod’s palace.<verse eid="ACT 23:35" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 23" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 24   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="ACT 24" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 24:1" />Five days later the high priest Ananias arrived with some councilmen and with this attorney named Tertullus.
        They appeared before the governor in the case against Paul. <verse eid="ACT 24:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 24:2" />After being called on, Tertullus began the prosecution of the case saying, “A good deal of peace has
        been obtained because of you and the reforms which—owing to your foresight—you’ve introduced into this
        nation <verse eid="ACT 24:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 24:3" />and which have been whole-heartedly accepted by everyone everywhere, your excellency Felix, with overwhelming
        gratitude. <verse eid="ACT 24:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 24:4" />But in order to not waste any more of your time, I beg you by the kindness you’re known for to listen
        for a moment. <verse eid="ACT 24:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 24:5" />You see, we find that this plague-of-a-man: #1—is instigating rebellions among all the Jews across the
        civilized world plus is a ringleader of the Nazarene faction; <verse eid="ACT 24:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 24:6" />#2—attempted to desecrate the temple; #3—has been arrested.<verse eid="ACT 24:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 24:7" /> <verse eid="ACT 24:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 24:8" />In regard to all of these affairs, you might want to examine them yourself to ascertain what it is we’re
        accusing him of.” <verse eid="ACT 24:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 24:9" />The Jews piled in alleging that this is so.<verse eid="ACT 24:9" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 24:10" />And Paul, given the nod from the governor to speak his rebuttal, replied, “From many years of being a
        judge for this nation, all the while being good-natured about getting to know the background material
        of my rebuttal, <verse eid="ACT 24:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 24:11" />you have the wherewithal to come to the realization that, from the time I left to travel to Jerusalem
        to worship there, no more than twelve days have gone by. <verse eid="ACT 24:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 24:12" />The Jews have not found me wrangling with anyone in the temple or exerting pressure which I fomented
        out of a group of people in the temple, nor doing the same in the synagogues, nor going from city to
        city doing the same, <verse eid="ACT 24:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 24:13" />neither can they present evidence to you pertinent to the accusations they’re leveling against me at
        the moment. <verse eid="ACT 24:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 24:14" />I hereby state the following to you: the religious beliefs I adhere to and worship the Father-God with
        are in accordance with ‘the Way’ (which they say is a sect of Judaism), in every respect exercising faith
        consistent with the Law of Moses and believing in what’s written in the rest of the Old Testament, <verse eid="ACT 24:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 24:15" />having hope in God, a hope which they too entertain for themselves, a soon-to-be afterlife of the righteous
        and—well—the unrighteous too. <verse eid="ACT 24:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 24:16" />I apply myself to this as well, in order to maintain a blameless conscience through it all towards God
        and towards my fellow comrades.<verse eid="ACT 24:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 24:17" />”As I had repeatedly over many, many years went to the temple and gave donations to the poor among my
        fellow-countrymen, I arrived in the temple bringing offerings and donations. <verse eid="ACT 24:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 24:18" />They found me in the temple with these offerings and in a state of ritualistic purification—but did not
        find me with a crowd or with rioters. <verse eid="ACT 24:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 24:19" />Some of the Jews from the Roman province of Asia—who ought to have to appear before you personally and
        submit accusations if they have some sort of complaint against me— <verse eid="ACT 24:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 24:20" />or should be made to state in person before you that they found some misconduct that warranted standing
        me before the council— <verse eid="ACT 24:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 24:21" />unless of course it’s all about this one squawk which I shouted out while I stood in their midst, ‘I’m
        on trial before you today over the doctrine of life after death!’—”<verse eid="ACT 24:21" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 24:22" />Felix adjourned the proceedings, knowing in detail the ins-and-outs of the Way from observation, and
        said, “When Colonel Lysias manages to get here, I’ll get to the bottom of your claims,” <verse eid="ACT 24:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 24:23" />while ordering the centurion to keep an eye on Paul while he let him relax and ordering him not to prevent
        any of his personal attendants from attending to his needs.<verse eid="ACT 24:23" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 24:24" />A few days later Felix appeared with his wife Drusilla (who was Jewish), summoned Paul, and listened
        to him talk about faith in Christ Jesus. <verse eid="ACT 24:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 24:25" />While he was making the case for righteousness, self-control, and the Coming Judgment, Felix became frightened
        and responded, “You’ll have to go now, but when I get the chance, I’ll call for you to come back.” <verse eid="ACT 24:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 24:26" />All the while too, he was hoping that he was going to get money from Paul; for that reason too, he kept
        on conversing with him, summoning him frequently.<verse eid="ACT 24:26" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 24:27" />Now his two-year term as governor ended, and Felix was replaced by a successor named Porcius Festus,
        and wishing for the Jews to owe him a favor, in the transition Felix kept Paul imprisoned.<verse eid="ACT 24:27" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 24" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 25   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="ACT 25" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 25:1" />So Festus assumed his tenure as governor over the region and went from Caesarea down to Jerusalem three
        days later, <verse eid="ACT 25:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 25:2" />and the chief priests and the leading Judeans informed him of the accusations against Paul and proceeded
        to ask him to step in <verse eid="ACT 25:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 25:3" />and do a favor for them in their case against Paul, that he be extradited to Jerusalem, as they were
        preparing an ambush to bump him off while on the way down. <verse eid="ACT 25:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 25:4" />As a result Festus decided to keep Paul in Caesarea, while he himself was planning to leave Jerusalem
        soon. <verse eid="ACT 25:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 25:5" />So he then says, “Let those of you who can make things happen accompany me and indict him of crimes if
        there turns out to be some discrepancy with this man.”<verse eid="ACT 25:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 25:6" />He spent no more than eight to ten days with them and went down to Caesarea. The next day he convened
        court as the presiding judge and called for Paul to be brought forth. <verse eid="ACT 25:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 25:7" />When he showed up in court, the Judeans who had come up from Jerusalem brought lots of severe charges
        against him, but the case for any of them was not strong enough to stick, <verse eid="ACT 25:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 25:8" />while Paul, speaking in his own defense, said, “I have not committed any infraction with respect to the
        Jews’ Law of Moses, nor with respect to the temple rules, nor with respect to Roman law.”<verse eid="ACT 25:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 25:9" />But Festus, wanting to do a favor for the Judeans so they would owe him one, replied to Paul, “Do you
        want to go down to Jerusalem and hold the trial for all of this down there with me as judge?” <verse eid="ACT 25:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 25:10" />Paul said, “I have taken a stand in the Roman court of law, where my trial must be held. I have done
        no wrong to the Jews, as you have come to know so well. <verse eid="ACT 25:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 25:11" />So now, if I am indeed guilty of doing something worthy of death, I won’t make excuses for getting the
        death penalty. But if nothing comes of what they’ve charged me with, nothing’s going to make them happy.
        I appeal my case to Caesar.” <verse eid="ACT 25:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 25:12" />After conferring with his council, Festus then replied, “You have appealed to Caesar, to Caesar you shall
        go.”<verse eid="ACT 25:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 25:13" />Several days went by and King Agrippa and Bernice arrived in Caesarea and greeted Festus and started
        hanging out with him. <verse eid="ACT 25:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 25:14" />In the course of spending a lot of days there, Festus went over the charges against Paul with the king
        from top to bottom, “There’s this man who was left imprisoned by Felix, <verse eid="ACT 25:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 25:15" />concerning whom the Jewish chief priests and councilmen tendered a request to me while I was there in
        Jerusalem, asking me to sentence him as though he had been convicted of a crime. <verse eid="ACT 25:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 25:16" />To which I replied that to surrender and hand over a given person before the defendant faces his prosecutors
        in the same physical location and submits testimony in his own defense against the charges is not the
        Roman way of doing things.<verse eid="ACT 25:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 25:17" />”So they came up here, and without delay I convened court the following day, sat in the judge’s chair,
        and called for the man to be brought in. <verse eid="ACT 25:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 25:18" />When it was the prosecution’s turn to present evidence, they kept on accusing him of violating the law,
        while I kept on suspecting that not a single one of the charges was a legitimate felony. <verse eid="ACT 25:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 25:19" />They kept on having issues with his religious beliefs and with this certain fellow who died named Jesus,
        but that was all. <verse eid="ACT 25:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 25:20" />I was perplexed about this ongoing debate of theirs and kept on asking him if he would like to go to
        Jerusalem and be put on trial down there for these things. <verse eid="ACT 25:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 25:21" />But when Paul appealed his case and asked that he be held in custody for the purpose of having the emperor
        decide the case, I ordered that he be held prisoner until I send him over to Caesar.”<verse eid="ACT 25:21" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 25:22" />Agrippa said to Festus, “I’ve been wanting to hear what this man has to say myself.”</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ACT 25:22">“Tomorrow,” he said, “You shall hear what he has to say.”<verse eid="ACT 25:22"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 25:23" />The next day Agrippa and Bernice—with much fanfare—went and entered the audience hall accompanied by
        a colonel and by prominent men of the city, and Festus called to have Paul brought out. <verse eid="ACT 25:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 25:24" />Festus said, “King Agrippa and all the men who are joining us: see this fellow whom the overwhelming
        majority of Jews keep hitting me up about in Jerusalem and here as well, shouting that he must no longer
        live? <verse eid="ACT 25:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 25:25" />I’ve been floored by the fact that nothing that he’s done deserves the death penalty, but this fellow
        nevertheless invoked his right of appeal to the emperor, to have his case transferred there for trial.<verse eid="ACT 25:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 25:26" />I don’t have anything definite to write down on this subject for the head-honcho; therefore I brought
        him before us and especially before you, King Agrippa, so that the inquiry which will take place now
        would result in something I can write to the emperor to be read when he reviews this man’s case. <verse eid="ACT 25:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 25:27" />The fact of the matter is, I think that sending a prisoner to the emperor and not specifying the accusations
        against him is absurd.”<verse eid="ACT 25:27" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 25" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 26   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="ACT 26" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 26:1" />Agrippa said to Paul, “Are you allowed to speak for yourself?” Paul then put his hand up and proceeded
        to issue a rebuttal: <verse eid="ACT 26:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 26:2" />“In regard to everything I’m accused of by the Jews, King Agrippa, I consider myself fortunate that I’m
        going to be giving a rebuttal before you today, <verse eid="ACT 26:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 26:3" />especially with you being an expert in anything that has to do with the Jewish people and in their issues
        and disputes as well. Therefore, I ask you to patiently listen to me.<verse eid="ACT 26:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 26:4" />”So now, all the Judeans have known firsthand the way I lived from the time I was a youth, namely what
        happened from the time it all started when I was among my fellow countrymen and was living in Jerusalem,<verse eid="ACT 26:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 26:5" />knowing me the entire time then. What they would say about it if they were put on the stand to testify
        is that I lived the life of a Pharisee, adhering to the strictness of our religion sect. <verse eid="ACT 26:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 26:6" />At the moment I’m on trial standing before you defending myself for the hope of our ancestors’ promises,
        which God caused to come into being; <verse eid="ACT 26:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 26:7" />for a hope which our fellow-countrymen, descendants of the same twelve tribes of Israel, are hoping to
        attain, earnestly performing rituals of worship day and night; for a hope for which I’m defending myself
        from charges which the Jews are pressing, Your Highness.<verse eid="ACT 26:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 26:8" />”Why have you all decided that it’s too far-fetched to believe that there’s life after death, God causing
        a person to live in a state of bliss? <verse eid="ACT 26:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 26:9" />Now—yes—I deemed it necessary to get personally involved in and actively participate in opposing everything
        Jesus of Nazareth stands for, and I did this a lot. <verse eid="ACT 26:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 26:10" />I did this in Jerusalem and had many of God’s very people locked up in prison, once I obtained the authority
        to do so from the chief priests, and I cast my vote for them to receive the death penalty. <verse eid="ACT 26:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 26:11" />Going through all the synagogues one after another punishing them on many occasions, I kept trying to
        force them to renounce their faith, and, fuming with rage against them, I continuing persecuting them
        even spilling over into neighboring cities.<verse eid="ACT 26:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 26:12" />”Engaged in such affairs, walking to Damascus with the authorization and permission of the chief priests
        with me, <verse eid="ACT 26:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 26:13" />while on the road at noon, I saw, Your Highness, a light coming from the sky overhead—a light brighter
        than the sun—shine around me and around my fellow travellers. <verse eid="ACT 26:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 26:14" />All of us fell flat on the ground, and I heard a voice say to me in Aramaic, <char style="wj">“Saul,
        Saul, why do you persecute me? It’s hard to swim against the tide</char><char style="wj">.”</char> <verse eid="ACT 26:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 26:15" />I said, “Who are you, sir?” The Lord said, <char style="wj">“This is Jesus, the one you’re persecuting.
        </char><verse eid="ACT 26:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 26:16" /><char style="wj">Enough—get up and stand on your feet. I became visible to you for this </char><char
        style="it"><char style="wj">purpose</char></char><char style="wj">: to appoint you to be an assistant
        and to appoint you to tell others of the truthfulness of</char><char style="wj"> both </char><char style="it"><char
        style="wj">the fact</char></char><char style="wj"> that you saw me </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">and
        what I told you then</char></char><char style="wj"> and that I will be seen</char><char style="wj"> by
        you </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">and you will be told more things</char></char><char style="wj">.
        </char><verse eid="ACT 26:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 26:17" /><char style="wj">I’m rescuing you and letting you escape from the </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">Israeli
        </char></char><char style="wj">folk-people</char><char style="wj"> and from the Gentiles and sending
        you </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">as a missionary </char></char><char style="wj">to the Gentiles
        </char><verse eid="ACT 26:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 26:18" /><char style="wj">to open their eyes for the one-time turning from darkness to light and from </char><char
        style="it"><char style="wj">being </char></char><char style="wj">of the authority of Satan to </char><char
        style="it"><char style="wj">being</char></char><char style="wj"> close to</char><char style="it"><char
        style="wj"> </char></char><char style="wj">God</char><char style="wj">, and for them by faith in me to
        receive forgiveness of sins and their very own piece of the pie, so to speak</char><char style="wj">,
        among the people whom God separated </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">to Himself</char></char><char
        style="wj">by means of faith.”</char><verse eid="ACT 26:18" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 26:19" />”As a result, King Agrippa, I was not left in a state of disobedience or disbelief by the heavenly vision.<verse eid="ACT 26:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 26:20" />On the contrary—I proceeded to tell everyone that they must be changing their hearts and their ways and
        be turning to where they are close to God and to perform deeds reflective of a change of heart and of
        ways, first telling this to those in Damascus but not only to them but to those in Jerusalem, to the
        entire Judean countryside, and to the Gentiles. <verse eid="ACT 26:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 26:21" />Because of all of this, the Judeans seized me when I was in the temple and proceeded to try to have me
        killed. <verse eid="ACT 26:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 26:22" />So getting the help of that which comes from God up until this moment, I have taken a stand and am testifying
        in court today, letting the insignificant and the great as well know the truthfulness of what was going
        to happen, telling them nothing apart from what the prophets (and Moses too) spoke, which I assert is
        this: <verse eid="ACT 26:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 26:23" />#1—The Messiah is capable of experiencing suffering; #2—A prototype of those who come back from the dead
        is going to announce to the Israeli folk-people and to the Gentiles that there is a light.”<verse eid="ACT 26:23" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 26:24" />While he was still making his rebuttal, Festus said loudly, “You’re crazy, Paul! All of that studying
        you’ve done reading all those books has driven you insane!”<verse eid="ACT 26:24" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 26:25" />Paul said, “I’m not crazy, Your Excellency Festus, rather I’m uttering sentences consisting of the honest
        truth and of sanity. <verse eid="ACT 26:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 26:26" />You see, the king, whom I’m speaking freely and in a straightforward way to, understands these topics.
        In fact I don’t believe that any of these topics are over his head; the fact is, this new religion called
        ‘Christianity’ hasn’t been practiced in a way that it’s been kept in the closet. <verse eid="ACT 26:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 26:27" />Do you believe, King Agrippa, in the Bible? From what I’ve seen, I know that you believe.”<verse eid="ACT 26:27" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 26:28" />Agrippa said to Paul, “In a little way you’re talking me into making myself a Christian.”<verse eid="ACT 26:28" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 26:29" />Paul said, “Would to God I would persuade in both a little way and in a big way, and not just you only
        but everyone who’s listening to me today, to become like me except for the shackles,” <verse eid="ACT 26:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 26:30" />and the king, the governor &amp; Bernice, and those seated with them got up, <verse eid="ACT 26:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 26:31" />withdrew somewhere private, and proceeded to talk to one another saying that this man has committed nothing
        worthy of the death penalty or imprisonment. <verse eid="ACT 26:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 26:32" />Agrippa said to Festus, “That fellow would’ve walked free had he not appealed his case to Caesar.”<verse eid="ACT 26:32" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 26" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 27   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="ACT 27" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 27:1" />As it was decided that we would sail to Italy, they proceeded to transfer custody of Paul and some other
        prisoners to a centurion named Julius, a member of the Imperial Battalion. <verse eid="ACT 27:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 27:2" />We boarded a ship in Adramyttium which was about to sail down the Turkish coast and hoisted sail, while
        Aristarchus, a Macedonian from Thessalonica, accompanied us. <verse eid="ACT 27:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 27:3" />The next day we stopped at Sidon. Julius did a kind deed for Paul and permitted him to go to his friends
        and receive care for his health. <verse eid="ACT 27:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 27:4" />From there we set out to sea and sailed the long way, on the eastern side of Cyprus, because the winds
        were against us, <verse eid="ACT 27:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 27:5" />sailed through the deep water off the coast of Cilicia and Pamphylia, and arrived at the town of Myra
        in Lycia. <verse eid="ACT 27:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 27:6" />There, the centurion found an Alexandrian ship sailing to Italy, and we boarded it. <verse eid="ACT 27:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 27:7" />After several days of making slow headway, we showed up over in Cnidus. Because the wind wasn’t in our
        favor, we sailed the long way around Crete down the coast of Salmone <verse eid="ACT 27:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 27:8" />and with difficulty sailed along the coast and came to some place called Fair Havens, which is near a
        town called Lasea.<verse eid="ACT 27:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 27:9" />As a good amount of time had gone by, and it being dangerous to travel on the Mediterranean Sea because
        the Day of Atonement was already past (i.e, it was already fall), Paul kept on urging, <verse eid="ACT 27:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 27:10" />“Men, I’m looking at what will happen, that there’s going to be damage and much loss—not only to the
        cargo and the ship but of our lives—on the voyage.” <verse eid="ACT 27:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 27:11" />But the centurion was persuaded more by what the helmsman and the captain were saying than by what Paul
        was saying. <verse eid="ACT 27:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 27:12" />Now since the harbor there was unsuitable for passing the winter, the majority decided to hoist sail
        and leave, if perchance they could make it to Phoenix and pass the winter there, which is a harbor in
        Crete which faces southwest and has a northwesterly wind.<verse eid="ACT 27:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 27:13" />The south wind blew gently; thinking that they had a window of opportunity, they lifted anchor and proceeded
        to sail along the coast of Crete. <verse eid="ACT 27:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 27:14" />But not long after, a hurricane called a “Northeasterly” came down from Crete and plowed into them. <verse eid="ACT 27:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 27:15" />As the ship was caught in the wind and couldn’t withstand it, they lowered the sails and drifted. <verse eid="ACT 27:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 27:16" />Running under the protection of a small island called Cauda, we were just barely able to get the ship
        under control preventing it from smashing into the rocks. <verse eid="ACT 27:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 27:17" />When they raised the waterline of the hull, they used cables to support the weight of the ship and hold
        it together. Afraid that they might run aground on the banks of Syrtis, they lowered the anchor and were
        driven about while configured this way.<verse eid="ACT 27:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 27:18" />Battered by the storm, the next day we proceeded to jettison boxes, jars, and cargo containers overboard,<verse eid="ACT 27:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 27:19" />and on the third day we pitched gear and tackle. <verse eid="ACT 27:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 27:20" />With neither the sun nor the stars shining for many days and as no small hurricane was raging, we abandoned
        all hope of survival, <verse eid="ACT 27:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 27:21" />and having gone without food for a long time, Paul stood up, had them gather around, and said, “Oh you
        guys—you really should’ve listened to me and done as I told you and not put out to sea in Crete, and
        none of this damage and loss would’ve happened. <verse eid="ACT 27:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 27:22" />But now I advise you to cheer up; the fact is, none of you is going to lose his life—but the ship will
        be lost. <verse eid="ACT 27:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 27:23" />You see, last night an angel of God, whose I am and whom I serve and worship, stood by me <verse eid="ACT 27:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 27:24" />saying, ‘Don’t be afraid, Paul. You must appear before Caesar. And—get ahold of this—God has graciously
        and freely given a gift to you: He will spare the lives of all those sailing with you.’ <verse eid="ACT 27:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 27:25" />With this in mind, cheer up, men. You see, I believe in God, that He’ll make it turn out just the way
        the angel has spoken when he spoke to me. <verse eid="ACT 27:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 27:26" />But we’ll have to run aground on some island.”<verse eid="ACT 27:26" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 27:27" />Now as the fourteenth night came around, we were drifting about the Adriatic Sea, and about midnight
        the sailors began to suspect that they were nearing land. <verse eid="ACT 27:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 27:28" />After sounding the depth by dropping a line with a lead weight, we measured a depth of twenty fathoms
        (120ft/37m). A short while later, we measured fifteen (90ft/27m), <verse eid="ACT 27:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 27:29" />and fearing that we’d smash against the rocks, we cast four anchors off the ship’s stern and began to
        hope and pray for day to come. <verse eid="ACT 27:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 27:30" />Trying to flee the ship, the sailors lowered the ship’s utility boat into the water, pretending that
        they were going to extend the bow’s anchor lines. <verse eid="ACT 27:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 27:31" />Paul said to the centurion and the soldiers, “If those guys don’t stay in the ship, you won’t survive.”<verse eid="ACT 27:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ACT 27:32" />The soldiers then cut the utility boat’s ropes and let it be driven away.<verse eid="ACT 27:32" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ACT 27:33" />Up until daylight was about to appear, Paul kept on encouraging everyone to have something to eat saying,
        “It’s been fourteen days of waiting it out now, and we haven’t eaten anything. <verse eid="ACT 27:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ACT 27:34" />With this in mind, I encourage you all to put some food in your stomach, as this is for your own well-being
        and could save your life. Fact is, not a single one of the hairs on your head will be lost.” <verse eid="ACT 27:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ACT 27:35" />After he said this, he took a loaf of bread, offered thanks to God in front of everyone in the ceremony
        done many times before, broke it, and began to eat. <verse eid="ACT 27:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ACT 27:36" />Everyone cheered up and partook of food. <verse eid="ACT 27:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ACT 27:37" />All totaled, there were 276 of us onboard the ship. <verse eid="ACT 27:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="ACT 27:38" />After they’d eaten, they lightened the ship by throwing the stores of wheat overboard into the water.<verse eid="ACT 27:38" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="ACT 27:39" />When daylight broke, they looked and looked but weren’t making out any land which had no rocky shoreline,
        but they started to notice a bay which had a suitable beach, and they got together and decided that it
        might be possible to run the ship aground on it. <verse eid="ACT 27:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="ACT 27:40" />They cut the anchors loose and let them sink to the bottom of the sea and at the same time disconnected
        the rudder controls from the rudder, hoisted the foresail to utilize the wind, and headed for the beach.<verse eid="ACT 27:40" />
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="ACT 27:41" />They encountered a place where two bodies of water converge and ran the ship aground. While the bow stayed
        firmly planted, the aft on the other hand began to break off from the rest of the ship due to the force
        of the waves. <verse eid="ACT 27:41" />
      <verse number="42" style="v" sid="ACT 27:42" />A plan was put together by the soldiers to kill the prisoners, lest any one of them escape by swimming
        away, <verse eid="ACT 27:42" />
      <verse number="43" style="v" sid="ACT 27:43" />but wanting Paul to survive, the centurion thwarted their plan by first of all ordering those who are
        able to swim to the shore to jump overboard and get away, <verse eid="ACT 27:43" />
      <verse number="44" style="v" sid="ACT 27:44" />and for the others to get on a plank or something-or-another from the ship and paddle their way to shore.
        And this was the way that everyone made it to dry ground and survived.<verse eid="ACT 27:44" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 27" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 28   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="28" style="c" sid="ACT 28" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ACT 28:1" />Once we were safe, we came to the understanding that the island’s called Malta, <verse eid="ACT 28:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ACT 28:2" />and the natives began to shower us with an inordinate amount of kindness: you see, on account of the
        sudden rain coming down on us and the cold, they lit a fire and welcomed every one of us. <verse eid="ACT 28:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ACT 28:3" />When Paul gathered a bunch of sticks and put them on the fire, a viper fled the heat, sunk his fangs
        into him, and latched onto his hand. <verse eid="ACT 28:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ACT 28:4" />As the natives saw the viper hanging off his hand, they began to say to one another, “This guy definitely
        was a murderer. He escaped the sea but justice didn’t allow him to live.” <verse eid="ACT 28:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ACT 28:5" />So then he shook the viper off into the fire and nothing bad happened to him. <verse eid="ACT 28:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ACT 28:6" />They kept waiting for him to swell up soon or drop dead suddenly. While they were waiting and looking,
        nothing unusual happened to him, and they changed their minds and began to say that he’s a god.<verse eid="ACT 28:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ACT 28:7" />In the area that surrounds that place that they were at was a piece of property that belonged to the
        most prominent person on the island, a man by the name of Publius. He took us into his house for three
        days, extending hospitality to us strangers. <verse eid="ACT 28:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ACT 28:8" />Publius’s father came down with on and off fever and dysentery which kept forcing him to lie down. Paul
        went over to him, became acquainted with him, prayed, laid his hands on him, and healed him. <verse eid="ACT 28:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ACT 28:9" />When this happened, everyone else on the island who was run down with maladies of some sort started coming
        to him and was being healed or otherwise treated. <verse eid="ACT 28:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ACT 28:10" />They gave us many donatives as an allowance, and while we were putting out to sea, they put necessities
        on the ship.<verse eid="ACT 28:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ACT 28:11" />Three months later we put out to sea in a ship that had wintered on the island of Alexandrian, a ship
        called “Gemini.” <verse eid="ACT 28:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ACT 28:12" />After we went up to Syracuse, we stayed there for three days. <verse eid="ACT 28:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ACT 28:13" />From there we sailed the circuit and arrived in Rhegium. After one day elapsed, a wind came up from the
        south, and after a second day, we went to Puteoli, <verse eid="ACT 28:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ACT 28:14" />where we found fellow-comrades, and they cordially invited us to stay for seven days. This is the way
        we arrived in Rome: <verse eid="ACT 28:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ACT 28:15" />The comrades then heard what happened to us and went all the way down to the Forum of Appius and the
        Three Taverns to meet us. When Paul saw them, he thanked God and strengthened his nerve and stiffened
        his composure. <verse eid="ACT 28:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ACT 28:16" />Now when we entered Rome, Paul was given permission to live by himself and with his guard-soldier.<verse eid="ACT 28:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ACT 28:17" />What occurred three days later is that he summoned the leading Jews together. Once they got together,
        he proceeded to tell them, “Men, comrades, I, a prisoner who was handed over to the Romans back in Jerusalem,
        did nothing which was against the Israeli folk-people or the customs of our forefathers. <verse eid="ACT 28:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ACT 28:18" />The very people who examined me kept wishing to set me free because there was no charge which I was inherently
        guilty of which warranted death. <verse eid="ACT 28:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ACT 28:19" />Facing opposition from the Judeans, I was forced to appeal my case to Caesar—not that I had any charges
        to press against my fellow countrymen. <verse eid="ACT 28:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ACT 28:20" />So I made the request to see you and to talk to you for this reason: you see, it’s because of the hope
        of Israel I’m wearing these chains.”<verse eid="ACT 28:20" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ACT 28:21" />They said, “We have neither received anything in writing about you from the Judeans, nor have any one
        of the comrades showed up informing us of anything along these lines or saying something bad about you.<verse eid="ACT 28:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ACT 28:22" />We would like to hear from you, for you to tell us what your thoughts are; for we certainly do know that
        this sect called Christianity is spoken against by everyone.”<verse eid="ACT 28:22" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ACT 28:23" />They reserved a day for him, and many went to visit him and were treated to his hospitality, guests to
        whom he kept on expounding and solemnly stating the truthfulness of God’s interaction with mankind (God’s
        kingdom) and making persuasive arguments for them to believe in various things about Jesus and to believe
        in various things from the Old Testament from early in the day until evening. <verse eid="ACT 28:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ACT 28:24" />With him using logical arguments, they indeed kept being agreeable to his propositions and conceding
        his points, but in spite of that they refused to act in faith and believe. <verse eid="ACT 28:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ACT 28:25" />While in a state of disagreement with one another, they were politely told it was time to leave after
        Paul made a remark in which he said that the Holy Spirit put it beautifully when he spoke to our ancestors
        through the prophet Isaiah,<verse eid="ACT 28:25" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ACT 28:26" />“Go to this people and say,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 28:26">‘You will hear news of something,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 28:26">But there’s no way at all that you’ll understand it,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 28:26">And while looking at something, you will see it,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 28:26">But there’s no way at all that you’ll gaze upon it.<verse eid="ACT 28:26"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ACT 28:27" />The fact is, this people’s collective heart became lethargic,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 28:27">And with difficulty they heard that something with their ears,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 28:27">And they’ve closed their eyes,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 28:27">Lest they, while using their eyes, might gaze upon something</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 28:27">And, while using their ears, might hear something,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 28:27">And would understand in their heart </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 28:27">And would redirect their lives in the right way,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ACT 28:27">And I will heal them when they do.’<verse eid="ACT 28:27"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ACT 28:28" />”So let it be known to you all that this rescue program of God’s was sent to the Gentiles; they especially
        will listen to it.” <verse eid="ACT 28:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ACT 28:29" /><verse eid="ACT 28:29" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ACT 28:30" />He lived on his own in a rented house for an entire two years, and welcomed as guests anyone coming to
        interact with him in a friendly visit, <verse eid="ACT 28:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ACT 28:31" />preaching how God interacts with mankind (God’s kingdom) and teaching various things about the Lord Jesus
        Christ, preaching and teaching unhindered with total boldness and confidence.<verse eid="ACT 28:31" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="ACT 28" />
</usx>
