<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- The Bernmeister's New Testament, Abridged Edition -->
<!-- Copyright © 2024 Bernard M. Woodland -->
<!-- Version 1 -->
<!-- Public domain -->
<!-- The Bernmeister's NT Version 1 -->
<usx version="3.0">
  <!--   *******************   -->
  <!--   Titles and TOC Info   -->
  <!--   *******************   -->
  <book code="MRK" style="id">The Bernmeister's NT</book>
  <para style="h">Mark</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Gospel of Mark</para>
  <para style="toc2">Mark</para>
  <para style="toc3">Mark</para>
  <para style="mt2">THE GOSPEL OF</para>
  <para style="mt1">MARK</para>
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  1   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="MRK 1" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 1:1" />The Beginning of the Good News of Jesus Christ, Son of God<verse eid="MRK 1:1" />
    </para>
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 1:2" />…Just as it had been written by the Prophet Isaiah:
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 1:2"></para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 1:2">See here—I will send my messenger</para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 1:2">To where your attention is fixated,</para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 1:2">Who’ll prepare your way<verse eid="MRK 1:2"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 1:3" />The sound of shouting in the countryside:
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 1:3">“Block off the road the Lord will take!</para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 1:3">Barricade the streets he’ll be on!”<verse eid="MRK 1:3"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 1:4" />John the Baptist came on the scene in the countryside preaching a baptism—a water immersion-type of initiation
        ceremony—signifying a total commitment to a change in conduct to live the right way and signifying an
        initiation into a forgiveness of sins. <verse eid="MRK 1:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 1:5" />All of the Judean region and everyone in Jerusalem were coming out and were being baptized by him in
        the Jordan River, one after another, while pouring their hearts out in confessing their sins out loud.<verse eid="MRK 1:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 1:6" />John dressed himself in a camel hair outfit wrapped in a leather belt and for food ate grasshoppers and
        wild honey. <verse eid="MRK 1:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 1:7" />He preached, “One’s coming after me who’s greater than me, for whom I’m not worthy of bending over and
        unfastening one of the straps on his sandals. <verse eid="MRK 1:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 1:8" />Me—I baptize in water, but he—he’ll baptize you in the Holy Spirit.”<verse eid="MRK 1:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 1:9" />Jesus of Nazareth, Galilee came on the scene in those days and was baptized by John. <verse eid="MRK 1:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 1:10" />As he came straight up out of the water, he saw the sky parting and the Spirit descending upon him like
        a dove. <verse eid="MRK 1:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 1:11" />A voice spoke from out of the sky, “You are my Beloved Son. I’m quite pleased with you.”<verse eid="MRK 1:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 1:12" />Immediately the Spirit drove him into the countryside. <verse eid="MRK 1:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 1:13" />He was out there in the middle of nowhere for forty days, being tempted by Satan. He was fighting for
        his life, and all the while the angels were attending to him.<verse eid="MRK 1:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 1:14" />After John had been taken into custody, Jesus came to Galilee preaching God’s message of good news, <verse eid="MRK 1:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 1:15" />and saying that the time had arrived and that God’s involvement with you (God’s kingdom) had drawn near;
        and saying, <char style="wj">“Go about changing your ways and believing in the Good News.”</char><verse eid="MRK 1:15" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 1:16" />While passing by the Sea of Galilee, he saw Simon and his brother Andrew casting a net, seeing that they
        were fishermen. <verse eid="MRK 1:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 1:17" />Jesus said to them, <char style="wj">“Come be my followers, and I’ll make you into fishermen who fish
        for men.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 1:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 1:18" />Right away they left their nets and followed him. <verse eid="MRK 1:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 1:19" />He continued onwards a bit further and saw James, son of Zebedee, and his brother John, while they were
        in the boat mending the nets. <verse eid="MRK 1:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 1:20" />Right away he called out to them, and they left their father Zebedee in the boat with the hired hands
        and departed to be his followers.<verse eid="MRK 1:20" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 1:21" />They came to Capernaum, and without delay he started teaching in the synagogue there on the Sabbaths.<verse eid="MRK 1:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 1:22" />They were amazed at his teaching, since he was teaching in a captivating manner, and not like their designated
        teachers, the Scribes. <verse eid="MRK 1:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 1:23" />In an instant, there was a man right there in their synagogue with a demonic spirit, and he screamed,<verse eid="MRK 1:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 1:24" />”We have no beef with you, Jesus of Nazareth; did you come to annihilate us? I know who you are: you’re
        the Holy One of God.” <verse eid="MRK 1:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 1:25" />Jesus sternly took charge over him saying, <char style="wj">“Shut up and come out of him!” </char><verse eid="MRK 1:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 1:26" />The demonic spirit shook him real good, cried out in a loud voice, and then exited him. <verse eid="MRK 1:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 1:27" />Everyone was amazed, to the extent that they began to discuss and argue among themselves, “Just who is
        this guy?…Fresh teaching delivered in a captivating manner…He even takes charge over demonic spirits,
        and they obey him.” <verse eid="MRK 1:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 1:28" />Immediately, the news about him spread to everyone in the entire area surrounding Galilee.<verse eid="MRK 1:28" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 1:29" />Right after leaving the synagogue, they went with James and John to Simon and Andrew’s house. <verse eid="MRK 1:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 1:30" />Simon’s mother-in-law was laid out with a fever, and immediately they spoke to Jesus about her. <verse eid="MRK 1:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 1:31" />He went over to her, took her hand, pulled her up, and the fever left, and she began to attend to their
        needs. <verse eid="MRK 1:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 1:32" />When it was late in the day and the sun was setting, they began to bring him all those having something
        wrong with them and the demon-possessed. <verse eid="MRK 1:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 1:33" />The whole city gathered at the door, <verse eid="MRK 1:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 1:34" />and he healed many of those who had something wrong with them consisting of a disease of one kind or
        another, and cast out many demons, and while casting them out wasn’t letting the demons say anything,
        because they knew who he was.<verse eid="MRK 1:34" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 1:35" />Early in the morning, before daybreak, he left and went out to a place where nobody was around and prayed
        and prayed there. <verse eid="MRK 1:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 1:36" />Simon and those with him went out to hunt him down. <verse eid="MRK 1:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 1:37" />They found him and, engaging him in conversation, said, “Everyone’s looking for you.” <verse eid="MRK 1:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 1:38" />Continuing the conversation, he said, <char style="wj">“Let’s go somewhere else, to an area where there’s
        towns in the vicinity.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 1:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 1:39" />They went throughout all of Galilee preaching in the synagogues there and casting out demons.<verse eid="MRK 1:39" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 1:40" />A leper approached him, pleading with him, “If you so desire, you can purge this disease from me.” <verse eid="MRK 1:40" />
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 1:41" />He had pity on him, extended his hand, touched him, and pronounces, <char style="wj">“I do so desire;
        be purged of this disease.” </char><verse eid="MRK 1:41" />
      <verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 1:42" />Immediately it left him; he was purged of the disease. <verse eid="MRK 1:42" />
      <verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 1:43" />Without wasting any time, he sternly and with an inner indignation gave him specific instructions and
        then cut him loose, <verse eid="MRK 1:43" />
      <verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 1:44" />telling him, <char style="wj">“Make sure you don’t say anything to anyone about this, but go your way
        and show yourself to the priest and bring along with you the offering that the Old Testament commands
        as an official submission for the certification of the purging of this disease.” </char><verse eid="MRK 1:44" />
      <verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 1:45" />But he departed and began going around enthusiastically telling lots of people what had happened and
        spreading the story and its acclamation around, resulting in him no longer being able to enter a city,
        but instead having to stay outside in the countryside.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 1:45">And they began to come to him from every direction.<verse eid="MRK 1:45"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="MRK 1" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  2   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="MRK 2" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 2:1" />Several days after entering Capernaum, word got out that he was staying in a house there. <verse eid="MRK 2:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 2:2" />Many converged on it, to the extent that nobody could get in or out of the door anymore, and he kept
        on speaking the word of God to them. <verse eid="MRK 2:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 2:3" />Four men arrived carrying a stretcher that had someone who was paralyzed on it. <verse eid="MRK 2:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 2:4" />Not being able to carry him through the crowd, they pulled away the roof where he was and dug out a hole
        in order to lower the stretcher on which the paralyzed fellow was lying. <verse eid="MRK 2:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 2:5" />Seeing their faith, Jesus said to the one paralyzed, <char style="wj">“Son, your sins are forgiven.”
        </char><verse eid="MRK 2:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 2:6" />Some of the designated teachers were sitting there mulling this over in their hearts, <verse eid="MRK 2:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 2:7" />”How can he talk that way to this guy? He’s blaspheming; who’s able to forgive sins, except for the one-and-only
        God?” <verse eid="MRK 2:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 2:8" />Immediately coming to the realization in his spirit exactly what they had thought up, Jesus engages them
        in conversation, <char style="wj">“Why did you, inside of yourselves, think these things up? </char><verse eid="MRK 2:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 2:9" /><char style="wj">What’s easier to say to the one paralyzed, ‘Your sins are forgiven,’ or, ‘Get up, take
        your stretcher, and walk around’? </char><verse eid="MRK 2:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 2:10" /><char style="wj">But so that you would know that the Man has the authority on earth to forgive sins…”
        </char>he turns and speaks to the paralyzed fellow, <verse eid="MRK 2:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 2:11" /><char style="wj">”…I say to you, pick up your stretcher and go on home.” </char><verse eid="MRK 2:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 2:12" />And in front of everybody he got up, without delay picked up his stretcher, and left, to everyone’s amazement
        and to their glorification of God saying, “We’ve never seen anything like this before.”<verse eid="MRK 2:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 2:13" />Again, he ventured out near the sea. Everyone in the crowd started coming to him, and he began teaching
        them. <verse eid="MRK 2:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 2:14" />As he was passing through, he saw Levi son of Alphaeus sitting at the customs table, and tells him directly,
        “Be my follower.” And he got up and became his follower. <verse eid="MRK 2:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 2:15" />As he sat down to dine at home, many tax collectors and other sinners gathered there to eat with Jesus.<verse eid="MRK 2:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 2:16" />The designated teachers, the ones affiliated with the Pharisees, observing that he takes meals with sinners
        and tax collectors, were saying to his disciples, “How is it that he dines with the tax collectors and
        other sinners?” <verse eid="MRK 2:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 2:17" />Jesus heard this and said to them, <char style="wj">“Healthy people don’t need a doctor, but those who
        have something wrong with them do. I didn’t come to call on those right with God but rather on sinners.”</char><verse eid="MRK 2:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 2:18" />John’s disciples and the Pharisees were fasting, and they approached him with a question, “What’s the
        reason that John’s disciples fast and the Pharisees’ disciples fast, but your disciples don’t fast?”<verse eid="MRK 2:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 2:19" />Jesus said, <char style="wj">“The groom’s cronies can’t fast when the groom’s around, can they? As long
        as the groom is with them, they’re not able to fast. </char><verse eid="MRK 2:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 2:20" /><char style="wj">But there’ll come a day when the groom is taken away, and that’s the day they’ll start
        fasting.” </char><verse eid="MRK 2:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 2:21" /><char style="wj">No one uses a patch made from new material to patch an old garment with; otherwise,
        the new material will wind up tearing itself away from the old, and a worse gap will appear. </char><verse eid="MRK 2:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 2:22" /><char style="wj">And no one puts freshly-squeezed grape juice into old wineskins; otherwise, the wine
        will cause the skins to burst, and both the wine and the skins will be ruined. Rather, grape juice goes
        into new wine skins.”</char><verse eid="MRK 2:22" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 2:23" />He happened to be passing through the grain fields on days which were Sabbath days, and his disciples
        began to make their way through the fields stripping the grain off the heads of the stalks. <verse eid="MRK 2:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 2:24" />The Pharisees proceeded to say to him, “Take a look—they’re doing what’s forbidden on the Sabbath.” <verse eid="MRK 2:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 2:25" />Looking deeper at the situation, he said to them, <char style="wj">“Didn’t you read about what David
        did when the need arose and he got hungry—and so did those who were with him? </char><verse eid="MRK 2:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 2:26" /><char style="wj">How, when Abiathar was high priest, he entered the house of God and ate the holy bread,
        which no one’s allowed to eat except the priests, and—not only that—he passed it out to those who were
        with him?”</char> <verse eid="MRK 2:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 2:27" />He summarized, <char style="wj">“The Sabbath came into being for the benefit of mankind, and not mankind
        for the benefit of the Sabbath, </char><verse eid="MRK 2:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 2:28" /><char style="wj">the result being that the Man is also master over the Sabbath.”</char><verse eid="MRK 2:28" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="MRK 2" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  3   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="MRK 3" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 3:1" />Yet again he introduced himself to those in the synagogue and attended a meeting. There was a man there
        with a shriveled-up hand, <verse eid="MRK 3:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 3:2" />and they were watching him closely, to see if he was going to heal him on the Sabbath, so that they’d
        have something to accuse him of. <verse eid="MRK 3:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 3:3" />He addressed the man with the shriveled-up hand, <char style="wj">“Get up and stand front and center.”</char><verse eid="MRK 3:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 3:4" />He challenged them, <char style="wj">“Is it permissible on the Sabbath to do a good deed or to do bad,
        to save someone’s life or to kill someone?” </char>They remained silent. <verse eid="MRK 3:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 3:5" />He looked all around, staring at them in fury, being deeply grieved over the callousness of their hearts,
        and said to the man intently, <char style="wj">“Stretch your hand out.” </char>He stretched it out, and
        his hand was restored. <verse eid="MRK 3:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 3:6" />After the Pharisees departed, they wasted no time in meeting with the Herodians about him, to figure
        out how they could kill him.<verse eid="MRK 3:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 3:7" />Jesus, accompanied by his disciples, ventured over to the sea, and a great many followed him from Galilee,
        and from Judea, <verse eid="MRK 3:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 3:8" />and from Jerusalem, and from Idumea, and from the other side of the Jordan River, and from the areas
        around Tyre and Sidon—a great many, hearing about how much he was doing, went to him. <verse eid="MRK 3:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 3:9" />And because of the crowd, he spoke to his disciples about getting a boat, so that they wouldn’t press
        in on him. <verse eid="MRK 3:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 3:10" />Indeed, he treated many, resulting in them mobbing him in order that they might receive a touch from
        him, whoever was getting the tar beaten out of him by disease or whatnot. <verse eid="MRK 3:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 3:11" />And, time and time again, the demonic spirits, when they saw him, prostrated themselves before him in
        homage and screamed out, “You are the Son of God!” <verse eid="MRK 3:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 3:12" />And, time and time again, he was sternly silencing them so they would not cause him to be plainly known
        as such.<verse eid="MRK 3:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 3:13" />He hiked up a mountain and summoned those whom he had been wanting to have as his disciples, and they
        came to him. <verse eid="MRK 3:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 3:14" />He made twelve, and he made them so that they would be with him and so that he could send them out to
        preach his message <verse eid="MRK 3:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 3:15" />and to have authority to cast out demons. <verse eid="MRK 3:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 3:16" />He assigned the name “Peter” to Simon, <verse eid="MRK 3:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 3:17" />and there was James son of Zebedee and his brother John, to whom he assigned the name “Sons of Thunder,”<verse eid="MRK 3:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 3:18" />Andrew, Philip, Bartholomew, Matthew, Thomas, James son of Alphaeus, Thaddeus, Simon the Canaaanite (i.e.,
        Zealot), <verse eid="MRK 3:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 3:19" />and Judas Iscariot, his betrayer.<verse eid="MRK 3:19" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 3:20" />Now he came to a house. Once again, the crowd converged on it, resulting in them not being able to get
        a bite to eat. <verse eid="MRK 3:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 3:21" />When the neighbors caught wind of this, they came out to get him under control, since they had been saying
        all along that he’s lost his mind. <verse eid="MRK 3:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 3:22" />And the designated teachers, the Scribes, made the journey from Jerusalem and had been saying that he’s
        possessed by the Chief Demon himself, and that, by means of the chief, he casts out the underling-demons.<verse eid="MRK 3:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 3:23" />He called them over and began to teach them by using analogies: <char style="wj">“How can one demon cast
        out another demon? </char><verse eid="MRK 3:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 3:24" /><char style="wj">If a kingdom is divided into parts which are pitted against each other, that kingdom
        will fall apart. </char><verse eid="MRK 3:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 3:25" /><char style="wj">And if an organization is divided into parts which are pitted against each other, that
        organization will fall apart. </char><verse eid="MRK 3:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 3:26" /><char style="wj">And if Satan has one demon oppose another demon, and they split into hostile factions,
        his kingdom will fall apart—and that’s the end of that. </char><verse eid="MRK 3:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 3:27" /><char style="wj">More to the point—no one can enter the tough guy’s house, unless he first subdues the
        tough guy. </char><verse eid="MRK 3:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 3:28" /><char style="wj">I tell you for sure, that ornery folk will be forgiven of anything and of the random
        blasphemies that they blurt out, </char><verse eid="MRK 3:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 3:29" /><char style="wj">but if anyone were to blaspheme the Holy Spirit, he won’t ever be forgiven—he’s guilty
        of an eternal sin.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 3:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 3:30" />He said all this because they were going about saying, “He has a demonic spirit.”<verse eid="MRK 3:30" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 3:31" />His mother and brothers came and were standing outside and sent him word, calling on him. <verse eid="MRK 3:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 3:32" />Seated around him was a crowd, and they said to him, “Hey, your mother and your brothers are outside
        looking for you.” <verse eid="MRK 3:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 3:33" />Surprisingly, he replied, <char style="wj">“Who is my mother and my brothers?”</char> <verse eid="MRK 3:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 3:34" />He looked around at those sitting in a circle around him and said, <char style="wj">“Take a look here—my
        mother and my brothers.” </char><verse eid="MRK 3:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 3:35" /><char style="wj">Whoever does the will of God, that’s my brother and sister and mother.”</char><verse eid="MRK 3:35" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="MRK 3" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  4   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="MRK 4" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 4:1" />On another occasion, he began to teach near the sea. A huge crowd gathered around him, causing him to
        have to get in a boat and sit out in the sea; everyone in the crowd stayed on dry land and squeezed in
        as close as they could to the shoreline. <verse eid="MRK 4:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 4:2" />He began to teach them by means of analogy, telling many. In one of his sermons he was telling them this:<verse eid="MRK 4:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 4:3" /><char style="wj">”Listen up! There was once a farmer who went out to sow. </char><verse eid="MRK 4:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 4:4" /><char style="wj">While sowing, some of the seed happened to fall up and down the pathway, and the birds
        came and ate it all up, </char><verse eid="MRK 4:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 4:5" /><char style="wj">while some of the other seed fell on the rocky ground, where there wasn’t much soil,
        and, because the soil there wasn’t deep, it immediately germinated, </char><verse eid="MRK 4:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 4:6" /><char style="wj">and when the sun rose, it was scorched, and it dried up due to it not having established
        deep roots. </char><verse eid="MRK 4:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 4:7" /><char style="wj">Yet other fell in the place where there were weeds, and the weeds sprung up, engulfed
        it, and choked it, and it didn’t yield any produce. </char><verse eid="MRK 4:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 4:8" /><char style="wj">Nevertheless, though, some seed fell on the good ground and, springing up and growing,
        yielded produce: some yielding 30-to-1, and some 60-to-1, and some 100-to-1.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 4:9" />And he kept telling them, <char style="wj">“A word to the wise is sufficient.”</char><verse eid="MRK 4:9" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 4:10" />When they got together by themselves, those around him, along with the Twelve, asked him about the analogies.<verse eid="MRK 4:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 4:11" />He began by saying, <char style="wj">“The mystery of God’s Involvement with Mankind (God’s kingdom) is
        given to you, but to those on the outside (i.e. those who are not a part of God’s kingdom), all these
        things are just analogies, </char><verse eid="MRK 4:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 4:12" /><char style="wj">so that,</char>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 4:12"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 4:12"><char style="wj">“While looking, they may look and not see</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 4:12"><char style="wj">(i.e., they’re aware of it, but they don’t get it),</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 4:12"><char style="wj">And while hearing, they may hear and not comprehend</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 4:12"><char style="wj">(i.e., it goes in one ear and out the next),</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 4:12"><char style="wj">Lest they were to turn to it and be forgiven”</char><verse eid="MRK 4:12"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 4:13" />He said, <char style="wj">“Don’t you get this analogy? How then will you comprehend all the analogies?
        </char><verse eid="MRK 4:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 4:14" /><char style="wj">The sower sows the word. </char><verse eid="MRK 4:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 4:15" /><char style="wj">The ones where the word is sown up and down the pathway—when these people hear the word,
        immediately Satan comes and takes away the word which had been sown in their hearts. </char><verse eid="MRK 4:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 4:16" /><char style="wj">The ones where the word is sown on the rocky ground—when these people hear the word,
        they immediately receive it with joy, </char><verse eid="MRK 4:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 4:17" /><char style="wj">and not having established roots, their joy is but temporary, for a timespan, a brief
        passing chapter in life; and then when persecution or the pressures of distress happen on account of
        the word, they immediately fall apart. </char><verse eid="MRK 4:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 4:18" /><char style="wj">Still there are others, where the word is sown among the weeds—these are the ones that
        have heard the word, </char><verse eid="MRK 4:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 4:19" /><char style="wj">and the never-ending worries and anxieties, the self-delusion of wealth, and those things
        which go hand-in-hand with the cravings which still linger in your mind, as they enter in to your heart,
        engulf the word and choke it, and it won’t yield any produce. </char><verse eid="MRK 4:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 4:20" /><char style="wj">The ones where the word is sown upon the good ground—now those are the ones who hear
        the word, take hold of it, and yield produce, some at 30-to-1, some at 60-to-1, some at 100-to-1.”</char><verse eid="MRK 4:20" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 4:21" /><char style="wj">He proceeded to tell them, “The house lamp is not brought out to be put under the bread
        basket or under the couch, is it? Is it not brought out to be placed on the lampstand? </char><verse eid="MRK 4:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 4:22" /><char style="wj">Indeed, there is nothing hidden but that it would manifest itself, nor has there been
        anything purposely hidden away but that it would come into manifestation. </char><verse eid="MRK 4:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 4:23" /><char style="wj">A word to the wise is sufficient.”</char><verse eid="MRK 4:23" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 4:24" /><char style="wj">He proceeded to tell them, “Monitor what you hear. The quantity which you deem sufficient
        is the quantity which will be deemed sufficient for you. </char><verse eid="MRK 4:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 4:25" /><char style="wj">For he who has, it will be given to him; and he who does not have, even that which he
        has will be taken away from him.”</char><verse eid="MRK 4:25" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 4:26" /><char style="wj">He proceeded to tell them, “This is the way God’s involvement with mankind (God’s kingdom)
        is: it’s like a man who goes and casts seed upon the ground </char><verse eid="MRK 4:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 4:27" /><char style="wj">and goes to bed and gets up over and over again, day after day and night after night,
        and the seed sprouts and gets taller—just how, he has no idea. </char><verse eid="MRK 4:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 4:28" /><char style="wj">The ground in and of itself brings forth the crop, starting first with the blade, then
        the grain head, then the mature head. </char><verse eid="MRK 4:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 4:29" /><char style="wj">Now when the crop reaches full maturity, right away he sends for the sickle, because
        the harvest has arrived.”</char><verse eid="MRK 4:29" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 4:30" /><char style="wj">He proceeded to tell them, “How do I draw up a comparison to God’s involvement with
        mankind (God’s kingdom)? Or, in what analogy should it be presented? </char><verse eid="MRK 4:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 4:31" /><char style="wj">It’s like a mustard seed, which, when sown, is about the smallest seed you’ll find,
        </char><verse eid="MRK 4:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 4:32" /><char style="wj">and, when sown, pops up and becomes the biggest crop-yielding plant you’ll find and
        forms huge branches, so much so that the birds of the sky can nest in its shade.”</char><verse eid="MRK 4:32" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 4:33" />He kept speaking the word of God to them by means of many analogies such as these, doing it to the degree
        that they continued to be able to make sense of what he was saying. <verse eid="MRK 4:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 4:34" />And, apart from analogies, he wasn’t telling them anything. But he explained everything to his own disciples
        when they were by themselves.<verse eid="MRK 4:34" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 4:35" />When it got to be late in the day, he prompted them, <char style="wj">“Let’s cut across to the other
        side.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 4:36" />After dismissing the crowd they joined up with him as he was already in the boat they planned to use.
        Other boats were alongside it. <verse eid="MRK 4:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 4:37" />A windstorm appeared, and the waves kept crashing on the boat, enough to fill it. <verse eid="MRK 4:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 4:38" />He, though, was in the stern sleeping on the cushions. They woke him and sought to engage him, “Teacher,
        don’t you care that we’re dying here?” <verse eid="MRK 4:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 4:39" />And he got up and sternly silenced the wind and said to the sea, <char style="wj">“Quiet—stifle it!”
        </char>And the wind died down and a great calm appeared. <verse eid="MRK 4:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 4:40" />He said to them, <char style="wj">“What a bunch of chickens you all are. You still don’t have any faith,
        do you?”</char> <verse eid="MRK 4:40" />
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 4:41" />They were dumbfounded with awe and reverence and started saying to one another, “So now, who is this
        guy, that even the wind and the sea obey him?”<verse eid="MRK 4:41" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="MRK 4" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  5   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="MRK 5" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 5:1" />He got to the other side of the sea, to the Gerasenes region. <verse eid="MRK 5:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 5:2" />Right away, while he was still getting out of the boat, from out of the tombs a man having a demonic
        spirit accosted him, <verse eid="MRK 5:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 5:3" />who lived there in the tombs. No one had the ability to chain him up anymore, <verse eid="MRK 5:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 5:4" />on account of him, many times, having his arms secured in chains and his feet in stocks and breaking
        out of the chains and stocks after shredding them to pieces—no one was powerful enough to restrain him.<verse eid="MRK 5:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 5:5" />Day and night he was up in the tombs and in the mountains screaming and cutting himself up with stones.<verse eid="MRK 5:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 5:6" />Seeing Jesus from a distance, he ran and prostrated himself before him <verse eid="MRK 5:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 5:7" />and yelled in a loud voice, “I have no beef with you, Jesus, son of the Highest God! In God’s name I’m
        begging you—don’t torment me!” <verse eid="MRK 5:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 5:8" />…since he was about to say to him, <char style="wj">“Come out of him, you foul spirit!”</char> <verse eid="MRK 5:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 5:9" />He asked him, <char style="wj">“What’s your name?” </char>He replied, “My name’s ‘Regiment’, since there’s
        a lot of us.” <verse eid="MRK 5:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 5:10" />He was pleading with him a good deal, so that he wouldn’t send them outside the region. <verse eid="MRK 5:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 5:11" />Now, there was a huge herd of pigs feeding there at the mountain. <verse eid="MRK 5:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 5:12" />They begged him, “Send us over to the pigs, so that we can enter them.” <verse eid="MRK 5:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 5:13" />He permitted them, and the regiment of foul spirits departed and entered the pigs, and the herd bolted
        over the cliff and into the sea—about two thousand of them—and drowned in the sea.<verse eid="MRK 5:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 5:14" />Those feeding them proceeded to run away, and they told everyone in the city and in the countryside,
        and they came to see what happened. <verse eid="MRK 5:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 5:15" />They went to where Jesus was and observed the demon-possessed man sitting, clothed, and in a sound state
        of mind—the one who had the regiment—and they got scared. <verse eid="MRK 5:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 5:16" />They described to those who came to look around what happened to the demon-possessed man and about the
        pigs. <verse eid="MRK 5:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 5:17" />They began to plead with him to leave their mountains. <verse eid="MRK 5:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 5:18" />While he was boarding the boat, the demon-possessed man asked if he could be with him from then on, <verse eid="MRK 5:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 5:19" />but he didn’t allow it, but instead instructed him, <char style="wj">“Go on back home, to your own folk,
        and let them know what the Lord has done for you, the mercy He has had on you.” </char><verse eid="MRK 5:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 5:20" />He left and began to preach what Jesus did for him in Decapolis, and everyone was in awe.<verse eid="MRK 5:20" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 5:21" />Again, Jesus crossed over in the boat to the other side, and a large crowd converged on him, while he
        was still near the sea. <verse eid="MRK 5:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 5:22" />One of the synagogue leaders named Jairus came, and, seeing him, fell at his feet <verse eid="MRK 5:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 5:23" />and went to pleading with him a great deal, saying, “My baby’s at death’s door,” in order that he would
        come and put his hand on her, so that she would be spared and would live. <verse eid="MRK 5:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 5:24" />He left with him, and a huge crowd began to follow him and was constantly pressing in on him.<verse eid="MRK 5:24" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 5:25" />A woman who had a hemorrhage for twelve years, <verse eid="MRK 5:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 5:26" />having suffered a great deal at the hands of many doctors, spending everything she had—and nothing was
        helping but instead things were trending more to the worse— <verse eid="MRK 5:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 5:27" />heard about Jesus, came up behind him in the crowd and touched his outer cloak, <verse eid="MRK 5:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 5:28" />since she kept on saying to herself, “If I were to just touch his cloak, I‘ll pull through.” <verse eid="MRK 5:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 5:29" />Her hemorrhage stopped immediately, and her body told her that she had been healed from this calamity
        of illness. <verse eid="MRK 5:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 5:30" />Right away Jesus, having discerned in himself that miraculous power had proceeded out of him, turned
        to the crowd and said repeatedly, <char style="wj">“Who touched my garment?”</char> <verse eid="MRK 5:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 5:31" />The disciples proceeded to say, “You see the crowd pressing in on you and you’re asking, ‘Who touched
        me?’” <verse eid="MRK 5:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 5:32" />He looked around to see who did this. <verse eid="MRK 5:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 5:33" />Now the woman, scared and trembling, aware of what had happened to her, came and fell before him and
        told him the whole truth. <verse eid="MRK 5:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 5:34" />He said to her, <char style="wj">“Ma’am, your faith has pulled you through. Carry on in peace (i.e.,
        go your way free of conflict, duress, or affliction) and be recuperated entirely from your calamity of
        illness.”</char><verse eid="MRK 5:34" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 5:35" />While he was yet still talking, someone from the synagogue leader’s household arrived saying, “Your daughter’s
        dead; no need for you to bother the teacher anymore.” <verse eid="MRK 5:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 5:36" />Now Jesus, having listened in to the report as it was being spoken, addresses the synagogue ruler, <char
        style="wj">“Don’t be afraid—just believe.” </char><verse eid="MRK 5:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 5:37" />He wouldn’t let anyone accompany him, except for Peter, James, and his brother John. <verse eid="MRK 5:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 5:38" />He came to the synagogue leader’s house, and he sees commotion, weeping, and much lamentation, <verse eid="MRK 5:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 5:39" />and he entered and gaining their attention said, <char style="wj">“What’s the commotion about and why
        all the crying?” </char><verse eid="MRK 5:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 5:40" />They began to ridicule him. He, though, threw everyone out and took the child’s mother and father and
        those with him and went in to where the child was. <verse eid="MRK 5:40" />
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 5:41" />He took the child’s hand and said to her, <char style="wj">“Talitha koum!” </char>which translated means,
        <char style="wj">“Young lady, I’m speaking to you: get up!”</char> <verse eid="MRK 5:41" />
      <verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 5:42" />Immediately the girl got up and began to walk around, since she was twelve years old. Immediately, out
        of enormous delight, they lost it. <verse eid="MRK 5:42" />
      <verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 5:43" />He left orders with them, going over them in detail, not to make this known to anyone, and he told them
        to give her something to eat.<verse eid="MRK 5:43" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="MRK 5" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  6   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="MRK 6" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 6:1" />He departed from there and came to his hometown, and his disciples followed him. <verse eid="MRK 6:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 6:2" />On a Saturday, the Sabbath, he began to teach in the synagogue, and many of the listeners were amazed
        saying, “Where did he get these things from, and who bestowed the wisdom on him, and who gave his hands
        the ability to perform such miracles as these? <verse eid="MRK 6:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 6:3" />Isn’t this fellow the craftsman, Mary’s son and James, Joses, Juda, and Simon’s brother? Aren’t his sisters
        from around here?” And they took aversion to him. <verse eid="MRK 6:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 6:4" />He was saying to them that a prophet isn’t honored in his hometown, in his synagogues, and in his own
        home, <verse eid="MRK 6:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 6:5" />and he couldn’t perform a single miracle there, except for healing a few ailments, by laying his hands
        on a few people. <verse eid="MRK 6:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 6:6" />He was astonished at their refusal to believe.
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 6:6">He went around teaching in the surrounding towns, <verse eid="MRK 6:6"/>
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 6:7" />and he summoned the Twelve and began to send them out in pairs, gave them authority over demonic spirits,<verse eid="MRK 6:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 6:8" />and charged them not to take anything on the road with them except a staff only—no food, no backpack,
        no spare cash; <verse eid="MRK 6:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 6:9" />moreover, he told them to be sure to show up wearing sandals and to refrain from putting on two sets
        of undergarments. <verse eid="MRK 6:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 6:10" />He continued speaking to them, <char style="wj">“Whenever you enter a house, stay there until it’s time
        to leave town. </char><verse eid="MRK 6:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 6:11" /><char style="wj">Whatever place won’t receive you or hear what you have to say, as you’re leaving that
        place, shake the dust off the bottom of your sandals like a key witness testifying in court.”</char><verse eid="MRK 6:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 6:12" />They dispersed and preached with the goal in mind of having people fundamentally change the way they
        conduct their lives. <verse eid="MRK 6:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 6:13" />Time and time again they cast out many demons and applied soothing oil to many people who had ailments,
        and one after another was being healed.<verse eid="MRK 6:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 6:14" />Now King Herod heard the news, since his reputation was spreading. They were saying that John the Baptist
        rose from the dead, and this is the means by which the miracles are accomplished by him. <verse eid="MRK 6:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 6:15" />Others were saying that he’s Elijah. Still others were saying that he’s a prophet like one of the prophets
        in the Old Testament. <verse eid="MRK 6:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 6:16" />After Herod heard all of this, he started going around saying, “The guy I personally beheaded—John—that’s
        who was resurrected.”<verse eid="MRK 6:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 6:17" />The fact is, Herod himself had dispatched his men and had John taken into custody and locked him up in
        jail on account of his brother Philip’s wife Herodias, because he had married her; <verse eid="MRK 6:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 6:18" />you see, John had been telling Herod that it’s not permissible for him to be married to his brother’s
        wife. <verse eid="MRK 6:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 6:19" />So Herodias maintained a grudge against him and was wanting to kill him, and wasn’t yet able to do so,<verse eid="MRK 6:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 6:20" />since, throughout, Herod had a reverential awe of John, knowing him to be an upstanding man, right in
        the eyes of God and holy, and was keeping him safe. After listening to him many times, he became conflicted,
        yet still enjoyed listening to him.<verse eid="MRK 6:20" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 6:21" />There came a day when the opportunity presented itself, when, on Herod’s birthday, she prepared a special
        dinner for his gentry, for the high-ranking army officers, and for the top leaders of Galilee. <verse eid="MRK 6:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 6:22" />Herodias’s daughter entered and danced and pleased Herod and his fellow dinner guests. The king said
        to the young miss, “Whatever you want, ask me, and I’ll give it to you.” <verse eid="MRK 6:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 6:23" />He swore up and down to her multiple times, “Whatever you ask me for, I’ll give it to you—anything you
        want—anything at all.” <verse eid="MRK 6:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 6:24" />She excused herself and said to her mother, “What should I ask for?” Her mother said, “John the Baptist’s
        head.” <verse eid="MRK 6:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 6:25" />Straightaway she rejoined the party and with hasty eagerness said, “I want you to give me John the Baptist’s
        head on a platter—right now.” <verse eid="MRK 6:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 6:26" />From head to toe the king became deeply sorry, but because of the promises and the dinner guests didn’t
        want to deny her request. <verse eid="MRK 6:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 6:27" />The king ordered that his head be brought in at once. They went out and beheaded him in jail <verse eid="MRK 6:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 6:28" />and brought his head on a platter and gave it to the young miss, who gave it to her mother. <verse eid="MRK 6:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 6:29" />When his disciples heard about this, they came and took away his body and placed it in a tomb.<verse eid="MRK 6:29" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 6:30" />Now the disciples assembled back where Jesus was at and told him what they did and what they taught.<verse eid="MRK 6:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 6:31" />He comforted them, <char style="wj">“You and only you go to a place where nobody’s around and rest up
        a bit,</char>” since a lot of people were coming and going, and they couldn’t find a moment to have a
        meal. <verse eid="MRK 6:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 6:32" />So they left by themselves in the boat to go to a remote location. <verse eid="MRK 6:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 6:33" />They were seen departing, and a lot of people figured out where they were going and came out of all the
        cities and, in one pack, ran and got there ahead of them. <verse eid="MRK 6:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 6:34" />Departing, he saw a large crowd and felt sorry for them, because they were like sheep without a shepherd,
        and began to teach them many things. <verse eid="MRK 6:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 6:35" />Much of the day had already passed by, and the disciples came to him and proceeded to say,
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 6:35">“We’re out in the middle of nowhere and it’s getting late. <verse eid="MRK 6:35"/>
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 6:36" />Disperse them, so that they can go out into the surrounding countryside and towns and buy something to
        eat.”<verse eid="MRK 6:36" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 6:37" />His response to that was, <char style="wj">“Give them something to eat yourselves.”</char>
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 6:37">They, in turn, said, “So, now, we go out and buy $20,000 worth of bread and distribute it?”<verse eid="MRK 6:37"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 6:38" />He, in turn, said, <char style="wj">“How much food do you have? Go take a look.”</char>
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 6:38">They counted it up and gave him the results, “Five loaves and two fishes.”<verse eid="MRK 6:38"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 6:39" />He had them find a nice spot to relax where the grass was tall and had them break up into dinner parties.<verse eid="MRK 6:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 6:40" />They seated themselves in lots of hundreds and fifties. <verse eid="MRK 6:40" />
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 6:41" />He took the five loaves and the two fishes, looked up in the sky, gave thanks, broke the bread, and gave
        it to his disciples for them to go about placing it within their reach. <verse eid="MRK 6:41" />
      <verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 6:42" />Everyone ate to their full, <verse eid="MRK 6:42" />
      <verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 6:43" />and there were twelve basketfuls of bread scraps and fish left over. <verse eid="MRK 6:43" />
      <verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 6:44" />There were five thousand grown men there eating that day.<verse eid="MRK 6:44" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 6:45" />Right away, the disciples had to get into the boat and head out before him to the other side, to Bethsaida,
        while he dismissed the crowd. <verse eid="MRK 6:45" />
      <verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 6:46" />He took his leave of them and hiked up into the mountain to pray. <verse eid="MRK 6:46" />
      <verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 6:47" />Near sundown, the boat was out in the middle of the sea, while he was by himself on land. <verse eid="MRK 6:47" />
      <verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 6:48" />Watching them struggling to row, since they were up against a contrary wind, around four o’clock in the
        morning, he came to them walking on the water and was going to pass them by. <verse eid="MRK 6:48" />
      <verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 6:49" />Upon seeing him walking about on the water, they thought it was a ghost and shouted out loud; <verse eid="MRK 6:49" />
      <verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 6:50" />indeed, everyone saw him and was terrified. Immediately he engaged them in conversation saying, <char
        style="wj">“Relax, it’s me, don’t be afraid.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 6:50" />
      <verse number="51" style="v" sid="MRK 6:51" />He went over to where they were and got into the boat, and the wind died down. They were completely stupefied,<verse eid="MRK 6:51" />
      <verse number="52" style="v" sid="MRK 6:52" />since they hadn’t put all the pieces together in regard to the incident of the bread, and, what’s more,
        their hearts had been hardened.<verse eid="MRK 6:52" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="53" style="v" sid="MRK 6:53" />Having crossed over to land, they came to Gennesaret and docked. <verse eid="MRK 6:53" />
      <verse number="54" style="v" sid="MRK 6:54" />As they were getting out of the boat, people immediately recognized him. <verse eid="MRK 6:54" />
      <verse number="55" style="v" sid="MRK 6:55" />Everyone from that whole region there rushed around the lake to see him, and they proceeded to carry
        around the lake on cots those who had something wrong with them, wherever it was being reported that
        he was at. <verse eid="MRK 6:55" />
      <verse number="56" style="v" sid="MRK 6:56" />And whatever place he were to enter—a town, a city, a place in the countryside—they were placing those
        having illnesses in the town square, and they were begging him if they could just touch a part of his
        clothing, and whoever were to touch a part of it would be snatched away from the clutches of their illness.<verse eid="MRK 6:56" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="MRK 6" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  7   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="MRK 7" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 7:1" />The Pharisees and some of the designed teachers came from Jerusalem and congregated around him. <verse eid="MRK 7:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 7:2" />They were observing some of his disciples taking their meals with defiled hands (that is, with unwashed
        hands), <verse eid="MRK 7:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 7:3" />since the Pharisees and all the Jews won’t eat if they haven’t washed their hands up to their wrists,
        adhering to the time-honored traditions, <verse eid="MRK 7:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 7:4" />and if they come from the marketplace or the town square, they won’t eat until they take a ceremonial
        bath; plus they adhere to many more things that have been handed down through the years…the ceremonial
        washing of wine chalices, of jugs, of utensils— <verse eid="MRK 7:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 7:5" />and the Pharisees and designated teachers asked him, “Why is it that your disciples aren’t in the habit
        of observing the time-honored traditions, but eat their meals with tainted hands?” <verse eid="MRK 7:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 7:6" />He said, <char style="wj">“Isaiah sure was right when he prophesied about you—the hypocrites—as it is
        written:</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 7:6"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 7:6"><char style="wj">“This people honors Me with their lips</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 7:6"><char style="wj">But their hearts are held at a distance from me.</char><verse eid="MRK 7:6"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 7:7" /><char style="wj">So they worship Me to no avail</char>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 7:7"><char style="wj">Teaching man’s commandments.</char><verse eid="MRK 7:7"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 7:8" /><char style="wj">”Abandoning the commandment of God, you adhere to the tradition of men.” </char><verse eid="MRK 7:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 7:9" />He kept on going, <char style="wj">“Great job rejecting the commandment of God in order to adhere to
        your traditions. </char><verse eid="MRK 7:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 7:10" /><char style="wj">Now, the Old Testament says, ‘Financially support your mother and father’, and ‘Let
        he who bad-mouths his mother or father be put to death’. </char><verse eid="MRK 7:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 7:11" /><char style="wj">But you all say, ‘That payment which I was obligated to send you has instead been designated
        as an offering to God’, </char><verse eid="MRK 7:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 7:12" /><char style="wj">meaning that such a person is off the hook for sending funds to his mother and father.
        </char><verse eid="MRK 7:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 7:13" /><char style="wj">You’re disregarding the word of God by the tradition handed down to you. You do all
        sorts of things like that.”</char><verse eid="MRK 7:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 7:14" />He summoned the crowd and kept with the subject, saying, <char style="wj">“Everyone, listen to me and
        get ahold of this. </char><verse eid="MRK 7:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 7:15" /><char style="wj">There’s nothing outside of a person which, by going into him, can defile him; but rather
        those things which proceed out of a person are what defiles the person.” </char><verse eid="MRK 7:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 7:16" /><verse eid="MRK 7:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 7:17" />When he entered a house, away from the crowd, his disciples started asking him about the illustration.<verse eid="MRK 7:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 7:18" />He said to them, <char style="wj">“You don’t get it either? Don’t you know that everything on the outside
        which goes into a person can’t defile him, </char><verse eid="MRK 7:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 7:19" /><char style="wj">because it doesn’t go into his heart, but instead goes into his intestines, and then
        leaves him going into the toilet (thereby declaring that, henceforth, you’re allowed to eat any kind
        of food)?”</char> <verse eid="MRK 7:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 7:20" />He continued on saying, <char style="wj">“The stuff which proceeds out of a person—that’s what defiles
        the person. </char><verse eid="MRK 7:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 7:21" /><char style="wj">Indeed, from within a person’s heart comes out of it the conniving common to mankind…sexual
        immorality, thievery, murder, </char><verse eid="MRK 7:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 7:22" /><char style="wj">adultery, greed, utter corruption, intentional misleading, strong out-of-control desire,
        evil trains of thought, blasphemy or bad-mouthing, arrogance, reckless stupidity. </char><verse eid="MRK 7:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 7:23" /><char style="wj">All of these inner evils proceed to the outside and defile a person.”</char><verse eid="MRK 7:23" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 7:24" />He wrapped things up there and left for the region of Tyre. He entered a house, since he wasn’t wanting
        to have direct contact with anyone. <verse eid="MRK 7:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 7:25" />But instead, without delay a woman who had a daughter who was overcome with having a demonic spirit heard
        about him and came and fell at his feet. <verse eid="MRK 7:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 7:26" />But the woman was a non-Jew, a Syro-Phoenician by nationality. She drove home her point asking him if
        he’d cast the demon out of his daughter. <verse eid="MRK 7:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 7:27" />And he drove home his point saying to her,
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 7:27"><char style="wj">“Let the children eat until they’re full first, since it wouldn’t be right to take the
        children’s bread and toss it to the dogs.”</char><verse eid="MRK 7:27"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 7:28" />But after some thought she replied, “Lord, even the dogs groveling under the table are fed from the children’s
        crumbs.”<verse eid="MRK 7:28" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 7:29" />He said to her, <char style="wj">“On account of this statement, go your way: the demon has gone out of
        your daughter, for good.”</char><verse eid="MRK 7:29" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 7:30" />After arriving back home, she found the child bedfast and the demon gone for good.<verse eid="MRK 7:30" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 7:31" />Again, he left Tyre and went through Sidon to the Sea of Galilee, to the central area of Decapolis. <verse eid="MRK 7:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 7:32" />They brought him a man who was deaf and who could barely speak, and they asked him to lay his hand on
        him. <verse eid="MRK 7:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 7:33" />He took him aside, in order to be away from the crowd and to have some privacy, and he stuck his fingers
        in his ears, and, after he spat, touched all around his tongue. <verse eid="MRK 7:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 7:34" />He looked up in the sky, let out a groan from deep within, and said to him <char style="wj">“Effatha!”</char>,
        which means, <char style="wj">“Be opened up, all the way!”</char>. <verse eid="MRK 7:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 7:35" />His hearing was restored, and his speaking impairment was broken, and he began to speak correctly. <verse eid="MRK 7:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 7:36" />He gave them orders, in no uncertain terms, not to tell anyone, but the more he would leave orders, the
        more they went about spreading the word to others. <verse eid="MRK 7:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 7:37" />They were continuously overflowing with amazement saying, “All the good he’s accomplished—he even makes
        the deaf hear and the dumb speak.”<verse eid="MRK 7:37" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="MRK 7" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  8   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="MRK 8" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 8:1" />Around that time, a huge crowd had formed yet again. As they didn’t have anything to eat, he summoned
        his disciples and engages them thus, <verse eid="MRK 8:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 8:2" /><char style="wj">”I feel deeply sorry for the crowd, because they’ve been staying here with me for three
        days already, and they don’t have anything to eat. </char><verse eid="MRK 8:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 8:3" /><char style="wj">If I were to disperse them not having eaten in a long time, they’d collapse on the way
        home; and some of them came from far away.”</char><verse eid="MRK 8:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 8:4" />They replied, “Where can any of these people here get enough food to eat out in the middle of nowhere?”<verse eid="MRK 8:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 8:5" />He asked, <char style="wj">“How much bread do you have?”</char>
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 8:5">They said, “Seven loaves.”<verse eid="MRK 8:5"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 8:6" />He told the crowd to find a spot on the ground to relax, and he took the seven loaves, gave thanks, broke
        them, and began to hand them to his disciples, so that they would place them within reach of the crowd;
        and they distributed them. <verse eid="MRK 8:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 8:7" />They had a few fishes too, and after consecrating them, he said for them to be distributed as well. <verse eid="MRK 8:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 8:8" />They ate until they were full, and there were seven basketfuls of leftover scraps and pieces. <verse eid="MRK 8:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 8:9" />Now there were four thousand men there, and he dispersed them. <verse eid="MRK 8:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 8:10" />Immediately, he got into the boat with his disciples and went to Dalmanutha.<verse eid="MRK 8:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 8:11" />The Pharisees came out and began to question him, looking for a spectacular miracle. <verse eid="MRK 8:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 8:12" />He groaned in his spirit and uttered, <char style="wj">“Why does this prevailing Zeitgeist seek a spectacular
        miracle? Mark my words: there’s not a chance that those of that mindset will ever get one.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 8:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 8:13" />He left them, yet again got into the boat, and went to the other side.<verse eid="MRK 8:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 8:14" />Except for one loaf, they forgot to take any bread along with them in the boat. <verse eid="MRK 8:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 8:15" />He proceeded to open up with them about what was on his mind, <char style="wj">“Look out for the Pharisees’
        and Herodians’ yeast.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 8:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 8:16" />They went over this again and again with one another, since they didn’t have any bread. <verse eid="MRK 8:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 8:17" />Knowing this, he addressed them, <char style="wj">“After all this discussion, what’s this conclusion
        that you’ve come to: that you don’t have any bread? You haven’t noticed yet, nor have you put all the
        pieces together, have you? Are your hearts that callous? </char><verse eid="MRK 8:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 8:18" /><char style="wj">While you have eyes, you don’t see, and while you have ears, you don’t listen? You all
        don’t remember? </char><verse eid="MRK 8:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 8:19" /><char style="wj">When I dedicated the five loaves for the five thousand, how many leftover basketfuls
        of scraps did we pick up?—twelve. </char><verse eid="MRK 8:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 8:20" /><char style="wj">When I dedicated the seven loaves for the four thousand, how many basketfuls of scraps
        did we pick up?—seven.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 8:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 8:21" />He continued speaking, <char style="wj">“You still don’t get it, do you?”</char><verse eid="MRK 8:21" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 8:22" />He arrived at Bethsaida. They brought him a blind man and begged him to touch him. <verse eid="MRK 8:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 8:23" />He took the blind man’s hand and brought him outside of the town, spat on his eyes, laid his hands on
        him, and asked him, <char style="wj">“What do you see?” </char><verse eid="MRK 8:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 8:24" />He opened his eyes, looked about, and said repeatedly, “I’m looking at the people here, because I see
        tree-like objects walking around.” <verse eid="MRK 8:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 8:25" />Yet again he laid his hands on his eyes, and his vision was restored completely, and he was seeing clearly
        at a distance. <verse eid="MRK 8:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 8:26" />He sent him home saying, <char style="wj">“Please don’t go into town.”</char><verse eid="MRK 8:26" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 8:27" />Jesus and his disciples left for the town of Caesarea, Philippi. On the way, he asked his disciples,
        <char style="wj">“Who do folks say that I am?” </char><verse eid="MRK 8:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 8:28" />They said, “John the Baptist…others say Elijah…still others say one of the prophets like in the Old Testament.”<verse eid="MRK 8:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 8:29" />He asked the question, coming from himself, <char style="wj">“And who do you—never mind everyone else—say
        that I am?” Peter, mindful of the question, answers, “</char>You are the Messiah, the Christ.” <verse eid="MRK 8:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 8:30" />He sternly commanded them not to tell anyone about him.<verse eid="MRK 8:30" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 8:31" />He began to explain to them that the Man must endure a good amount of suffering and be rejected by the
        high court, the chief priests, and the designated teachers, will be killed, and will rise from the dead
        after three days. <verse eid="MRK 8:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 8:32" />He was speaking this fact plainly. Peter cornered him and began to reprimand him. <verse eid="MRK 8:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 8:33" />He turned and, looking at his disciples, scolded Peter, “Take a hike, you minion of Satan! You’re not
        exercising common-sense wisdom in the things of God—see—but rather the things of mankind.”<verse eid="MRK 8:33" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 8:34" />He summoned the crowd to join him and his disciples and said to them, <char style="wj">“If anyone desires
        to follow after me, let him deny himself, let him take up his cross, and let him follow me. </char><verse eid="MRK 8:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 8:35" /><char style="wj">The fact is, whoever desires to preserve his life destroys it; and he who destroys his
        life for my sake and for the sake of the Good News will preserve it. </char><verse eid="MRK 8:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 8:36" /><char style="wj">For what benefit is it to a person to gain the whole world and lose his life? </char><verse eid="MRK 8:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 8:37" /><char style="wj">For what can a man give in exchange for his life? </char><verse eid="MRK 8:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 8:38" /><char style="wj">For whoever is ashamed of me and of my words in this prevailing Zeitgeist of adultery
        and lawlessness, the Man will also be ashamed of him when he comes in the glory of his Father with the
        holy angels.”</char><verse eid="MRK 8:38" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="MRK 8" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  9   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="MRK 9" />
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 9:1" />He continued speaking to them: <char style="wj">“I really mean it when I tell you that some who got to
        stand right here won’t taste death until they get the chance to behold God’s involvement with mankind
        (God’s kingdom) having made its arrival in a deluge of miraculous power.”</char><verse eid="MRK 9:1" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 9:2" />Six days later, Jesus took Peter, James, and John with him and brought them to a high mountain, by themselves,
        and he transformed himself in their presence. <verse eid="MRK 9:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 9:3" />His clothing shined a bright white, in a way like no sort of bleach on this planet can whiten. <verse eid="MRK 9:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 9:4" />Elijah and Moses together as a pair appeared to them, and they were having a conversation with Jesus.<verse eid="MRK 9:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 9:5" />Peter thought a bit and said to Jesus, “Jesus—good thing we’re here with you. We’ll make three little
        holy edifices: one for you, one for Moses, and one for Elijah.” <verse eid="MRK 9:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 9:6" />The fact is, he didn’t know what to say; they had become terrified indeed. <verse eid="MRK 9:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 9:7" />A cloud appeared, engulfing them in a shadow, and a voice appeared out of the cloud, “This is my Beloved
        Son: listen to him again and again.” <verse eid="MRK 9:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 9:8" />Suddenly, they looked around and didn’t see anyone else with them except for Jesus only.<verse eid="MRK 9:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 9:9" />While they were descending the mountain, he ordered them not to repeat in detail what had happened to
        anyone, except after the Man is resurrected from the dead. <verse eid="MRK 9:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 9:10" />They kept the matter to themselves, discussing with one another what to be “resurrected from the dead”
        means. <verse eid="MRK 9:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 9:11" />Questioning him, they said, “Why is it that the designated teachers say that Elijah has to come first?”<verse eid="MRK 9:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 9:12" />In the course of telling them he said, <char style="wj">“Sure—Elijah comes and sets everything right
        again; but how is it that, concerning the Man, the Old Testament states that he must suffer greatly and
        be treated with utter contempt? </char><verse eid="MRK 9:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 9:13" /><char style="wj">Anyway—I’m telling you that even Elijah has come, and they did to him all the things
        they had always wanted to do, just like it had been recorded about him in the Old Testament.”</char><verse eid="MRK 9:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 9:14" />Having arrived back at where his disciples were, they saw that a huge crowd had surrounded them and that
        designated teachers were arguing with them. <verse eid="MRK 9:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 9:15" />Straightaway, the entire crowd, seeing them, got in a tizzy, rushed over, and began to hail him. <verse eid="MRK 9:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 9:16" />He asked, <char style="wj">“What seems to be the problem?”</char><verse eid="MRK 9:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 9:17" />Someone in the crowd answered, “Teacher, I brought my son, who has a demonic spirit of muteness, to you.<verse eid="MRK 9:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 9:18" />Whenever it takes control of him, it throws him on the ground, and he foams at the mouth and gnashes
        his teeth, and he goes rigid, tucking into a fetal position. I spoke to your disciples so that they would
        cast it out, and they weren’t able to.” <verse eid="MRK 9:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 9:19" />He answered, <char style="wj">“Oh, this prevailing Zeitgeist of unbelief! How long do I have to hold
        your hand for? How long do I have to put up with you for?—Bring him to me.” </char><verse eid="MRK 9:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 9:20" />They brought him to him, and seeing him, the spirit immediately caused him to go into convulsions, drop
        to the ground, and roll around foaming at the mouth. <verse eid="MRK 9:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 9:21" />He asked his father, <char style="wj">“How long has this been going on?</char>” He said, “Since childhood.<verse eid="MRK 9:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 9:22" />Another thing…a lot of times he throws him into fire and into water, in order to destroy him—so now,
        if you can do anything, have a heart and help me out here.” <verse eid="MRK 9:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 9:23" />Jesus said to him, <char style="wj">“About that ‘if-you-can-do-anything’ thing: all things are possible
        to the one believing.” </char><verse eid="MRK 9:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 9:24" />Immediately the boy’s father began to say over and over, “I believe—help me with my unbelief!” <verse eid="MRK 9:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 9:25" />Now Jesus, seeing that the crowd rushed on over to join them, dropped the hammer on the demonic spirit,
        <char style="wj">“I command you, you deaf and dumb spirit: come out of him and never reenter.”</char><verse eid="MRK 9:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 9:26" />He screamed and shook him with one last convulsion and came out. He was laid out like a dead body, so
        much so that many were going around saying that he died. <verse eid="MRK 9:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 9:27" />Jesus grabbed his hand and pulled him up, and he stood up. <verse eid="MRK 9:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 9:28" />After they got to be alone in a house, his disciples asked him, “Why is it that we couldn’t cast it out?”<verse eid="MRK 9:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 9:29" />He said, <char style="wj">“This type can’t be cast out by anyone except by prayer.”</char><verse eid="MRK 9:29" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 9:30" />They left there and started going throughout Galilee, and all the while didn’t want to have any interaction
        with anyone, <verse eid="MRK 9:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 9:31" />since he kept on working at getting his disciples up to speed, saying repeatedly, <char style="wj">“People
        are going to take the Man into custody, they’ll kill him, and, after he’s dead, he’ll be resurrected
        in three days.” </char><verse eid="MRK 9:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 9:32" />They weren’t making any sense of the remark and all the while were afraid to ask him about it.<verse eid="MRK 9:32" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 9:33" />They went to Capernaum. When they got back home, he asked, <char style="wj">“What were you trying to
        figure out on the way over?”</char> <verse eid="MRK 9:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 9:34" />They kept quiet, since on the way over they were trying to figure out who among them was number-one.<verse eid="MRK 9:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 9:35" />He took a seat, called the Twelve over, and engages them, <char style="wj">“If someone wants to be number-one,
        he must assume last place out of everyone and become everyone’s servant.” </char><verse eid="MRK 9:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 9:36" />He took a child, stood him in front of them, put his arm around him, and told them, <verse eid="MRK 9:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 9:37" /><char style="wj">”Whoever receives a child, like this one here, as part of their Christian duty receives
        me, and whoever receives me doesn’t receive me per se but receives the One who sent me.”</char><verse eid="MRK 9:37" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 9:38" />John said to him, “Teacher, we saw a guy casting out demons, assuming to do so under your authority,
        and we intervened and prevented him from doing it, because he’s not one of our trainees nor is he affiliated
        with us.” <verse eid="MRK 9:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 9:39" />Jesus said, <char style="wj">“Don’t get in his way, since there is no one, when presuming to act under
        my authority, who will do something supernatural and will then be able to quickly turn to bad-mouth me.
        </char><verse eid="MRK 9:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 9:40" /><char style="wj">The fact is, he who’s not against us is in favor of us. </char><verse eid="MRK 9:40" />
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 9:41" /><char style="wj">Indeed, if one were to do you a good turn because you are considered to be Christians,
        I tell you for sure that in no uncertain terms would this person lose out on the payment that’s coming
        to him.”</char><verse eid="MRK 9:41" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 9:42" /><char style="wj">”Whoever tries to trip up or draw into sin even the most insignificant person who believes
        in me, he’d be better off tossed into the ocean and standing at the bottom of it with a millstone strapped
        to his neck. </char><verse eid="MRK 9:42" />
      <verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 9:43" /><char style="wj">And if your right hand (i.e., whatever thing you’re doing) causes you to sin, chop it
        off (i.e., quit it—period): you’re better off going through life maimed than being sent to hell having
        two hands, into the Inextinguishable Fire. </char><verse eid="MRK 9:43" />
      <verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 9:44" /><char style="wj"> </char><verse eid="MRK 9:44" />
      <verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 9:45" /><char style="wj">And if your foot (i.e., the direction your life is going in; what you’re in the habit
        of doing) causes you to sin, chop it off: you’re better off going through life lame than to be sent to
        hell having two feet. </char><verse eid="MRK 9:45" />
      <verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 9:46" /><char style="wj"> </char><verse eid="MRK 9:46" />
      <verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 9:47" /><char style="wj">And if your eye (i.e., what your attention is continuously focused on) causes you to
        sin, yank it out: you’re better off going through life with one eye than to be sent to hell having both
        eyes, </char><verse eid="MRK 9:47" />
      <verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 9:48" /><char style="wj">where their parasitic worm infection will never go away and the fire won’t go out.</char><verse eid="MRK 9:48" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 9:49" /><char style="wj">”For all meats roasted by a fire will be salted.</char><verse eid="MRK 9:49" />
      <verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 9:50" /><char style="wj">Salt is good. But if the salt loses its saltiness, with what will you season the meats?
        You have salt embedded in yourselves; live in peace with one another.”</char><verse eid="MRK 9:50" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="MRK 9" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 10   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="MRK 10" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 10:1" />He headed out from there and went to the Judean area, on the other side of the Jordan River, and a crowd
        gathered around him again, and he began teaching them again per usual. <verse eid="MRK 10:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 10:2" />Some Pharisees went up to him and started asking if it’s legal for a husband to divorce his wife, trying
        to catch him in a mistake. <verse eid="MRK 10:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 10:3" />His reply to them was, <char style="wj">“What does the Old Testament command you to do?” </char><verse eid="MRK 10:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 10:4" />They said, “The Old Testament allows you ‘…to write a divorce certificate and cut her loose’.” <verse eid="MRK 10:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 10:5" />Jesus said, <char style="wj">“This commandment, when written, was directed towards your hard-heartedness.
        </char><verse eid="MRK 10:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 10:6" /><char style="wj">But from the beginning of creation, ‘He made them man and woman, husband and wife. </char><verse eid="MRK 10:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 10:7" /><char style="wj">On account of this, a man shall leave behind his mother and father and shall stick to
        his woman, his wife, </char><verse eid="MRK 10:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 10:8" /><char style="wj">and the two will be made into one flesh, resulting in their no longer being two individual
        fleshes but one flesh.’ </char><verse eid="MRK 10:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 10:9" /><char style="wj">That which God joined let no person separate.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 10:10" />When they got back home again, the disciples asked him about this. <verse eid="MRK 10:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 10:11" />He tells them, <char style="wj">“Whoever cuts his wife loose (i.e., divorces her) and marries another
        woman commits adultery with her, </char><verse eid="MRK 10:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 10:12" /><char style="wj">and if she, having been cut loose from her husband, marries another, she commits adultery.”</char><verse eid="MRK 10:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 10:13" />They brought children to him for him to affect through touch, but his disciples scolded them. <verse eid="MRK 10:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 10:14" />Seeing this, Jesus became indignant and said to them, <char style="wj">“Evermore let the children come
        to me, and don’t get in their way, since whom God interacts with (God’s kingdom) is drawn from such as
        these. </char><verse eid="MRK 10:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 10:15" /><char style="wj">Let me tell you what: whoever won’t receive God’s kingdom like a child would, certainly
        won’t enter it.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 10:16" />He put his arms around them and pronounced a blessing over them while laying his hands on them.<verse eid="MRK 10:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 10:17" />While venturing out on the road, someone ran up, fell to his knees before him, and asked him,
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 10:17">“Good teacher, what do I have to do to lay claim to that special fullness of life (eternal life)?”<verse eid="MRK 10:17"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 10:18" />Jesus said, “Why do you call me ‘good’? Nobody’s good except for one person: God. <verse eid="MRK 10:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 10:19" />You know the commandments…do not murder…do not commit adultery…don’t steal…don’t lie when called on to
        make a statement for the record…don’t rip each other off…honor your mother and father.”<verse eid="MRK 10:19" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 10:20" />So he said, “Teacher, I’ve been vigilant to keep all of these since I was a teenager.”<verse eid="MRK 10:20" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 10:21" />So Jesus stared at him and felt an appreciation for the great value of his life and said, <char style="wj">“You’re
        missing one piece: go out and sell what you have and give it to the poor, and you’ll have treasure in
        heaven, and come back to this spot and be my follower.”</char><verse eid="MRK 10:21" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 10:22" />Now he became melancholy over this remark and departed with a sulk, since he owned a lot of stuff. <verse eid="MRK 10:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 10:23" />Jesus looked around and mused to his disciples, <char style="wj">“How difficult indeed it is for someone
        who owns a lot of stuff to have God interact with him (enter God’s kingdom).”</char> <verse eid="MRK 10:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 10:24" />His disciples were simply stunned by this statement. But again Jesus, from out of his contemplation,
        said to them, <char style="wj">“Boys, how difficult it is to enter God’s kingdom. </char><verse eid="MRK 10:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 10:25" /><char style="wj">It’s easier for a camel to crouch down and crawl through a small gate portal than for
        a rich person to enter God’s kingdom.” </char><verse eid="MRK 10:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 10:26" />But still in a state of shock, they say to one another, “And how can anyone be kept from this?” <verse eid="MRK 10:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 10:27" />Jesus stared at them and declares, <char style="wj">“With people, it’s not possible—certainly not without
        God; for all things are possible with God.” </char><verse eid="MRK 10:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 10:28" />Peter proceeded to say to him, “Look—we for our part left everything so that we could become your followers.”<verse eid="MRK 10:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 10:29" />Jesus said, <char style="wj">“I’m telling you for sure: nobody who’s left his home or his brother or
        sister or mother or father or child or livelihood on account of me and on account of the Good News </char><verse eid="MRK 10:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 10:30" /><char style="wj">will fail to receive big time—right now in this present age—homes, brothers, sisters,
        mothers, children, livelihoods—along with persecution, and that special fullness of life (eternal life)
        in the age to come. </char><verse eid="MRK 10:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 10:31" /><char style="wj">And many who are first will be last and last first.”</char><verse eid="MRK 10:31" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 10:32" />They were on their way over to Jerusalem, and Jesus was leading the pack. They were all the while stunned:
        those following his lead were in a state of fear. Confiding in the Twelve, he began to go over with them
        what would happen to him, the things in motion that were converging. <verse eid="MRK 10:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 10:33" /><char style="wj">”…Because, you see, we’re going to Jerusalem, and the Man will be apprehended by the
        chief priests and the designated teachers, they’ll sentence him to death, and hand him over to the Gentiles.
        </char><verse eid="MRK 10:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 10:34" /><char style="wj">They’ll make fun of him, spit on him, flog him, and kill him, and after three days,
        he’ll be resurrected.”</char><verse eid="MRK 10:34" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 10:35" />James and John, the sons of Zebedee, wandered over to him and said to him,
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 10:35">“Teacher, we want to ask a favor of you.”<verse eid="MRK 10:35"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 10:36" />He said, <char style="wj">“What do you want me to do for you?”</char><verse eid="MRK 10:36" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 10:37" />They said, “Let one of us be your number-one man and the other your number-two when you’re invested in
        your regal power.”<verse eid="MRK 10:37" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 10:38" />Jesus said, <char style="wj">“You don’t have any idea what you’re asking for. Can you go through what
        I have to go through or get in up to your neck in the same things I have to?”</char><verse eid="MRK 10:38" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 10:39" />They said, “We can.”
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 10:39">Jesus said, <char style="wj">“What I’ll go through, so will you, and what I’ll be up to my neck in, so
        will you. </char><verse eid="MRK 10:39"/>
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 10:40" /><char style="wj">But to be my number-one or number-two man is not for me to grant, but is reserved for
        those for whom it has been prepared.”</char><verse eid="MRK 10:40" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 10:41" />Once they heard about this, the ten became furious with James and John. <verse eid="MRK 10:41" />
      <verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 10:42" />Jesus called them over and tells them, <char style="wj">“You’re aware that those considered to be leaders
        of the peoples throughout the earth subjugate the populace, and their chiefs, filled with charisma and
        valor, maintain absolute authority over them. </char><verse eid="MRK 10:42" />
      <verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 10:43" /><char style="wj">But it will not be this way among you; instead, whoever would desire to be a charismatic,
        valor-filled chief among you will be everyone’s servant, </char><verse eid="MRK 10:43" />
      <verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 10:44" /><char style="wj">and whoever would desire to be number-one among you will be everyone’s servant, </char><verse eid="MRK 10:44" />
      <verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 10:45" /><char style="wj">seeing that the Man didn’t come to be served either, but instead to serve and to give
        his life-being as a ransom payment to ransom the many.”</char><verse eid="MRK 10:45" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 10:46" />They came to Jericho, and while he, his disciples, and a sizeable crowd were departing Jericho, the son
        of Timaeus, Bartimaeus by name, a blind beggar, was sitting alongside the road. <verse eid="MRK 10:46" />
      <verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 10:47" />Having heard that Jesus of Nazareth was the reason for the crowd, he began to cry out repeatedly, saying,
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 10:47">“Jesus, you marvelous godsend, have pity on me!”<verse eid="MRK 10:47"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 10:48" />Many scolded him to hush him up, but he cried out all the more, “You marvelous godsend, have pity on
        me!”<verse eid="MRK 10:48" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 10:49" />Jesus stood still and said, <char style="wj">“Call him over.”</char>
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 10:49">They called for the blind man, saying to him, “Brace yourself—get up, he’s calling you.”<verse eid="MRK 10:49"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 10:50" />He threw off his cloak, shot up, and went to Jesus. <verse eid="MRK 10:50" />
      <verse number="51" style="v" sid="MRK 10:51" />Jesus answered, <char style="wj">“What can I do for you?”</char>
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 10:51">The blind man said, “Teacher—I just want to see again.”<verse eid="MRK 10:51"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="52" style="v" sid="MRK 10:52" />Jesus said, <char style="wj">“Get going now, your faith has pulled you through.” </char>Immediately,
        he regained his sight and took to the road, as he started being his follower.<verse eid="MRK 10:52" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="MRK 10" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 11   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="MRK 11" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 11:1" />When they neared Jerusalem, arriving at Bethphage and Bethany at the Mount of Olives, he sent out two
        of his disciples. <verse eid="MRK 11:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 11:2" />He, giving instructions, says to them, <char style="wj">“Go over to the town across the way from where
        you’re at, and as you go in, immediately you’ll find a colt which no person has ever mounted tied down.
        Untie it and start bringing it back. </char><verse eid="MRK 11:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 11:3" /><char style="wj">If anyone says to you, ‘Why are you doing this?’ Say, ‘His master needs it,’ and bring
        it back here right away.</char>” <verse eid="MRK 11:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 11:4" />They left and found a colt tied to a gate which was up against the street, and they untied it. <verse eid="MRK 11:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 11:5" />Some people who were standing there proceeded to tell them, “What are you doing, untying the colt?” <verse eid="MRK 11:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 11:6" />They told them what Jesus said, and they left them alone. <verse eid="MRK 11:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 11:7" />They then bring the colt to Jesus, toss their outer garments on it, and he mounted it. <verse eid="MRK 11:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 11:8" />Many people spread their outer garments out on the road, and others spread tall grass out, which was
        chopped down and brought over from the fields. <verse eid="MRK 11:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 11:9" />Those preceding and those following kept on shouting out,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 11:9"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 11:9">Rescue us!</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 11:9">Praise be to him who comes at the Lord’s behest.<verse eid="MRK 11:9"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 11:10" />Praise be to the coming monarchy of our patriarch David.
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 11:10">Rescue us to the max!<verse eid="MRK 11:10"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 11:11" />He entered Jerusalem and went into the temple complex and looked around at everything. It being late
        in the day already, he departed with the Twelve for Bethany. <verse eid="MRK 11:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 11:12" />The next day, while they were leaving Bethany, <verse eid="MRK 11:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 11:13" />seeing from a distance a fig tree that was in leaf, he went over to it, if perchance he would find anything
        nestled in it, and when he got up close to it, he found nothing except for leaves, since figs weren’t
        in season. <verse eid="MRK 11:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 11:14" />He considered the situation and said, <char style="wj">“No longer—forever and ever—will anyone eat fruit
        which you’ve yielded.”</char> And his disciples were listening when he said it.<verse eid="MRK 11:14" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 11:15" />They then come to Jerusalem. After entering the temple complex, he began to throw out the salesmen and
        the merchandisers doing business in the temple, and he turned over the tables of the money changers and
        of those who were seated selling doves. <verse eid="MRK 11:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 11:16" />He wasn’t letting anyone transport boxes containing merchandise through the temple. <verse eid="MRK 11:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 11:17" />He was going about instructing them and, as part of doing so, said to them, <char style="wj">“Has it
        not been written in the Scriptures, ‘My house shall be called a house of prayer among all the nations’?—But
        you have made it into a robber’s hideout.” </char><verse eid="MRK 11:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 11:18" />The chief priests and the designated teachers heard about this and were trying to find a way they could
        eliminate him; the fact was, the crowd was amazed at his teaching. <verse eid="MRK 11:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 11:19" />He was in the habit of leaving the city when evening arrived.<verse eid="MRK 11:19" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 11:20" />Passing by in the morning, they saw the fig tree shriveled up from the roots on up. <verse eid="MRK 11:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 11:21" />Peter recalled the incident and as a result says, “Teacher, look—the fig tree which you cursed is all
        shriveled up.” <verse eid="MRK 11:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 11:22" />Jesus, considering what happened, replied to them, <char style="wj">“Have the God-kind of faith. </char><verse eid="MRK 11:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 11:23" /><char style="wj">I’m telling you the truth—if someone were to speak to this mountain, ‘Be lifted up and
        thrown into the sea,’ and would not doubt in his heart but instead would believe that that which he says
        is coming to pass, it will be that way with him. </char><verse eid="MRK 11:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 11:24" /><char style="wj">On account of this, I say to you: all things which you all ask for in prayer, believe
        that you have received, and it will be that way with you. </char><verse eid="MRK 11:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 11:25" /><char style="wj">And when you’re standing up praying, if you have something against someone, forgive,
        so that our Father in heaven would forgive you of your sins.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 11:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 11:26" /><verse eid="MRK 11:26" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 11:27" />He went to Jerusalem again. While he was walking about the temple compound, the chief priests, the designated
        teachers, and the councilmen approached him. <verse eid="MRK 11:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 11:28" />They started speaking to him,
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 11:28">“By what authority do you do these things? In other words, who gave you the authority to do these things?”<verse eid="MRK 11:28"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 11:29" />Jesus said, <char style="wj">“You answer my question, and I’ll answer yours. </char><verse eid="MRK 11:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 11:30" /><char style="wj">John’s baptism: was his authority to baptize derived from heaven or from mankind?—Answer
        me.”</char><verse eid="MRK 11:30" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 11:31" />They talked it over amongst themselves, saying, “If we say ‘From heaven’, he’ll say, ‘Then why didn’t
        you believe in him?’ <verse eid="MRK 11:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 11:32" />But if we say, ‘From mankind,’…”—They feared the crowd, since everyone considered John to be a prophet.<verse eid="MRK 11:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 11:33" />They answered Jesus, “We don’t know.”
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 11:33">And Jesus then tells them, <char style="wj">“Nor will I tell you by what authority I do these things.”</char><verse eid="MRK 11:33"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="MRK 11" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 12   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="MRK 12" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 12:1" />He proceeded to speak to them by means of analogy: <char style="wj">“A man planted a vineyard, put a
        fence around it, dug a wine press for it, leased it out to tenant gardeners, and went abroad. </char><verse eid="MRK 12:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 12:2" /><char style="wj">When the harvest season came, he sent a servant to the tenants to get his cut of the
        vineyard’s produce. </char><verse eid="MRK 12:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 12:3" /><char style="wj">They took him, beat him up, and sent him away empty-handed. </char><verse eid="MRK 12:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 12:4" /><char style="wj">Again, he sent them another servant, and they slapped him around and treated him with
        contempt. </char><verse eid="MRK 12:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 12:5" /><char style="wj">He sent yet another, and they killed that poor fellow too. And many others…some they
        beat, others they killed. </char><verse eid="MRK 12:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 12:6" /><char style="wj">He thought to himself, ‘I still have one more: a beloved son.’ Last of all, he sent
        him to them saying, ‘They’ll respect my son.’ </char><verse eid="MRK 12:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 12:7" /><char style="wj">But those tenants said to themselves, ‘This is the heir; come on, let’s go kill him,
        and we’ll lay claim to the estate.’ </char><verse eid="MRK 12:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 12:8" /><char style="wj">They took him, kicked him out of the vineyard, and killed him. </char><verse eid="MRK 12:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 12:9" /><char style="wj">What, then, will the vineyard owner do? He’ll go and kill those tenants and lease out
        the vineyard to others. </char><verse eid="MRK 12:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 12:10" /><char style="wj">You’ve never read this verse, have you,</char>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 12:10"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 12:10"><char style="wj">“The stone which the masons inspected and rejected—</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 12:10"><char style="wj">This became the main cornerstone.</char><verse eid="MRK 12:10"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 12:11" /><char style="wj">By the Lord’s doing it came to pass</char>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 12:11"><char style="wj">And is something our eyes are in awe over.”</char><verse eid="MRK 12:11"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 12:12" />All the while they were seeking to get ahold of him, but were afraid of the crowd, since they knew that
        the analogy was directed at them. They left him alone and departed.<verse eid="MRK 12:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 12:13" />They sent some of the Pharisees and some Herod supporters to him in order to catch him making a mistake
        while conversing. <verse eid="MRK 12:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 12:14" />They went and said to him, “Teacher, we know that you’re honest and that what you teach is the true way
        to God and that you could care less what anyone thinks about you, all the more so since you’re not affected
        by people’s attitudes, but you teach God’s way in a truthful manner. Do we have to pay Caesar the poll
        tax or not? Shall we pay or not pay?” <verse eid="MRK 12:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 12:15" />Having a full view of their hypocrisy presented before him, he said,
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 12:15"><char style="wj">“Why are you trying to trip me up? Bring me a coin used for the tax payment so that
        I can take a look at it.”</char><verse eid="MRK 12:15"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 12:16" />They brought him one.
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 12:16">He then says, <char style="wj">“Whose picture do you see etched in here?”</char></para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 12:16">They said, “Caesar’s.”<verse eid="MRK 12:16"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 12:17" />Jesus said, <char style="wj">“Give Caesar’s things to Caesar, and God’s things to God.”</char>
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 12:17">They were stunned.<verse eid="MRK 12:17"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 12:18" />The Sadducees, who claim that there is no life after death, went up to him and put a question to him,<verse eid="MRK 12:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 12:19" />”Teacher, the Old Testament says that if someone’s brother dies and leaves a wife behind but didn’t leave
        a son, his brother will take the woman as his wife for the purpose of producing a male offspring for
        the sake of his dead brother. <verse eid="MRK 12:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 12:20" />There were seven brothers. The first got married to a woman and died, not leaving a descendent, <verse eid="MRK 12:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 12:21" />and the second took her as his wife and died, not leaving a descendent, and the third, and so forth.<verse eid="MRK 12:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 12:22" />The seven left no descendent. Last of all, the woman died. <verse eid="MRK 12:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 12:23" />Which of them will she be the wife of in the after-life, since all seven had married her?”<verse eid="MRK 12:23" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 12:24" />Jesus said, <char style="wj">“Is it not on account of your not being familiar with the Scriptures nor
        with God’s supernatural ability that you get off-base? </char><verse eid="MRK 12:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 12:25" /><char style="wj">The fact is, when you die and live on in the after-life, there is no marriage, but instead
        you exist like the angels exist in the spiritual world. </char><verse eid="MRK 12:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 12:26" /><char style="wj">But concerning life after death, that is, the fact that you take up a new life after
        you die: haven’t you read the story about the burning bush in the Old Testament where it says, ‘I myself
        am the God of Abraham and the God of Isaac and the God of Jacob.’? </char><verse eid="MRK 12:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 12:27" /><char style="wj">God’s not a God of the dead but of the living. You’re really off-base.”</char><verse eid="MRK 12:27" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 12:28" />One of the designated teachers heard them debating and seeing how well he replied to them asked him,
        “Which is the most important commandment?” <verse eid="MRK 12:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 12:29" />Jesus answered, <char style="wj">“The most important one is, ‘Hear, Israel, the Lord your God is one,
        </char><verse eid="MRK 12:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 12:30" /><char style="wj">and you will love the Lord your God from your entire heart, from your entire life being,
        from your entire mind, and from out of your entire might.’ </char><verse eid="MRK 12:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 12:31" /><char style="wj">The second most important commandment is, ‘You will love your neighbor as yourself.’
        There’s no other commandment greater than these.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 12:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 12:32" />The designated teacher said to him, “Well-said, teacher, you really hit the nail on the head, since,
        ‘He is One and there is no other one than Him,’ <verse eid="MRK 12:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 12:33" />plus the quotation ‘…to love him from the entire heart and from the entire conscience and from the entire
        strength,’ plus the quotation ‘…to love a neighbor as yourself’ exceeds all burnt offerings and sacrifices.”<verse eid="MRK 12:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 12:34" />Jesus, seeing that he got it, replied, <char style="wj">“You’re not far from God choosing to have a relationship
        with you (from God’s kingdom).”</char> No one had the guts to ask him anything else any more.<verse eid="MRK 12:34" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 12:35" />After some thought, Jesus proceeded to speak, teaching in the temple, <char style="wj">“Who do the designated
        teachers say that the Messiah is? </char><verse eid="MRK 12:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 12:36" /><char style="wj">David himself spoke by the Holy Spirit,</char>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 12:36"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 12:36"><char style="wj">”An all-powerful Lord said to my lord,</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 12:36"><char style="wj">Be my right-hand man</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 12:36"><char style="wj">Until I decide to subdue your enemies and subjugate them to you</char><verse eid="MRK 12:36"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 12:37" /><char style="wj">”David himself calls him lord, so how can he be his descendant?” </char>The crowd, which
        was large, listened to him with delight.<verse eid="MRK 12:37" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 12:38" />He continued his teaching by saying to them, <char style="wj">“Observe how the designated teachers like
        going about in the marketplaces and town squares wearing long robes, </char><verse eid="MRK 12:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 12:39" /><char style="wj">and occupy the most prestigious seats in the synagogues and at banquets, </char><verse eid="MRK 12:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 12:40" /><char style="wj">those who gobble up widows’ homes and ostentatiously pray long-winded prayers: these
        guys will receive quite a harsh sentence on judgment day.”</char><verse eid="MRK 12:40" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 12:41" />He seated himself across from the collection basket, and watched and watched people, just what amount
        of money they were tossing into the basket; the rich people were tossing in great amounts. <verse eid="MRK 12:41" />
      <verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 12:42" />This one widow came and tossed in a couple of dollars. <verse eid="MRK 12:42" />
      <verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 12:43" />He called his disciples over and said, <char style="wj">“I’m telling you the honest-to-goodness truth:
        this widow, poor though she is, put in more than everyone else, </char><verse eid="MRK 12:43" />
      <verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 12:44" /><char style="wj">since everyone contributed out of their abundance, but out of her lack she tossed in
        every cent that she had, everything she had to live on.”</char><verse eid="MRK 12:44" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="MRK 12" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 13   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="MRK 13" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 13:1" />While leaving the temple, one of his disciples then says, “Teacher, look—what breathtaking stones and
        edifices.” <verse eid="MRK 13:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 13:2" />Jesus said to him, <char style="wj">“See these great edifices here? Not a single stone here will remain
        on top of another stone which will not in any way get torn down.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 13:3" />Sitting across from temple on the Mount of Olives alone with Peter, James, John, and Andrew, <verse eid="MRK 13:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 13:4" />they asked him confidentially, “When will these things take place, and what will be the sign indicating
        when the conclusion of all things is supposed to happen?” <verse eid="MRK 13:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 13:5" />Jesus began by saying to them, <char style="wj">“See to it that no one gets you off-base; </char><verse eid="MRK 13:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 13:6" /><char style="wj">many will come claiming to have my authority saying, ‘I am the one-and-only one,’ and
        many will get off-base. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 13:7" /><char style="wj">When you hear about there being wars and news of wars that are right around the corner,
        don’t get rattled: these things have to happen, but it’s not over yet. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 13:8" /><char style="wj">You see, nations and ethnic groups will assert themselves against or attack other nations
        and ethnic groups, and kingdoms against kingdoms; there’ll be earthquakes from place to place; there’ll
        be famines—these are the first labor pains. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 13:9" /><char style="wj">For your part, look after yourselves; they’ll take you into custody and drag you before
        the local council, they’ll work you over in the synagogues, and on account of me you’ll be made to stand
        before rulers and kings and testify before them. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 13:10" /><char style="wj">The Good News must be proclaimed to all the nations and ethnic groups. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 13:11" /><char style="wj">When they take you away into custody, don’t worry beforehand what you’ll say, but instead
        what you’re going to say will be given to you the very moment it’s needed; you see, it’s not you who’s
        doing the talking but rather the Holy Spirit. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 13:12" /><char style="wj">A brother will betray a brother to the point of death, and a father his son, and children
        will turn against their parent, defy them, and become hostile towards them, and because of this they’ll
        be put to death. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 13:13" /><char style="wj">You’ll be hated by everyone on account of you doing what I told you to do. He who perseveres
        until it’s all over—that’s the sort of guy who’ll survive.</char><verse eid="MRK 13:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 13:14" /><char style="wj">”When you see the ‘abomination that causes things to fall into desolation’—the Prophet
        Daniel’s prophecy—standing where it shouldn’t (have the one who reads this out loud to the congregation
        get up to speed on this ahead of time), then have those in Judea flee to the mountains. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 13:15" /><char style="wj">Don’t have whoever’s on the porch go down, go in, and fetch anything out of the house,</char><verse eid="MRK 13:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 13:16" /><char style="wj">and don’t have whoever’s in the field turn around and grab his coat. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 13:17" /><char style="wj">Oh, how terrible it’ll be for women at that time who are pregnant or have infants!</char><verse eid="MRK 13:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 13:18" /><char style="wj">Hope to God that it won’t be wintertime. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 13:19" /><char style="wj">You see, there’ll be a tremendous amount of suffering, such which hasn’t occurred from
        the beginning of time until now and will never happen again. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 13:20" /><char style="wj">If it weren’t for those days having been cut short, then not a single living being would
        survive; but those days will be cut short on account of the Chosen Ones. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 13:21" /><char style="wj">At that time, if someone says to you, ‘Look here—the Messiah’ or ‘Here he is’, don’t
        believe him, </char><verse eid="MRK 13:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 13:22" /><char style="wj">since false messiahs will come to the forefront and produce great signs and wonders
        in order to deceive, if possible, the Chosen Ones. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 13:23" /><char style="wj">Keep your eyes open—I’ve told you this ahead of time.</char><verse eid="MRK 13:23" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 13:24" /><char style="wj">”More to the point, though, in those days, after that ordeal of suffering,</char>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 13:24"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 13:24"><char style="wj">“The sun will go dark,</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 13:24"><char style="wj">And the moon won’t shine.</char><verse eid="MRK 13:24"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 13:25" /><char style="wj">The stars will be falling out of the sky.</char>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 13:25"><char style="wj">The wonder and might of those things</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 13:25"><char style="wj">In the sky extending into heaven will be shaken.</char><verse eid="MRK 13:25"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 13:26" /><char style="wj">”Then they’ll see the Man coming in the clouds with great might and glory, </char><verse eid="MRK 13:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 13:27" /><char style="wj">and then he will send the angels and will gather his Chosen Ones from every corner of
        the earth, from one side of the planet to another.</char><verse eid="MRK 13:27" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 13:28" /><char style="wj">”Learn from the example of the fig tree: when its branches become tender and its leaves
        bud, know that summer is right around the corner. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 13:29" /><char style="wj">The same thing applies to you: when you finally do see these things taking place, understand
        that it’ll be real soon, as it’s right at your doorstep. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 13:30" /><char style="wj">You can count on what I’m telling you: that very period in the history of mankind won’t
        go away until all these things come to pass. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 13:31" /><char style="wj">The sky and the earth will go away, but my words will never-ever go away.</char><verse eid="MRK 13:31" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 13:32" /><char style="wj">”But concerning that day and hour (i.e., the exact moment), nobody knows, neither the
        angels in heaven nor the Son—nobody except for the Father. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 13:33" /><char style="wj">See that you’re ready, since you don’t know what the timeframe will be—</char><verse eid="MRK 13:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 13:34" /><char style="wj">like a man who’s frequently on the road, who, when leaving home, left his servants in
        charge of each of his various estate shops and commanded the doorkeeper to keep watch. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 13:35" /><char style="wj">So now, stay alert, since you don’t know when the estate owner will come, whether it
        be at sunset…whether in the middle of the night…whether just before daybreak…whether at daybreak. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 13:36" /><char style="wj">May he not come all of a sudden and catch you all asleep. </char><verse eid="MRK 13:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 13:37" /><char style="wj">But the point that I’m making in this story applies to you all as well: Stay focused!”</char><verse eid="MRK 13:37" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="MRK 13" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 14   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="MRK 14" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 14:1" />Now in two days the Passover and the Feast of Unleavened Bread was scheduled to start. The chief priests
        and the designated teachers were looking and looking for a way to use some sort of trickery to get ahold
        of him and kill him. <verse eid="MRK 14:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 14:2" />In this regard, they kept on saying, “Not in the midst of the festival, lest the people riot.”<verse eid="MRK 14:2" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 14:3" />While staying in Bethany, in Simon the leper’s house, while he was sitting at the dinner table, a woman
        with a jar of fragrant ointment—the pure, genuine expensive stuff—went up to him, cracked the jar open,
        and poured it all out on his head. <verse eid="MRK 14:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 14:4" />Now some of them who were there were furious, complaining amongst themselves, “What does her wasting
        of this ointment accomplish? <verse eid="MRK 14:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 14:5" />The fact is, this ointment here could’ve been sold for upwards of $30,000, and the proceeds donated to
        the poor.” They were fuming with indignation over her. <verse eid="MRK 14:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 14:6" />But Jesus said, <char style="wj">“Leave her alone—why are you hassling her? She did me a favor. </char><verse eid="MRK 14:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 14:7" /><char style="wj">You see, you’ll always have the poor among you, and whenever you want you can do a kind
        deed for them, but you’ll not always have me around. </char><verse eid="MRK 14:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 14:8" /><char style="wj">She did what she could to embalm my body ahead of time as part of the burial mummification.
        </char><verse eid="MRK 14:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 14:9" /><char style="wj">Mark my words: wherever the Good News will be proclaimed—wherever in the whole world—what
        she did will also be talked about in memory of her.”</char><verse eid="MRK 14:9" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 14:10" />Judas Iscariot, one of the Twelve, left to meet up with the chief priests, in order for him to deliver
        Jesus into their custody. <verse eid="MRK 14:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 14:11" />When they heard the proposal, they were delighted and promised to give him a wad of cash. They began
        to look for an opportune moment to apprehend him.<verse eid="MRK 14:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 14:12" />On the first day of the Feast of Unleavened Bread, the day when they slaughtered the Passover sacrifice,
        his disciples, querying him, say, “Where do you want us to venture out to, to make the arrangements for
        you to partake of the Passover meal?” <verse eid="MRK 14:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 14:13" />He dispatched two of his disciples telling them, <char style="wj">“Go into the city, and a man carrying
        a pot of water will encounter you; follow him. </char><verse eid="MRK 14:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 14:14" /><char style="wj">Whatever place he happens to enter, say to the owner, ‘The teacher says, where is my
        dining room, the one where I’ll partake of the Passover meal with my disciples?’, </char><verse eid="MRK 14:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 14:15" /><char style="wj">and he personally will show you a large, upstairs room with everything spread out and
        ready, and there you’ll make the arrangements for us.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 14:16" />The disciples departed and went into the city and found things to be just like he told them, and they
        made the Passover meal arrangements.<verse eid="MRK 14:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 14:17" />When it got to be late in the day, he arrived with the Twelve. <verse eid="MRK 14:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 14:18" />While they were dining and relaxing, Jesus said, <char style="wj">“Mark my words—I’m telling you, one
        of you dining here with me will betray me.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 14:19" />They became deeply upset, and they went on and on, one after another, telling him, “It’s not me.” <verse eid="MRK 14:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 14:20" />But he said, <char style="wj">“It’ll be one of the Twelve, one who raises his glass to offer a toast.
        </char><verse eid="MRK 14:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 14:21" /><char style="wj">And here’s the thing—sure—the Man will follow the trajectory that’s been specified by
        the verses in the Scriptures that talk about him. But on the other hand, bad things are in store for
        the person through whom the Man will be apprehended as a result of betrayal; that guy would be better
        if he’d never been born.”</char><verse eid="MRK 14:21" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 14:22" />While still eating, he took a loaf of bread, gave thanks, broke it, gave it to them, and said, <char
        style="wj">“Take this. This is my body.” </char><verse eid="MRK 14:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 14:23" />He took a cup, gave thanks, gave it to them, <verse eid="MRK 14:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 14:24" />and said, <char style="wj">“This is my blood of the covenant, that which is poured out on behalf of many.
        </char><verse eid="MRK 14:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 14:25" /><char style="wj">I’m telling you for certain that I absolutely won’t drink from what’s generated from
        the vineyard until that day when God’s master plan manifests (in God’s kingdom) when I’ll drink it afresh.”
        </char><verse eid="MRK 14:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 14:26" />After they sang some hymns, they left for the Mount of Olives.<verse eid="MRK 14:26" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 14:27" />Jesus then says to them, <char style="wj">“All of you will fall out with me tonight, because it has been
        recorded in the Scriptures,</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 14:27"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 14:27"><char style="wj">“I will strike the shepherd,</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 14:27"><char style="wj">And the sheep will scatter all over the place</char><verse eid="MRK 14:27"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 14:28" /><char style="wj">”But never mind that—after my resurrection, I’ll go on out ahead of you to Galilee.”
        </char><verse eid="MRK 14:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 14:29" />Peter said to him, “Even if everyone else falls out, I won’t, uh-uh.” <verse eid="MRK 14:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 14:30" />Jesus said to him, <char style="wj">“I’m telling you for certain that before the rooster crows twice,
        you will have denied me three times.” </char><verse eid="MRK 14:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 14:31" />All the more vehemently he kept on saying, “Even if I have to die with you, I won’t deny you—no way!”
        The others, one after another, were saying the same thing.<verse eid="MRK 14:31" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 14:32" />They went to a place called Gethsemane, and he said to his disciples, <char style="wj">“Sit here until
        I’m done praying.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 14:33" />He took along with him Peter, James, and John and started to become gripped with agony and consternation.<verse eid="MRK 14:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 14:34" />He, in the midst of it, says, <char style="wj">“My life-being is pained all throughout in grief to the
        point of death: stay here with me and stay focused.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 14:35" />He wandered out a bit and fell on the ground and began to pray and pray, praying if it’s possible that
        this hour pass him by. <verse eid="MRK 14:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 14:36" />In the midst of that he was saying, <char style="wj">“Abba—my Father—by You, all things are possible:
        let this ordeal pass me by. But in any case, not what I want but what You want.”</char><verse eid="MRK 14:36" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 14:37" />He went and found them sleeping and then says to Peter, <char style="wj">“Simon, you’re asleep? You didn’t
        have the stamina to focus for one hour? </char><verse eid="MRK 14:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 14:38" /><char style="wj">Evermore stay focused in prayer, so that you don’t reach the point where trials can
        break you; indeed the spirit is gung-ho, but human nature is weak.”</char><verse eid="MRK 14:38" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 14:39" />Again, he went out and prayed the same prayer, <verse eid="MRK 14:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 14:40" />and again he found them sleeping; they didn’t know what they would say in response to him since their
        eyelids were sagging. <verse eid="MRK 14:40" />
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 14:41" />He came a third time and said to them, <char style="wj">“You chose to sleep in the interim and get rested
        up?—The moment has come—here we go: the Man is being handed over into the hands of sinners. </char><verse eid="MRK 14:41" />
      <verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 14:42" /><char style="wj">Get up, let’s go; look—the one facilitating my arrest has arrived.”</char><verse eid="MRK 14:42" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 14:43" />Right away, while he was still speaking, Judas, one of the Twelve, showed up with a large party armed
        with swords and clubs sent from the chief priests, designated teachers, and councilmen. <verse eid="MRK 14:43" />
      <verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 14:44" />His betrayer had set up a signal ahead of time, saying, “Whomever I greet with a kiss, seize him, secure
        him, and take him away.” <verse eid="MRK 14:44" />
      <verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 14:45" />He went straight over to him and then says, “Teacher,” and kissed him cordially. <verse eid="MRK 14:45" />
      <verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 14:46" />They laid their hands on him and grabbed ahold of him. <verse eid="MRK 14:46" />
      <verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 14:47" />One of the men standing there with Jesus (and who was one of his associates, supporters, and defenders)
        unsheathed a sword, attacked the chief priest’s slave, and sliced off his ear. <verse eid="MRK 14:47" />
      <verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 14:48" />Jesus considered what had happened and said to the party, <char style="wj">“So you came out to seize
        me with swords and clubs, like you’re pouncing on a thug? </char><verse eid="MRK 14:48" />
      <verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 14:49" /><char style="wj">Day by day, I was at the same place you were at in the temple complex teaching, and
        you didn’t grab me? Anyways—this happened in order to fulfill the Scriptures.”</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:49" />
      <verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 14:50" />Everyone who was standing there with Jesus deserted him and began to flee. <verse eid="MRK 14:50" />
      <verse number="51" style="v" sid="MRK 14:51" />A certain young man (a teenager) tagged along behind him, clothed only in a linen garment around his
        private parts. They grabbed him, <verse eid="MRK 14:51" />
      <verse number="52" style="v" sid="MRK 14:52" />but he shed the garment they grabbed and ran away naked.<verse eid="MRK 14:52" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="53" style="v" sid="MRK 14:53" />They took Jesus away to the high priest, and all the chief priests, the councilmen, and the designated
        teachers gathered together there. <verse eid="MRK 14:53" />
      <verse number="54" style="v" sid="MRK 14:54" />Peter followed him from a distance, until he was within the courtyard of the chief priest’s domicile,
        and he took a seat alongside the attendants, warming himself up next to the fire used as the light source.<verse eid="MRK 14:54" />
      <verse number="55" style="v" sid="MRK 14:55" />Now the chief priests and all the councilmen were trying to find someone to testify under oath against
        Jesus in order to sentence him to death, but they weren’t having any success finding anyone. <verse eid="MRK 14:55" />
      <verse number="56" style="v" sid="MRK 14:56" />To that ends, many were saying phony things against him in court under oath, but the testimonies weren’t
        compelling. <verse eid="MRK 14:56" />
      <verse number="57" style="v" sid="MRK 14:57" />Some of the ones taking the witness stand and testifying against him were saying, <verse eid="MRK 14:57" />
      <verse number="58" style="v" sid="MRK 14:58" />”We personally heard him say, ‘I’ll tear down this man-made temple myself, and in three days I’ll build
        another one, one that’s not man-made’,” <verse eid="MRK 14:58" />
      <verse number="59" style="v" sid="MRK 14:59" />but this testimony wasn’t adequate enough to produce a guilty verdict either. <verse eid="MRK 14:59" />
      <verse number="60" style="v" sid="MRK 14:60" />The high priest stood up in front of everyone and, by means of inquiry, asked Jesus, “You don’t have
        anything to say in response to those who’ve testified against you?” <verse eid="MRK 14:60" />
      <verse number="61" style="v" sid="MRK 14:61" />He kept silent and wouldn’t say anything in response. Again, the high priest asked him, “Are you the
        Messiah, the Christ, the Blessed Son?”, <verse eid="MRK 14:61" />
      <verse number="62" style="v" sid="MRK 14:62" />and he said, <char style="wj">“I am the one-and-only one. And,</char>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 14:62"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 14:62"><char style="wj">“You will see the Man</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 14:62"><char style="wj">In his role as a powerful right-hand man</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="MRK 14:62"><char style="wj">Coming with the clouds of the sky”</char><verse eid="MRK 14:62"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="63" style="v" sid="MRK 14:63" />Then the high priest became unglued and in a rage starting breaking things, all the while saying, “What
        further testimony do we need? <verse eid="MRK 14:63" />
      <verse number="64" style="v" sid="MRK 14:64" />You all heard the blasphemy; what’s it looking like to you?” So everyone there sentenced him to death.<verse eid="MRK 14:64" />
      <verse number="65" style="v" sid="MRK 14:65" />Some of them began to go about spitting on him, blindfolding him, and striking him, saying to him, “Prophesy.”
        And then the attendants took him and slapped him around.<verse eid="MRK 14:65" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="66" style="v" sid="MRK 14:66" />Being outside in the courtyard, Peter was approached by one of the high priest’s servant girls. <verse eid="MRK 14:66" />
      <verse number="67" style="v" sid="MRK 14:67" />She saw Peter warming himself up, took a good hard look at him, and then says to him, “You too were with
        Jesus of Nazareth.” <verse eid="MRK 14:67" />
      <verse number="68" style="v" sid="MRK 14:68" />He denied it, saying, “I have no first-hand knowledge or understanding of what you’re saying,” and he
        left the courtyard to go out to the porch. A rooster crowed. <verse eid="MRK 14:68" />
      <verse number="69" style="v" sid="MRK 14:69" />While looking at him, the servant girl began talking to the bystanders again, “This guy’s one of them.”<verse eid="MRK 14:69" />
      <verse number="70" style="v" sid="MRK 14:70" />He denied it again. Again, a bit later, the bystanders were saying to Peter, “Seriously—you’re one of
        them, since you’re a Galilean.” <verse eid="MRK 14:70" />
      <verse number="71" style="v" sid="MRK 14:71" />He began to cuss repeatedly and to swear by oaths, “I don’t know this person, whomever it is that you’re
        talking about.” <verse eid="MRK 14:71" />
      <verse number="72" style="v" sid="MRK 14:72" />Immediately a rooster crowed a second time. Peter remembered the statement which Jesus made, that before
        a rooster crows twice, you will have denied me three times. It hit him like a ton of bricks, and he started
        crying.<verse eid="MRK 14:72" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="MRK 14" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 15   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="MRK 15" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 15:1" />Without delay, late in the night the chief priests, along with all the councilmen and the designated
        teachers, convened a meeting, bound Jesus, carried him away, and delivered him into Pilate’s custody.<verse eid="MRK 15:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 15:2" />Pilate asked him, “You’re the king of the Jews?” He answered him, “Whatever you say.” <verse eid="MRK 15:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 15:3" />The chief priests accused him of many things. <verse eid="MRK 15:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 15:4" />Again, Pilate asked him, “You’re not going to say anything in response? Take a look at how many accusations
        they’ve leveled against you.” <verse eid="MRK 15:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 15:5" />But to Pilate’s astonishment, Jesus didn’t have anything more to say.<verse eid="MRK 15:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 15:6" />He had an ongoing tradition, done at each festival, of releasing one prisoner for them, whomever they’d
        ask for. <verse eid="MRK 15:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 15:7" />There was one called Barabbas who had been imprisoned along with the revolutionaries, in particular those
        who had committed murder during the insurrection. <verse eid="MRK 15:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 15:8" />The crowd came over and initiated making the request, in accordance with his usual practice. <verse eid="MRK 15:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 15:9" />Pilate responded to them, “Do you want me to set the king of the Jews free?”, <verse eid="MRK 15:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 15:10" />since he was aware that the chief priests had him arrested out of envy. <verse eid="MRK 15:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 15:11" />Now, the chief priests had whipped the crowd into a frenzy, in order that their preference would be to
        release Barabbas.<verse eid="MRK 15:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 15:12" />Again, Pilate responded to them,
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 15:12">“So now, what do you want me to do with the one who’s called the King of the Jews?”<verse eid="MRK 15:12"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 15:13" />Again, they shouted, “Crucify him!”<verse eid="MRK 15:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 15:14" />Pilate said to them multiple times, “…Because he’s done what wrong?”
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="MRK 15:14">But they shouted all the more, “Crucify him!”<verse eid="MRK 15:14"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 15:15" />Intending to placate the crowd, Pilate set Barabbas free and handed over Jesus, after he had him flogged,
        to be crucified.<verse eid="MRK 15:15" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 15:16" />The soldiers led him away to a courtyard inside the compound, the one used by the governor’s security
        guards, and called over the entire company of guards. <verse eid="MRK 15:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 15:17" />They clothed him in a robe a nobleman would wear and placed on him a crown, a wreath woven from thorns.<verse eid="MRK 15:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 15:18" />They began to go about greeting him, “Pleased to meet you King of the Jews.” <verse eid="MRK 15:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 15:19" />They kept on hitting him on the head with a rod, spitting on him, and getting on their knees in an act
        of subservience to him. <verse eid="MRK 15:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 15:20" />When they finished ridiculing him, they took the robe off and put his clothes back on him, and they led
        him away to be crucified.<verse eid="MRK 15:20" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 15:21" />They pressed into service a random passerby, Simon of Cyrene (the one who’s the father of Alexander and
        Rufus), who happened to be coming in from working out in the fields, to carry his cross. <verse eid="MRK 15:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 15:22" />They brought him up on top of the place called Golgotha, which translated means “Skull Place.” <verse eid="MRK 15:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 15:23" />They kept on trying to give him spiced wine, but he wouldn’t take it. <verse eid="MRK 15:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 15:24" />They crucified him and divvied up his clothing, rolling dice to see who was going to get to take it away.<verse eid="MRK 15:24" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 15:25" />Now it was mid-morning when they performed the crucifixion on him. <verse eid="MRK 15:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 15:26" />There was a sign stating the reason why he was crucified, and it read, “The king of the Jews.” <verse eid="MRK 15:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 15:27" />They crucified two thugs with him, together as a group, one to the left of him and one to the right of
        him. <verse eid="MRK 15:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 15:28" /> <verse eid="MRK 15:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 15:29" />Those who passed by reviled him, nodding their heads left and right saying, “Ah! The one who’ll supposedly
        destroy the temple and rebuild it in three days— <verse eid="MRK 15:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 15:30" />Save yourself: come down off that cross.” <verse eid="MRK 15:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 15:31" />In the same way, the chief priests and the designated teachers, going back and forth with each other
        making fun of him, in the midst of that were saying, “He went and rescued others, but he cannot save
        himself. <verse eid="MRK 15:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 15:32" />The Messiah, the Christ, the King of Israel: let him come down from the cross now, so that we would see
        and believe.” Even his fellow crucifixion-mates kept on taunting him.<verse eid="MRK 15:32" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 15:33" />When it got to be noon, darkness appeared over the entire planet until late afternoon, <verse eid="MRK 15:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 15:34" />and in the late afternoon, Jesus shouted in a loud voice, <char style="wj">“Eloi, eloi, lema sabachthani?”</char>,
        which is translated, <char style="wj">“My God, my God, why have you abandoned me?” </char><verse eid="MRK 15:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 15:35" />Some of the bystanders heard this and started saying, “Look, he’s calling on Elijah.” <verse eid="MRK 15:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 15:36" />Someone ran and soaked a sponge in a mixture of water and vinegar that the soldiers commonly drank, put
        it on a rod, and proceeded to offer it to him to drink, saying, “Let’s see if Elijah comes and takes
        him down from off the cross,” <verse eid="MRK 15:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 15:37" />but Jesus let out a great cry and passed away, <verse eid="MRK 15:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 15:38" />and the temple curtain was torn in two from top to bottom. <verse eid="MRK 15:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 15:39" />Seeing this, the army captain standing across from him said, “This man really was the embodiment of a
        son of God.” <verse eid="MRK 15:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 15:40" />Now there were also women watching at a distance, among whom were Mary Magdalene, Mary mother of James
        the younger and of Joses, and Salome, <verse eid="MRK 15:40" />
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 15:41" />those women who were ever his followers and were constantly attending to his needs when he was in Galilee,
        and many other women who accompanied him to Jerusalem.<verse eid="MRK 15:41" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 15:42" />It had gotten to be late, and since it was a preparatory day (that is, a pre-feast day or pre-Sabbath
        preparatory day), <verse eid="MRK 15:42" />
      <verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 15:43" />Joseph of Arimathea, an influential councilman, who also was himself a true believer, got up the courage,
        entered Pilate’s compound, and went up to Pilate and asked for Jesus’s body. <verse eid="MRK 15:43" />
      <verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 15:44" />But Pilate wondered if he had in fact died already, and summoned the captain and asked him if it had
        been a while since he died. <verse eid="MRK 15:44" />
      <verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 15:45" />Getting up to speed with the captain, he presented the body to Joseph as a gift, <verse eid="MRK 15:45" />
      <verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 15:46" />and Joseph purchased a cloth sheet made of linen and used for wrapping, took him down, rolled him up
        in the sheet, put him in a tomb, one which had been hewn out of a rock formation, and rolled a stone
        over the tomb’s entrance. <verse eid="MRK 15:46" />
      <verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 15:47" />Now Mary Magdalene and Mary the mother of Joses were monitoring where he was being placed.<verse eid="MRK 15:47" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
  <chapter eid="MRK 15" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 16   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="MRK 16" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 16:1" />After sundown, just after the Sabbath restrictions came to a close, Mary Magdalene, Mary mother of James,
        and Salome bought fragrant spices in order to go and apply to his body, covering it all over. <verse eid="MRK 16:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 16:2" />Very early on Sunday morning, when the sun had just risen, they went to the tomb. <verse eid="MRK 16:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 16:3" />They were repeatedly saying amongst themselves, “Who’s going to roll the stone back away from the entrance
        of the tomb?”, <verse eid="MRK 16:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 16:4" />and they all at once looked up and observed that the stone had been rolled away (it was simply enormous,
        you see). <verse eid="MRK 16:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 16:5" />They came to the tomb and saw a man who looked to be in his late teens or early twenties sitting off
        to the right wearing a long white robe, and they were startled out of their wits. <verse eid="MRK 16:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 16:6" />But he then tells them, “Don’t be startled. Jesus of Nazareth who had been crucified has been resurrected;
        he’s not here—take a look at the place where they put him. <verse eid="MRK 16:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 16:7" />In any event, go your way and tell his disciples—and Peter—that he’s heading out before them to Galilee.
        They’ll see him there, just like he told them they would.” <verse eid="MRK 16:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 16:8" />They exited the tomb and began to run away like mad, since they were in a state of shock and were shaking
        all over. They didn’t say anything to anyone, since they were still too terrified to do so.<verse eid="MRK 16:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 16:9" />After he had been resurrected early Sunday morning, he appeared first to Mary Magdalene, whom he had
        cast out seven demons out of. <verse eid="MRK 16:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 16:10" />That lady went and told the news to those who had been mourning and weeping with her, <verse eid="MRK 16:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 16:11" />and those who heard that he’s alive and that he had been seen by her refused to believe it.<verse eid="MRK 16:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 16:12" />Now after these appearances, he appeared in a different form to two of them while they were going out
        to the countryside, <verse eid="MRK 16:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 16:13" />and those very people went away and told everyone else—they didn’t believe those people either.<verse eid="MRK 16:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 16:14" />Now last of all he appeared to the Eleven while they were relaxing taking a meal, and he chewed them
        out for their refusal to believe and for their hardness of heart, because they didn’t believe those who
        had beheld him resurrected. <verse eid="MRK 16:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 16:15" />He said to them, <char style="wj">“Go into all the inhabited world and preach a complete round of the
        Good News to anything that has two legs. </char><verse eid="MRK 16:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 16:16" /><char style="wj">He who has believed and has been baptized will be kept from destruction, but he who
        has refused to believe will be condemned. </char><verse eid="MRK 16:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 16:17" /><char style="wj">These supernatural signs will accompany those who have believed: by my authority they
        will cast out demons; they will speak tongues which are new, never-heard-before languages; </char><verse eid="MRK 16:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 16:18" /><char style="wj">they will remove serpents, taking them out of the way; and if they were to drink something
        poisonous, it will certainly not harm them; they’ll lay hands on the sick and sickly, and they’ll get
        well.”</char><verse eid="MRK 16:18" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 16:19" />So then the Lord Jesus, after speaking to them, was taken up into the sky and assumed his position as
        God’s chief executive. <verse eid="MRK 16:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 16:20" />But those very disciples went out and preached everywhere, the Lord working alongside and cooperating
        with them like a fellow-worker, and the message kept on being confirmed, established, and made certain
        by means of the supernatural signs following happening right there on the spot, right on their heels.<verse eid="MRK 16:20" />
    </para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 16" />
</usx>
