<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- The Bernmeister's New Testament, Unabridged Edition -->
<!-- Copyright © 2024 Bernard M. Woodland -->
<!-- Version 1 -->
<!-- Public domain -->
<!-- The Bernmeister's NT, Unabridged Version 1 -->
<usx version="3.0">
  <!--   *******************   -->
  <!--   Titles and TOC Info   -->
  <!--   *******************   -->
  <book code="1CO" style="id">The Bernmeister's NT, Unabridged</book>
  <para style="h">1 Corinthians</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Epistle of 1 Corinthians</para>
  <para style="toc2">1 Corinthians</para>
  <para style="toc3">1 Cor.</para>
  <para style="mt2">THE EPISTLE OF</para>
  <para style="mt1">1 CORINTHIANS</para>
  <!--   ************   -->
  <!--   Introduction   -->
  <!--   ************   -->
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="ipi">The inhabitants of the Greek city of Corinth were better educated and more affluent than most of Paul’s
    other churches, and the contents of his letters to the Corinthians show a church which is a mixture of
    polar extremes, of extremes in spirituality and carnality; extremes in maturity and immaturity; extremes
    in fervency and apathy. The list goes on. But perhaps more than any other NT church, the church at Corinth
    was most like the church in the modern West, and for this reason when one reads the epistle, it’s as
    though Paul had us in mind specifically when he wrote it.</para>
  <para style="ipi">Paul’s many talents are on display in this letter. He’s not just a lofty theologian, but he can handle
    difficult people, doing so with a mixture of encouragement, rebuke, and reasoning. He appeals to their
    best side, he chastises them when their bad side dominates. But he never forgets to remind them that
    they’re specially chosen people.</para>
  <para style="ipi">The rich variety of content in this letter, and the great chapter on love, the chapters on the gifts
    of the Spirits, the chapter on death and resurrection are simply the highlights, reflects the breadth
    of the Corinthians’ spirituality. If we today are Corinth, then by proxy we are the recipients of a rich
    epistle, and this should give us hope.</para>
  <para style="ib"></para>
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  1   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="1CO 1" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 1:1" /><char style="it">From </char>Paul, who has the calling of an apostle (a missionary) of Christ Jesus through
        the will of God, and his comrade<char style="sup">[a]</char> Sosthenes—<verse eid="1CO 1:1" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 1:2" />To God’s church which exists in Corinth, those set apart by Christ Jesus <char style="it">from the unbelievers
        in this world</char>, those called to be holy in unison with those everywhere who are calling upon the
        name of our Lord Jesus Christ (i.e., those invoking Jesus’s promises, his authority, and his favorable
        disposition)—<verse eid="1CO 1:2" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 1:3" />Grace and peace to you from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.<verse eid="1CO 1:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 1:4" />When it comes to you, I’m always thanking my God for<char style="sup">[b]</char> the grace He’s given
        you in Christ Jesus, <verse eid="1CO 1:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 1:5" />because in him you’ve been enriched in all things, in every concept <char style="it">imaginable</char><char
        style="sup">[c]</char><char style="it"> </char>and in all <char style="it">sorts of </char>knowledge
        and understanding, <verse eid="1CO 1:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 1:6" />just as the testimony of Christ (i.e., the official statement about Christ) has been both made firm and
        has been confirmed in you, <verse eid="1CO 1:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 1:7" />so that you’re not lacking in any Holy Spirit-generated gift, ministry, or manifestation of the Holy
        Spirit<char style="sup">[d]</char>, eagerly awaiting the revelation of Christ Jesus our Lord, <verse eid="1CO 1:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 1:8" />who will also establish us until the end of time <char style="it">so that we’re</char> blameless in the
        day of our Lord Jesus Christ. <verse eid="1CO 1:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 1:9" />Faithful is the God through whom we’ve been called into the fellowship of His son Jesus Christ our Lord.<verse eid="1CO 1:9" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 1:10" />I appeal to you, comrades, through the name (i.e., the authority) of our Lord Jesus Christ, <char style="it">pleading
        to you</char> that you would always be on the same page<char style="sup">[e]</char> and that there not
        be divisions among you, but that you’d be fitted and mended together with the same mind and with the
        same knowledge and understanding. <verse eid="1CO 1:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 1:11" />In this regard and concerning you, it’s been made clear to me by Chloe’s family and her servants, my
        <char style="it">dear </char>comrades, that there’s strife going on between you. <verse eid="1CO 1:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 1:12" />I’ll say this: some of you say “I’m Paul’s devotee <char style="it">exclusively</char>” while others
        say “I’m Apollos’s devotee <char style="it">exclusively</char>” or “I’m Peter’s<char style="sup">[A]</char>
        devotee <char style="it">exclusively</char>”, or “I’m Christ’s devotee <char style="it">exclusively.</char>”<verse eid="1CO 1:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 1:13" />Has Christ been divided up <char style="it">into pieces</char>? Paul wasn’t crucified on your behalf,
        was he? Or, were you baptized (i.e., initiated into the Christian faith) on Paul’s sole authority to
        be a member of Paul’s camp? <verse eid="1CO 1:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 1:14" />Thank God<char style="sup">[g]</char> I didn’t baptize any of you except Crispus and Gaius, <verse eid="1CO 1:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 1:15" />lest anyone say that they were baptized on my sole authority to be a member of my camp. <verse eid="1CO 1:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 1:16" />Now I did baptize Stephanas’s family and servants, but as far as the rest of you, I’m not absolutely
        sure<char style="sup">[B]</char> if I baptized anyone else. <verse eid="1CO 1:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 1:17" />You see, Christ didn’t send me to go about baptizing <char style="it">in order to build a camp of my
        own followers </char>but to go about evangelizing instead<char style="sup">[C]</char>, not in wisdom
        which comes out of a message, so that the cross of Christ wouldn’t be rendered ineffectual.<verse eid="1CO 1:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 1:18" />The message of the cross, you see, is stupidity to those who are lost and dying on the one hand, but
        to those who are being saved (i.e., being rescued from spiritual, moral, and physical calamity), it’s
        the power of God. <verse eid="1CO 1:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 1:19" />For it’s written <char style="it">in the Old Testament</char>:
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 1:19"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 1:19">I’ll destroy the wisdom of the wise,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 1:19">And I’ll annul the understanding of those who understand<verse eid="1CO 1:19"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 1:20" />Where’s the wise man? Where’s the scholar? Where’s this generation’s <char style="it">premier</char>
        debater? Hasn’t God turned this world’s wisdom into stupidity?<verse eid="1CO 1:20" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 1:21" />You see, by the wisdom of God, since the world through <char style="it">its </char>wisdom didn’t come
        to recognize, discern, understand, or know God,<char style="it"> </char>God was more than happy through
        the stupidity of what was preached to save those who made the decision to believe. <verse eid="1CO 1:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 1:22" />Forasmuch as Jews chase after stupendous miracles<char style="sup">[h]</char> and Westerners<char style="sup">[i]</char>
        chase after wisdom, <verse eid="1CO 1:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 1:23" />we, on the other hand, preach a crucified-Christ; for Jews it’s the root-cause of the failure caused
        by disobedience<char style="sup">[j]</char> on the one end of the stick, on the other end of the stick,
        for Westerners it’s stupidity, <verse eid="1CO 1:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 1:24" />but to them who are “the Called” (i.e., those whom God has summoned to be His people and who have heeded
        the summons), Jews and Westerners alike, Christ <char style="it">is </char>God’s power and God’s wisdom,<verse eid="1CO 1:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 1:25" />since the “stupidity” of God is wiser than <char style="it">the wisdom to be found in </char>mankind,
        and the “weakness” of God is stronger than <char style="it">the strength to be found in </char>mankind.<verse eid="1CO 1:25" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 1:26" />To this point, consider your <char style="it">group</char> “the Called”: if one looks at their backgrounds
        only<char style="sup">[k]</char>, not very many of them are wise, not many powerful, not many from high-society
        families or nobility. <verse eid="1CO 1:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 1:27" />No, God’s chosen the stupid things of the world to put to shame the wise <char style="it">things</char>,
        and the weak things of the world to put to shame the strong, <verse eid="1CO 1:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 1:28" />and God’s chosen the lowly born and those things which are contemptuous—<char style="it">He’s chosen
        </char>the things that don’t exist to abolish what does, <verse eid="1CO 1:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 1:29" />so that any and every human endeavor or accomplishment apart from God can’t be presented proudly before
        Him in the statement, “See—look what I did!”<char style="sup">[l]</char> <verse eid="1CO 1:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 1:30" />But <char style="it">what’s come out</char> of Him is that you’re melded<char style="sup">[m]</char>
        with Christ Jesus, who became to us wisdom from God, righteousness, and likewise holiness and redemption
        (i.e., the recovery of what you once had), <verse eid="1CO 1:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 1:31" />so it’d turn out just like it’s written <char style="it">in the Old Testament, </char>“Let the one who
        brags about his accomplishments brag in the Lord.”<verse eid="1CO 1:31" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrade</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brother</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">for</char>…Lit: <char style="it">at</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">every concept imaginable</char>…Or: <char style="it">every word of prophecy imaginable</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">all word</char>. The meaning is ambiguous and must therefore be decided by context (v.
        17, for one). For the choice of <char style="it">concept</char>, ref. note of John 1:1.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Holy Spirit-generated gift, ministry, or manifestation of the Holy Spirit</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">spiritual</char>, where it refers to the Holy Spirit and not a human or spirit in the
        sense of attitude. Ref. 1 Cor. 12:1.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">be on the same page</char>…Lit: <char style="it">say the same thing</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">on Paul’s sole authority to be a member of Paul’s camp</char>…Lit: <char style="it">into
        the name of Paul</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">thank God</char>…Lit: <char style="it">I thank God that</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">stupendous miracles</char>…Lit: <char style="it">signs</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Westerners</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Greeks</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the root-cause of the failure caused by disobedience</char>…Lit: <char style="it">a
        stumbling block</char> [<char style="it">skandalon</char>, <char style="w" strong="G04625">σκάνδαλον</char>)].
        Ref. note of Matt. 18:6.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">if one looks at their backgrounds only</char>…Lit: <char style="it">according to</char>
        [<char style="it">the</char>] <char style="it">flesh</char>. This conclusion is drawn after a study of
        all the usages in the NT of the words <char style="it">flesh </char>and <char style="it">body.</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">any and every human endeavor or accomplishment apart from God can’t be presented proudly
        before Him in the statement, “See—look what I did!”</char>…Lit: <char style="it">all flesh won’t boast
        before God</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[m]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[m]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">melded</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Peter’s</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Cephas’s</char>. <char style="it">Cephas</char>
        is the Aramaic word for <char style="it">Rock; </char>the Gk. translation of <char style="it">Cephas</char>
        is <char style="it">Peter</char>. John makes a point of quoting Jesus when he gave Peter his new name
        (John 1:42). Paul’s preference of the Aramaic name <char style="it">Cephas</char> over the Gk. name <char
        style="it">Peter</char> shows his respect for Peter, a respect rooted in Jesus having named him, which
        is determining who he is and what he’s about.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">absolutely sure</char>…Lit: <char style="it">know</char>. The Gk. word for <char style="it">know
        </char>used here means knowing something to be a fact by observing that it’s so; therefore, Paul’s talking
        about knowing something for certain. He apparently can’t recall for certain who he baptized and who he
        didn’t. One can infer that he baptized a lot of people.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Christ didn’t send me to go about baptizing in order to build a camp of my own followers
        but to go about evangelizing instead</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Christ didn’t send me to go about baptizing
        but to go about evangelizing instead</char>. An example of the necessity of adding select interpolations;
        in this case the phrase <char style="it">in order to build a camp of my own followers </char>is not in
        the GT. One surmises from the context that Paul assumed that the reader would supply these words. Not
        adding this phrase makes Paul’s statement oxymoronic at face value. Evangelization, when successful,
        results in people receiving Christ, and those who receive Christ should be baptized. Therefore, successful
        evangelization results in baptism; you cannot have the one without the other. Since Paul was sent as
        an apostle to evangelize the Gospel, he must’ve been sent to baptize (either himself personally or someone
        working with him) them as well.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="1CO 1" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  2   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="1CO 2" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 2:1" />When I went and visited you, comrades<char style="sup">[a]</char>, I didn’t go <char style="it">there</char>
        <char style="it">and use </char>heady, intellectual language and sublime speech while telling you about
        the mystery of God. <verse eid="1CO 2:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 2:2" />You see, I decided that when among you I’d <char style="it">appear as though </char>I knew no <char style="it">other
        facts whatsoever </char>except <char style="it">things</char> <char style="it">about</char> Jesus Christ
        and <char style="it">the fact that </char>this fellow was crucified. <verse eid="1CO 2:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 2:3" />I appeared to you<char style="it"> </char>as one lacking vigor and strength and as downright fearful,
        and was frequently trembling<char style="sup">[A]</char>, <verse eid="1CO 2:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 2:4" />and my message and my preaching weren’t in words that were wise and persuasive but <char style="it">were
        accompanied </char>by a powerful demonstration of <char style="it">the</char> Spirit <char style="it">that’s
        difficult to describe if you’ve never experienced it</char><char style="sup">[b]</char>, <verse eid="1CO 2:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 2:5" />so that your faith wouldn’t be <char style="it">a faith grounded </char>in human wisdom but would be
        in the power of God instead.<verse eid="1CO 2:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 2:6" />Now we speak <char style="it">words of</char> wisdom among those who are mature, a wisdom, however, not
        of this age nor of the rulers of this age (i.e., the demon spirits which have controlling influence over
        this world), rulers who are being rendered ineffective and brought to nothing— <verse eid="1CO 2:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 2:7" />instead we speak <char style="it">words of </char>God’s wisdom in a mystery, a wisdom which has been
        hidden <char style="it">up to this point</char>, a wisdom which God knew beforehand in eternity past
        and intended for our glory, <verse eid="1CO 2:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 2:8" />a wisdom which none of the rulers of this age knew, understood, or recognized, for if they had, they
        wouldn’t have crucified the Lord of Glory. <verse eid="1CO 2:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 2:9" />No, <char style="it">the wisdom isn’t like that, </char>it’s like it’s written <char style="it">instead</char>:
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 2:9"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 2:9">That which eye hasn’t seen and ear hasn’t heard</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 2:9">And hasn’t arisen <char style="it">and come to rest</char> upon any human heart—</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 2:9">That which God prepared for those who love Him<verse eid="1CO 2:9"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 2:10" />God revealed it to us through the Spirit: for the Spirit thoroughly searches and investigates everything,
        even the deep things of God. <verse eid="1CO 2:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 2:11" />For what person knows firsthand the intimate details and intentions<char style="sup">[c]</char> of a
        given person except for that person’s spirit that’s in him? In the same way, no one has known, understood,
        or recognized the intimate details and intentions of God except the Spirit of God.<verse eid="1CO 2:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 2:12" />Now we have not received the spirit of the world but rather the Spirit who <char style="it">proceeds</char>
        out of God, so that we would know firsthand what God has given to us as an expression of His grace— <verse eid="1CO 2:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 2:13" /><char style="it">and what was given to us is</char> also that which we speak, not speaking in human teachings
        <char style="it">consisting of</char> words of wisdom but rather in teachings of the Spirit <char style="it">consisting
        of the</char> fitting together nicely of Holy Spirit-related content with <char style="it">other</char>
        Holy Spirit-related content<char style="sup">[B]</char>. <verse eid="1CO 2:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 2:14" />A person who’s dominated by his mind, intellect, or emotions <char style="it">instead of by his spirit</char><char
        style="sup">[C]</char> won’t receive the things of the Spirit of God; in fact, to him such things are
        stupid, and he cannot know, understand, or recognize them because such things are spiritually examined
        and decided as a result. <verse eid="1CO 2:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 2:15" />But the spiritual person examines and decides all things, but he himself isn’t examined and <char style="it">his
        life </char>decided by anyone.<verse eid="1CO 2:15" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 2:16" />Who has known, understood, or recognized the Lord’s mind?
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 2:16">Who mentors Him?</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 2:16"></para>
    <para style="m" vid="1CO 2:16">We, however, have a mind which is of Christ.<verse eid="1CO 2:16"/>
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">with a powerful demonstration of the Spirit that’s difficult to describe if you’ve never
        experienced it</char>…Lit: <char style="it">with </char>[or <char style="it">in</char>]<char style="it">
        Spirit and power</char>. A hendiadys. Ref. note of Matt. 3:11.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">intimate details and intentions</char>…Lit: <char style="it">those things</char>. As
        “those things” is vague, it means a number of different things.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">lacking vigor and strength and downright fearful, and was frequently trembling</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">in weakness and in fear and in much trembling</char>. Judging based on the context,
        Paul was exhibiting weakness and fear when speaking to the Corinthians—not when preaching publicly. The
        reason he was in weakness and fear was out of reverence for the message of Christ crucified accompanied
        by a strong presence of the Holy Spirit, which presence was manifesting itself (“demonstration of the
        Spirit”) in the gifts and miracles (the “power of God”) listed in the twelfth chapter. Paul made himself
        smaller so as to not quench the Holy Spirit (1 Thess. 5:19), so as to give the Holy Spirit greater license
        to manifest his power. As we know from the NT, Paul was not naturally like this; on the contrary, he
        was the opposite. But the Corinthians put such a high premium on speakers with great oratory skills,
        those who speak persuasively and compellingly and who have great charisma and flamboyant personalities,
        that they viewed Paul with disdain.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">of the Spirit consisting of the fitting together nicely of Holy Spirit-related content
        with other Holy Spirit-related content…Lit: of Spirit, spirituals to spirituals combining</char>…Literal
        Gk: <char style="it">pneumatos pneumatikois pneumatika sunkrinontes </char>[πνεύματος, πνευματικοῖς πνευματικὰ συγκρίνοντες,
        <char style="w" strong="G04151">πνεύματος</char>), <char style="w" strong="G04152">πνευματικοῖς</char>),
        <char style="w" strong="G04152">πνευματικὰ</char>), <char style="w" strong="G04793">συγκρίνοντες</char>)].
        Note that the word <char style="it">spiritual </char>refers to the Holy Spirit. The successive words
        <char style="it">pneumatos pneumatikois pneumatika</char> comprise an alliteration, rhyme, assonance,
        or pun of a sort, and it’s possible that Paul personally coined it. The word <char style="it">sunkrinontes
        </char>means <char style="it">combining; putting together so that they fit together well; drawing a conclusion
        by comparing</char>. Now, there is ambiguity as to whether <char style="it">pneumatos </char>and<char
        style="it"> pneumatikois, </char>which are different forms of the same word <char style="it">spirituals</char>,
        means <char style="it">spiritual things </char>or <char style="it">people who are spiritual. </char>The
        ambiguity permits the following renderings to be defensible: <char style="it">combining spiritual things
        with spiritual things; combining spiritual things with spiritual people;</char> <char style="it">combining
        spiritual people with spiritual people; explaining spiritual things in spiritual terms; interpreting
        spiritual things in spiritual terms; interpreting spiritual things to spiritual people. </char>Such cases
        of ambiguity are resolved by the context and by how the words or phrases in question are used elsewhere,
        particularly if by the same author.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">A person who’s dominated by his mind, intellect, or emotions</char> <char style="it">instead
        of by his spirit…</char>Lit: <char style="it">a soulish-man</char>. The word <char style="it">soulish
        </char>is derivative of the word <char style="it">soul </char>[<char style="it">psuchā</char>, <char
        style="w" strong="G05590">ψυχή</char>)], where we get the word <char style="it">psyche</char>. It refers
        to the mind, intellect, and emotions. The psyche and the spirit are two distinct and different parts
        of a person (ref. 1 Thess. 5:23; Heb. 4:12). Translations usually render <char style="it">soulish </char>as
        <char style="it">natural</char>, referring to a person who goes about life looking and acting as though
        the spiritual world doesn’t exist, as though there’s no existence after death, etc. Also, ref. note of
        1 Thess. 2:8.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="1CO 2" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  3   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="1CO 3" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 3:1" />But I, comrades<char style="sup">[a]</char>, wasn’t able to speak to you like I would to people attuned
        to and dominated by spiritual things but rather like I would to people attuned to and dominated by fleshly
        things (i.e., things that have to do with our lives in the natural, even touching our carnal appetites),
        same as I would to those who are babies in Christ. <verse eid="1CO 3:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 3:2" />I fed you milk, not solid<char style="it"> </char>food,<char style="it"> </char>as you were not yet able
        <char style="it">to digest solid food, having not been weaned off milk</char>—but even now you still
        can’t <char style="it">handle solid food; </char><verse eid="1CO 3:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 3:3" />You’re still fleshly, you see: where there’s jealousy and strife still <char style="it">found</char>
        among you, are you not fleshly, and do you not leads lives dictated by the <char style="it">undesirable</char>
        human tendencies<char style="sup">[b]</char>?<verse eid="1CO 3:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 3:4" />For example, when one <char style="it">of you</char> says, “I’m Paul’s devotee <char style="it">exclusively</char>,”
        and another <char style="it">of you</char> says, “I’m Apollos’s devotee <char style="it">exclusively</char>,”
        are you not being dominated by your <char style="it">undesirable</char> human tendencies<char style="sup">[c]</char>?<verse eid="1CO 3:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 3:5" />So who is Apollos? Who is Paul—they’re ministers, and you came to believe <char style="it">in Christ
        </char>through their ministries, and <char style="it">all the steps involved and the ministries that
        were a part of leading you to Christ happened </char>to each person as the Lord granted <char style="it">that
        it happen</char>. <verse eid="1CO 3:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 3:6" />I planted <char style="it">the seed</char>, Apollos watered <char style="it">it</char>, but it was God
        who made it grow, <verse eid="1CO 3:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 3:7" />so that neither the one doing the planting nor the one doing the watering is <char style="it">the most
        important part of the process</char>, but God who makes things grow <char style="it">is the most important</char>.<verse eid="1CO 3:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 3:8" />The one who does the planting and the one who does the watering are on the same team<char style="sup">[d]</char>,
        and each will receive an individual-specific wage according to his own individual labor<char style="sup">[e]</char>.<verse eid="1CO 3:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 3:9" />We’re God’s coworkers, you see, <char style="it">laboring together in</char> God’s field, <char style="it">whereas
        </char>you’re the building-project which God’s constructing, <verse eid="1CO 3:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 3:10" /><char style="it">being constructed</char> according to the grace of God which was given to me as a judicious
        chief architect and principal contractor. Accordingly, I laid the foundation, and another <char style="it">subcontractor</char>
        <char style="it">came after me and</char> built <char style="it">the structure</char> <char style="it">on
        top of the foundation</char>, but let each <char style="it">subcontractor </char>look over what<char
        style="sup">[f]</char> he built, <char style="it">to ensure that it was done correctly</char>. <verse eid="1CO 3:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 3:11" />The fact of the matter is that no one can lay any other foundation other than the one which has been
        laid, which foundation is Jesus Christ. <verse eid="1CO 3:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 3:12" />Now if some <char style="it">subcontractor</char> builds upon the foundation <char style="it">by</char>
        <char style="it">putting in place </char>gold, silver, gemstones (i.e., the subcontractor did a high-quality
        job), wood, hay, or straw (i.e., the subcontractor did a low-quality job) <char style="it">structures</char>
        <char style="it">upon that foundation</char>, <verse eid="1CO 3:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 3:13" />the <char style="it">quality of the</char> work that that particular<char style="sup">[g]</char> <char
        style="it">subcontractor</char> did will become apparent to everyone, since some cataclysmic event will
        eventually occur that is enormously stressful<char style="sup">[h]</char> <char style="it">to the structure</char>,
        making<char style="it"> its true strengths and deficiencies </char>abundantly clear to everyone, since
        <char style="it">these true strengths and weaknesses </char>are revealed by fire (i.e., intense stress),
        and the fire will determine what kind of<char style="it"> </char>job was done by putting it through the
        wringer. <verse eid="1CO 3:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 3:14" />If any of the built-up construction remains, <char style="it">the subcontractor</char> will get paid;<verse eid="1CO 3:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 3:15" />if any of the built-up construction is burned up, he’ll lose money on <char style="it">the project</char>,
        but he’ll be spared <char style="it">of </char>personal <char style="it">ruin</char>, but he’ll lose
        his entire investment through the ordeal<char style="sup">[i]</char>.<verse eid="1CO 3:15" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 3:16" />Don’t you know that you are a temple of God and that the Spirit of God has taken up residence in you?<verse eid="1CO 3:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 3:17" />If someone trashes, ruins, or destroys the temple of God, God will trash that guy. The temple of God—the
        very thing that you are—is holy, you see.<verse eid="1CO 3:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 3:18" />Let no one fool himself utterly <char style="it">in this regard</char>: if any of you considers himself
        to be wise in this age, let him become stupid, so that he would become wise; <verse eid="1CO 3:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 3:19" />for the wisdom of this world is stupidity to<char style="sup">[j]</char> God. In fact, it’s written <char
        style="it">in the Old Testament</char>:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 3:19"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 3:19">He’s catching the wise in their subtle trickery<verse eid="1CO 3:19"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 3:20" />And another <char style="it">verse says</char>,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 3:20"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 3:20">The Lord understands the arguments of the wise—</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 3:20"><char style="it">He knows</char> that they’re futile<verse eid="1CO 3:20"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 3:21" />So then, let no one be charged up and beam with pride over<char style="sup">[k]</char> people <char style="it">that
        they’re devotees of.</char> The fact of the matter is, all of you— <verse eid="1CO 3:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 3:22" />whether <char style="it">we’re referring to</char> Paul, Apollos, or Peter<char style="sup">[l]</char>—or
        whether <char style="it">we’re talking about </char>life, death, the past, or the future— <verse eid="1CO 3:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 3:23" />are Christ’s <char style="it">devotees</char><char style="sup">[m]</char>, and Christ is <char style="it">a
        devotee</char> of God.<verse eid="1CO 3:23" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">lead lives dictated by the undesirable human tendencies</char>…Lit: <char style="it">walk
        about according to men</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">are you not being dominated by your undesirable human tendencies</char>…Lit: <char style="it">are
        you not men</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">on the same team</char>…Lit: <char style="it">one</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">labor</char>…Also: <char style="it">toil</char>. This word is commonly used in the context
        of hard labor in a wheat field, etc. and is part of the metaphor for planting and watering.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">what</char>…Lit: <char style="it">how</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">that particular</char>…Lit: <char style="it">each</char>. Paul apparently didn’t word
        this very well.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">some cataclysmic event will eventually occur which is enormously stressful</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">the day</char>. Assume interpolation “of testing,” to make this “the day of testing.”
        <char style="it">The day </char>is an idiom used throughout the NT, similar to <char style="it">the hour
        </char>and <char style="it">the season.</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">he’ll be spared of personal ruin, but he’ll lose his entire investment through the ordeal</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">he personally will be saved, but in such a way as through fire</char>. <char style="it">Through
        fire</char> is apparently an idiom; the precise meaning is not entirely certain.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">to</char>…Lit: <char style="it">with</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">be charged up and beam with pride over</char>…Lit: <char style="it">boast</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Peter</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Cephas</char>. Ref. note of 1 Cor. 1:12.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[m]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[m]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Christ’s devotees</char>…Lit: <char style="it">of Christ</char>. Same wording as 1 Cor.
        1:12 “of Paul, of Apollos,” etc.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="1CO 3" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  4   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="1CO 4" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 4:1" />Let a person frame his perception of us this way: that we’re attendants of Christ and stewards of the
        mystery of God. <verse eid="1CO 4:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 4:2" />In regard to <char style="it">stewardship, </char>it’s a minimum requirement that a person who’s a steward
        be found faithful. <verse eid="1CO 4:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 4:3" />But it’s not a big deal for me to be examined and then judged by you or by any human tribunal <char style="it">for
        that matter</char>, nor do I judge myself in self-examination. <verse eid="1CO 4:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 4:4" />In fact, I’m not self-conscious <char style="it">about </char>anything <char style="it">I might’ve done
        wrong</char>, but—no—I haven’t been exonerated of all wrong-doing in this <char style="it">stewardship
        of mine</char>, but the Lord is the one who examines and judges me, <verse eid="1CO 4:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 4:5" />so that you won’t judge me before the timeframe <char style="it">set aside for judgment</char>, <char
        style="it">that is </char>until the Lord happens to come, who <char style="it">in the course of judging</char>
        will also will illuminate the hidden things of darkness and will put the plans, strategies, intentions,
        and collaborations of the hearts out in the open, and at that time the praise from God to each person
        <char style="it">for what he did right </char>will appear.<verse eid="1CO 4:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 4:6" />But because of you, comrades<char style="sup">[a]</char>, I made the change and applied these things
        to Apollos and me, so that through our<char style="it"> example</char> you would learn the <char style="it">meaning
        of</char> “Don’t be so high-and-mighty that the stuff that’s written <char style="it">in the Bible</char>
        somehow doesn’t apply to you<char style="sup">[b]</char>,” so that your egos don’t become overly-inflated,
        with one person <char style="it">thinking himself to be </char>superior <char style="it">in understanding
        something </char>to the one <char style="it">who explained that something to him in the first place,
        both </char>opposed to someone who has a different <char style="it">opinion</char><char style="sup">[A]</char>.<verse eid="1CO 4:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 4:7" />Furthermore, who determines what all the different <char style="it">points of view </char>are among you
        and sorts you into categories<char style="it"> based on viewpoint</char>?</para>
    <para style="p" vid="1CO 4:7">What do you have that you didn’t go out and get<char style="sup">[c]</char>? And if you got <char style="it">the
        things you decided to get</char>, why do you carry on<char style="sup">[d]</char> like you never got
        <char style="it">them</char>? <verse eid="1CO 4:7"/>
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 4:8" />You’ve already gotten plenty enough—<char style="it">you’re</char> already rich—you live like kings<char
        style="sup">[e]</char> <char style="it">when you’re </char>apart from us—it sure would be great if you
        <char style="it">actually </char>became kings, so that we could live like kings together with you. <verse eid="1CO 4:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 4:9" />You see, I’m thinking that God made an exhibit out of us—the apostles, <char style="it">the</char> lowliest<char
        style="sup">[B]</char><char style="it"> of people</char>—putting us on display, making us appear to everyone
        as though we’re men who’re condemned to death, since we became a spectacle to the world, to angels, and
        to <char style="it">all of </char>mankind. <verse eid="1CO 4:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 4:10" />We are idiots on account of Christ, but you are logical and sensible in Christ; we are weak, you are
        strong; we are glorious, you are dishonored. <verse eid="1CO 4:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 4:11" />Up until this very moment in time, we went hungry and thirsty, had no clothes to wear, were beaten, were
        homeless, <verse eid="1CO 4:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 4:12" />and toiled doing hard manual labor. While being abused, we bless; while being persecuted, we endure;<verse eid="1CO 4:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 4:13" />while being slandered, we speak softly<char style="sup">[f]</char>. Up until now, we<char style="it">’ve
        been</char> <char style="it">treated </char>like <char style="it">we’re </char>the scum of the world;
        <char style="it">like we’re </char>everyone’s garbage.<verse eid="1CO 4:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 4:14" />I’m not writing these things to shame you or to put you on a guilt trip, rather I’m writing to you as
        though you’re my children, ones who are dear to me, and I’m admonishing, warning, and instructing you
        as such. <verse eid="1CO 4:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 4:15" />You see, even if you had a million tutors in Christ, you still wouldn’t have<char style="it"> </char>many
        fathers (i.e., those who were instrumental in your conversion) <char style="it">in Christ</char><char
        style="sup">[g]</char>, seeing that I begot you in Christ Jesus through the Gospel. <verse eid="1CO 4:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 4:16" />So I’m pleading with you: get to where you imitate me<char style="sup">[h]</char>. <verse eid="1CO 4:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 4:17" />Because of this <char style="it">desire on my part, </char>I sent you Timothy, who is my dear child <char
        style="it">in Christ </char>and who’s faithful in the Lord, who’ll remind you <char style="it">to imitate
        </char>the way I do things in Christ Jesus, just like I teach everyone in churches everywhere.<verse eid="1CO 4:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 4:18" />As I’m not heading in your direction to visit you <char style="it">at the moment</char>, some <char style="it">of
        you</char> have acquired inflated egos. <verse eid="1CO 4:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 4:19" />But if it was the Lord’s will, I’d leave immediately and travel as quickly as possible to visit you<char
        style="sup">[i]</char>, and I’ll recognize and discern not the message<char style="sup">[j]</char> of
        those who’ve reached the point where their egos are inflated but rather <char style="it">their</char>
        power; <verse eid="1CO 4:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 4:20" />for the kingdom of God (i.e., God’s interaction with mankind) is not in a message but in power. <verse eid="1CO 4:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 4:21" />Which would you rather have? That I’d take a staff with me <char style="it">to correct you with </char>when
        I go visit you, or that <char style="it">I’d visit you </char>in<char style="it"> </char>a<char style="it">
        </char>love-spirit and with soft-spoken gentleness?<verse eid="1CO 4:21" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Don’t be so high-and-mighty that the stuff that’s written in the Bible somehow doesn’t
        apply to you</char>…Lit: <char style="it">don’t</char> [<char style="it">be</char>] <char style="it">above
        that which has been written</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">go out and get</char>…Also: <char style="it">take</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">carry on</char>…Lit: <char style="it">boast</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">live like kings</char>…Lit: <char style="it">reigned; gained a kingdom</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">speak softly</char>…Also: <char style="it">exhort; encourage; help</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">even if you had a million tutors in Christ, you still wouldn’t have many fathers</char>
        <char style="it">(i.e., those who were instrumental in your conversion)in Christ</char>…Lit: <char style="it">if
        you were to have ten thousand tutors in Christ, but rather not many fathers</char>. Paul didn’t word
        this well; taking what he meant to say and not what he actually did say. Also, the ten thousand is a
        hyperbole.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">get to where you imitate me</char>…Lit: <char style="it">become imitators of me</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I’d leave immediately and travel as quickly as possible to visit you</char>…Lit: <char
        style="it">I will go quickly to you</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">message</char>…Also: <char style="it">word</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">your egos don’t become overly-inflated, with one person thinking himself to be superior
        in understanding something to the one who explained that something to him in the first place, both opposed
        to someone who has a different opinion</char>…Lit: <char style="it">you would be puffed up one above
        the one against another who’s different</char>. Several translators (me included) are not sure what Paul
        was saying here. In cases like these, there may be an idiom present. Also, the appearance of the definite
        article in <char style="it">above the one </char>is emphatic, as many times such an article is dropped
        after a preposition.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">lowliest</char>…Lit: <char style="it">last</char>. Paul sees himself as the lowliest
        in regard to how comfortable his life is and because of his guilt over persecuting the church in his
        past life. The NT names 24 apostles, and he certainly was not the least of all of them.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="1CO 4" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  5   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="1CO 5" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 5:1" />News is going around that there’s actually fornication (i.e., sexual immorality) among you, the sort
        of fornication that you don’t even<char style="it"> find</char> among the heathens, to the effect that
        someone’s having <char style="it">sex with</char> his stepmother<char style="sup">[a]</char>. <verse eid="1CO 5:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 5:2" />You’ve become smug over this and what’s the more haven’t mourned (i.e., prayed deep, heart-felt prayers
        of grieving and sorrow) in order that the one who’s committed this atrocity be removed from your midst.<verse eid="1CO 5:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 5:3" />To address this topic, although away physically-speaking but present spiritually-speaking<char style="sup">[A]</char>,
        I have already judged the one who’s doing this as if I was present <verse eid="1CO 5:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 5:4" />by the authority vested in me by our Lord Jesus Christ<char style="sup">[b]</char>, my spirit<char style="sup">[c]</char>
        having gathered together with you all in the power of the our Lord Jesus <verse eid="1CO 5:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 5:5" />to hand a person such as him over to Satan (and to hand him over once and be done with it<char style="sup">[d]</char>)
        for the destruction of the flesh, so that the spirit will avoid utter calamity when the Lord “settles
        all Family business” so-to-speak<char style="sup">[B]</char>.<verse eid="1CO 5:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 5:6" />You talking a big talk<char style="sup">[e]</char> doesn’t make you look good—Don’t you know that a tiny
        pinch of yeast <char style="it">when placed in a batch of dough </char>will spread to the entire batch,
        <char style="it">causing every last bit of it to ferment</char>? <verse eid="1CO 5:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 5:7" />Scrub <char style="it">every bowl and utensil that came in contact with </char>the old yeast thoroughly,
        so that you’d be a fresh batch of dough the way that you <char style="it">really</char> are: yeast-free
        <char style="it">dough</char>. Add to this the fact that Christ was slaughtered and offered as our Passover
        lamb sacrifice, <verse eid="1CO 5:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 5:8" />so that we would not partake of the <char style="it">Passover</char> meal<char style="sup">[C]</char>
        with <char style="it">bread contaminated by </char>yeast <char style="it">from the previous batch</char><char
        style="sup">[f]</char> nor <char style="it">contaminated by </char>the yeast of unfathomably-wicked evil<char
        style="sup">[g]</char>, but with the yeast-free <char style="it">bread </char>of sincerity and truth
        instead.<verse eid="1CO 5:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 5:9" />In the <char style="it">previous </char>letter I wrote that you shouldn’t associate with fornicators,<verse eid="1CO 5:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 5:10" /><char style="it">but I didn’t mean not to associate </char>with<char style="it"> </char>any fornicator
        who’s a part of this <char style="it">corrupt </char>society <char style="it">we live in</char>, or with
        the greedy and rapacious<char style="sup">[D]</char> or with idolaters; otherwise, if that were the case,
        you’d have to leave <char style="it">this corrupt </char>society <char style="it">and shun it forever.
        </char><verse eid="1CO 5:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 5:11" />I wrote to you just now<char style="sup">[E]</char> not to associate <char style="it">with someone</char>
        if <char style="it">that</char> someone who goes by the name “comrade<char style="sup">[h]</char>” were
        to be a fornicator, or someone who’s greedy, or an idolater, or someone who cusses or uses abusive language,
        or a drunkard, or someone who’s rapacious—don’t share a meal<char style="sup">[i]</char> with them either.<verse eid="1CO 5:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 5:12" />Furthermore, why should I care about<char style="sup">[j]</char> judging those on the outside? Aren’t
        you the ones who judge those on the inside? <verse eid="1CO 5:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 5:13" />God judges those on the outside. <char style="it">The Old Testament says, </char>“Get rid of<char style="sup">[k]</char>
        your evil person.”<verse eid="1CO 5:13" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">stepmother</char>…Lit: <char style="it">father’s wife</char>. Assume this is <char style="it">stepmother</char>
        and not <char style="it">mother</char>; Paul would’ve simply said <char style="it">mother </char>if that
        were the case.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">by the authority vested in me by our Lord Jesus Christ</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in
        the name of our Lord Jesus</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">my spirit</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the spirit of mine</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">and to hand him over once and be done with it</char>…The verb tense of <char style="it">hand
        over </char>implies <char style="it">and be done with it</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">talking a big talk</char>…Also: <char style="it">boast</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">with</char> <char style="it">bread contaminated by </char>yeast <char style="it">from
        the previous batch…</char>Lit: <char style="it">old yeast</char>. Since this is a repeat of the words
        <char style="it">old yeast </char>used in v. 7, Paul is referring to the same thing from that verse.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">unfathomably-wicked evil</char>…Lit: <char style="it">evil and wicked</char>. A hendiadys.
        Ref. note of Matt. 3:11.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrade</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brother</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">share a meal</char>…Lit: <char style="it">eat</char>. This insinuates having fellowship
        over a meal.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">why should I care about</char>…Lit: <char style="it">what to me</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">get rid of</char>…Lit: <char style="it">remove out of</char>. Similar wording as the
        word <char style="it">removed </char>used in v. 2. This OT quotation is likely where Paul based the instruction
        of v. 2 upon.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">physically-speaking but present spiritually-speaking</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in
        body but present in spirit</char>, or, <char style="it">in body but present in the Spirit</char>. The
        ambiguity of whether it’s <char style="it">in spirit </char>or <char style="it">in the Spirit </char>is
        rendered <char style="it">in spirit </char>because of the parallelism of <char style="it">in body, </char>and
        also the phrase <char style="it">the spirit of mine </char>in v.4. The argument on the flip side of the
        coin, to mean <char style="it">in the Spirit:</char> <char style="it">in the spirit </char>with the explicit
        inclusion of the definite article the majority of the time refers to the Holy Spirit.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">will avoid utter calamity when the Lord “settles all Family business” so-to-speak</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">will be saved in the Day of the Lord</char>. The <char style="it">Day of the Lord </char>is
        the same as when Michael Corleone tells Carlo “Today I settled all Family business” in <char style="it">The
        Godfather</char>—but of course, the Lord judges in righteousness, but the Don did not. The Day of the
        Lord is the swift, sudden, violent, decisive judgment upon those who obviously deserve it, who, from
        a human perspective, should’ve received it earlier. Paul refers to the Day of the Lord in 1 Thess. 5:2,
        the concept originating foremost from Joel (Joel 1:15; 2:1,11,31; 3:14) but occurs in other OT books
        as well (Amos 5:20; Zeph. 1:7; Zech. 14:1).</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">partake of the Passover meal</char>…Lit: <char style="it">celebrate</char>. The Gk.
        word <char style="it">celebrate</char> is a verb form of the Gk. word rendered <char style="it">festival</char>,
        which in addition to meaning <char style="it">festival </char>refers to religious observances which aren’t
        accompanied by festivity, including simple meals like the Passover meal. But this verse demonstrates
        the metaphor Paul draws comparing Christians to the unleavened bread used in the Passover unleavened
        bread (matzah). Starting with Moses commanding the Israelites to purge every spec of yeast from the entire
        nation and eat matzah instead of real bread for the Passover, yeast and bread infected by it symbolize
        sin, impurity, and the tendency for attitudes—sinful ones in particular—to spread.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[D]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[D]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">greedy and rapacious</char>…A hendiadys perhaps. The Gk. word for <char style="it">greedy
        </char>means <char style="it">to want more and more</char>; the Gk. word for <char style="it">rapacious
        </char>means <char style="it">grabbing</char> <char style="it">or</char> <char style="it">seizing things</char>.
        Also, Paul associates greed, fornication, and idolatry in this verse and in Eph. 5:3,5; there are more
        references in the NT as well. These sins are interrelated.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[E]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[E]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I wrote to you just now</char>…Lit: <char style="it">I wrote to you now</char>. Paul
        says <char style="it">I wrote </char>instead of <char style="it">I write, </char>using the past tense
        instead of the present to refer to what he’s about to write at the end of the sentence. This would make
        sense if one were to assume that Paul first wrote a draft of this epistle, perhaps on wax tablets, made
        corrections, then copied the edited version onto the scroll which was sent to Corinth.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="1CO 5" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  6   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="1CO 6" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 6:1" />Does any one of you have the audacity to have a civil dispute which you’re having with another <char
        style="it">comrade </char>arbitrated by those who are unrighteous, and not by the saints (i.e., your
        fellow-believers)? <verse eid="1CO 6:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 6:2" />Or are you <char style="it">simply </char>unaware of the fact that the saints will judge the world? If
        the world is to be judged by you, you’re capable <char style="it">of forming</char> arbitration panels
        for <char style="it">settling </char>petty <char style="it">disputes</char>. <verse eid="1CO 6:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 6:3" />Don’t you know that we’ll judge angels?—We’re that much more <char style="it">capable </char>then <char
        style="it">of judging</char> day-to-day affairs.<verse eid="1CO 6:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 6:4" />So when you do happen to form a panel <char style="it">for arbitrating </char>day-to-day affairs, you
        put those in the church who are despised and lowly-esteemed on the panel. <verse eid="1CO 6:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 6:5" />Shame on you<char style="sup">[a]</char>—Isn’t there even one of you who has wisdom when it comes to
        this sort of thing, someone who can straighten out a situation his comrade is in<char style="sup">[b]</char>?<verse eid="1CO 6:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 6:6" />Instead, a comrade takes another comrade to court, and the court consists of unbelievers<char style="sup">[c]</char>.<verse eid="1CO 6:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 6:7" />You’re already undergoing a complete moral breakdown indeed by taking each other to court: why don’t
        you just be wronged? Why don’t you just be cheated? <verse eid="1CO 6:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 6:8" />Instead <char style="it">of enduring being wronged</char>, you’re wronging and cheating others, and <char
        style="it">you’re doing </char>this <char style="it">to fellow</char> comrades. <verse eid="1CO 6:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 6:9" />Don’t you know that those who wrong others won’t inherit the kingdom of God (i.e., won’t have a relationship
        with God; have Him involved with their lives)? Don’t be fooled: neither fornicators nor idolaters nor
        adulterers nor catamites<char style="sup">[A]</char> nor homosexuals <verse eid="1CO 6:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 6:10" />nor thieves nor the greedy—<char style="it">there’ll be </char>no drunkards, none of those who cuss and
        use abusive language, none of those who are rapacious—<char style="it">these people</char> won’t inherit
        the kingdom of God. <verse eid="1CO 6:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 6:11" />And that’s what some of you were—but no more: you were washed, you were sanctified (i.e., separated,
        set apart, and declared holy), you were justified (i.e. examined by a judge and cleared of any charges)
        by the authority<char style="sup">[d]</char> of our Lord Jesus Christ and in the Spirit of our God.<verse eid="1CO 6:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 6:12" />To me, everything is permissible but not everything is beneficial.<char style="sup">[B]</char> To me,
        everything’s permissible, but I’ll not be put under the control of anything. <verse eid="1CO 6:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 6:13" />Food is <char style="it">meant </char>for the stomach, and the stomach is <char style="it">meant </char>for
        food, but God will do away with <char style="it">food </char>and <char style="it">stomach </char>both.
        The body’s not <char style="it">meant </char>for fornication but for the Lord, and the Lord <char style="it">is
        meant </char>for the body. <verse eid="1CO 6:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 6:14" />God both raised the Lord <char style="it">from the dead </char>and will raise us <char style="it">from
        the dead </char>through His power.<verse eid="1CO 6:14" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 6:15" />Don’t you know that our bodies are a piece of Christ<char style="it">’s body</char>? Shall I take these
        things—<char style="it">shall I take </char>a piece of Christ<char style="it">’s body </char>and make
        it a piece <char style="it">which is a part</char> of a prostitute?—Don’t even think about it<char style="sup">[e]</char>.<verse eid="1CO 6:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 6:16" />Don’t you know that he who unites with a prostitute or a woman who’s a fornicator becomes<char style="sup">[f]</char>
        a single body <char style="it">with her through the bond of sex</char>? “For,” He says, “the two <char
        style="it">will be made </char>into one flesh.” <verse eid="1CO 6:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 6:17" />The one who unites with the Lord becomes a single spirit with him<char style="sup">[g]</char>. <verse eid="1CO 6:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 6:18" />Run as fast as you can away from fornication (i.e., sexual acts which are immoral): all sins that a person
        happens to commit are <char style="it">done </char>outside the body, but the fornicator commits a sin
        <char style="it">which is done </char>to (or even into) his own body<char style="sup">[C]</char>. <verse eid="1CO 6:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 6:19" />Don’t you know that our collective-body is a temple which is a dwelling-place for the Holy Spirit to
        dwell in, thereby living<char style="it"> </char>among us<char style="sup">[D]</char>, the <char style="it">Spirit
        </char>which you have from God, and that you don’t own yourselves<char style="sup">[h]</char>? <verse eid="1CO 6:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 6:20" />You’ve been bought at a high price; therefore, glorify<char style="sup">[i]</char> God with your collective-body.<verse eid="1CO 6:20" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Shame on you</char>…Lit: <char style="it">I speak to your shame</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">straighten out a situation his comrade is in</char>…Lit: <char style="it">can judge
        back-from-the-midst of his brother</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a comrade takes another comrade to court, and the court consists of unbelievers</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">a brother judges </char>[also<char style="it">, seeks a decision</char>]<char style="it">
        with a brother, and this at unbelievers</char>. Some liberties taken.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">by the authority of</char>…Lit<char style="it">: in the name of</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">don’t even think about it</char>…Lit: <char style="it">let it not come-into-being</char>.
        Ref. note of Rom. 3:4.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">becomes</char>…Lit: <char style="it">is</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">becomes a single spirit with him</char>…A mirror of the wording in v. 16, <char style="it">becomes
        a single body with her</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">don’t own yourselves</char>…Lit<char style="it">: are not your own</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">glorify</char>…Paul choice of verb tense to make this a harsh command</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">catamites</char>…Also<char style="it">: those who are effeminate</char>…Lit: <char style="it">soft
        to the touch. </char>The commentators aren’t exactly sure what this refers to; some say it refers to
        a man who lives a soft life—which is reasonable. But considering that the context is egregious sexual
        sin, and that the other sins listed in this verse are severe, this word here might refer to men who dress
        like and behave as though they’re women. </char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">To me, everything is permissible but not everything is beneficial</char>…Though Paul
        said that everything is permissible, it’s impossible to accept this statement at face-value, as he lists
        a few things in this chapter which are not permissible for anyone to do, stealing and being covetous
        for example. How is this logical dilemma to be solved? Paul is stating his perspective—his philosophy—on
        whether he will engage in an activity or not. Rather than looking at some deed as permissible or forbidden,
        he changes the perspective to look at whether said deed is beneficial or non-beneficial. The understanding
        is that whether it’s permissible or not will logically align with whether it’s beneficial or not. The
        examples of greed and covetousness Paul categorizes as non-beneficial, so it’s irrelevant whether they’re
        permissible or not, since Paul’s not going to do them anyways because they’re non-beneficial. By this
        reasoning, whether something is permissible or not is moot. Adopting this perspective goes a long way
        to resolving the issue of legalism which inevitably arises in the pursuit of religion.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">all sins that a person happens to commit are done outside the body, but the fornicator
        commits a sin which is done to (or even into) his own body</char>…The reason why fornication differs
        from all other sins, being a sin done to your body, is given in the previous verses: a fornicator unites
        his body with the person he commits the act with, and the two become a single body. When a couple is
        united sexually, their bodies merge into one body. Merging your body with someone who’s trash causes
        your body to be corrupted by the trash from the other body.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[D]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[D]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a temple which is a dwelling-place for the Holy Spirit to dwell in, thereby living among
        us</char>…Lit: <char style="it">a temple among us of </char>[<char style="it">the</char>]<char style="it">
        Holy Spirit</char>. According to Gk. grammar, the placement of <char style="it">among us </char>between
        the two phrases <char style="it">a temple </char>and <char style="it">of the Holy Spirit </char>indicates
        the tight coupling of the phrase <char style="it">among us </char>to the other two phrases. So Paul’s
        saying that our bodies form a temple and within this temple the Holy Spirit dwells. The analogy is the
        temple of Jerusalem in which God’s presence dwelled in the Holy of Holies.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="1CO 6" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  7   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="1CO 7" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 7:1" />To elaborate on what I wrote to you <char style="it">in the previous letter</char>, it’s good for a man
        not to go about touching a woman for the purpose of instigating<char style="sup">[A]</char><char style="it">
        sexual arousal. </char><verse eid="1CO 7:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 7:2" />But because <char style="it">of the</char> <char style="it">variety and volume </char>of<char style="it">
        </char>the fornications (i.e., sexual acts which are immoral) <char style="it">taking place around you,
        </char>let each man<char style="it"> </char>have his own woman to be his wife, and likewise let each
        woman have her own man to be her husband. <verse eid="1CO 7:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 7:3" />Let the husband fulfill his obligation <char style="it">of having sex </char>with his wife; likewise,
        let the wife do the same with her husband. <verse eid="1CO 7:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 7:4" />The wife doesn’t get to dictate what goes on with her own body<char style="sup">[a]</char>, but the husband
        does; likewise, the husband doesn’t get to dictate what goes on with his own body, but the wife does.<verse eid="1CO 7:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 7:5" />Don’t deprive each other <char style="it">of sex</char>, unless it’s for an agreed-upon time in order
        to devote yourselves to prayer, and get back at it<char style="sup">[b]</char> (i.e., back to having
        sex) so that Satan not tempt you because of your lack of self-control. <verse eid="1CO 7:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 7:6" />In saying this, I’m offering you a concession and not giving you a command. <verse eid="1CO 7:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 7:7" />I want all men to be like me, but each has his own gift from God instead, one person this way, the other
        person that way.<verse eid="1CO 7:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 7:8" />I’m telling those who aren’t married or who are widows that it would be good if they would stay the way
        I am. <verse eid="1CO 7:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 7:9" />But if they can’t control themselves, have them get married; it’s better to marry than to burn <char
        style="it">with sexual desire, </char>you see<char style="it">. </char><verse eid="1CO 7:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 7:10" />To those who are already married, I’m having the wives take a command (not me <char style="it">giving
        the command</char> but the Lord) for them not to leave <char style="it">their</char> husbands. <verse eid="1CO 7:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 7:11" />Now if she happens to leave<char style="sup">[B]</char> him <char style="it">anyways</char>, have her
        remain single or be reconciled with her husband. And <char style="it">I’m having </char>the husbands
        <char style="it">take a command </char>to not divorce<char style="sup">[B]</char> their wives. <verse eid="1CO 7:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 7:12" />I’m telling the rest of you (<char style="it">me talking, </char>not the Lord) <char style="it">this:
        </char>if some man has a wife who’s an unbeliever, and she consents to live with him, don’t have him
        divorce her; <verse eid="1CO 7:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 7:13" />if <char style="it">some </char>wife has a husband who’s an unbeliever, and this fellow consents to live
        with her, don’t have her divorce him. <verse eid="1CO 7:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 7:14" />You see, the unbelieving-husband is set apart to God as holy and specially protected by Him<char style="sup">[c]</char>
        by the <char style="it">believing </char>wife, and the unbelieving-wife is set apart as holy and specially
        protected by the comrade<char style="sup">[d]</char> <char style="it">who is her husband</char>; if that
        were not the case, their children would be unholy, spiritually contaminated, and not set apart to God<char
        style="sup">[c]</char>, but now <char style="it">that there’s a believing spouse in the picture, </char>they’re
        holy and specially protected. <verse eid="1CO 7:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 7:15" />Now if an unbelieving <char style="it">husband or wife</char> leaves <char style="it">his believing spouse</char>,
        let him or her part ways: the comrade, whether man or woman, isn’t under any obligation<char style="sup">[e]</char>
        in such case. God has called us <char style="it">to live</char> in peace (<char style="it">i.e., live
        free of the conflict, duress, or affliction that many unbelieving spouse brings</char>) <char style="it">whatever
        our situation might be</char><char style="sup">[C]</char>; <verse eid="1CO 7:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 7:16" />in this regard, how do you know, wives, if you’ll <char style="it">succeed in </char>rescuing your <char
        style="it">unbelieving </char>husbands from spiritual and moral calamity<char style="sup">[f]</char>?
        Or how do you know, husbands, if you’ll <char style="it">succeed in</char> rescuing your <char style="it">unbelieving
        </char>wives from spiritual and moral calamity?<verse eid="1CO 7:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 7:17" />Moving on <char style="it">to topics relevant </char>to every person…Have each person lead his life in
        the way that the Lord deems appropriate for the particular situation he was in when he became a believer<char
        style="sup">[D]</char>. I’m giving the same command to all the churches <char style="it">which I started</char>.<verse eid="1CO 7:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 7:18" />Had you already been circumcised when called (i.e., had you made a vow to obey the Law of Moses prior
        to becoming a believer )?—Don’t obliterate the effects of circumcision<char style="sup">[E]</char> (i.e.,
        don’t obliterate the effects of this vow). Was anyone called when they were uncircumcised (i.e., did
        anyone become a believer but at no time ever made a vow to obey the Law of Moses)?—Don’t get circumcised
        (i.e., don’t make such a vow). <verse eid="1CO 7:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 7:19" />The circumcision <char style="it">in the case of the believer who was circumcised already</char> is irrelevant
        and not an issue whatsoever, and the uncircumcision <char style="it">in the case of the believer who
        wasn’t circumcised already </char>is irrelevant and not an issue whatsoever, but the keeping of God’s
        commandments <char style="it">is the real issue </char>instead. <verse eid="1CO 7:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 7:20" />Whatever situation or set of circumstances a person was in when he was called (i.e., when he became a
        believer), he should stay in that situation or set of circumstances. <verse eid="1CO 7:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 7:21" />Were you called <char style="it">when you were </char>a slave?—Don’t worry about it; instead, if you
        get the chance to gain your freedom, by all means take advantage of the opportunity. <verse eid="1CO 7:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 7:22" />Furthermore, the person who was called by the Lord (i.e., became a believer) while a slave is the Lord’s
        freeman; in the same way, he who was called while free is Christ’s slave. <verse eid="1CO 7:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 7:23" />You’ve been bought at a high price: don’t become other peoples’ slaves. <verse eid="1CO 7:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 7:24" /><char style="it">Whatever </char>situation and circumstances each person was in when he was called, comrades,
        have him remain in <char style="it">this situation</char> <char style="it">when he gets</char> with God.<verse eid="1CO 7:24" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 7:25" />About the young ladies who have never been married<char style="sup">[g]</char>: I don’t have a command
        from the Lord, but I’ll give an opinion as one who’s been shown mercy by the Lord <char style="it">enabling
        me </char>to be reliable. <verse eid="1CO 7:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 7:26" />These are my thoughts about living through the difficulties of the present time, <char style="it">namely
        </char>that it’s good for a person <char style="it">to live</char> the following way: <verse eid="1CO 7:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 7:27" />Are you bound <char style="it">by commitment </char>to a wife?—Don’t try to separate from her. Separated
        from a wife?—Don’t go looking for <char style="it">another </char>woman. <verse eid="1CO 7:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 7:28" />But if you do happen to get married, you haven’t sinned. And if the <char style="it">typical</char> young
        lady<char style="sup">[g]</char> <char style="it">in the church </char>happens to get married, she hasn’t
        sinned. <char style="it">Folks</char> such as these will face hard times in their natural lives<char
        style="sup">[h]</char>; I’m trying to spare you <char style="it">this grief</char>.<verse eid="1CO 7:28" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 7:29" /><char style="it">Let</char> me tell you what, comrades, a compressed window of time is <char style="it">all
        that</char> remains <char style="it">of our lives</char>, so that those who have wives should live as
        though they don’t <char style="it">have wives</char>, <verse eid="1CO 7:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 7:30" />and those who weep as though they don’t weep, and those who rejoice as though they don’t rejoice, and
        those who deal in business as though they’ve halted trading, <verse eid="1CO 7:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 7:31" />and those using the world as though they don’t use it; when you get right down to it, the world we live
        in in its present form is passing away. <verse eid="1CO 7:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CO 7:32" />I don’t want you to be consumed by or worry about the trivial day-to-day affairs of life. He who’s not
        married is consumed by and worries about the things of the Lord, how he might be pleasing to him, <verse eid="1CO 7:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CO 7:33" />but he who’s married is consumed by and worries about things of the world we live in and the people we
        live around, how he might <char style="it">use these things to </char>be pleasing to the wife <char style="it">he
        has</char>, <verse eid="1CO 7:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CO 7:34" />and he reaches the point where he’s constantly consumed by these and worries about them continually.
        Both the woman who’s single and the young lady who’s never been married are consumed by and worry about
        the things of the Lord, so they would be holy both in body and in spirit. But she who’s married is consumed
        by and worries about the things of the world, how she’s going to please her husband. <verse eid="1CO 7:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CO 7:35" />I’m telling you this for your own benefit—not so I can put you on a leash, but so it would result in
        a seemly, undistracted devotion to the Lord.<verse eid="1CO 7:35" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CO 7:36" />Now if someone’s behaving inappropriately towards the young lady he’s in a relationship with, and he
        thinks she might be “overly-ripe<char style="sup">[F]</char>” in such a way that he’s obliged to <char
        style="it">make something</char> happen (i.e., she’s pregnant, he thinks it might be too hard to hide
        anymore, and he’ll have to do something about it), let him do what he wants to do—he’s not committing
        a sin <char style="it">in doing so</char>—let them get married. <verse eid="1CO 7:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CO 7:37" />But he who has taken a firm stand in his heart, not having <char style="it">to act out of </char>necessity
        but has the upper-hand over<char style="sup">[i]</char> his individual <char style="it">sexual </char>desire,
        and has decided in his own heart to stay a virgin<char style="sup">[j]</char> <char style="it">rather
        than sleep with his girlfriend or fiancée</char>, does well, <verse eid="1CO 7:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CO 7:38" />with the result that both he <char style="it">who waits until</char> marriage handles his virginity well,
        but he who remains single will do better, <char style="it">as he’ll be spared the difficulties I wrote
        about here</char>.<verse eid="1CO 7:38" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CO 7:39" />The wife is <char style="it">morally </char>bound <char style="it">to her husband </char>as long as her
        husband lives, but if her husband were to pass away, she’s free to marry whom she wants, only <char style="it">she
        must marry </char>in the Lord (i.e., marry in such a way that’s pleasing to the Lord; marry another believer).<verse eid="1CO 7:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CO 7:40" />But in my opinion she’d be happier if she were to stay the way she is (i.e., stay unmarried after becoming
        a widow), and I think I have <char style="it">the agreement of </char>the Spirit of God too.<verse eid="1CO 7:40" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">doesn’t get to dictate what goes on with her own body</char>…Lit: <char style="it">doesn’t
        have authority over her body</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">get back at it</char>…Lit: <char style="it">be again at the same</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">set apart to God as holy and specially protected by Him</char>…<char style="it">unholy,
        spiritually contaminated, and not set apart to God</char>…Lit: <char style="it">sanctified</char>…<char
        style="it">unclean</char>. The words sanctified and unclean used together in this verse originate in
        the OT usage of holy and unclean, which carries into the NT.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrade</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brother</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">under any obligation</char>…Lit: <char style="it">has been enslaved</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">succeed in rescuing your unbelieving husbands from spiritual and moral calamity</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">save the husband</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">young lady who’s never been married…young lady</char>…Lit: <char style="it">virgins…virgin</char>.
        Ref. note of Matt. 25:1.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">in their natural lives</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in the flesh</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the upper hand over</char>…Also: <char style="it">control over</char>…Lit: <char style="it">authority
        concerning</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">virginity</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the of-oneself virgin</char>. Paul uses the word
        <char style="it">virgin </char>a few times in this passage, but his use of the reflexive pronoun <char
        style="it">oneself </char>inserted between the definite article and the word <char style="it">virgin
        </char>selects <char style="it">virginity, </char>a secondary meaning of the Gk. word for <char style="it">virgin.
        </char>Note Paul’s careful insertion of the reflexive pronoun both here and in v. 38.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">to go about touching a woman for the purpose of instigating</char>…First, the Gk. verb
        for<char style="it"> touch </char>[<char style="it">haptō</char>, <char style="w" strong="G00681">ἅπτω</char>)]
        appears in the present tense, insinuating continuous action rather than a one-time act—hence the added
        phrase <char style="it">go about touching</char>. Second, this verb is unusual in that it has one meaning
        when used in the active voice (<char style="it">to light on fire) </char>and another meaning when used
        in the middle voice (<char style="it">to touch</char>). Since the active voice is the primary tense,
        the meaning in the middle voice influenced by a hint of the meaning from the active voice. Most of the
        NT occurrences of this verb are in the middle voice, and they not only mean <char style="it">to touch
        </char>but also acquire some of the active voice’s definition to more specifically mean <char style="it">to
        touch for the purpose of instigating something. </char>This verb is used when Jesus touches someone to
        heal them; he touched the person but did so for a purpose. What is “lit on fire” so-to-speak is determined
        by the context, and the context of v. 1 here insinuates touching sexually. To further reinforce the point
        that <char style="it">haptō </char>means more than a simple touch, take a close look at Col. 2:21. Note
        how <char style="it">haptō </char>appears in that passage with <char style="it">thigganō </char><char
        style="w" strong="G02345">θιγγάνω</char>)<char style="it">. </char>They both mean <char style="it">to
        touch </char>but thigganō<char style="it"> </char>means touching without instigating anything; to touch
        lightly; to brush up against something. Had they meant the same thing, Paul wouldn’t have used two different
        verbs.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">leave</char>…<char style="it">divorce</char>…Different Gk. words are used for <char
        style="it">leave </char>and <char style="it">divorce </char>here; we infer from this verse here and from
        other NT references (such as Matt. 5:31) that, in ancient times, only the husband had the right to instigate
        a legal divorce. A wife, however, would at times simply leave her husband without fulfilling the legalities
        of a divorce. This might explain the two different words used here.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">God has called us to live in peace (i.e., live free of the conflict, duress, or affliction
        that many unbelieving spouse brings)</char> <char style="it">whatever our situation might be</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">God has called us in</char> [or: <char style="it">with</char>; <char style="it">by</char>]
        <char style="it">peace</char>. Apparently, “God has called us to live in peace” means that it’s not God’s
        will for a Christian to be married to a person who’s violent, who’s abusive, who’s reckless, who’s irresponsible
        to the point of it causing harm to the family, etc. Notice that it says “God has called us to live in
        peace,” and not “God has called us to be happy” (Christians shouldn’t necessarily be “happy” but they
        should have joy). In other words, this isn’t a license for a person to divorce simply because he’s unhappy.
        But it is a license for a Christian who was married before he became a Christian to divorce an unbelieving
        spouse if that spouse is causing trouble.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[D]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[D]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">have each person lead his life in the way that the Lord deems appropriate for the particular
        situation he was in when he became a believer</char>…Lit: <char style="it">as the Lord partitioned</char>
        [<char style="it">an inheritance</char>] <char style="it">each as God has called</char>…Or: <char style="it">as
        the Lord partitioned</char> [<char style="it">an inheritance</char>] <char style="it">as God has called
        each</char>. Some guesswork as to what exactly Paul was saying. He seems to be making a comparison to
        dividing an inheritance, the inheritance being a biblical theme that refers to the specific plans God
        has for an individual or a particular group, plans which are bespoke for that person or group.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[E]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[E]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Don’t obliterate the effects of circumcision</char>…What Paul meant by this can be seen
        in his own life. Paul used the fact that he was circumcised to his advantage from time to time, as he
        writes later in 9:22, “I am made all things to all men, that I might by all means save some.” Examples
        are found in Acts 18:18, 21:23–29.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[F]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[F]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">overly-ripe</char>…Or: <char style="it">beyond her prime</char>…Lit: <char style="it">beyond
        peak</char>. The passage of vv. 36–38 has puzzled translators, and every rendering is not without criticism.
        To a large extent it hinges on what <char style="it">beyond peak </char>means in this context. Some believe
        it means that the virgin woman is <char style="it">beyond her prime </char>in age, but the meaning of
        <char style="it">beyond peak </char>which best fits the context is a woman who’s pregnant and beginning
        to show or perhaps or is a woman who’s late in her monthly cycle.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="1CO 7" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  8   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="1CO 8" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 8:1" />Now about <char style="it">the issue of eating</char> meat sacrificed to idols, every one of us has <char
        style="it">our own </char>understanding <char style="it">of how this ought to be handled</char>. The
        understanding <char style="it">a person has on a given issue </char>makes him rather full of himself,
        but the love <char style="it">shown in the handling of said issue </char>edifies. <verse eid="1CO 8:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 8:2" />If any given person thinks he’s reached the point where he’s acquired some <char style="it">level of</char>
        understanding, he has not yet understood <char style="it">the matter </char>as it must be understood.<verse eid="1CO 8:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 8:3" />If someone loves God, this individual has been known and understood by Him.<verse eid="1CO 8:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 8:4" />So now, about the consumption of food offered to idols: we know for a fact that <char style="it">the
        </char>idols in the world don’t amount to a hill of beans<char style="sup">[a]</char>, and no person
        or thing is God except for One <char style="it">being only</char><char style="sup">[b]</char>. <verse eid="1CO 8:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 8:5" />Now, granted, there are those who claim there are gods, whether <char style="it">they be </char>in the
        sky, in the atmosphere, among the stars, in a spiritual world beyond that, or on the earth, so that there’re
        many gods and many lords, <verse eid="1CO 8:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 8:6" />but from our point of view there’s one God the Father, out of Whom <char style="it">are</char> all things,
        and we <char style="it">are returned</char> to Him and to the Lord Jesus Christ, through whom <char style="it">are
        </char>all things, and we <char style="it">are </char>through him.<verse eid="1CO 8:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 8:7" />That aside, we are not <char style="it">on the same level </char>in every <char style="it">aspect of
        </char>understanding. Up until now some people have been in the habit of eating food sacrificed to idols,
        and since their consciences are weak<char style="sup">[A]</char> (i.e., their consciences prod them with
        pangs of guilt over matters they have a deficient understanding of, in this case in regard to food sacrificed
        to idols), they violate<char style="sup">[c]</char> their consciences. <verse eid="1CO 8:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 8:8" /><char style="it">Eating or not eating this </char>food doesn’t get us anywhere<char style="sup">[d]</char>
        with God: we’re neither worse off if we were to not eat <char style="it">it </char>nor are we better
        off if we were to eat <char style="it">it</char>.<verse eid="1CO 8:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 8:9" />See to it that the right you have <char style="it">to eat such food </char>doesn’t somehow in and of
        itself become a stumbling block<char style="sup">[e]</char> (i.e., an influence for causing sin) for
        those who have a weak<char style="it"> conscience</char>. <verse eid="1CO 8:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 8:10" />You see, if someone <char style="it">with a weak conscience </char>were to watch you, a person who has
        <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">correct </char>understanding <char style="it">on this issue,
        </char>sitting at the dinner table<char style="sup">[f]</char> with food sacrificed to idols <char style="it">lying</char>
        <char style="it">on the plate in front of you</char>, wouldn’t his conscience, because it’s in a state
        of weakness, being built up in regard to the eating of foods sacrificed to idols (i.e., because of an
        incorrect understanding in regard to this issue of food sacrificed to idols, his conscience has been
        conditioned to respond with guilt when it ought not)? <verse eid="1CO 8:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 8:11" />You see, he who’s weak—the comrade<char style="sup">[g]</char> whom Christ died for—is being destroyed
        by your <char style="it">correct </char>understanding. <verse eid="1CO 8:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 8:12" />In the way that you sin against the comrades and beat on their weak consciences, you sin against Christ.<verse eid="1CO 8:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 8:13" />That’s why if food causes my comrade to stumble, there’s no way whatsoever that I’ll ever eat sacrificial
        meat again, so that I won’t be a stumbling block to my brother.<verse eid="1CO 8:13" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">don’t amount to a hill of beans</char>…Lit: <char style="it">are nothing</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">one being only</char>…Lit: <char style="it">one</char>. Alludes to the statement “God
        is One”; ref. James 2:19.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">violate</char>…Lit: <char style="it">defiling</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">doesn’t get us anywhere with</char>…Lit: <char style="it">doesn’t present us to</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">stumbling block</char>…Ref. note of Matt. 18:6.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">sitting at the dinner table</char>…Lit: <char style="it">reclining</char>. Ref. note
        of Matt. 9:10.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrade</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brother</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">their conscience are weak</char>. In his epistles, Paul talks about four types of consciences:
        a good conscience, an evil conscience, a weak conscience, and a seared conscience. A person’s conscience
        is something that affirms when he’s doing right but condemns when he does wrong. From this context, we
        can deduce that a weak conscience is one which has been programmed with an incorrect understanding of
        the truth and therefore misfires, sending the wrong signals for the wrong reasons, causing a person to
        experience guilt over something he shouldn’t and not experience it over something he should. </char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="1CO 8" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  9   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="1CO 9" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 9:1" />Am I not a freeman? Am I not an apostle (i.e., have I not been sent by God to pioneer the spread of Christianity)?
        Have I not seen our Lord Jesus with my own eyes? Are you not my accomplishment in the Lord? <verse eid="1CO 9:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 9:2" />If I’m not an apostle <char style="it">sent </char>to <char style="it">root </char>others <char style="it">in
        Christianity</char>, at least I’m <char style="it">an apostle sent </char>to <char style="it">root </char>you;
        in fact, you’re my certificate of authenticity of my having been sent by the Lord. <verse eid="1CO 9:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 9:3" />My rebuttal to those examining me for the purpose of judging and condemning me is the same.<verse eid="1CO 9:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 9:4" />Do we not have the right to <char style="it">be hosted in such a way that we </char>eat and drink <char
        style="it">for free</char>? <verse eid="1CO 9:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 9:5" />Do we not have the right to have a fellow-comrade-wife accompany us as she follows our lead<char style="sup">[a]</char>
        <char style="it">on our journeys and have her hosted as well</char>, as all the other apostles of the
        Lord and Peter<char style="sup">[b]</char> <char style="it">do</char>?— <verse eid="1CO 9:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 9:6" />Or is it just Barnabas and I who don’t have the right to not <char style="it">have to</char> work <char
        style="it">to support ourselves</char>? <verse eid="1CO 9:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 9:7" />When did any soldier ever serve <char style="it">in the army </char>and<char style="it"> have to</char>
        pay for his own rations? Who plants a vineyard and doesn’t feed off what it produces? Or who cares for
        a ewe and doesn’t feed off the sheep’s milk?<verse eid="1CO 9:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 9:8" />I’m not talking from a human perspective<char style="sup">[c]</char>, or talking <char style="it">about
        concepts </char>that the Law does not also talk about. <verse eid="1CO 9:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 9:9" />The fact of the matter is, in the Law of Moses it’s written, “Don’t put a muzzle on an oxen while it’s
        threshing <char style="it">wheat</char>.” You don’t think God cares about <char style="it">the</char>
        <char style="it">welfare of </char>the oxen <char style="it">when it’s threshing</char>, do you? <verse eid="1CO 9:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 9:10" />Or is <char style="it">it that</char> <char style="it">the Law’s </char>addressing <char style="it">this
        topic </char>for our benefit? Furthermore, it’s written <char style="it">in the Law</char> for our benefit
        that the sower ought to sow and the thresher to thresh with the hope of getting a percentage of the harvest.<verse eid="1CO 9:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 9:11" />If we sowed into you the Holy Spirit-related things<char style="sup">[d]</char> <char style="it">which
        are the backbone of your spiritual lives</char>, is it a big deal if we reap the physical things <char
        style="it">we need to live by </char>from you? <verse eid="1CO 9:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 9:12" />If others have the right of taking a percentage from you, don’t we all the more so?
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="1CO 9:12">No, we’re not asserting this right; instead we put up with all <char style="it">kinds of </char>things
        so that nothing would hinder the Gospel, the good-news message of Christ. <verse eid="1CO 9:12"/>
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 9:13" />Don’t you know that they who work the sacred <char style="it">duties in the temple </char>feed on <char
        style="it">the sacrifices offered at</char> the temple; <char style="it">that </char>they who attend
        to the altar divide <char style="it">the spoils </char>of the altar among themselves? <verse eid="1CO 9:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 9:14" />In the same way the Lord planned for and commanded those who proclaim the Gospel to make their living
        from the Gospel. <verse eid="1CO 9:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 9:15" />I have not used any of these <char style="it">mandates</char>. I didn’t write about these things to make
        them happen to me; in fact, I’d rather die than have someone invalidate the proud assertions which I
        openly pride myself in. <verse eid="1CO 9:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 9:16" />Should I proclaim the Gospel, it’s not my place to make proud assertions, you see: by necessity they’re
        imposed on me. I’ll be in deep trouble<char style="sup">[e]</char>, you see, should I not proclaim the
        Gospel. <verse eid="1CO 9:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 9:17" />If I put this into practice voluntarily, you see, I’ll earn my pay<char style="sup">[f]</char>. If <char
        style="it">I do this</char> voluntarily, I’ve reached the point where I can be entrusted with a managerial
        position. <verse eid="1CO 9:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 9:18" />So what’s my pay rate? <char style="it">I’m not getting paid a penny s</char>o that I can present the
        Gospel free of charge with a view towards me not exercising my right <char style="it">to receive financial
        support</char> <char style="it">as</char> <char style="it">one who proclaims </char>the Gospel.<verse eid="1CO 9:18" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 9:19" />Being a freeman, freed from all things, in all things I made myself a slave, so that I’d win over the
        many. <verse eid="1CO 9:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 9:20" />I became a Jew to the Jews so that I would win over Jews: to those who live under the Law <char style="it">of
        Moses</char>, I <char style="it">let myself be</char> under the Law (<char style="it">though</char> as
        far as my own personal life is concerned, I’m not under the Law), so that I would win over those under
        the Law. <verse eid="1CO 9:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 9:21" />I became lawless (i.e., not living under the Law of Moses or under any God-based set of rules for that
        matter) to the lawless (<char style="it">though </char>not living lawlessly apart from God, but being
        law-bound as a part of Christ) in order to win over the lawless. <verse eid="1CO 9:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 9:22" />I became powerless to control my own circumstances<char style="sup">[g]</char> to those who are powerless
        over their circumstances so that I would win over the powerless. I became all things to all people so
        I’d save (i.e., rescue from calamity, spiritual, moral, and otherwise) some. <verse eid="1CO 9:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 9:23" />But everything<char style="it"> I do, </char>I do for the sake of <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">proclamation
        of </char>the Gospel so I’d become a workman who specializes in it.<verse eid="1CO 9:23" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 9:24" />Don’t you know that those who compete in track &amp; field run races but only one of them gets the first-place
        trophy<char style="sup">[A]</char>? Play to win—that’s the way you compete.<char style="sup">[h]</char><verse eid="1CO 9:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 9:25" />Everyone who competes in athletics trains, and those folks do so in order to get a trophy which can <char
        style="it">and undoubtedly will</char> lose its prestige over time<char style="sup">[i]</char>, but we
        <char style="it">train to win a trophy</char><char style="sup">[j]</char><char style="it"> which </char>will
        always remain prestigious; <verse eid="1CO 9:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 9:26" />hence, as far as I’m concerned, I don’t <char style="it">train for</char> the race without setting any
        specific personal goals to meet<char style="sup">[k]</char>. I <char style="it">train to </char>box in
        such a way that <char style="it">in the ring </char>I’ll land punches and not wind up with fistfuls of
        air<char style="sup">[l]</char>. <verse eid="1CO 9:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 9:27" />Uh-uh—I apply strict, punishing disciple to my body (i.e., to my carnal nature in particular), treating
        it roughly and wearing it down; I subdue it and make it my slave, lest I, having proclaimed <char style="it">the
        Gospel to others, </char>should somehow or someway fail to live up to the standard it sets.<verse eid="1CO 9:27" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">to have a fellow-comrade-wife accompany us as she follows our lead</char>…Lit: <char
        style="it">to lead about a sister-woman</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Peter</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Cephas</char>. Ref. note of 1:12.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">from a human perspective</char>…Lit: <char style="it">according to man</char>. Same
        phrase used elsewhere<char style="it">: human standards</char> (Rom. 3:5); <char style="it">undesirable
        human tendencies</char> (1 Cor. 3:3).</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the Holy Spirit-related things</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the spirituals. </char>Ref.
        1 Cor. 12:1.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I’ll be in deep trouble</char>…Lit: <char style="it">woe to me</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I’ll earn my pay</char>…Lit: <char style="it">I have a wage</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">powerless to control my own circumstances</char>…Lit: <char style="it">weak</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Play to win, that’s the way you compete</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Run in this way,
        that you take it</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">can and undoubtedly will lose its prestige over time</char>…Lit: <char style="it">is
        corruptible</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">train to win a trophy</char>…Lit: <char style="it">run</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">without setting any specific personal goals to meet</char>…Lit: <char style="it">not
        aimlessly</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I train to box in such a way that in the ring I’ll land punches and not wind up with
        fistfuls of air</char>…Or: <char style="it">I</char> [<char style="it">train to</char>] <char style="it">box
        in such a way as</char> [<char style="it">not mindlessly</char>] <char style="it">shadow-boxing</char>
        …Lit: <char style="it">I box in such a way as not beating air</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">only one of them gets the first-place trophy</char>…In ancient Greek culture, there
        was no second or third place, etc. You either win or lose. There’s no distinction if you were to barely
        come in second place or if you were to come in last place.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="1CO 9" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 10   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="1CO 10" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 10:1" />I don’t want you to fail to understand this, comrades<char style="sup">[a]</char>, <char style="it">the
        fact </char>that our forefathers—all of them—were <char style="it">always </char>under the cloud <char
        style="it">which they followed after leaving Egypt, </char>and all of them passed through the <char style="it">Red
        </char>Sea, <verse eid="1CO 10:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 10:2" />and every one of them was initiated into and joined up with Moses in totality<char style="sup">[A]</char>
        by virtue of the cloud and the sea<char style="sup">[b]</char>, <verse eid="1CO 10:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 10:3" />and every one of them was fed from the same spiritual food, <verse eid="1CO 10:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 10:4" />and every one of them drank from the same spiritual source: they drank out of the Spiritual Trailing
        Rock (and the rock was Christ).<verse eid="1CO 10:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 10:5" />But God was not pleased with many of them; <char style="it">their dead bodies </char>were strewn about
        the wilderness as we see. <verse eid="1CO 10:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 10:6" />Now the lives these people led is an example, a pattern, a parallel of our own lives, so that we not
        have strong yearnings bordering on sensual passions for evil, just as some of them had. <verse eid="1CO 10:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 10:7" />Neither become idolaters, just as some of them did, as it’s written <char style="it">in the Old Testament</char>,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 10:7"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 10:7">The folk-people sat down to eat and drink</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 10:7">And <char style="it">when they were done </char>got up to play<char style="sup">[B]</char><verse eid="1CO 10:7"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 10:8" />Nor commit fornication (i.e., behave in a sexually immoral way), just as some of them committed fornication,
        and <char style="it">as a result </char>twenty-three thousand dropped dead in one day. <verse eid="1CO 10:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 10:9" />Nor test Christ (i.e., use a circumstance as a test to see if Christ will pass from your point of view),
        just as some of them tested him and <char style="it">as a result </char>were destroyed by serpents. <verse eid="1CO 10:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 10:10" />Nor grumble, murmur, or complain just as some of them grumbled and <char style="it">as a result </char>were
        destroyed by the Destroyer.<verse eid="1CO 10:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 10:11" />Now those things <char style="it">that happened to them </char>turned out to be an example, a pattern,
        a parallel of our own lives, and it was recorded <char style="it">in the Bible</char> to make us aware
        <char style="it">that this applies to us</char>, whom the ends of the ages<char style="sup">[C]</char>
        have arrived at and are staring us in the face, <verse eid="1CO 10:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 10:12" />so that the one who thinks he stands (i.e., the one who thinks he’s immune to sin) should see to it that
        he doesn’t fall (i.e., fall to sin). <verse eid="1CO 10:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 10:13" />No temptation has been taken hold of <char style="it">by the person being tempted </char>if it were not
        for the fact that humans are susceptible to it. But God is faithful, Who won’t permit us to be tempted
        beyond what we’re capable of. No, He’ll make an exit <char style="it">strategy </char>consisting of the
        ability to bear <char style="it">the temptation</char> while under the weight of it.<verse eid="1CO 10:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 10:14" />Therefore, my dear <char style="it">comrades</char>, get as far away from the idolatry <char style="it">you’re
        surrounded with </char>as fast as you can<char style="it">.</char> <verse eid="1CO 10:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 10:15" />I’m talking <char style="it">to you </char>as <char style="it">though I’m speaking</char> to sensible
        people. You decide <char style="it">the sensibility of </char>what I’m saying. <verse eid="1CO 10:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 10:16" />The cup of blessing (i.e., the cup of communion wine) which we pronounce a blessing <char style="it">with</char>,
        is it not an intimate association with the blood of Christ? The loaf of bread which we break <char style="it">during
        communion</char>, is it not an intimate association with the body of Christ<char style="sup">[D]</char>?<verse eid="1CO 10:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 10:17" />Because <char style="it">the </char>loaf is a single entity, <char style="it">we </char>the many are
        one body; we all partake <char style="it">of pieces which come </char>out of the one <char style="it">loaf</char>,<char
        style="it"> </char>you see. <verse eid="1CO 10:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 10:18" />Take a look at Israel, physically speaking: don’t they who feed themselves with the meat of the sacrificial
        animals have an intimate association with the altar and share in the work which goes on there? <verse eid="1CO 10:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 10:19" />So what exactly am I trying to tell you<char style="sup">[c]</char>? That idolatry is something <char
        style="it">which needs to be taken seriously</char><char style="sup">[d]</char>? Or that food sacrificed
        to an idol is something <char style="it">which needs to be taken seriously</char>? <verse eid="1CO 10:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 10:20" />Uh-uh—What they sacrifice they sacrifice to demons and not to God; I don’t want an intimate association
        between you and demons to form. <verse eid="1CO 10:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 10:21" />You can’t be drinking from the Lord’s cup (i.e., following the Lord’s plan for your lives<char style="sup">[e]</char>)
        and from demons’ cup; you can’t be partaking of the Lord’s table (i.e., receiving the Lord’s provision
        for your nourishment<char style="sup">[f]</char>, and for all of your needs for that matter) and of the
        demons’ table. <verse eid="1CO 10:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 10:22" />Or do you <char style="it">intend to</char> provoke the Lord to wrath<char style="sup">[g]</char>? We
        aren’t more powerful than he, are we?<verse eid="1CO 10:22" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 10:23" />Everything is permissible, but not everything is beneficial.<char style="sup">[h]</char> Everything is
        permissible, but not everything edifies. <verse eid="1CO 10:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 10:24" />Let no one pursue his own interests <char style="it">exclusively</char><char style="sup">[i]</char> but
        the next person’s <char style="it">as well</char>. <verse eid="1CO 10:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 10:25" />Eat any sort of meat which is sold at the marketplace without any qualms<char style="sup">[j]</char>;
        <char style="it">the Bible says,</char> <verse eid="1CO 10:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 10:26" />“The abundant, splendid variety of things that the earth contains was put there by the Lord’s doing<char
        style="sup">[k]</char>,” you see. <verse eid="1CO 10:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 10:27" />If someone who’s an unbeliever invites you over <char style="it">to his house </char>and you want to
        go, eat everything that’s laid out on the table or put on your plate without having any qualms about
        eating any of it. <verse eid="1CO 10:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 10:28" />If someone were to tell you, “This is meat which was sacrificed <char style="it">in a pagan ritual</char>,”
        don’t eat it on account of that person who pointed it out and because of <char style="it">the </char>misgivings
        <char style="it">surrounding it</char>—<verse eid="1CO 10:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 10:29" />I don’t mean because of your own misgivings but because of the other person’s. Now just why is what I’m
        free to do or not do decided by another person’s misgivings? <verse eid="1CO 10:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 10:30" />If I partake <char style="it">in the eating of certain foods </char>by means of grace (i.e., using the
        license I’ve been given), why are terrible things said about me in connection with He Whom I offer up
        thanksgiving to? <verse eid="1CO 10:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 10:31" />So whether you eat <char style="it">or don’t eat something </char>or whether you drink <char style="it">or
        don’t drink something </char>or whether you do <char style="it">or don’t do anything else</char>, everything
        <char style="it">you end up doing</char>, do to God’s glory. <verse eid="1CO 10:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CO 10:32" />Get to where you’re not inadvertently causing a Jew or Westerner<char style="sup">[l]</char> or <char
        style="it">anyone in </char>God’s church to get offended or to fall to temptation, <verse eid="1CO 10:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CO 10:33" />just as I too try to fit in with everyone <char style="it">by not offending them or causing alarm among
        them</char>, not pursuing my own interests but rather <char style="it">the interests </char>of the<char
        style="it"> </char>majority, so that they might be saved.<verse eid="1CO 10:33" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">by virtue of the cloud and the sea</char>…Also: <char style="it">in the cloud and in
        the sea</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">what exactly am I trying to tell you</char>…Lit: <char style="it">what am I saying</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">idolatry is something</char> <char style="it">which needs to be taken seriously</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">idolatry is something</char>. Same expression used in Gal. 6:3; the meaning of it can
        be inferred from that passage.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">drinking from the Lord’s cup (i.e., following the Lord’s plan for your lives)</char>…The
        metonymy of the cup is best understood from its usage in Matt. 20:22; Mark 10:38 and in others.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">partaking of the Lord’s table (i.e., receiving the Lord’s provision for your nourishment)</char>…The
        metonymy of the table is best understood from its usage in 2 Sam. 9:7–13; 1 Kings 4:27; Neh. 5:17; Psalm
        23:5; 69:22; 78:19 and in others.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">do you intend to provoke the Lord to wrath</char>…Lit: <char style="it">are you provoking
        the Lord to wrath</char> [also, <char style="it">to jealousy</char>].</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Everything is permissible, but not everything is beneficial</char>…Paul repeats what
        he said in earlier in 6:12; Ref. note there.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">his own interests exclusively</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the things of himself</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">qualms</char>…Lit<char style="it">: judging through the conscience</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">The abundant, splendid variety of things that the earth contains was put there by the
        Lord’s doing</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the earth and its fullness</char> [<char style="it">are</char>]
        <char style="it">of the Lord</char>. <char style="it">The earth and its fullness</char> is a hendiadys;
        ref. note of Matt. 3:11.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a Westerner</char>…Lit: <char style="it">a Greek</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">was initiated into and joined up with Moses in totality</char>…Lit: <char style="it">were
        baptized into Moses</char>. The usage of <char style="it">baptize </char>here anchors its definition
        in the NT. In my opinion, the most complete definition of <char style="it">baptidzō </char><char style="w"
        strong="G00907">βαπτίζω</char>), the Gk. word for <char style="it">to baptize</char>, is the definition
        that James H. Strong gives: <char style="it">whelm. </char>Ref. Luke 12:50. The Israelites passing through
        the Red Sea is symbolic of baptism.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">The folk-people sat down to eat and drink and when they were done got up to play</char>…At
        first, this quotation seems irrelevant with respect to idolatry, that other verses from Exod. would’ve
        been better suited to highlight the golden calve story, but the opposite is true: it is an accurate description.
        Idolatry is attributing care, provision, and protection (in Bible terms, the saving and the salvation)
        to a false god, to worship that god as being the provider, celebrating the fact that he cares and provides
        for you. The eating, drinking, and playing points to this celebration.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the ends of the ages</char>…This expression is similar to “Last Days” (ref. note of
        John 6:39), and both lend support to the idea of there being different ages of mankind. Furthermore,
        God’s dealings with man change from age to age, and there’s a progression as mankind passes through the
        ages. Quoting Wikipedia, “At the core of dispensationalism is the concept that God has acted in different
        ways in dealing with his chosen people throughout human history.” The <char style="it">ends of the ages
        </char>is the age in which God makes available the ability to come to Him through Christ directly. The
        <char style="it">ends </char>(plural) is not only the singular command to accept Christ but also includes
        outpourings of the Holy Spirit.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[D]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[D]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">an intimate association with the body of Christ</char>…Lit: <char style="it">a fellowship</char>
        [also <char style="it">a commonality</char>] <char style="it">of the body of Christ</char>. This verse
        adds clarification to what Jesus meant when he held up the bread and said “This is my body” (Luke 22:19).
        Partaking in the communion bread is fellowship with the body of Christ, but Jesus didn’t literally mean
        that the bread becomes his body.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="1CO 10" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 11   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="1CO 11" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 11:1" />Imitate me, just as I too imitate Christ.<char style="sup">[a]</char><verse eid="1CO 11:1" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 11:2" />I applaud you since you keep in the front of your mind my entire collection of teaching<char style="sup">[b]</char>
        and you firmly adhere to the instruction as I presented and entrusted it to you. <verse eid="1CO 11:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 11:3" />I want you to know for certain that Christ is the head of every man<char style="sup">[A]</char>; the
        man <char style="it">which God created </char>is the head of woman; God is the head of Christ. <verse eid="1CO 11:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 11:4" />Any man who has <char style="it">something </char>down over his head while praying or prophesying disgraces
        his head.<char style="sup">[B]</char> <verse eid="1CO 11:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 11:5" />Any woman who’s praying or prophesying with her head unveiled disgraces her head: it’s the same thing
        as having her hair cut off, in fact; <verse eid="1CO 11:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 11:6" />for if a woman isn’t veiled, have her cut her hair off too. If it’s disgraceful for a woman to have her
        hair cut off or her head shaved, have her put a veil on.<verse eid="1CO 11:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 11:7" />In regard to this topic, a man certainly doesn’t have to put a veil over his head, as his very existence
        is as God’s image and glory<char style="sup">[c]</char> (i.e., His crowning achievement in creation;
        His pride and joy; what He treasures the most; His complement), but the woman is man’s glory (i.e., man’s
        pride and joy; what he treasures above all else; the reflection of the finest in him; his complement).<verse eid="1CO 11:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 11:8" />You see, man isn’t derived from woman<char style="sup">[d]</char>, but <char style="it">the other way
        around</char>: woman is derived from man. <verse eid="1CO 11:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 11:9" />Also, taking a closer look at this, man wasn’t created because of the woman, but rather woman <char style="it">was
        created </char>because of the man. <verse eid="1CO 11:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 11:10" />Because of this the woman ought to have control over <char style="it">her</char> head because of the
        angels.<char style="sup">[C]</char> <verse eid="1CO 11:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 11:11" />Nevertheless in the Lord neither <char style="it">does</char> woman <char style="it">exist </char>apart
        from man nor does man <char style="it">exist </char>apart from woman; <verse eid="1CO 11:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 11:12" />for just as the woman <char style="it">was created </char>out of the man, in the same way as that the
        man too <char style="it">is birthed </char>through the woman, and all the things <char style="it">we
        see in creation</char> <char style="it">come </char>out of God.<verse eid="1CO 11:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 11:13" />Decide among yourselves: is it fitting for a woman to pray to God while unveiled? <verse eid="1CO 11:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 11:14" />Doesn’t even nature itself teach you that if a man were to wear his hair long, it would surely be dishonorable
        for him <char style="it">to do so</char>? <verse eid="1CO 11:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 11:15" />But if a woman were to wear her hair long, it would be glory to her (i.e., it would magnify her, highlighting
        and complementing her; it would be a point of pride for her)? Because the long hair has been given to
        her as a substitute for an article of clothing she would wrap around herself. <verse eid="1CO 11:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 11:16" />But in case someone’s thinking about starting an argument over this, we don’t have such a custom, nor
        do <char style="it">any one of the other </char>of God’s churches.<verse eid="1CO 11:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 11:17" />While preparing the command <char style="it">I’m about to give you</char>, I didn’t have anything good
        to say about you, since your getting together as a group is not for the better but for the worse. <verse eid="1CO 11:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 11:18" />More to the point, at the head of the list is the reports that I hear that there are divisions which
        constantly exist among you when you get together as a church, and I believe that at least some of it
        is true. <verse eid="1CO 11:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 11:19" />Furthermore, there has got to be factions among you, where each faction consists of the people who share
        the same opinion about something, so that it’s become evident that those who decide what does or doesn’t
        fly have come to the forefront among you.<verse eid="1CO 11:19" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 11:20" />So your coming together at the same <char style="it">gatherings</char> isn’t to partake of the Lord’s
        meal, <char style="it">is it?</char> <verse eid="1CO 11:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 11:21" />At the meal <char style="it">served at the gathering, </char>each person in fact gets a head-start on
        his eating with the idea of getting more than the next guy, and <char style="it">as a result </char>one
        <char style="it">fellow</char> goes hungry on the one hand, while one <char style="it">fellow</char>
        gets drunk on the other. <verse eid="1CO 11:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 11:22" />Furthermore, don’t you have pubs and restaurants<char style="sup">[e]</char> for eating and drinking
        <char style="it">at</char>? Or do you have contempt for the church of God and humiliate those who don’t
        have <char style="it">enough to get by on</char>? What was I <char style="it">supposed to</char> tell
        you? Was I <char style="it">supposed to</char> applaud you <char style="it">for doing this</char>? I
        don’t have any applause in this particular case.<verse eid="1CO 11:22" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 11:23" />Delving into this topic more deeply, I received from the Lord and took to heart that which I also presented
        and entrusted to you, that the night the Lord Jesus was betrayed and arrested, he took a loaf, <verse eid="1CO 11:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 11:24" />prayed, broke it, and said,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 11:24"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 11:24"><char style="wj">This is my body which is</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 11:24"><char style="it"><char style="wj">Lifted up, broken, and distributed </char></char><char style="wj">for
        your sakes.</char><char style="sup">[D]</char>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 11:24"><char style="wj">Do this for the purpose of refreshing your memories of me.</char><verse eid="1CO 11:24"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 11:25" />In the same fashion he also took the cup while dining, saying,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 11:25"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 11:25"><char style="wj">This cup is the new covenant </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">ratified </char></char><char
        style="wj">by means of my blood.</char>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 11:25"><char style="wj">As often as you choose to or happen to drink </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">from
        the cup,</char></char>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 11:25"><char style="wj">Do this for the purpose of refreshing your memories of me.</char><verse eid="1CO 11:25"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 11:26" />For as often as you happen to or choose to eat this bread and drink this cup, you proclaim the death
        of the Lord until whatever <char style="it">time </char>he ends up coming, <verse eid="1CO 11:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 11:27" />so that he who perchance eats the bread or drinks the cup of the Lord unworthily will be culpable of
        the body and the blood of the Lord. <verse eid="1CO 11:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 11:28" />Have a person examine and test himself and prove to himself and approve of himself, and have him eat
        from the loaf and drink from the cup in this manner; <verse eid="1CO 11:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 11:29" />you see, he who eats and drinks <char style="it">the communion meal unworthily </char>eats and drinks
        judgment (i.e., a guilty verdict) upon himself <char style="it">by </char>not evaluating the body. <verse eid="1CO 11:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 11:30" />For this reason many of you are weak and frail (i.e., are run down with a long-running illness or have
        maladies<char style="sup">[f]</char>), and a good number of you are in the process of dying<char style="sup">[g]</char>.<verse eid="1CO 11:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 11:31" />If we were to examine and judge ourselves (i.e., examine ourselves and acknowledge our own guilt), we
        would not be judged and pronounced guilty. <verse eid="1CO 11:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CO 11:32" />Being judged by the Lord, you are disciplined, trained, and corrected, so that you won’t be condemned
        together with the world (i.e., with the unbelievers and the entire ungodly system they created). <verse eid="1CO 11:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CO 11:33" /><char style="it">Rember</char> <char style="it">this</char>, my comrades<char style="sup">[h]</char>,
        so that when gathering together for the purpose of eating, wait for one another <char style="it">rather
        than getting a head-start on eating</char>. <verse eid="1CO 11:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CO 11:34" />If someone’s famished, have him eat in a pub or restaurant, so that he won’t join in on <char style="it">one
        of your meal gatherings </char>in such a way that it results in him being judged and pronounced guilty.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="1CO 11:34">Now <char style="it">as far as </char>the other <char style="it">issues</char> <char style="it">I mean
        to address,</char> I’ll settle these whenever I happen to come visit.<verse eid="1CO 11:34"/>
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Imitate me, just as I too imitate Christ</char>…This appears to be a dangling sentence
        that should’ve been appended to the end of the previous chapter.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">my entire collection of teaching</char>…Lit: <char style="it">my all</char> [<char style="it">everything</char>]</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">God’s image and glory</char>…This may be a hendiadys; ref. note of Matt. 3:11. If this
        is the case, it would be rendered <char style="it">God’s image in all of its wonderful glory</char>.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">derived from woman</char>…Lit: <char style="it">out of woman</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">pubs and restaurants</char>…Lit: <char style="it">houses</char>. The Gk. word for <char
        style="it">house </char>also means <char style="it">building</char> in a generic sense, a building which
        is not a residence. In this context, Paul seems to be referring to establishments and not homes per se.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">run down with a long-running illness or have maladies</char>…Ref. note of Matt. 4:23</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">dying</char>…Lit: <char style="it">sleeping</char>. Ref. 1 Cor. 7:39.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the man which God created is the head of woman</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the man
        is the head of woman. </char>The Gk. words for <char style="it">man</char> and <char style="it">woman</char>
        used here are used in some of Paul’s other writings (1 Cor. 7:1–3; Eph. 5:22–23; 1 Tim. 2) and elsewhere
        in the NT to refer to <char style="it">husband </char>and <char style="it">wife, </char>introducing the
        potential for ambiguity. Paul was cognizant of this as he was committing his words to paper (parchment,
        actually) and explicitly selected <char style="it">wife </char>or <char style="it">husband </char>by
        saying <char style="it">own woman </char>and <char style="it">own man </char>in 1 Cor. 7:2 and <char
        style="it">own man </char>in Eph. 5:22. Since <char style="it">own woman </char>or <char style="it">own
        man </char>doesn’t appear in the 1 Cor. 11 passage referenced here, Paul means <char style="it">man </char>and
        <char style="it">woman. </char>The context favors this conclusion as well.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Any man who has something down over his head while praying or prophesying disgraces
        his head</char>…One can only speculate as to what exactly Paul is talking about in this passage. Having
        said that, cultural traditions stretch back for millennia, traditions where women wear head covering.
        It appears that Paul is talking about a tradition which was peculiar to the Corinthians, where it was
        shameful for a man to have something over his head in a public forum of some sort, while it was shameful
        for a woman to not have something over her head in the same forum. There’s a parallel between one’s head
        which is a body part and one’s head which is the next level up in the submission chain (Paul speaks of
        the “head” in Eph. 5:23 the same way). So the woman not having a covering over her head would be seen
        as a sign of disrespect to her head, to man.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Because of this the woman ought to have control over her head because of the angels</char>…Speculation
        again due to the ambiguity in this verse. The Gk. words for <char style="it">have control over </char>can
        also be rendered <char style="it">be</char> <char style="it">having authority. </char>The phrase <char
        style="it">through the angels </char>can be rendered in a couple of variations such as <char style="it">by
        means of the angels, on account of, </char>or <char style="it">through the angels. </char>The question
        is whether <char style="it">her head</char> (lit., <char style="it">the head</char>)<char style="it">
        </char>in this verse refers to the woman’s physical head or to her higher-up (man). Assuming that the
        latter is the case and that <char style="it">head </char>here doesn’t refer to her physical head, then
        this would mean that the woman exercises power, authority, and control over the man, but it is done by
        means of the angels. This agrees with Paul’s previous observation that woman came out of man, but man
        is birthed by woman; both woman comes from man, and man comes from woman; neither is superior; both are
        dependent on the other. This is simply a restatement of v. 12. In keeping with this, the woman has authority
        (has control over) the man, a control which is accomplished on a spiritual level by the employment of
        angels.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[D]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[D]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">This is my body which is lifted up, broken, and distributed for your sakes</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">This is my body which is on your behalf</char>. What Jesus was did with the bread at
        the Last Supper is what was done to his body: it was lifted up, broken, and distributed to everyone around
        the table.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="1CO 11" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 12   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="1CO 12" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 12:1" />Concerning spirituals<char style="sup">[A]</char> (things which are of nature related to the Holy Spirit:
        i.e., spiritual gifts, ministries, and extraordinary manifestations of the Holy Spirit), comrades<char
        style="sup">[a]</char>, I don’t want you to fail to understand this. <verse eid="1CO 12:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 12:2" />You know for a fact that when you were pagans in close contact with<char style="sup">[b]</char> the <char
        style="it">mute and </char>dumb idols, as long as<char style="sup">[c]</char> you kept on being led<char
        style="sup">[d]</char> <char style="it">by the evil spirits those idols attracted, </char>you were being
        led astray. <verse eid="1CO 12:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 12:3" />This is why I’m making you understand that no one while speaking by means of the Spirit of God says “Jesus
        <char style="it">is </char>accursed,” and no one <char style="it">when speaking by the influence of a
        spirit </char>can say “Jesus <char style="it">is</char> Lord” except <char style="it">if the influence
        is </char>by the Holy Spirit.<verse eid="1CO 12:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 12:4" />Now there’s a variety of gifts, gifts which are freely given by God as an act of grace and not as something
        which have been earned by the recipient, but the same Spirit. <verse eid="1CO 12:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 12:5" />And there are a variety of ministries, but the same Spirit still. <verse eid="1CO 12:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 12:6" />And there are a variety of effects <char style="it">produced by the Holy Spirit</char>, but the same
        God Who works every little piece of everything<char style="sup">[e]</char>. <verse eid="1CO 12:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 12:7" />To each is given the manifestation of the Spirit for the common good. <verse eid="1CO 12:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 12:8" />In this regard, through the Spirit is given to one person<char style="sup">[B]</char> <char style="it">the
        </char>word of wisdom, but on the other hand to another person <char style="it">the </char>word of knowledge
        according to the same Spirit, <verse eid="1CO 12:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 12:9" />to another <char style="it">special </char>faith by the same Spirit, but to another gifts of healings<char
        style="sup">[C]</char> by the same Spirit, <verse eid="1CO 12:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 12:10" />but to another the working of miracles, but to another prophecy, but to another the discerning of spirits,
        but to another a <char style="it">different </char>kind of tongue, to another the interpretation of tongues.<verse eid="1CO 12:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 12:11" />The one-in-the-same Spirit works all of these <char style="it">gifts, ministries, and effects</char>,
        divvying them up and parceling them out to each individual just the way He wants.<verse eid="1CO 12:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 12:12" />In fact, just as the body is a single unit and has many parts, and all the parts, <char style="it">even
        though</char> there’s many of them, comprise one body, it’s the same way with Christ. <verse eid="1CO 12:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 12:13" />You see, every one of us was inducted<char style="sup">[f]</char> into one body by one Spirit, whether
        <char style="it">a given person </char>was Jewish, was a Westerner<char style="sup">[g]</char>, whether
        a slave or freeman—all of us have been made to drink <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">the
        water of life from </char>one Spirit; <verse eid="1CO 12:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 12:14" />for the body <char style="it">does not consist </char>of one part <char style="it">only </char>but of
        many parts. <verse eid="1CO 12:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 12:15" />If the foot were to say, “I’m not a hand—I’m not one of the parts the body has,” then because of this
        <char style="it">claim </char>it’s not a constituent body part? <verse eid="1CO 12:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 12:16" />And if the ear were to say, “I’m not an eye, I’m not part of the body,” because of <char style="it">saying
        </char>this, it’s not part of the body? <verse eid="1CO 12:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 12:17" />If the entire body was <char style="it">just one giant </char>eye, how would you hear? If the entire
        body was <char style="it">just one giant </char>ear, how could you smell anything?<verse eid="1CO 12:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 12:18" />So as it turns out God put every one of the parts into position just the way He wanted. <verse eid="1CO 12:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 12:19" />If every little piece<char style="sup">[h]</char> was one <char style="it">type of </char>part <char
        style="it">only</char>, where would that leave the body? <verse eid="1CO 12:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 12:20" />It turns out that while there’re many parts indeed, there’s but one body. <verse eid="1CO 12:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 12:21" />The eye can’t <char style="it">get away with </char>telling the hand “I don’t need you”; furthermore,
        the head can’t tell the feet “I don’t need you” either. <verse eid="1CO 12:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 12:22" />No—the parts of the body which seem to be weaker are more necessary <char style="it">than they appear
        to be</char>. <verse eid="1CO 12:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 12:23" />We assign a greater value to the parts of the body we deem to be of little value<char style="sup">[D]</char>,
        and we put a greater amount of clothing over our private parts <char style="it">to ensure that they’re
        well-hidden</char>, <verse eid="1CO 12:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 12:24" />but the valuable parts have no need <char style="it">of that</char>. No—God composed—He blended together
        and mixed—the body by having given more value to those parts lacking it <verse eid="1CO 12:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 12:25" />so there wouldn’t be division in the body, but that the members would care for each other <char style="it">treating
        each other</char> the same way. <verse eid="1CO 12:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 12:26" />If a <char style="it">single</char> member happens to suffer, all the members suffer along with it. If
        a <char style="it">single </char>member is glorified, all the members are glorified along with it.<verse eid="1CO 12:26" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 12:27" />Now you all are Christ’s body, and you as the individual members populate the various body parts<char
        style="sup">[i]</char>. <verse eid="1CO 12:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 12:28" />God has indeed placed in the church first apostles (i.e., missionaries sent out to pioneer new Christian
        works), second prophets, third teachers, <char style="it">those who perform </char>miracles, gifts of
        healings, <char style="it">those who </char>help in any of a multitude of ways<char style="sup">[j]</char>,
        administrations (i.e., guidance, governorship: literally the one who steers the ship), various tongues.<verse eid="1CO 12:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 12:29" />Not everyone’s an apostle, <char style="it">are they</char>? Not everyone’s a prophet, <char style="it">are
        they</char>? Not everyone’s a teacher, <char style="it">are they</char>? Not everyone performs miracles,
        <char style="it">do they</char>? <verse eid="1CO 12:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 12:30" />Not everyone has <char style="it">one of the various</char> gifts of healings, <char style="it">do they</char>?
        Not everyone speaks in tongues, <char style="it">do they</char>? Not everyone interprets <char style="it">messages
        in tongues, do they</char><char style="sup">[E]</char>? <verse eid="1CO 12:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 12:31" />But maintain a burning desire for the greater gifts.
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="1CO 12:31">Yet I’ll show you a road <char style="it">to take</char> which is superior <char style="it">to this</char><char
        style="sup">[F]</char>…<verse eid="1CO 12:31"/>
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">in close contact with</char>…Lit: <char style="it">with</char>. Same usage of the word
        <char style="it">with</char> as John used in the phrase <char style="it">the Concept was with God </char>(John
        1:1).</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">as long as</char>…A minor definition of the Gk. word <char style="it">hōs</char> <char
        style="w" strong="G05613">ὡς</char>)used here (a definition found in Thayer’s concordance). Justified
        by the context.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">kept on being led</char>….According to Max &amp; Mary, the Gk. particle <char style="it">an
        </char>inserted here emphasizes the continuous action insinuated by the imperfect tense of the verb <char
        style="it">to be led.</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">every little piece of everything</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the all in all</char>.
        Same expression used 1 Cor. 15:28; Eph. 1:23</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">inducted</char>…Lit: <char style="it">baptized</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Westerner</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Greek</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">every little piece</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the alls</char>. Used in v. 6 also.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">you as the individual members populate the various body parts</char>…Lit: [<char style="it">you
        are</char>] <char style="it">members out of</char> [<char style="it">the</char>] <char style="it">parts</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">those who help in any of a multitude of ways</char>…Lit: <char style="it">helps</char>.
        The Gk. word for <char style="it">help </char>literally means one who <char style="it">takes hold of
        something in place of another.</char> Also, ref. note concerning <char style="it">gifts of healings </char>in
        v. 28.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">spirituals</char>…The Gk. word <char style="it">pneumatikos </char><char style="w" strong="G04152">πνευματικός</char>).<char
        style="it"> </char>The Gk. noun <char style="it">pneuma </char>(spirit, πνεῦμα/Strong’s 4151) terminated
        with the adjective ending <char style="it">tikos, </char>a suffix<char style="it"> </char>which “marks
        ability or fitness” of the verb it appends according to Bullinger. The adjective, having been formed,
        is used substantively as a noun in this verse, forming a new noun. This new Gk. noun means “belonging
        to or of pneuma; of the pneuma.” As pneuma has multiple meanings—a spiritual being (the Holy Spirit,
        a human spirit, a demonic spirit); related to things of the spirit; prevailing attitude—pneumatikos acquires
        these flavors of meaning: related to or of the Holy Spirit; related to or of a human spirit; or simply
        the word <char style="it">spiritual</char> as it’s understood in English. Though Paul didn’t invent this
        word, he coined the usage of it in the NT. The meaning of pneumatikos in Paul’s writings is best understood
        from the way Paul uses it and from firsthand Christian experience—not from what’s written in the lexicons.
        When pneumatikos appears in the NT, the context will guide you as to which of these various definitions
        to use. In v. 1 here, the context suggests things related to or pertaining to the Holy Spirit, where
        <char style="it">Holy Spirit </char>is a synecdoche which refers to his workings, similar to the way
        Holy Spirit is used a synecdoche to refer to the baptism in the Holy Spirit (an example being Acts 8:15).
        So pneumatikos as used here refers to things that the Holy Spirit does and not the Holy Spirit himself
        per se. This is not the case in other NT usages of pneumatikos, as pneumatikos’s meaning is context-dependent.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">through the Spirit is given to one person</char>…The nine items listed in this passage,
        the Gifts of the Spirit, are all supernatural workings of the Holy Spirit, in spite of some of these
        item’s titles, titles which suggest that they are personal qualities. Among such titles is the first,
        the <char style="it">word of wisdom; </char>the Gk. word for <char style="it">word </char>in this context
        means a piece of information. The word <char style="it">wisdom, </char>apart from meaning wisdom, also
        means sophistication, cleverness, highly-skilled in a specific area, and even cunning. For the second
        item, the <char style="it">word of knowledge</char>, the Gk. word for <char style="it">knowledge </char>means
        knowledge or understanding which isn’t obtained through the physical senses. <char style="it">Faith </char>,
        the third item, must be talking about faith of a supernatural type, not to be confused with personal
        faith, which all believers must have and are encouraged to grow in.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Pentecostal tradition (and the Pentecostals have studied this passage the most) defines the spiritual
        gifts as follows:</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Word of wisdom—supernatural understanding of some future event</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Word of knowledge—supernatural knowledge of a current or past event</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Special faith—supernatural faith to receive a miracle</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Gifts of healings— spectacular healings, usually instantaneous</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Working of miracles—just like it sounds</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Prophecy—Holy Spirit-inspired utterance</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Discerning of spirits—the ability to see into the spiritual world; seeing angels or demons</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Tongues—Holy Spirit-inspired utterance in an unknown language</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Interpretation of tongues—Holy Spirit-inspired interpretation of an utterance in tongues</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">gifts of healings</char>…This is <char style="it">gifts of healings </char>(plural)
        not <char style="it">gift of healing </char>(singular). There is no single, generic gift of healing,
        rather there are a multitude of specialty healing gifts just like there’s a multitude of doctors who
        are specialists. Those who have a healing gift will usually excel at healing certain types or categories
        of disorders more than others. Similarly, when this same verse mentions <char style="it">helps</char>,
        it does so in the plural instead of singular because there’s a wide variety of helps ministries, and
        therefore people tend to specialize in one specific type of helps ministry.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[D]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[D]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">have little value</char>…Also: <char style="it">handle the necessary but distasteful
        body functions</char>…Lit: <char style="it">dishonorable</char>. Paul may be referring to hair: it has
        little functional value and serves little function, but gets dressed, clothed, and is something which
        is of value to us.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[E]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[E]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Not everyone speaks in tongues, do they? Not everyone interprets messages in tongues,
        do they</char>…Lit: <char style="it">not all speak in tongues; not all interpret</char>. Keep in mind
        that what’s spoken about in vv. 27–31 are ministries, a subset of the “spirituals” specified in v. 1.
        Ministry gifts are full-time callings, such as an apostle or teacher, a vocation that the Holy Spirit
        calls a person to and enables him to do on a regular basis. A ministry is done for the benefit of the
        body and not for a personal edification. As such, the tongues listed in v. 30 is a vocation, a ministry,
        something done for the edification of the body. Not everyone has this ministry. But there is another
        kind of tongues described in 14:4 which is for personal edification. The restriction of “not everyone
        speaks in tongues” doesn’t apply to the speaking in tongues done for personal edification.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[F]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[F]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Yet I’ll show you a way which is superior to this</char>…Lit: <char style="it">And yet
        I show you according to superior way</char>…The introduction to the 13<char style="sup">th</char> chapter.
        What is written about in the 12<char style="sup">th</char> chapter is a good way: miraculous manifestations
        by the Holy Spirit; the entire body of Christ working together in harmony. But it gets better.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="1CO 12" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 13   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="1CO 13" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 13:1" />If I were to speak in tongues of men and of angels but not have love, I will have become a blaring brass
        instrument<char style="sup">[a]</char> or clanging cymbal. <verse eid="1CO 13:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 13:2" />If I were to have a prophecy and <char style="it">that prophecy would give me the answers to life’s questions
        so I would </char>know for certain<char style="sup">[A]</char> all the mysteries and all the knowledge
        and understanding, or<char style="sup">[b]</char> if I were to have all the faith so as to move mountains
        <char style="it">from place to place</char>, but not have love, I am nothing. <verse eid="1CO 13:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 13:3" />And if I were to sell everything I own and tender my body to be burned, but not have love, it is helping
        me nothing.<verse eid="1CO 13:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 13:4" />The love <char style="it">of which I speak </char>is patient, the love is kind, isn’t jealous and doesn’t
        cause rivalry, doesn’t vaunt itself and act as a show-off, isn’t full of itself, <verse eid="1CO 13:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 13:5" />doesn’t act unseemly or indecently, doesn’t seek its self-interest<char style="sup">[c]</char>, doesn’t
        gaslight others, doesn’t keep a mental scorecard of the bad things <char style="it">done to it</char>,<verse eid="1CO 13:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 13:6" />doesn’t rejoice at the wrongdoing <char style="it">of others</char> but joins in the rejoicing in the
        truth; <verse eid="1CO 13:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 13:7" /><char style="it">it </char>endures all things, believes all things, hopes all things, endures all things.<verse eid="1CO 13:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 13:8" />The love <char style="it">of which we speak </char>never breaks down<char style="sup">[d]</char>. Should
        there be prophecies, they’ll be done away with; should there be tongues, they’ll cease; should there
        be knowledge and understanding, it’ll be done away with.<char style="sup">[B]</char><char style="sup">[C]</char><verse eid="1CO 13:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 13:9" />The fact of the matter is that we know and understand from <char style="it">the perspective </char>of
        a part <char style="it">of the whole </char>and we prophecy<char style="it"> </char>from <char style="it">the
        perspective </char>of a part, <verse eid="1CO 13:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 13:10" />but when the Complete comes, the Partial will be done away with. <verse eid="1CO 13:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 13:11" />When I was a child, I was talking like a child, was thinking like a child, was reasoning like a child—when
        I became a man, I did away with the things of childhood. <verse eid="1CO 13:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 13:12" />Furthermore, at the moment <char style="it">we’re seeing life as though </char>we’re looking at the vague
        reflection <char style="it">cast </char>by a mirror, but some time in the future <char style="it">we’ll</char>
        <char style="it">look</char> <char style="it">at life as though we’re </char>looking <char style="it">at
        it </char>face-to-face; at the moment my knowing and understanding comes out of a <char style="it">single
        </char>part <char style="it">of the whole, </char>but some time in the future I’ll know and understand
        <char style="it">life </char>exactly just as I have been known and understood <char style="it">by God
        </char>exactly.<verse eid="1CO 13:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 13:13" />At the present time faith, hope, and love remain—these three—but the greatest of them is love.<verse eid="1CO 13:13" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a brass instrument</char>…Lit: a copper</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">or</char>…Lit: <char style="it">and</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">its self-interest</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the things of itself</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">breaks down</char>…Lit: <char style="it">falls</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">know for certain</char>…The Gk. verb <char style="it">oida </char><char style="w" strong="G01492">οἶδα</char>)<char
        style="it">, </char>in contrast to the Gk. root verb <char style="it">ginōskō </char><char style="w"
        strong="G01097">γινώσκω</char>)used for <char style="it">knowledge and understanding </char>in this verse.
        <char style="it">Oida </char>is knowing by seeing (by physical sense); <char style="it">ginōskō </char>is
        understanding something which is abstract. This difference is exemplified in 2 Cor. 5:16, where both
        <char style="it">ginōskō </char>and oida are used in the same verse. Furthermore, in this verse Paul
        said “if I were to have a prophecy” and not “if I were to prophesy.” In other words, Paul said “if I
        were to possess a prophecy” and not “if I were to prophesy [i.e. speak a prophetic utterance].” He goes
        on to insinuate that the prophecy would contain the answers to the mysteries of life—hence the choice
        of the word <char style="it">oida </char>instead of <char style="it">ginōskō </char>when he said “know
        all the mysteries, etc.”</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Should there be prophecies, they’ll be done away with; should there be tongues, they’ll
        cease; should there be knowledge and understanding, it’ll be done away with</char>…Some have used this
        verse as a basis to argue that prophecies and tongues have ceased because the time for it to cease has
        come already. But notice that Paul mentions three things: prophecy, tongues, and knowledge. All three
        of these will cease at the same time, and not just two of three. It’s obvious that the third item knowledge
        hasn’t ceased yet, therefore the other two haven’t either.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">knowledge and understanding, it’ll be done away with…</char>There is a time coming,
        as specified in the v. 10, when the “perfect” will come, and the “partial” will be done away with. Has
        this time come yet? No, it couldn’t have. Verse 8 lists three things that will cease when this time arrives:
        prophecy, tongues, and knowledge. Not one, not two, but all three will cease. Some have taught in the
        past that this time arrived when the last book of the Bible was written, therefore tongues and prophecy
        have ceased. But what about knowledge? Paul tells us in a few other places in his epistles that he desires
        for Christians to increase in knowledge-certainly it has not ceased, and therefore the fulfillment cannot
        have been the completion of the NT canon.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">But there is coming a time—probably after death—when all three will cease, including knowledge. One might
        see why tongues and prophecy will cease, but what about knowledge? Does this mean that when we get to
        heaven, we’ll forget everything we knew on the earth? I should think not. The answer lies a bit deeper,
        specifically in an understanding of the Gk. word used for <char style="it">know</char>. NT Gk. has two
        principle verbs for “to know,” and from the verbs all the other forms, in this case the nouns, are derived.
        The first word is <char style="it">oida</char>, and it&apos;s actually an awkward form of another verb
        which means “to see.” The other word is <char style="it">gnōskō</char>. Oida and <char style="it">ginōskō</char>,
        although both translated &quot;to know&quot;, have distinct meanings. Oida means to know because a fact
        or thing is obvious, it’s something one knows because one has seen it, hence the connection to the verb
        “to see.” Ginōskō, on the other hand, refers to knowledge that one has obtained without the use of the
        senses. Ginōskō involves a level of abstraction, or reasoning, to arrive at the thing known, since it’s
        not directly discernable. For example, I “oida” that the shirt I’m wearing is red, but I “<char style="it">ginōskō
        </char>“ that the spare-penny dish at the checkout line at the convenience store is usually empty, because
        people are more apt to reach for a penny when they’re two or three cents short of the next dollar than
        they are to remember to put their spare pennies in the dish. Ginōskō is also a root used to derive other
        words, but in every case the meaning still involves some thought process. Hence, ginōskō or its derivatives
        are, among others, translated “understand,” “discern,” or “recognize.” In the NT, ginōskō is sometimes
        used in reference to spiritual knowledge, because spiritual things cannot be seen, and faith, by nature,
        believes in what one cannot see, and therefore is always abstract.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">But there’s coming a day when the faith necessary to believe in God won’t be necessary, because we won’t
        be living on this earth anymore. All ginōskō knowledge will be replaced with oida knowledge, which will
        not cease—only ginōskō knowledge will. Questions and mysteries will be done away with too, at that time.
        But while we’re still here on earth, there are certain things we must know without having seen, or having
        conclusive proofs demonstrated to us. There’s things that also happen to us, or to others we know, that
        are a mystery. Why did this tragedy occur? Many ask, was it God’s will? Where was God in all of this?
        A lot of things we don’t—nor ever will—know the answer to, not here on this earth. This doesn’t mean
        that there’s not a good explanation for it; what it does mean is that the explanation is beyond our reach.
        Often when people don’t have the answer, they must fill that unknowing in them and produce their own
        explanation, and often this results in speculations about God’s will. This has become the source of a
        lot of poor doctrine. Just accept the fact that there are certain things that we’ll never understand
        in this lifetime until the perfect comes, but that there’s probably a good explanation for these things.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="1CO 13" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 14   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="1CO 14" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 14:1" />Pursue love and have a burning desire for the spirituals (i.e., spiritual gifts and manifestations of
        the Holy Spirit), but more so that you would prophesy <char style="it">than speak in tongues</char>.<verse eid="1CO 14:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 14:2" />You see, the one who speaks in tongues isn’t talking to people <char style="it">when he’s speaking in
        tongues </char>but is talking to God instead. In fact no one hears <char style="it">him speak</char>
        <char style="it">intelligibly</char>: he speaks mysteries by <char style="it">his</char> spirit<char
        style="sup">[a]</char>. <verse eid="1CO 14:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 14:3" />Converseley, the one who prophesies speaks edification; exhortation, encouragement, comfort, advice;
        and consolation to people. <verse eid="1CO 14:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 14:4" />The one who speaks in tongues edifies himself (i.e., builds himself up); the one who prophesies edifies
        the church. <verse eid="1CO 14:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 14:5" />I want all of you to speak in tongues and speak in tongues, but more so that you would prophesy and prophesy.
        The one who prophesies is more important<char style="sup">[b]</char> than the one who speaks in tongues,
        unless he were to interpret <char style="it">what was spoken in tongues, </char>so that the church would
        receive edification.<verse eid="1CO 14:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 14:6" />So now, comrades<char style="sup">[c]</char>, if I were to go up to you and proceed to speak<char style="sup">[d]</char>
        in tongues, how would it benefit you, except if I were to convey a revelation, an understanding, a prophecy,
        or a teaching<char style="sup">[e]</char>? <verse eid="1CO 14:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 14:7" />Nevertheless the inanimate objects which are designed to produce specific, coherent sound patterns, whether
        <char style="it">we’re talking about a </char>flute or <char style="it">a </char>harp<char style="sup">[f]</char>—if
        <char style="it">one of them</char> were to not put out distinct musical notes, how will the flute-playing
        or harp-playing be comprehensible? <verse eid="1CO 14:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 14:8" />Furthermore, if a bugle were to play an indistinguishable tune, who would get into position for battle?<verse eid="1CO 14:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 14:9" />Similarly, if you were to not form intelligible words in whatever language you speak in, how would what’s
        spoken be comprehensible? The fact of the matter is that you would just be wasting your breath<char style="sup">[g]</char>.<verse eid="1CO 14:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 14:10" />Who knows just how many different languages there are worldwide, and none of them consists of a set of
        incomprehensible sounds. <verse eid="1CO 14:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 14:11" />So if I were to not have the voice-control <char style="it">to utter words correctly in a given language</char>,
        from the perspective of the person I’m speaking to, I’ll appear to whomever I’m speaking to as though
        I’m a person from another country who can’t speak the native language<char style="sup">[h]</char>, and
        he’ll appear the same way to me. <verse eid="1CO 14:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 14:12" />Likewise, you too, since you are zealous of spirituals (i.e., manifestations of the Holy Spirit), seek
        that which furthers the edification of the church.<verse eid="1CO 14:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 14:13" />In light of this, let the one speaking in tongues pray that he would interpret <char style="it">what
        he’s speaking</char>. <verse eid="1CO 14:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 14:14" />You see, if I were to pray in tongues, my spirit would be<char style="it"> </char>praying but my mind
        wouldn’t be involved in the production of the words<char style="sup">[i]</char>. <verse eid="1CO 14:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 14:15" />So what’s <char style="it">the conclusion</char>? I will pray in the Spirit<char style="sup">[j]</char>,
        but I will pray also with the mind. I will sing a song<char style="sup">[A]</char> <char style="it">of
        praise to the Lord </char>in the Spirit, but I will also sing a song with the mind. <verse eid="1CO 14:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 14:16" />Otherwise, if you were to give a praise, blessing, or consecration with <char style="it">the</char> spirit,
        a person who isn’t versed in the things of the Spirit and doesn’t speak in tongues<char style="sup">[B]</char>—how
        will he say “amen” (i.e., speak a verbal affirmation) upon <char style="it">hearing </char>Your Blessing<char
        style="sup">[k]</char>, since he doesn’t know what you’re saying? <verse eid="1CO 14:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 14:17" />For you certainly give a blessing well, but the other <char style="it">person who’s not versed in the
        things of the Spirit </char>doesn’t get anything out of it. <verse eid="1CO 14:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 14:18" />I give God thanks that I speak in tongues more than you all, <verse eid="1CO 14:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 14:19" />but putting that to the side, <char style="it">when I’m</char> in a church I want to speak five words
        <char style="it">or so</char> using my mind so that I would pass on instruction to others, rather than
        a million words in an <char style="it">unknown </char>language.<verse eid="1CO 14:19" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 14:20" />Comrades, don’t become children in <char style="it">your</char> thought processes, but instead, act like
        toddlers with the evil <char style="it">you’re inundated with</char> and become adults in <char style="it">your</char>
        thought processes. <verse eid="1CO 14:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 14:21" />It’s written in the Old Testament<char style="sup">[l]</char>:
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 14:21"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 14:21">“In different tongues</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 14:21">And by the lips of different people</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 14:21">I will speak to this folk,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 14:21">And they won’t even hear and obey Me</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 14:21"><char style="it">As I speak </char>in this way,” says the Lord<verse eid="1CO 14:21"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 14:22" /><char style="it">This is the case</char> so much so that the tongues <char style="it">referred to by
        this Old Testament passage </char>are intended to be a sign (i.e., a miracle God performed, done in such
        a way to demonstrate beyond any doubt that He did it) not to those who believe but rather to those who
        refuse to believe<char style="sup">[C]</char>. <verse eid="1CO 14:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 14:23" />So if the entire church were to gather together in one place and everyone were to speak in tongues and
        a person who isn’t versed in the things of the Spirit or speak in tongues or an unbeliever were to enter,
        they’d come to the conclusion that you all are insane, wouldn’t they? <verse eid="1CO 14:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 14:24" />But if everyone were to prophecy and some unbeliever or someone who’s not versed in the Spirit were to
        enter, everything <char style="it">inside of him</char> will be exposed by everyone, he’ll be examined
        by everyone, <verse eid="1CO 14:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 14:25" />the secrets of his heart will get to where they’re out in the open for everyone to see, so that he’ll
        worship God as he falls on his face, telling everyone that God really is among you.<verse eid="1CO 14:25" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 14:26" />What’s the bottom line<char style="sup">[m]</char>, comrades? When you get together as a group, each
        has a hymn, <char style="it">each</char> has a teaching, <char style="it">each</char> has a revelation,
        <char style="it">each</char> has a <char style="it">message in </char>tongues, <char style="it">each</char>
        has an interpretation <char style="it">of a message in tongues. </char>Let everything that happens serve
        the purpose of edification— <verse eid="1CO 14:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 14:27" />Should someone speak in tongues, <char style="it">let there be </char>two or at the most three <char
        style="it">messages given </char>at a time one after the other and let one <char style="it">person </char>interpret
        <char style="it">each message</char>.<char style="sup">[D]</char> <verse eid="1CO 14:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 14:28" />Now if there’s no interpreter, have him remain silent in church, but let him speak <char style="it">in
        tongues </char>to himself and to God<char style="sup">[E]</char>.<verse eid="1CO 14:28" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 14:29" />Let a handful<char style="sup">[n]</char> of prophets speak, and let the others go through <char style="it">what
        they prophesy</char> and judge it piece by piece. <verse eid="1CO 14:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 14:30" />Now if <char style="it">something </char>were to be revealed to another person<char style="it"> </char>seated
        <char style="it">nearby or in the congregation</char>, have the first one silence himself. <verse eid="1CO 14:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 14:31" />The fact is all of you can prophecy one after another, so that everyone would learn and be exhorted,
        comforted, counseled, and advised; <verse eid="1CO 14:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CO 14:32" />the spirits of prophets are subordinate to and take directions from prophets.<char style="sup">[F]</char><verse eid="1CO 14:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CO 14:33" />You see, God is not a product of confusion but of peace.
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="1CO 14:33">As in all the congregations of those who believe in Christ, <verse eid="1CO 14:33"/>
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CO 14:34" />have the women in the churches keep silent. The fact of the matter is, I don’t allow them to speak <char
        style="it">aloud</char> <char style="it">addressing the entire congregation</char><char style="sup">[G]</char>,
        but have them submit instead, just as the Old Testament concurs. <verse eid="1CO 14:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CO 14:35" />If they want to learn something in particular, let them ask their husbands at home; it’s disgraceful
        for a woman to speak <char style="it">aloud in a disrupting way </char>in church you see— <verse eid="1CO 14:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CO 14:36" />Or did the word of God issue forth from you? Or are you the only ones it came down and met<char style="sup">[o]</char>?<verse eid="1CO 14:36" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CO 14:37" />If someone is considered to be a prophet or spiritual (i.e., the Holy Spirit manifests spiritual gifts
        through him), let him come to recognize and understand that what I’m writing to you is a commandment
        from the Lord. <verse eid="1CO 14:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CO 14:38" />But if someone will not understand, let him remain without understanding. <verse eid="1CO 14:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CO 14:39" />So then, my comrades, seek to prophesy and prophesy and to speak and speak in tongues, not preventing
        speaking<char style="it"> </char>in tongues— <verse eid="1CO 14:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CO 14:40" />But let everything be done properly and orderly.<verse eid="1CO 14:40" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">by</char> <char style="it">his</char> <char style="it">spirit</char>…Or: <char style="it">with
        the Spirit</char>…Lit: <char style="it">by</char> [or <char style="it">in</char>; <char style="it">with</char>]
        [<char style="it">the</char>] <char style="it">spirit</char>.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">more important</char>…Lit: <char style="it">greater</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">proceed to speak</char>…Lit: <char style="it">speaking</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a revelation, a knowledge, a prophecy, or a teaching</char>…The Gk. wording insinuates
        that this is a comprehensive list</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">whether we’re talking about a flute or a harp</char>…The usage of the Gk. word for <char
        style="it">whether </char>in this verse implies that Paul’s referring to the flute or the harp only to
        the exclusion of all other instruments. Ref. note of Rev. 18:22</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">wasting your breath</char>…Lit: <char style="it">speaking to air</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a person from another country who can’t speak the native language</char>…Lit: <char
        style="it">a barbarian</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">be involved in the production of the words</char>…Lit: <char style="it">is unfruitful</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">in the Spirit</char>…Or: <char style="it">with the spirit</char>. Some ambiguity exists.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Your Blessing</char>…The Gk. construct insinuates that the message is the speaker’s
        own peculiar message</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the Old Testament</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the Law</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[m]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[m]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">what’s the bottom line</char>…Lit: <char style="it">so what is</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[n]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[n]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a handful</char>…Lit: <char style="it">two or three</char>. An expression; also used
        in Matt. 18:20.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[o]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[o]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">are you the only ones it came down and met</char>…Also: <char style="it">to you only
        it arrived</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">sing a song</char>…Lit: <char style="it">to pluck</char> [<char style="it">the strings
        of a musical instrument like a harp; to play a stringed instrument; to sing to the music of a harp</char>].
        Weak as it may be, this is one of the few pieces of evidence in the Bible of post-resurrection believers
        using musical instruments in worship.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a person who isn’t versed in the things of the Spirit and doesn’t speak in tongues</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">the one filling up the place of the outsider</char>. The phrase <char style="it">the
        one filling up the place </char>is an expression, and what deeper meaning or further nuance that this
        expression communicates, I don’t know . The Gk. word for <char style="it">outsider </char>is contingent
        on the context. Given a skill, profession, or some area of knowledge, the “outsider” is a novice, is
        unskilled, or is ignorant when it comes to the matter at hand.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">This is the case so much so that the tongues referred to by this Old Testament passage
        are intended to be a sign (i.e., a miracle God performed, done in such a way to demonstrate beyond any
        doubt that He did it)</char> <char style="it">not to those who believe but rather to those who refuse
        to believe</char>…Lit: <char style="it">so much so that the tongues are intended to be a sign not to
        those who believer but rather to those </char>[<char style="it">in</char>]<char style="it"> unbelief</char>.
        A puzzling verse. J.B. Phillips, author of <char style="it">The New Testament in Modern English </char>(1958
        version), wrote, “This is the sole instance of the translator’s departing from the accepted text. He
        felt bound to conclude, from the sense of the next three verses, that we have here either a slip of the
        pen on the part of Paul, or, more probably, a copyist’s error.” In other words, Phillips is justifying
        the fact that he swapped a couple words to make sense of this verse. I disagree with Phillips; however,
        this verse must be supplied with interpolations to make sense of it. Verse 22 begins with the Gk. word
        <char style="it">hōste</char> [<char style="it">so much so</char> <char style="w" strong="G05620">ὥστε</char>)].
        Hōste connects two thoughts, and an interpolation has been added to beginning of the verse to make this
        more apparent (Matt. 12:12 is an example). Verse 22 is tightly coupled with v. 21, being linked to the
        quotation from Is. 28:11–12. What this means is that tongues is a sign that the prophecy from Isaiah
        has been fulfilled, so that those who don’t believe should recognize it as the fulfillment of this prophecy.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[D]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[D]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Should someone speak in tongues, let there be two or at the most three messages given
        at a time one after the other and let one person interpret each message</char>…As Paul left a few key
        words to one’s imagination, it’s not quite clear which of a couple different things he meant. It seems
        that these verses here are referring to one person speaking, as the words <char style="it">someone </char>in
        <char style="it">should someone speak; him </char>in <char style="it">let him remain silent; </char>and
        <char style="it">him </char>in <char style="it">let him speak to himself </char>are all singular.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[E]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[E]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">let him speak in tongues to himself and to God</char>…Lit: <char style="it">let him
        speak to himself and to God</char>. The interpolation <char style="it">in tongues </char>is justifiable
        based on the context and is affirmed by v. 2, which says that a person who speaks in tongues speaks to
        God. Many have taken the first half of v. 28, “Now if there’s no interpreter, have him remain silent
        in church,” to mean that there should be no speaking in tongues in church whatsoever unaccompanied by
        an interpretation. For this reason, Paul added the second half of v. 28 to allow speaking in tongues
        done without interpretation, as long as it’s done quietly (i.e. <char style="it">to himself</char>).</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Many claim that the Bible commands that all speaking in tongues must be followed by an interpretation,
        but there’s not a single example of a message in tongues followed by an interpretation when one closely
        examines every instance of speaking in tongues in Acts. In fact, in each of those instances, not only
        was there no interpretation given, but everyone was speaking in tongues at the same time. None of those
        who were speaking in tongues in Acts are “outsiders” (see above note), so it’s alright for them all to
        speak in tongues at the same time since they’ll all be self-edified.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Furthermore, as v. 28 says “…have him remain silent in church…” but also says “…let him speak to himself
        and to God,” we should infer that what Paul meant by “remain silent in the church” is actually a command
        to not speak in a loud voice so as to address the congregation rather than a command to not speak at
        all—otherwise, how can such a person simultaneously remain silent and speak to himself? This observation
        gains importance later on in this chapter when Paul talks about women keeping silent in church. The same
        applies in that case for women: he’s not saying that women can’t talk at all in church, rather he’s saying
        women shouldn’t talk out loud in a way that they address the entire congregation. This observation makes
        sense, as the problem in the Corinthian church was multiple parties trying to speak to the entire congregation
        at the same time, talking over top of each other—one speaking to himself or speaking in a subdued voice
        was not the problem.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[F]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[F]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the spirits of prophets are subordinate to and take directions from prophets</char>…Regardless
        of whether prophets have been given the unction from the Holy Spirit to prophecy, the may choose not
        to, and this is not a slight against the Holy Spirit. This passage insinuates that a prophet will receive
        such unction but will have to wait his turn to deliver it. Put another way, the Holy Spirit will at times
        give unctions to multiple people at the same time, but it’s up to them to deliver these messages serially.
        An unction from the Holy Spirit can be held for a period of time—it doesn’t have to be blurted out the
        moment it’s received.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[G]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[G]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">to speak</char> <char style="it">aloud</char> <char style="it">addressing the entire
        congregation</char>…Lit: <char style="it">to speak</char>. Ref. note of v. 27 for justification for adding
        <char style="it">aloud addressing the entire congregation. </char>Paul is not forbidding women to engage
        in normal conversation while at church; that notion is preposterous.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Continuing on in vv. 35–36, Paul says it’s disgraceful for a woman to speak in church. Paul’s statement
        “If they want to learn something in particular, let them ask their husbands at home” implies that the
        women were disrupting the entire church by interrupting the speaker with a question. Not only were they
        interrupting the speaker, Paul’s remark, “did the word of God issue forth from you (etc),” indicates
        that their questions did not come from a sincere, humble desire to learn but from a position of arrogance,
        from a know-it-all attitude. These reasons are why Paul said it was disgraceful for the women (these
        women) to speak in church.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">But we know that women were permitted to speak in church at that time, since Acts 21:9 mentions four
        young women who prophesied. In order to prophesy, these women would have to do so in a church setting,
        and doing so meant that they were addressing the congregation while prophesying. This fourteenth chapter
        plus the ancient treatise called the <char style="it">Didache </char>indicate that the first century
        church had prophets stand up and address the congregation in prophesies on a regular basis—something
        which is radically different than even what Pentecostals do nowadays. I imagine that the four daughters
        of Acts 21:9 took their turn at the pulpit.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="1CO 14" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 15   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="1CO 15" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 15:1" />I’m making you understand, comrades<char style="sup">[a]</char>, the Gospel (i.e., the good-news message)
        which was evangelized to you, which in addition you received (i.e., took hold of in your hearts and applied
        to your own selves), and in which you stand (i.e., in this you are established, you remain stable and
        steadfast, and in this you withstand the pressures of life), <verse eid="1CO 15:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 15:2" />and through which you are being saved (i.e., time after time being rescued from life’s calamities) by
        some concept<char style="sup">[b]</char> evangelized to you if you keep a tight grip <char style="it">on
        what you received</char>, unless of course you weren’t serious when you <char style="it">made the decision
        </char>to believe (i.e., you frivolously, heedlessly, inconsiderately, without purpose, without just
        cause, without careful thought, without due consideration, or haphazardly made the decision).<verse eid="1CO 15:2" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 15:3" />You see, I gave the highest priority to putting into you what I too received, <char style="it">namely
        </char>that Christ died on behalf of us sinners according to the Scriptures, <verse eid="1CO 15:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 15:4" />that he was buried, that he rose on the Third Day, <verse eid="1CO 15:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 15:5" />and that he was seen by Peter<char style="sup">[c]</char>, and then after that by the twelve <char style="it">disciples</char>.<verse eid="1CO 15:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 15:6" />After that he was seen by over five-hundred people at the same time, the majority of whom have stayed
        alive until now, but some of them have passed away<char style="sup">[d]</char>. <verse eid="1CO 15:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 15:7" />After that, he was seen by James and then by all of the apostles. <verse eid="1CO 15:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 15:8" />Last of all he was seen by me too, the bastard-stepchild<char style="sup">[e]</char> sort of.<verse eid="1CO 15:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 15:9" />You see, I am the most insignificant of the apostles, one who is not worthy enough to be called an apostle
        because I persecuted God’s church. <verse eid="1CO 15:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 15:10" />By the grace of God I am what I am, but His grace wasn’t wasted on me; instead I worked harder than all
        of them, not me personally but rather the grace of God in conjunction with me. <verse eid="1CO 15:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 15:11" />So whether I’m <char style="it">the one doing the preaching </char>or those <char style="it">other</char>
        <char style="it">apostles are the ones doing it</char>, we preach this same message in the same fashion,
        and you believed this same message in the same fashion<char style="sup">[f]</char>.<verse eid="1CO 15:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 15:12" />Now if <char style="it">the belief that</char> Christ was raised from the dead is being preached, how
        is it that certain individuals among you claim that there is no resurrection from the dead<char style="sup">[g]</char>
        (i.e., once a person dies, his total existence ceases; there is no life after death, nor can a person
        return from the dead since the moment he dies he ceases to exist)? <verse eid="1CO 15:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 15:13" />If there’s no resurrection from the dead, not even Christ has been raised from the dead. <verse eid="1CO 15:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 15:14" />If Christ hasn’t been raised, then our preaching <char style="it">of Christ </char>is a waste of time
        and your faith is a waste of time— <verse eid="1CO 15:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 15:15" />And it’ll be obvious to everyone that we lie under oath, since we swore by God under oath that He raised
        Christ—whom He didn’t raise—<char style="it">from the dead</char>, since the dead <char style="it">supposedly
        </char>aren’t raised. <verse eid="1CO 15:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 15:16" />You see, if the dead aren’t raised, not even Christ has been raised. <verse eid="1CO 15:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 15:17" />But if Christ hasn’t been raised, your faith is pointless; you are still <char style="it">trapped </char>in
        your sins— <verse eid="1CO 15:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 15:18" />and those who’ve passed away in Christ have perished too. <verse eid="1CO 15:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 15:19" />If we who in this life have hoped in Christ have been stranded<char style="sup">[h]</char>, we are the
        most pathetic people of all.<verse eid="1CO 15:19" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 15:20" />But it turns out that Christ has been raised from the dead, a premier<char style="sup">[i]</char> of
        those who’ve passed away. <verse eid="1CO 15:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 15:21" />You see, since death <char style="it">came </char>through a <char style="it">single, specific </char>person,
        resurrection from the dead (i.e., hope of existing after death; life after death; blissful existence
        in the afterlife) also <char style="it">came</char> through a <char style="it">single, specific </char>person.<verse eid="1CO 15:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 15:22" />To this point, just as everyone died (i.e., died spiritually: underwent a stagnation of waste, joylessness,
        futility, and destruction; eventually died physically) by means of Adam, likewise everyone in Christ
        shall be made alive by means of Christ too. <verse eid="1CO 15:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 15:23" />But <char style="it">the resurrection will occur </char>by each person’s ranking: Christ <char style="it">the
        </char>premier <char style="it">first</char>, then <char style="it">after him </char>those who are affiliated
        with Christ <char style="it">will be resurrected </char>at his coming, <verse eid="1CO 15:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 15:24" />then comes the End, when the kingdom of God the Father<char style="sup">[j]</char> will be transferred
        into <char style="it">his</char> hands, entrusted <char style="it">to him</char> for <char style="it">him
        </char>to do as <char style="it">he </char>wills, when He’ll abolish every ruler, every authority, and
        every power<char style="sup">[A]</char>; <verse eid="1CO 15:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 15:25" />you see, it’s absolutely necessary<char style="sup">[k]</char> that he reign and reign until such a time
        that all of his enemies be put under his feet (i.e., all his enemies be subjected to him: totally subdued
        and under his absolute control). <verse eid="1CO 15:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 15:26" />Death will be the last enemy to be destroyed; <verse eid="1CO 15:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 15:27" />you see, <char style="it">it’s written, </char>“He put all things under his feet.” When the circumstances
        arise in which He happens to say “all things have been subjected<char style="sup">[l]</char>,” it goes
        without saying that the Father’s not included in the “all things.” <verse eid="1CO 15:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 15:28" />But when those circumstances arise when He subjects all things to him, then in addition the son himself
        will be subjected to the One Who subjected all things to him, so that God would become every little piece
        of everything<char style="sup">[m]</char>.<verse eid="1CO 15:28" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 15:29" />But if all this is not the case, what are they going to do, they who are getting themselves baptized
        as a symbol of their resurrection from the dead<char style="sup">[B]</char>? If the dead are definitely
        not resurrected, why are they being baptized as a symbol of them not being dead? <verse eid="1CO 15:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 15:30" />Why do we take risks <char style="it">with our lives </char>every moment? <verse eid="1CO 15:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 15:31" />Day after day I die by the lofty oath sworn to look after you, comrades, which I keep in Christ Jesus
        our Lord.<char style="sup">[n]</char> <verse eid="1CO 15:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CO 15:32" />That I had my back against the wall and was fighting for my life<char style="sup">[o]</char> in Ephesus,
        what’s the point of doing it all if the dead aren’t resurrected. <char style="it">Wouldn’t we be better
        off doing what Isaiah said?—</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:32"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:32">Let us eat and drink<char style="sup">[p]</char> <char style="it">and live it up,</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:32">For tomorrow we shall die<verse eid="1CO 15:32"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CO 15:33" />Don’t be fooled <char style="it">into believing that; realize this instead</char>:
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:33"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:33">The wrong crowd corrupts good conduct<verse eid="1CO 15:33"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CO 15:34" />Snap out of it and don’t continue in sin. In fact, some <char style="it">of you </char>don’t have a knowing,
        recognition, or understanding of God. Shame on you<char style="sup">[q]</char>.<verse eid="1CO 15:34" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CO 15:35" />Moving on though, someone’s bound to say<char style="sup">[r]</char>, “How will the dead be resurrected
        (i.e., how’s it possible for a dead person to obtain a new body)?” What kind of body will they get <char
        style="it">in the afterlife</char>? <verse eid="1CO 15:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CO 15:36" /><char style="it">How</char> brainless you <char style="it">are</char>! What someone sows doesn’t spring
        to life unless it happens to die, <verse eid="1CO 15:36" />
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CO 15:37" />and what one sows isn’t the body (i.e., the same biological form) of what it will become. No—you sow
        a bare seed…perhaps it’s wheat…perhaps it’s some other <char style="it">grain</char>… <verse eid="1CO 15:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CO 15:38" />But God gives it a body (i.e., a plant form) the way He wanted and <char style="it">gives </char>a unique,
        peculiar body to each type of seed sown. <verse eid="1CO 15:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CO 15:39" />Not all flesh (i.e., cell and tissue composition) is the same flesh (i.e., consists of the same kind
        of tissues, skeleton, muscle, skin, etc.). No—there’s one <char style="it">type of flesh </char>which
        corresponds to humans, another <char style="it">type of</char> flesh which corresponds to farm animals,
        another <char style="it">type of</char> flesh to birds, another <char style="it">type of</char> flesh
        to fish. <verse eid="1CO 15:39" />
      <verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CO 15:40" /><char style="it">There are </char>bodies (i.e., unique physical entities) in outer-space<char style="sup">[s]</char>
        and bodies on Earth, but no,<char style="it"> they’re not the same</char>: there’s one <char style="it">type
        of</char> glory (i.e., wonder, splendor, awe, something spectacular) <char style="it">for the entities</char>
        in space vs. another <char style="it">type of glory for the entities</char> on Earth; <verse eid="1CO 15:40" />
      <verse number="41" style="v" sid="1CO 15:41" />the uniqueness of glory that the sun has is a different glory than the type that the moon has, and there’s
        a different, unique type for the stars <char style="it">too</char>: in fact one star differs in its glory
        from that of another star.<verse eid="1CO 15:41" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="42" style="v" sid="1CO 15:42" />The resurrection from the dead works the same way. <char style="it">The body which is</char> sown is
        a mortal, decaying <char style="it">body </char>tainted with moral corruption; it’s resurrected an immortal,
        non-decayable <char style="it">body </char>untainted by moral corruption. <verse eid="1CO 15:42" />
      <verse number="43" style="v" sid="1CO 15:43" />It’s sown in dishonor, it’s resurrected in glory; sown in weakness, raised in power; <verse eid="1CO 15:43" />
      <verse number="44" style="v" sid="1CO 15:44" />sown a soul-body (i.e., a body having all the quintessential human elements: one that has a thirst for
        the things of this life, that thinks and feels as humans do, has human frailties), raised a spiritual-body.
        If it is a soul-body, it is also a spiritual-body: <verse eid="1CO 15:44" />
      <verse number="45" style="v" sid="1CO 15:45" />this is also the way it’s written <char style="it">in the Old Testament</char>,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:45"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:45">The first man Adam became<char style="sup">[t]</char> a living-soul</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:45"></para>
    <para style="m" vid="1CO 15:45">…The Last Adam <char style="it">became</char> a sprung-to-life-spirit. <verse eid="1CO 15:45"/>
      <verse number="46" style="v" sid="1CO 15:46" />No, the first <char style="it">Adam </char>wasn’t the spiritual-<char style="it">body prototype-man</char>
        rather the soul-<char style="it">body prototype-man</char>, then <char style="it">came </char>the spiritual<char
        style="it">-body prototype-man</char>. <verse eid="1CO 15:46" />
      <verse number="47" style="v" sid="1CO 15:47" />The first man <char style="it">came </char>out of the <char style="it">earth’s</char> dirt<char style="it">,
        </char>the second man <char style="it">came </char>out of the spiritual world<char style="sup">[u]</char>.<verse eid="1CO 15:47" />
      <verse number="48" style="v" sid="1CO 15:48" />As the dirt is, so too are the dirt<char style="it">-creations</char>; as the spiritual world is, so
        too are the spiritual<char style="it">-creations</char>. <verse eid="1CO 15:48" />
      <verse number="49" style="v" sid="1CO 15:49" />And just as we bore the image of the dirt, let us bear the image of the spiritual as well.<verse eid="1CO 15:49" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="50" style="v" sid="1CO 15:50" />I’ll say this, comrades, that flesh and blood<char style="sup">[v]</char> (i.e., the best that human
        ability can muster) cannot inherit the kingdom of God (i.e., cannot put you in a place where you have
        a relationship with God; where God works in and through your life); neither does decayable mortality
        tainted with moral corruption inherit non-decayable immortality untainted by moral corruption.<verse eid="1CO 15:50" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="51" style="v" sid="1CO 15:51" />Hey—I’ll tell you a mystery: we all shall not sleep (i.e., stay dead forever), but we all shall be changed<verse eid="1CO 15:51" />
      <verse number="52" style="v" sid="1CO 15:52" />in a split-second, in the time it takes to blink an eye, at the last bugle call: the bugle shall sound
        off, and the dead will be raised <char style="it">and become </char>non-decayable immortals untainted
        by moral corruption. <char style="it">Yes, </char>we ourselves shall be changed. <verse eid="1CO 15:52" />
      <verse number="53" style="v" sid="1CO 15:53" />You see, this decayable mortality must put on non-decayable immortality, and this mortal nature must
        put on an immortal nature. <verse eid="1CO 15:53" />
      <verse number="54" style="v" sid="1CO 15:54" />When this decayable mortality shall have put on non-decayable immortality, and this mortal nature shall
        have put on an immortal nature, then the verses will come to pass which say,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:54"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:54">Death is engulfed by victory.<verse eid="1CO 15:54"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="55" style="v" sid="1CO 15:55" />Death, where is your victory?
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="1CO 15:55">Death, where is your sting<char style="sup">[w]</char>?<verse eid="1CO 15:55"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="56" style="v" sid="1CO 15:56" />The sting of death is sin, and the power of sin is the Law (i.e., the Law of Moses; the set of commandments
        given by God)— <verse eid="1CO 15:56" />
      <verse number="57" style="v" sid="1CO 15:57" />But thank-you God, Who gives us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.<verse eid="1CO 15:57" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="58" style="v" sid="1CO 15:58" />So then, my dear comrades, get to where you’re<char style="sup">[x]</char> unshakeable, un-moveable,
        and un-perturbable, abounding and proliferating in the Lord’s work at all times, knowing for certain
        that your work in the Lord is not for nothing, is not going to waste.<verse eid="1CO 15:58" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">some concept</char>…Lit: <char style="it">some word; a certain concept</char>. Ref.
        note of John 1:1.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Peter</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Cephas</char>. Ref. note of 1:12.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">passed away</char>…Lit: <char style="it">slept</char>. Ref. 7:39.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the bastard-stepchild</char>…Lit: <char style="it">an untimely birth</char>; <char style="it">an
        abortion</char>. Some liberties taken, as Paul is speaking figuratively here.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">we preach this same message in the same fashion, and you believed this same message
        in the same fashion</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in this way we preach and in this way you believed</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">resurrection from the dead</char>…In other places translated “life after death.” Ref.
        notes of Mark 12:18, Luke 10:25 and other places.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">have been stranded</char>…Lit: <char style="it">are alone</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a premier</char>…Lit: <char style="it">a first fruit</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">God the Father</char>…Lit: <char style="it">God and Father</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">it’s absolutely necessary</char>…Lit: <char style="it">it must</char> [<char style="it">be</char>].
        A figure of speech.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">all things have been subjected</char>…This is a paraphrase of the prior quotation, “all
        things have been put under his feet.”</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[m]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[m]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">every little piece of everything</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the all in all</char>.
        Ref. 1 Cor. 12:6.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[n]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[n]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Day after day I die by the lofty oath sworn to look over you, comrades, which I keep
        in Christ Jesus our Lord</char>…Lit<char style="it">: Day after day I die swear by your boasting, comrades,
        which I have in Christ Jesus our Lord</char>. I’m guessing this is what Paul meant here.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[o]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[o]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">had my back against the wall and was fighting for my life</char>…Lit: <char style="it">according
        to man fought the wild beasts</char>. An idiom. It appears that Paul added <char style="it">according
        to man </char>[<char style="it">from a human perspective</char>] to indicate that he’s applying an idiom
        to a human experience and that one should not take his words literally. Ref. note of Mark 1:13.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[p]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[p]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">eat and drink</char>…A NT expression; in addition to the obvious—eating and drinking—it
        means to celebrate, party, feast.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[q]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[q]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Shame on you</char>…Lit: <char style="it">I speak to your shame</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[r]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[r]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">someone’s bound to say</char>…Lit: <char style="it">someone will say</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[s]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[s]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">outer-space</char>…Lit: <char style="it">upon-sky</char>. Ref. note of 1 Pet. 1:4.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[t]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[t]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">became</char>…Lit: <char style="it">became unto</char>. Seems to indicate something
        he arrived at.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[u]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[u]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the spiritual world</char>…Lit: <char style="it">heaven</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[v]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[v]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">flesh and blood</char>…A NT idiom</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[w]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[w]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">sting</char>…Also: <char style="it">prod</char> [<char style="it">a pointed stick used
        like a whip</char>]. Same word used in Acts 26:14 for <char style="it">goad. </char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[x]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[x]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">get to where you’re</char>…Lit: <char style="it">become</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">every ruler, every authority, and every power</char>…An explanation of the Gk. words
        for positions of authority and the like. The first three correspond to what’s quoted here:</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Ruler [archōn, <char style="w" strong="G00758">ἄρχων</char>)]—When referring to people, the very top
        of a hierarchy; the one who has the ultimate power over the entire hierarchy. It refers to a person or
        the people who are at the top of the pyramid, whatever that pyramid may be. It’s translated <char style="it">principalities
        </char>in Eph. 6:12 (KJV), and in that case does not refer to people but refers to demons, demons who
        are at the top of some demonic hierarchy. When referring to time, it’s the very start or beginning of
        an epoch of time, sometimes spoken of abstractly when the start of time isn’t known (John 1:1). The KJV
        translates this as <char style="it">prince </char>instead of the NASB’s <char style="it">ruler </char>in
        places such as John 16:11, etc. See below for more on <char style="it">prince</char>.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Authority [eksousia, <char style="w" strong="G01849">ἐξουσία</char>)]—The literal meaning is <char style="it">existing
        out of. </char>Power which is given to a person to act on behalf of a hierarchy, government, etc. which
        has the ultimate power. Also, one who’s given the legitimate right to exercise power. Also, the power
        itself, with the understanding that it was granted in such a way and not simply usurped; the position,
        the seat itself.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Power [dunamis, <char style="w" strong="G01411">δύναμις</char>)]—The natural, inherent capability to
        exercise control over others. The ability may or may not be legitimate or have been granted by the government
        or hierarchy. The word <char style="it">power </char>simply states the capability to exercise power,
        but does not specify where this ability comes from, whether the power is transferrable, or what the nature
        of it is; whereas the word <char style="it">authority</char>, while in certain contexts simply refers
        to power, is, in its essence, power which is derived from the main body; power delegated; legitimate
        power; non-usurped power. Therefore, dunamis may refer to usurped power or illegitimate power.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Leader [haegemon, <char style="w" strong="G02232">ἡγεμών</char>)]—This has two similar meanings. First
        is the Latin <char style="it">dux</char>: it’s the one who’s the leader; who takes charge and leads the
        way for others to follow; the commander, the one who not only makes the decisions everyone follows but
        is responsible for those decisions, whom everyone relies on to ensure that the decisions are intelligently
        made. The second is the Latin <char style="it">princeps</char>: the one who does a thing first. The princeps
        is the person who’s the most eminent, most distinguished, the first person; the leading citizen of the
        country; the person who’s the best at something and therefore has taken the lead; the person everyone
        relies on the most to lead the way when facing difficulties. In modern terms, the captain of a sports
        team is a princeps: the best player, and as the best takes the initiative the most, and as a result of
        taking the initiative, he’s the one who leads and drives the others to victory.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Dominion [kuriotās, <char style="w" strong="G02963">κυριότης</char>)]—The literal meaning is <char style="it">the
        nature of lordship</char>. It is “the majestic power that a lord wields, ruling power, lordship, dominion”
        (Danker &amp; Bauer). The nature of lordship is the assumption that the expected order of things is for
        there to be a lord and that this lord will rule over others, and that there are guidelines by which this
        is done, either codified in law or in an unspoken understanding. As this word is derived from <char style="it">lord</char>,
        it follows that it refers to the powers a lord has and the way that he obtained them. Unlike the word
        <char style="it">authority, </char>a lord is not a ruler who derives his power from the government, but
        rather is like the owner of a large private estate, say, somewhere out in a remote rural area. In a feudal
        system this would include a dukedom or earldom, but a lordship can be much smaller also. Those who live
        in remote, rural areas are in many respects autonomous from the rest of society, including the government.
        While the lord rules like an authority (eksousia), his sphere of power doesn’t fall under the authority
        to another, so within his sphere he’s not answerable to anyone else. As expected, this also refers to
        a lordship seat which is transferrable, like from father to son, etc.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Throne[(thronos, <char style="w" strong="G02362">θρόνος</char>)]—A ruler whose powers extend to sitting
        on a judgment seat: arbitrating disputes, acting as a judge in a civil or criminal proceeding; receiving
        emissaries; forming policy, including do so with the advice of a counsel. The throne is not an ad-hoc
        judgment seat, but is a persistent seat, passed from person to person. As is apparent, there’s overlap
        in these terms for rulers.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Pastor/shepherd [poimān, <char style="w" strong="G04166">ποιμήν</char>)]—(Ref. note of 1 Pet. 5:2). This
        Old Testament word means <char style="it">leader</char>, but the implication is that this person is leading
        ordinary people (sheep) and not soldiers under his chain of command. The sheep-analogy means that such
        a leader will have to deal with problems that are eradicated in an army due to the discipline instilled
        into that army. The problems Moses had to deal with when leading Israel in the wilderness are analogous
        to a shepherd over sheep. Since poimān has its roots in the Old Testament, the word is only used in conjunction
        with ecclesiastical leadership.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">To come forward as a leader [proistāmi,<char style="w" strong="G04291">προΐστημι</char>)]—This appears
        in the NT as a verb but is also used substantively as a noun. It literally means <char style="it">to
        stand forward</char>, and appears in Rom. 12:8; 1 Thess. 5:12; 1 Tim. 5:17. Danker &amp; Bauer defines
        it first, “to exercise a position of leadership, rule direct, be at the head of,” and second, “to have
        an interest in, show concern for, care for, give aid.” There are only three occurrences in the NT and
        all are in relation to church leadership. </char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Steward [oikonomos, <char style="w" strong="G03623">οἰκονόμος</char>)]—Someone whom a lord (the ruler
        of a sizeable estate) puts in charge of the affairs of the estate. Luke 12:42; 16:1; Titus 1:7 are examples.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Overseer, bishop [episkopos, <char style="w" strong="G01985">ἐπίσκοπος</char>)]—The Gk. word means “one
        who visits,” more specifically, “one who checks up on things to ensure that things are in order”; hence
        the NASB rendering <char style="it">episkopos</char> as <char style="it">overseer</char>. What we nowadays
        call a “head pastor.” Someone who’s the single individual who’s the head over a congregation. This position
        didn’t exist in the early days of the church, as the early church was ruled by elder councils, probably
        imitating the way that synagogues were ruled by elders. Apparently, as Christianity diverged more and
        more from Judaism, the forms of church government diverged as well, with churches replacing elder councils
        with bishops. </char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Deacon [diakonos, <char style="w" strong="G01249">διάκονος</char>)]—A deacon is a leader (a poiman) in
        the church who has oversight over a specific area in the church, but does not have total oversight like
        a bishop does. Deacons existed in both elder-ruled and bishop-ruled churches. Nowadays, we call a deacon
        an associate pastor or a ministry director. A deacon is similar to a steward (see how these two words
        are used together in Col 1:25) but applied to a church context, as the word’s used in the NT. Deacon
        appears in Rom. 12:7; 1 Cor. 16:15; Eph. 6:21; 1 Tim 3:10.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">Slave or servant [doulos, <char style="w" strong="G01401">δοῦλος</char>)]—This word is translated either
        servant or slave. As slavery was pervasive in the ancient world, most of the times a <char style="it">doulos</char>
        is a slave, but since the slavery-mindset is absent from us in modern times, we must make distinctions
        in this word. This word means a servant, a menial servant, one who takes orders and is not entrusted
        with any significant responsibilities. This word means a slave, someone who’s owned by another person;
        someone who’s locked into this position; forced servitude. Doulos as appears in the NT can refer to one
        or multiple of these definitions, and the most appropriate rendering is dictated by context. In the NT,
        a doulos can be a menial servant without specifically or explicitly referring to someone who’s locked
        into slavery, i.e. owned by another person. In this respect, a person who’s “locked into” a nine-to-five
        job is a doulos of a sort, even though he’s not a bona fide slave.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">they who are getting themselves baptized as a symbol of their resurrection from the
        dead</char>…Lit: <char style="it">being baptized </char>[<char style="it">or getting themselves baptized]
        on behalf of the dead</char>. Translators and commentators are puzzled at the meaning of this. Some guess-work
        is required. A good explanation from one of the commentators is that an interpolation was intended, one
        which changes <char style="it">the dead </char>to <char style="it">the resurrection of the dead. </char>Also,
        the prepositional phrase usually translated <char style="it">on behalf of </char>has been bent from its
        traditional meaning to mean something that symbolizes something else. Also, the verb <char style="it">to
        baptize </char>seems to acquire some middle voice usage, but that’s speculative. Those who disagree with
        these explanations—and there are several good reasons to do so—are welcome to explain how their interpretation
        makes better sense.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="1CO 15" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 16   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="1CO 16" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 16:1" />Concerning the matter of taking up a collection for the poor<char style="it"> and sending it </char>to
        God’s people<char style="sup">[a]</char> <char style="it">in Jerusalem</char>, do the same thing that
        I commanded the churches in Galatia to do: <verse eid="1CO 16:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 16:2" />Let each of you in private stash away <char style="it">a bit of your money</char> every Sunday<char style="sup">[b]</char>—whatever
        you can afford—so that when I come, there won’t be any collection-taking going on then. <verse eid="1CO 16:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 16:3" />When I make it over to your place, whomever you happen to decide upon to write letters of recommendation
        for, I’ll dispatch as couriers to take your gift to Jerusalem. <verse eid="1CO 16:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 16:4" />If there happens to be <char style="it">an issue of </char>respect<char style="sup">[A]</char>, they’ll
        come with me <char style="it">when I depart</char>.<verse eid="1CO 16:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 16:5" />I’ll come your way when I pass through Macedonia; I’ll be passing through Macedonia, you see. <verse eid="1CO 16:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 16:6" />Perhaps I’ll stay with you <char style="it">a while </char>or even spend the winter, so that you’ll send
        me on my way <char style="it">refreshed and prepared for the journey</char><char style="sup">[B]</char>
        wherever I happen to go; <verse eid="1CO 16:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 16:7" />you see, at the moment I don’t want to <char style="it">just </char>stop by for a short visit while passing
        through the area; you see, I hope to stay a while with you, if the Lord permits. <verse eid="1CO 16:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 16:8" />I’ll stay in Ephesus until Pentecost (i.e., until late May to early June). <verse eid="1CO 16:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 16:9" />In fact, a great door (i.e., a tremendous opportunity) has been opened for me and it looks promising,
        but <char style="it">I’ll have to face</char> many adversaries.<verse eid="1CO 16:9" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 16:10" />If Timothy happens to show up, see to it that he doesn’t get to where he’s intimidated by you<char style="sup">[c]</char>;
        he’s doing the Lord’s work like I’m doing, you see, <verse eid="1CO 16:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 16:11" />so don’t let anyone treat him disrespectfully or despise him. Send him forth to his next destination
        in peace (i.e., take care of him, treat him well, and send him out prepared for the journey), so that
        he manages to come to me, for I expect him with the <char style="it">group of </char>comrades<char style="sup">[d]</char>
        <char style="it">who’ll be coming</char>.<verse eid="1CO 16:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 16:12" />Concerning Comrade Apollos…I’ve encouraged him an awful lot to pay you a visit, doing so by travelling
        with the comrades <char style="it">who’ll be coming</char>, and it wasn’t his desire altogether to go
        at this time, but he’ll go in good time.<verse eid="1CO 16:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 16:13" />Stay focused<char style="sup">[e]</char>, take a firm stand in the faith, man up, seize control and hold
        on tightly. <verse eid="1CO 16:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 16:14" />Let everything you do manifest itself in love.<verse eid="1CO 16:14" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 16:15" />I appeal to you, comrades…you know first-hand Stephanas’s household, since they’re the crème de la crème
        <char style="it">of the</char> <char style="it">converts</char><char style="sup">[f]</char> of Achaia
        and have been put in positions of deacons for God’s people, the saints…<verse eid="1CO 16:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 16:16" /><char style="it">I appeal to you</char> that you too would submit to such <char style="it">fine individuals
        </char>as these and to all the fellow-workers and laborers. <verse eid="1CO 16:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 16:17" />I’m so glad that Stephanas, Fortunatus, and Achaicus showed up, that these fellows filled in the pieces
        that you’re missing<char style="sup">[g]</char>: <verse eid="1CO 16:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 16:18" />they gave rest to my spirit and to yours, so recognize <char style="it">the character and contribution
        of</char> men such as these.<verse eid="1CO 16:18" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 16:19" />The churches in <char style="it">the Roman province of </char>Asia send their greetings to you. Aquila
        and Priscilla send many greetings to you in the Lord and are joined in their greetings with the group
        of Christians who meet in their house. <verse eid="1CO 16:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 16:20" />All the comrades greet you. Give each other a hearty handshake and an affectionate hug—holy ones—<char
        style="it">for me.</char><char style="sup">[h]</char><verse eid="1CO 16:20" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 16:21" />The greeting <char style="it">written here </char>is in my own handwriting, that of Paul’s. <verse eid="1CO 16:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 16:22" />If anyone doesn’t like the Lord a lot<char style="sup">[i]</char>, let him be accursed. Maranatha (Do
        come Lord).<verse eid="1CO 16:22" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 16:23" />The grace of the Lord Jesus <char style="it">be </char>with you all. <verse eid="1CO 16:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 16:24" /><char style="it">May </char>my love <char style="it">be</char> with all of you in Christ Jesus.<verse eid="1CO 16:24" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">God’s people</char>…Lit: <char style="it">saints</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Sunday</char>…Lit: <char style="it">first of the Sabbath</char>. As they didn’t have
        names for the days of the weeks, they referred to each day by how many days past the Sabbath it is.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">doesn’t get to where he’s intimidated by you</char>…Lit: <char style="it">will be fearless
        towards you</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">stay focused</char>…Lit: <char style="it">watch</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">crème de la crème of the converts</char>…Lit: <char style="it">a first-fruit</char>.
        Ref. note of Rom. 8:23.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">filled in the pieces that you’re missing</char>…Lit: <char style="it">filled up your
        lack</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Give each other a hearty handshake and an affectionate hug—holy ones—for me</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">Greet each with a holy kiss</char>. Liberties taken.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">like the Lord a lot</char>…Lit: <char style="it">love</char> [<char style="it">phileo</char>]
        <char style="it">the Lord</char>. Note the Gk. word <char style="it">phileō </char><char style="w" strong="G05368">φιλέω</char>)
        is used and not <char style="it">agapaō </char><char style="w" strong="G00025">ἀγαπάω</char>)<char style="it">.
        </char>Ref. note of Matt. 10:37.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">an issue of respect</char> …Lit: <char style="it">worthy</char>. Same word used similarly
        in Rom. 16:2. Guessing that Paul was referring to the respect the Jewish believers in Jerusalem would
        give to Gentile couriers—although this is very much a guess on my part.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">send me on my way</char> <char style="it">refreshed and prepared for the journey</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">send me forth</char>. Based on the usage in the NT of the Gk. word for <char style="it">forth-send
        </char>(Acts. 15:3, 20:38, 21:5; Rom. 15:24; 1 Cor. 16:11; 2 Cor. 1:16; Titus 3:13; 3 John 1:6), the
        word appears to have an meaning beyond what its roots suggest of simply sending someone forth. Additionally,
        it appears to mean, “sending someone on a journey prepared for that journey; sending someone away one
        good terms after they’ve spent a long with you; sending someone away with sorrow at seeing them go, with
        gladness of the work they’ll do; sending someone out to accomplish a mission; sending someone with your
        support and blessings; recommending a person sent to the next party which will receive him.”</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="1CO 16" />
</usx>
