<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- The Bernmeister's New Testament, Unabridged Edition -->
<!-- Copyright © 2024 Bernard M. Woodland -->
<!-- Version 1 -->
<!-- Public domain -->
<!-- The Bernmeister's NT, Unabridged Version 1 -->
<usx version="3.0">
  <!--   *******************   -->
  <!--   Titles and TOC Info   -->
  <!--   *******************   -->
  <book code="2CO" style="id">The Bernmeister's NT, Unabridged</book>
  <para style="h">2 Corinthians</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Epistle of 2 Corinthians</para>
  <para style="toc2">2 Corinthians</para>
  <para style="toc3">2 Cor.</para>
  <para style="mt2">THE EPISTLE OF</para>
  <para style="mt1">2 CORINTHIANS</para>
  <!--   ************   -->
  <!--   Introduction   -->
  <!--   ************   -->
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="ipi">If it wasn’t enough that Paul wrote his longest epistle (slightly longer than Romans by verse count),
    he writes a second—and not a short one either. How did the Corinthians merit two lengthy epistles, whereas
    the Ephesians or Philippians did not?</para>
  <para style="ipi">And based on what Paul wrote in the first letter, does the second show any signs that the Corinthians
    improved? Is the second epistle a part II of the first? No, the tone that the letter begins in is completely
    different, as Paul repeatedly uses words like suffering, tribulation, and consolation in the first chapter.
    The second chapter finds Paul expressing sorrow; the sting from the first letter is apparent. Is the
    sting mutual, as the second epistles describes the anguish, sorrow, and even tears Paul underwent as
    he penned the first? But the end of the book is telling: Paul says “the more I love you, the less I’m
    loved” (12:15).</para>
  <para style="ipi">Of all the churches Paul founded, the Corinthian was not the most spiritual, but as it is true of a parent
    of several children whose favorite child is not the one who’s the best behaved, so it is with Paul and
    the Corinthians, as the volume he wrote to this church, the extremes of emotion, surpass the other churches.</para>
  <para style="ipi">In the first epistle to the Corinthians, Paul gives a hint here, a detail there, of the difficulties
    he faces. But in this second epistle, as Paul progresses through the letter, his allusions become sentences,
    then the sentences become paragraphs. This culminates in the twelfth chapter as he talks about his “thorn
    in the flesh”—an oft misinterpreted passage.</para>
  <para style="ipi">The Greek text is from one who has full command of the language, unlike the Gospels or like John’s writing.
    The writer was educated, the recipients were as well. Many times a more uncommon word was chosen when
    a simple word would have sufficed. But there is none of the awkwardness one finds, for example, in James
    or in the Gospels. The writing is fluid, howbeit with words and phrases omitted for brevity, like one
    does when texting on a phone. This is one of the more challenging NT books translate, ranking alongside
    Jude, but that also makes it one of the most satisfying.</para>
  <para style="ib"></para>
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  1   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="2CO 1" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 1:1" />Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus by God’s will, and <char style="it">his fellow </char>comrade<char style="sup">[a]</char>
        Timothy—</para>
    <para style="p" vid="2CO 1:1">To the church of God that is in Corinth, joined by the saints (i.e., God’s people) who are all over Achaia:<verse eid="2CO 1:1"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 1:2" />Grace and peace to you from God our Father and <char style="it">the </char>Lord Jesus Christ.<verse eid="2CO 1:2" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 1:3" /><char style="it">Give </char>praise <char style="it">to the </char>God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ,
        the Originator<char style="sup">[b]</char> of all sorts of<char style="sup">[c]</char> compassion and
        of advice, encouragement, and consolation, <verse eid="2CO 1:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 1:4" />which consoles, etc. us in all of our distresses<char style="sup">[d]</char>, resulting in our ability
        to console those in all kinds of distresses<char style="it"> </char>with the same consolation with which
        we’re being consoled by God. <verse eid="2CO 1:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 1:5" />Just as Christ’s sufferings proliferate to us, in the same way through Christ the consolation we <char
        style="it">receive</char> proliferates as well. <verse eid="2CO 1:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 1:6" />Whether we’re being pressured, <char style="it">it’s </char>for the sake of your consolation and salvation
        (i.e., your being rescued from spiritual, moral, mental, and physical calamity); whether we’re being
        consoled, <char style="it">it’s </char>for the sake of your consolation, a consolation which is accomplished
        by enduring the same sufferings which we too suffer. <verse eid="2CO 1:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 1:7" />And the hope which we have for you—our hope <char style="it">is </char>firm, fixed in the observation
        that as you are joint participants of the sufferings <char style="it">which we suffer</char>, in the
        same way <char style="it">you are joint participants </char>of the consolation as well.<verse eid="2CO 1:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 1:8" />In this regard, we don’t want you to be left in the dark, comrades, about the extreme difficulties we
        experienced in <char style="it">the Roman province of </char>Asia, that we were overloaded and overwhelmed
        to the point that we lost the will to live. <verse eid="2CO 1:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 1:9" />Anyways, <char style="it">deep </char>inside ourselves we concluded that we were doomed to die<char style="sup">[e]</char>,
        so we reached the point where we couldn’t be convinced that our own abilities <char style="it">would
        save us</char>, but <char style="it">were convinced</char> that the God who raises the dead <char style="it">would
        do so </char>instead: <verse eid="2CO 1:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 1:10" />He Who rescued us from a narrow brush with death<char style="sup">[f]</char>—and rescues us <char style="it">continuously</char>—we
        set our hope in Him that He’ll rescue <char style="it">us </char>yet again, <verse eid="2CO 1:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 1:11" />while you too were joining in lending a helping hand by the prayers that you prayed for us, so that the
        outcome of the stances, disposition, and full attention of many people<char style="sup">[g]</char> is
        that the mercy and kindness shown to us would be thanked by many on our behalf.<verse eid="2CO 1:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 1:12" />You see, our proud talk and bold claims<char style="sup">[h]</char> are on par with the solemn declaration
        of our conscience, since the lifestyle we led in the world (i.e., among those who aren’t believers) was
        by God’s simplicity and sincerity, not by the wisdom of flesh (i.e., by the cunning shrewdness of our
        own ability apart from God tainted by the carnal nature) but by God’s grace instead—<char style="it">and
        that lifestyle was </char>all the more <char style="it">so </char>with you. <verse eid="2CO 1:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 1:13" />In fact we’re writing to you nothing other than what you’re reading <char style="it">to the congregation
        </char>or what you’re coming to understand, but I hope that you continue to gain an exact understanding
        until it’s all said and done<char style="sup">[i]</char>, <verse eid="2CO 1:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 1:14" />just as you also gained an understanding of us, at least<char style="it"> </char>partially, that we are
        <char style="it">the reason for </char>your proud talk and bold claims just as you too <char style="it">will
        be </char>ours in the Day of the Lord Jesus (i.e., when he’s revealed in the fullness of his might).<verse eid="2CO 1:14" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 1:15" />We formed a long-term desire for this, for what we’ve reached the point where we’re convinced is<char
        style="it"> </char>the thing that we want to do more than anything else, <char style="it">namely </char>to
        go visit you, so that you would get a second grace (i.e., a second impartation of our face-to-face ministry),<verse eid="2CO 1:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 1:16" />and to continue on our journey through your <char style="it">city</char> to Macedonia, to <char style="it">resume
        </char>the journey going from Macedonia <char style="it">back </char>to your <char style="it">city</char>
        again, and to be sent forth by you (i.e., depart fully rested, provisioned, and in good spirits—all on
        account of the your generosity and hospitality) to the Jews in Judea.<verse eid="2CO 1:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 1:17" />So then, was this plan treated with a nonchalant thought-process? Or what I’m planning, I’m planning
        according to flesh (i.e., from my own self apart from God, according to my own needs, and somewhat tainted
        to feed my carnal appetite), so that it would be “the yes-yes and the no-no” with me (i.e., I’d vacillate
        or renege on what I planned or promised to do)? <verse eid="2CO 1:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CO 1:18" />But—by God—trust me<char style="sup">[j]</char> that the statements we made to you aren’t “<char style="it">the
        yes</char>-yes and <char style="it">the no</char>-no.” <verse eid="2CO 1:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CO 1:19" />To this point, God’s son Jesus Christ, who through us has been preached among you—through me, Siloam,
        and Timothy—hasn’t wound up being “<char style="it">the yes</char>-yes and <char style="it">the no</char>-no,”
        but rather has wound up being “yes” in him. <verse eid="2CO 1:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CO 1:20" />For as many promises as there are from God, in him they are <char style="it">all</char> “yes” (i.e.,
        no vacillating or reneging on them), and in light of this through him <char style="it">is </char>also
        the Amen (i.e., the acknowledgement of the finality of a matter; the familiar profession to God of “Let
        it be so”) to God with glory through us. <verse eid="2CO 1:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CO 1:21" />God’s establishing us together with you in Christ and anointed us. <verse eid="2CO 1:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CO 1:22" />He also stamped us with His seal of approval<char style="sup">[A]</char> and gave us the down payment<char
        style="sup">[B]</char> of the Spirit in our hearts.<verse eid="2CO 1:22" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CO 1:23" />I swear to God—cross my heart and hope to die<char style="sup">[k]</char>—that it was to spare you that
        I no longer went to Corinth— <verse eid="2CO 1:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CO 1:24" />not that we act in a domineering manner towards you of the Faith—no—we work together as helpers<char
        style="sup">[l]</char> of your grace: for you have stood by faith.<verse eid="2CO 1:24" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrade</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brother</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Originator</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Father</char>. This has a dual meaning: both
        God the Father and Someone who creates.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">all sorts of</char>…Lit: <char style="it">all</char>. A figure of speech. Use of the
        word <char style="it">all </char>figuratively also occurs 1 Tim. 6:10.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">distresses</char>…Also: <char style="it">tribulations</char>; <char style="it">extremely
        difficult circumstances</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">we concluded that we were doomed to die</char>…Lit: <char style="it">we had the sentence</char>
        [or <char style="it">diagnosis</char>] <char style="it">of death. </char>Appears to be an expression
        or idiom.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">from a narrow brush with death</char>…Lit: <char style="it">out of a great death</char>.
        Appears to be an expression.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the outcome of the stances, disposition, and full attention of many people</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">out of many faces</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">proud talk and bold claims</char>…Lit: <char style="it">boasting</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">until it’s all said and done</char>…Lit: <char style="it">until</char> [<char style="it">the</char>]
        <char style="it">end</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">by God—trust me</char>…Lit: <char style="it">God</char> [<char style="it">be</char>]
        <char style="it">faithful</char>. This appears to be an idiom.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I swear to God—cross my heart and hope to die</char>…Lit: <char style="it">I call upon
        witness-God upon my soul</char>. Some liberties taken.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">work together as helpers</char>…Lit: <char style="it">fellow workers</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">stamped us with His seal of approval</char>…Lit: <char style="it">sealed us. </char>Seals
        were used in ancient times the same way they are today, howbeit for the occasional different application.
        A messenger who was assigned the task of delivering a papyrus scroll with a message written on it to
        a remote destination was handed a scroll which was sealed. The sealing more than likely was a hot wax
        dripped across the overlapping edges of the scroll, so that when the wax cooled and hardened, the scroll
        couldn’t be opened and read without irreparably breaking the wax seal—similar to how an envelope, once
        opened, cannot be closed again and how, if it was opened, it would be apparent. In addition, the wax,
        while still hot, was stamped with a stamp or a signet ring which had a detailed image etched into it
        which became imprinted into the wax, so that the cooled wax retained this image. The receiver would inspect
        the image to make sure it was genuine, as only a limited set of stamps or signet rings would be made.
        The receiver would be ensured that the document was genuine, not a forgery from an imposter, as a potential
        imposter, though capable of writing a forgery, could not (at least easily) make a duplicate of the stamp
        or signet ring.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">So now, as Paul uses the word <char style="it">seal</char> a few times in his epistles, what he’s referring
        to is this:</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">1. God has placed his stamp of approval on something</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">2. The thing God stamped is genuine, valuable, and special</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">3. Any third party, someone other than God the stamper and the person being sealed, upon examination
        will be able to recognize that such a stamp is indeed from God</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">down payment</char>…Also: <char style="it">collateral</char>…Lit: <char style="it">surety;
        pledge. </char>As seen in the OT (one example is Prov. 6:1–5), loans were secured with collateral, so
        a person who needed to borrow a small amount of cash for a day or two could leave his cloak with the
        person who lends him the money as collateral. Now on a few occasions Paul in his epistles states that
        the Holy Spirit is given to us like collateral for a loan. What he means is:</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">1. God hands us something immediately with the promise He’ll “repay” us with something greater in the
        future. In other words, the Holy Spirit is God’s guarantee to us that He’ll give us something greater
        in the future</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">2. The Holy Spirit is something we get to hold onto and make use of in the meantime</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
      <char style="ft">3. The Holy Spirit will never—can never—be taken away from us, as he is “surety”</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="2CO 1" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  2   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="2CO 2" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 2:1" />Getting to the point, I made up my mind that I wouldn’t visit you again while laden with the pains of
        sorrow. <verse eid="2CO 2:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 2:2" />In fact, if I’m making you feel sorry, who in particular will cheer me up apart from the one I made feel
        sorry? <verse eid="2CO 2:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 2:3" />The very thing I wrote, I wrote so that I wouldn’t come for a visit and wind up being made sorry<char
        style="sup">[a]</char> by the ones I ought to rejoice over, as my nearness to you all has convinced me
        that my joy is derived from you all. <verse eid="2CO 2:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 2:4" />In fact, what I wrote to you through many tears came out of a great deal of distress and heart-felt anguish,
        not so that it would cause you sorrow, but so that you’d understand the abundant love which I have for
        you.<verse eid="2CO 2:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 2:5" />If a certain person has caused sorrow, he hasn’t caused me sorrow (<char style="it">actually </char>no,
        <char style="it">he has </char>partially), so I won’t dump<char style="sup">[b]</char> <char style="it">any
        more of this</char> on you all. <verse eid="2CO 2:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 2:6" />The very punishment <char style="it">inflicted </char>by the many is enough for such a person, <verse eid="2CO 2:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 2:7" />so that on the flip-side, you <char style="it">should be</char> all the more kind and merciful <char
        style="it">to him </char>and comfort and encourage <char style="it">him</char>, <char style="it">so that</char>
        such a person not somehow be deluged with even more sorrow. <verse eid="2CO 2:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 2:8" />In light of this I advise you to broadcast<char style="sup">[c]</char> love to him. <verse eid="2CO 2:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 2:9" />In fact, another reason I wrote is so that I could discern if you live up to my standards, <char style="it">that
        is </char>if you obey everything you’re told. <verse eid="2CO 2:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 2:10" />Now if you forgive <char style="it">somebody of </char>something, so do I; you see, if in addition <char
        style="it">to you </char>I <char style="it">forgave somebody of something</char>, what I’ve forgiven
        (assuming there’s something I’m forgiving), <char style="it">I did so </char>through you under the scrutiny<char
        style="sup">[d]</char> of Christ, <verse eid="2CO 2:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 2:11" />so that we won’t be swindled by Satan: we are not ignorant of his intentions, you see.<verse eid="2CO 2:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 2:12" />Now that I’ve arrived at Troas for the purpose of spreading the Gospel of Christ (i.e., the good news
        about Christ), a door has been opened to me in the Lord (i.e., in regard to the things of the Lord, a
        tremendous opportunity has presented itself to me), <verse eid="2CO 2:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 2:13" />I was uncomfortable<char style="sup">[e]</char> in my spirit not finding my fellow-comrade<char style="sup">[f]</char>
        Titus, so instead I excused myself, said goodbye to them, and left for Macedonia.<verse eid="2CO 2:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 2:14" />But thank-you God, Who always makes us roadies on Christ’s victory tour<char style="sup">[A]</char>,
        and Who’s propagating the fragrance of his knowledge<char style="sup">[g]</char> through us in all regions,<verse eid="2CO 2:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 2:15" />since in God we are a pleasant<char style="sup">[h]</char> aroma (<char style="it">like the incense they
        burned in the Old Testament, or the pleasing smell of a burnt offering</char>) of Christ among those
        being saved (i.e., those being rescued from calamity) and among those perishing; <verse eid="2CO 2:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 2:16" />we who on the one hand <char style="it">are </char>a whiff <char style="it">of going </char>from death
        to <char style="it">even more </char>death<char style="sup">[B]</char>, and on the other hand <char style="it">are
        </char>a whiff <char style="it">of going </char>from life to <char style="it">even more </char>life—and
        that’s not good enough for some people? <verse eid="2CO 2:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 2:17" />You see, we’re not like so many <char style="it">other preachers </char>who hustle<char style="sup">[i]</char>
        the word of God—no—<char style="it">we preach the Gospel </char>like it’s coming from someone who’s sincere
        through-and-through<char style="sup">[j]</char>—no—we speak <char style="it">the word of God </char>in
        Christ like it’s coming directly from God <char style="it">while</char> <char style="it">we</char> <char
        style="it">stand</char> before God<char style="sup">[k]</char>.<verse eid="2CO 2:17" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">wind up being made sorry</char>…Lit: <char style="it">have sorrow</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">dump</char>…<char style="it">on you</char>…Lit: <char style="it">burden you</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">broadcast</char>…Lit: <char style="it">preach</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">under the scrutiny of</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in the face of</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I was uncomfortable</char>…Also: <char style="it">I remained ill at ease</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">my fellow-comrade</char>…Lit: <char style="it">my brother</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">fragrance of his knowledge</char>…A well-crafted metaphor, one which is continued in
        the next couple of verses</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">pleasant</char>…Or<char style="it">: sweet-smelling</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">hustle</char>…The meaning of this Gk. word is “trade in, peddle, huckster.” It refers
        to “the tricks of small tradesmen,” so “…the word almost comes to mean <char style="it">adulterate” </char>(Danker
        &amp; Bauer).</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">like it’s coming from someone who’s sincere through-and-through</char>…Lit: <char style="it">as
        out of sincerity</char>. An idiom.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">we speak the word of God in Christ like it’s coming directly from God while we stand
        before God</char>…Lit: <char style="it">as from out of God before God in Christ we speak</char>. Same
        idiom as before.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">makes us roadies on Christ’s victory tour</char>…Or: <char style="it">leads us around
        in a triumphal procession in Christ</char>. Some liberties taken. The single Gk. word used here refers
        to the following: In Roman times, generals returned from a battlefield victory in a procession and led
        the procession through the capitol. The triumphal general and his lieutenants formed the vanguard of
        the procession; those in the defeated enemy’s army, including women and children, were bound and formed
        the rear of the procession, being led to the city to be sold as slaves. The analogy is that we are a
        part of the procession, though I prefer to believe that we’re part of the vanguard and not the rear,
        but that’s open to debate.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a whiff of going from death to even more death</char>…<char style="it">from life to
        even more life</char>…Lit: <char style="it">a smell out of death unto death</char>…<char style="it">out
        of life unto life</char>. Same Gk. wording as is used in in Paul’s statement <char style="it">from faith
        to faith </char>(Rom. 1:17), as this is the same expression. Similar to the English usage of <char style="it">whiff,
        </char>the usage here means <char style="it">a living example; a glimpse</char>. Paul’s life and his
        companions’ lives exemplify a life of death and, even more, of life and even more life. Paul goes into
        detail about the death he’s referring to in the eleventh and twelfth chapters; but in the midst of this
        Paul experiences more and more of the life of God.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="2CO 2" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  3   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="2CO 3" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 3:1" />Are <char style="it">my comrades and I</char> starting over again in doing self-promotion <char style="it">to
        bolster your opinion of us</char>? Put another way, we’re not in need of letters of recommendation <char
        style="it">to be sen</char>t to you or <char style="it">to be received</char> from you, like some people
        do, are we? <verse eid="2CO 3:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 3:2" />You are our letter <char style="it">of recommendation</char>, written in our hearts, understood and read
        by all people. <verse eid="2CO 3:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 3:3" />It’s plain for all to see that you are a letter of Christ transcribed and delivered<char style="sup">[a]</char>
        by us; not written with ink, but with the Spirit of the Living God; not <char style="it">written </char>in
        stone but <char style="it">written </char>in a flesh-heart.<verse eid="2CO 3:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 3:4" />We’re convinced that we have such a thing through Christ with God— <verse eid="2CO 3:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 3:5" />Not that we’re up-to-par in and of ourselves to <char style="it">where we </char>figure that something
        in particular <char style="it">which is good</char> was self-generated, but rather that our adequacy
        <char style="it">comes</char> out of God, <verse eid="2CO 3:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 3:6" />Who also made us up-to-par ministers of a new covenant, not of <char style="it">the </char>letter (i.e.,
        the literal, exacting listing of rules, compliance with those rules, and consequences for breaking them)
        but of <char style="it">the</char> Spirit: for the letter kills, but the Spirit causes things to spring
        into life.<verse eid="2CO 3:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 3:7" />Now if the administering of death, <char style="it">which was packaged</char> in letters etched<char
        style="it"> </char>in stone, occurred in glory to the point that it wasn’t possible for the run-of-the-mill
        Israelite<char style="sup">[b]</char> to gaze at Moses’s face because of the glory of his face—a glory
        that was deteriorating <char style="it">no less</char>— <verse eid="2CO 3:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 3:8" />how much more will the administering of the Spirit be accompanied by<char style="sup">[c]</char> glory?<verse eid="2CO 3:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 3:9" />Furthermore, if <char style="it">there was</char> glory in the administering of condemnation, how much
        more does the administering of righteousness exceed it in glory? <verse eid="2CO 3:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 3:10" />And furthermore, that which has been made glorious hasn’t been made glorious relative to<char style="sup">[d]</char>
        the glory which surpasses it. <verse eid="2CO 3:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 3:11" />In fact, if <char style="it">the glory </char>which has been nullified has been nullified by glory, <char
        style="it">the glory </char>which remains does so all the more in glory.<verse eid="2CO 3:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 3:12" />So having such hope, in our outspokenness and boldness we conceal nothing, <verse eid="2CO 3:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 3:13" />unlike Moses who placed a veil over his face so that the run-of-the-mill Israelites couldn’t gaze at
        the vestige of <char style="it">the glory </char>that was deteriorating— <verse eid="2CO 3:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 3:14" />not a chance—their minds were dead-set against it<char style="sup">[e]</char>. In fact to this very day
        the same veil remains uncovered at the reading of the Old Testament<char style="sup">[f]</char>, since
        it’s done away with in Christ. <verse eid="2CO 3:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 3:15" />No—to this day whenever the Old Testament<char style="sup">[f]</char> happens to be read aloud a veil
        lies over their heart, <verse eid="2CO 3:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 3:16" />but, if they were to turn to the Lord, the moment they do so, the veil gets taken off.<verse eid="2CO 3:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 3:17" />Now the Lord is <char style="it">in lockstep with </char>the Spirit, and there’s freedom where the Spirit
        of the Lord <char style="it">is</char>. <verse eid="2CO 3:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CO 3:18" />While gazing at the glory of the Lord with an uncovered face as though we’re looking intently in a mirror,
        we all are transformed into the same image <char style="it">going </char>from <char style="it">one gaze
        of </char>glory to <char style="it">another gaze of even more </char>glory<char style="sup">[g]</char>,
        just as <char style="it">we go </char>from <char style="it">one gaze of </char>the Spirit of the Lord
        <char style="it">to another gaze of even more of the Spirit</char>.<verse eid="2CO 3:18" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">transcribed and delivered</char>…Lit: <char style="it">serviced</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">run-of-the-mill Israelite</char>…Lit: <char style="it">sons of Israel</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">accompanied by</char>…Or: <char style="it">in</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">relative to</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in this respect because of</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">dead-set against it</char>…Lit: <char style="it">hardened</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the Old Testament</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the old covenant</char>…<char style="it">Moses</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">from one gaze of glory to another gaze of even more glory</char>…Lit<char style="it">:
        from glory to glory</char>. Ref. note of 2:16.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="2CO 3" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  4   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="2CO 4" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 4:1" />On account of this, <char style="it">that is of </char>having this administering <char style="it">of
        righteousness</char>, to the degree that we’ve been shown mercy, we don’t lose heart— <verse eid="2CO 4:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 4:2" />on the contrary, we quit for good doing those things that we’re ashamed of that we keep hidden<char style="sup">[a]</char>,
        not going here and there playing games with people<char style="sup">[b]</char>, nor putting a spin on<char
        style="sup">[c]</char> the word of God, rather by means of the propagation of the truth we leave a good
        impression deep inside of everyone else<char style="sup">[d]</char> <char style="it">while </char>under
        God’s scrutiny<char style="sup">[e]</char>. <verse eid="2CO 4:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 4:3" />But even if our Gospel, our Good News Message, is veiled, it’s veiled among those who are perishing,<verse eid="2CO 4:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 4:4" />among whom the god of this age (i.e., this current era of mankind’s history) blinded the minds of those
        who refuse to believe to where they don’t see the light of the Gospel of the glory of Christ, who is
        a spitting image of God. <verse eid="2CO 4:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 4:5" />You see, we don’t preach <char style="it">that </char>we<char style="it"> </char>ourselves <char style="it">are
        your superiors</char> but rather <char style="it">that </char>Jesus Christ <char style="it">is </char>Lord,
        and <char style="it">that </char>we ourselves <char style="it">are </char>your humble servants<char style="sup">[f]</char>
        on account of Jesus, <verse eid="2CO 4:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 4:6" />since the God Who said, “Light shall shine out of darkness,” <char style="it">is the One </char>Who shined
        in our hearts with <char style="it">the </char>light of the knowledge and understanding of the glory
        of God by means of the direct attention of<char style="sup">[g]</char> Jesus Christ.<verse eid="2CO 4:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 4:7" />We have this treasure in clay storage vessels (i.e., physical bodies) so that the over-and-above power
        would be of God and not from ourselves. <verse eid="2CO 4:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 4:8" /><char style="it">We’re </char>pressured from every direction and in trouble, but no—we’re not at the
        end of our rope<char style="sup">[h]</char>; confused as to what to do—but not totally confused; <verse eid="2CO 4:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 4:9" />persecuted but not abandoned; knocked off our feet but not destroyed; <verse eid="2CO 4:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 4:10" />always carrying around in our body the death of Jesus, so that the life of Jesus would also be manifested
        in our body. <verse eid="2CO 4:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 4:11" />You see, we the living are forever being forced into a position where death has control over us because
        of Jesus, so that the life of Jesus would also be manifested in our mortal body.<verse eid="2CO 4:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 4:12" />So then, the death <char style="it">I just described </char>is at work in us, but the life <char style="it">I
        likewise described is at work</char> in you. <verse eid="2CO 4:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 4:13" />Having a spirit of (i.e., a prevailing attitude of) faith that’s the same as what’s written <char style="it">in
        the Old Testament</char>, “I believed, and in light of it all<char style="it"> </char>I spoke,” we too
        believe, and in light of it all we too speak, <verse eid="2CO 4:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 4:14" />knowing for a fact that He who raised the Lord Jesus will also raise us together with Jesus and together
        with him cast us in a favorable light <char style="it">in God’s estimation</char><char style="sup">[i]</char>.<verse eid="2CO 4:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 4:15" />You see, all <char style="it">these </char>things are for your sake, so that the grace <char style="it">bestowed
        on us</char>, having proliferated through the thanksgiving of the many, would abound to God’s glory.<verse eid="2CO 4:15" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 4:16" />In light of this we’re not losing heart; on the contrary, even though our outer-person is deteriorating,
        yet our inner-person is being renewed day-in, day-out<char style="sup">[j]</char>. <verse eid="2CO 4:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 4:17" />To this point, the light weight of our affliction is incomparable to the heavy weight of glory at work
        in us, <verse eid="2CO 4:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CO 4:18" />while we’re not looking at the things which are seen but the things that are not seen: for the things
        which are seen are transient, but the things which are not seen are eternal.<verse eid="2CO 4:18" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">those things that we’re ashamed of that we keep hidden</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the
        hidden things of shame</char>. A figure of speech.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">playing games with people</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in craftiness</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">putting a spin on</char>…Lit: <char style="it">falsifying</char>. Comes from root meaning
        <char style="it">deceit; treachery.</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">we leave a good impression deep inside of everyone else</char>…Lit: <char style="it">commending
        ourselves to all consciences of men</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">while under God’s scrutiny</char>…Lit: <char style="it">before God</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">humble servants</char>…Lit: <char style="it">slaves</char>. A figure of speech.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the direct attention of</char>…Lit: [<char style="it">the</char>] <char style="it">face
        of</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">at the end of our rope</char>…Or: <char style="it">boxed in</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">cast us in a favorable light in God’s estimation</char>…Lit: <char style="it">present
        us, </char>or, <char style="it">make us presentable</char>. The picture is of a person presenting himself
        before a king, or someone presenting an offering at a temple. The implication is that the person or thing
        presented will leave a good impression.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">day-in, day-out</char>…Lit: <char style="it">day and day</char></char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="2CO 4" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  5   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="2CO 5" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 5:1" />In fact, we know for certain that if our Earth-suit<char style="sup">[a]</char> were to be demolished<char
        style="sup">[b]</char>, we have a building from God—an eternal building, one that’s not of human construction—way
        up in the sky<char style="sup">[c]</char>. <verse eid="2CO 5:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 5:2" />In connection to this we do groan, longing to put on (i.e., as though putting on a piece of clothing)
        our home—our cozy cottage<char style="sup">[d]</char>—<char style="it">which comes </char>from heaven.<verse eid="2CO 5:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 5:3" />If we really have put on <char style="it">our eternal building</char><char style="sup">[A]</char>, we
        won’t be caught naked. <verse eid="2CO 5:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 5:4" />Furthermore, we whose <char style="it">present form of </char>existence is with the Earth-suit do groan,
        being encumbered<char style="sup">[e]</char>, the crux of which is that we don’t want to be stripped
        of our garments but to be clothed instead, so that the death <char style="it">we carry about </char>would
        be thoroughly dowsed by the life. <verse eid="2CO 5:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 5:5" />Now He Who did the necessary work in us to make this very thing happen to us is God, the One Who gave
        us the down payment<char style="sup">[f]</char> of the Spirit.<verse eid="2CO 5:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 5:6" />So keep your chin up—always—and know for certain that making yourselves at home in the body will leave
        you far from home<char style="sup">[g]</char> with the Lord <verse eid="2CO 5:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 5:7" />(we go about our lives<char style="sup">[h]</char> by faith and not by sight, you see), <verse eid="2CO 5:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 5:8" />but with our chins held high and thinking positively, we’d rather be far from home in regard to the body
        but make ourselves at home with the Lord. <verse eid="2CO 5:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 5:9" />And so whether at home or away from home, we aspire to be pleasing to him: <verse eid="2CO 5:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 5:10" />the fact of the matter is that every one of us must appear before the Judge, Christ the Judge, so that
        each individual’s deeds, deeds which were committed by the body, whether they were good or bad—<char
        style="it">all of them</char>—would be brought <char style="it">before the Judge to be judged by him</char>.<verse eid="2CO 5:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 5:11" />Now that we’ve acquired a firm understanding of the fear of the Lord, we convince <char style="it">other</char>
        people <char style="it">to do the same</char>. We’ve been made manifest<char style="sup">[i]</char> to
        God (i.e., we’ve presented ourselves before God), and I hope to reach the point where we’ve been made
        manifest to your consciences as well— <verse eid="2CO 5:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 5:12" />Not that we’re trying to promote ourselves again<char style="sup">[j]</char>, but are giving you the
        chance to talk proudly about us instead, so that you would have <char style="it">something good to say
        </char>to those who take pride in and talk big about peoples’ behavior on the surface, or the masks people
        present to others, and not what’s in the heart. <verse eid="2CO 5:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 5:13" />The fact of the matter is that if it’s the case that I’ve lost my mind, <char style="it">I’ve lost my
        mind </char>for God; if it’s the case that I’m sane, <char style="it">I’m sane </char>for you. <verse eid="2CO 5:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 5:14" />The love of Christ has a tight grip on us, you see, and has determined <char style="it">that </char>this
        <char style="it">is the case</char>: that one <char style="it">person </char>died in everyone’s place<char
        style="sup">[k]</char> (therefore everyone died), <verse eid="2CO 5:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 5:15" />and he died in everyone’s place so that the living would no longer live for themselves but that they
        would instead live for him who died and was raised in their place.<verse eid="2CO 5:15" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 5:16" />An outcome of all this is that, from now on, there’s nobody we form a perception of according to <char
        style="it">the </char>flesh (i.e., according to a person’s physical body and outward appearance; his
        limited ability in and of himself), even if we had come to know and understand Christ according to <char
        style="it">the </char>flesh—but, no, we no longer know and understand <char style="it">him according
        to the flesh</char>.<verse eid="2CO 5:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 5:17" />An outcome of all this is that if someone is in Christ (melded with him: in him, with him, and living
        life by means of him), he’s a new type of species, a new kind of creature, a new creation: the old has
        come and gone<char style="sup">[l]</char> <char style="it">and</char>—get this—the new has come into
        being<char style="sup">[B]</char>. <verse eid="2CO 5:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CO 5:18" />Now all <char style="it">these new </char>things <char style="it">are </char>from God, Who by Christ
        reconciled us with Himself and gave us the Reconciliation Ministry, <verse eid="2CO 5:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CO 5:19" />that is that God was in Christ reconciling <char style="it">the </char>world (i.e., those who don’t know
        and live for God) to Himself, not holding all the times they crossed over the line in doing wrong as
        strikes against them<char style="sup">[m]</char>, and assigning to us <char style="it">the task of keeping
        and spreading </char>the message of reconciliation. <verse eid="2CO 5:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CO 5:20" />So we’re ambassadors of Christ as we’re encouraging, exhorting, and advising <char style="it">others
        </char>in matters pertaining to God. <char style="it">And this is the message we tell them: </char>“As
        a representative of Christ I ask you—I beg you—to be reconciled to God. <verse eid="2CO 5:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CO 5:21" />He who had never consummated sin was made<char style="sup">[n]</char> sin on our behalf so that we would
        become righteous of a nature of God’s righteousness<char style="sup">[C]</char> in him (melded with him:
        in him, with him, and living life by means of him).”<verse eid="2CO 5:21" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Earth-suit</char>…Lit: <char style="it">on-earth house of tent</char>. Some liberties
        taken.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">demolished</char>…Lit: <char style="it">completely broken into pieces</char>. The word
        describes breaking a stone edifice apart, as it’s the same root word Jesus used to describe the dispersal
        of the stones of the Temple.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">way up in the sky</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in the heavens</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">our home—our cozy cottage</char>…The Gk. word here is a diminutive form of <char style="it">house</char>,
        and as such acquires a connotation of coziness</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">encumbered</char>…Lit: <char style="it">weighed down</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">down payment</char>…Ref. note of 1:22</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">making yourself at home in the body will leave you far from home</char>…Lit (inserting
        a couple of key Gk. words): <char style="it">endāmountos </char><char style="w" strong="G01736">ἐνδημέω</char>)<char
        style="it">in the body ekdāmoumen </char><char style="w" strong="G01553">ἐκδημέω</char>). These two Gk.
        words forms a rhyme, assonance, or pun, making this a figure of speech.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">go about our lives</char>…Lit: <char style="it">walk around</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">manifest</char>…The same Gk. verb is rendered <char style="it">appear</char> in v. 10,
        and assuming that the reuse in v. 11 here links the two thoughts together, then what Paul means by “manifest”
        in v. 11 is similar to its usage in v. 10, i.e. of appearing before a judge to have your deeds reviewed
        and judged.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Not that we’re trying to promote ourselves again</char>…Same wording as 3:1</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">in everyone’s place</char>…Also: <char style="it">on everyone’s behalf</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">come and gone</char>…Lit: <char style="it">passed by</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[m]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[m]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">not holding all the times they crossed over the line in doing wrong as strikes against
        them</char>…Lit: <char style="it">not reckoning their trespasses to them</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[n]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[n]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">was made</char>…Lit: <char style="it">made</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">If we really have put on</char> <char style="it">our eternal building …</char>Or: <char
        style="it">If we really have shed our clothing</char>….The UBS Greek NT, 3<char style="sup">rd</char>
        Edition reads<char style="it"> shed our clothing</char> (also, <char style="it">undressed </char>or <char
        style="it">stripped naked</char>);<char style="it"> </char>the photocopies of both Codex Vaticanus and
        Codex Sinaiticus read <char style="it">put on </char>instead (and a translation of the Latin Vulgate
        agrees), therefore most of the translators render this <char style="it">put on </char>and not <char style="it">undressed.
        </char>One can only speculate if the UBS made a mistake here or if they changed the reading based on
        “internal” considerations and didn’t footnote with a citation of the various manuscripts. The UBS reading
        makes sense: assuming such a reading, the “undressing” referred to would be the same as “if our Earth-suit
        were to be demolished” (v. 1). When the physical body is destroyed, we’ll be clothed with a heavenly
        body, rather than being “found naked.”</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the new has come into being</char>…The KJV says “all things are become new.” The words
        “all things” are not found in the better manuscripts.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">righteous of a nature of God’s righteousness</char>…Lit: [<char style="it">a</char>]
        <char style="it">righteousness of God</char>. Noteworthy is that, in the GT, there’s no definite article
        preceding <char style="it">righteousness. </char>This verse does not say we would become the righteousness
        of God (insertion of definite article before <char style="it">righteous</char>), but that we would become
        righteous in a way that our righteousness is of the same nature as God’s righteousness. This is a far
        cry from becoming equivalent to God in His righteousness—which is an absurd proposition.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="2CO 5" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  6   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="2CO 6" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 6:1" />Being those who work together <char style="it">to minister to others</char><char style="sup">[a]</char>,
        we do plead with you to not take in God’s grace and have nothing to show for it. <verse eid="2CO 6:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 6:2" />In fact, <char style="it">the Old Testament </char>says,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 6:2"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 6:2">I heard you just in time</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 6:2">And I helped you</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 6:2">That time you needed to be rescued<char style="sup">[b]</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 6:2"></para>
    <para style="m" vid="2CO 6:2">Hey! “Just in time” is now—Hey! “The time you needed to be rescued” is now.<verse eid="2CO 6:2"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 6:3" />Don’t give anyone any reason to be seriously offended<char style="sup">[c]</char> <char style="it">by
        something you did wrong</char>, so that the ministry <char style="it">of God’s grace</char> won’t be
        criticized— <verse eid="2CO 6:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 6:4" />Uh-uh—leaving others with an impression that’s expected of<char style="it"> </char>God’s ministers, <char
        style="it">and doing this </char>with a good deal of perseverance, <char style="it">doing this </char>in<char
        style="it"> </char>times of distress, in times of privation, while in anguish, <verse eid="2CO 6:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 6:5" />while being whipped or beaten, while in prison, during riots, while doing hard, grueling work, in sleepless
        nights, while going hungry; <verse eid="2CO 6:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 6:6" /><char style="it">doing this </char>with purity, with understanding, with patience, with kindness; <char
        style="it">do this </char>in the Holy Spirit, in sincere love, <verse eid="2CO 6:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 6:7" />with a message of truth<char style="sup">[d]</char>, in <char style="it">the </char>power of God, by
        being armed with the armor and weapons of righteousness that the left and right hands are accustomed
        to handle<char style="sup">[e]</char>; <verse eid="2CO 6:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 6:8" />through glory and disgrace, through a bad reputation and a good reputation; as though we’re deceived
        and as though we know the truth, <verse eid="2CO 6:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 6:9" />as though we’re not known or understood and as though we’re known and understood, as though we’re dying
        but—hey—we’re <char style="it">still </char>alive; as though we’re being reprimanded but not sentenced
        to death, <verse eid="2CO 6:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 6:10" />as though we’re in pain but ever rejoicing, as though we’re poor but becoming quite wealthy, as though
        we own nothing but own everything.<verse eid="2CO 6:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 6:11" />We haven’t stopped engaging you in dialogue<char style="sup">[f]</char>, Corinthians; our heart is fixed<char
        style="it"> </char>wide open <char style="it">to you</char>. <verse eid="2CO 6:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 6:12" />Don’t be closed off to us—but <char style="it">with</char> <char style="it">the sort of</char> “closed
        off” <char style="it">which keeps us</char> in your tender affections. <verse eid="2CO 6:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 6:13" />When it’s your turn to reciprocate (I’m talking to you like I would to a child), open yourselves up <char
        style="it">to us</char>.<verse eid="2CO 6:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 6:14" />Don’t get unevenly yoked (i.e., like an ox and a donkey yoked together on the same plow harness) with
        unbelievers. What partnership is there between righteousness and lawlessness (i.e., the refusal to be
        restrained by the rules of God or of man)? What do light and darkness have in common? <verse eid="2CO 6:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 6:15" />What harmony is there between Christ and the Devil<char style="sup">[g]</char>? How does a believer partake
        in joint ventures with an unbeliever? <verse eid="2CO 6:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 6:16" />How does God’s temple approve of or validate <char style="it">an</char> idol’s <char style="it">temple</char>?
        You are a temple of the Living God, in fact, just as God said,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 6:16"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 6:16">“I will dwell and move among them,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 6:16">And I will be their God,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 6:16">And they will be my folk-people.<verse eid="2CO 6:16"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 6:17" />In light of this come out from their midst
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 6:17">And be separate,” Says the Lord,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 6:17">“And don’t touch things which</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 6:17">Are vile, disgusting, and forbidden to touch<char style="sup">[h]</char>,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 6:17">And I will receive you and take you in,<verse eid="2CO 6:17"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CO 6:18" />And I will be a Father to you,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 6:18">And you will be sons and daughters to Me,”</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 6:18">Says the Lord Almighty.<verse eid="2CO 6:18"/>
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">those who work together to minister to others</char>…Lit: <char style="it">fellow worker</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">that time you needed to be rescued</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in a day of salvation</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">seriously offended</char>…Lit: <char style="it">a stumbling</char>. Ref. note of Matt.
        18:6.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a message of truth</char>…Or: [<char style="it">the</char>] <char style="it">word of
        truth</char>…Lit: <char style="it">word of truth</char> [with the definite article before <char style="it">word</char>
        inferred]</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">by being armed with the armor and weapons of righteousness that the left and right hands
        are accustomed to handle</char>…Lit: <char style="it">through the armors of righteousness of the lefts
        and rights</char>. A metaphor.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">We haven’t stopped engaging you in dialogue</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Our mouth remains
        open to you</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the Devil</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Belial</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">vile, disgusting, and forbidden to touch</char>…Lit: <char style="it">unclean</char></char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="2CO 6" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  7   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="2CO 7" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 7:1" />So having these promises <char style="it">I quoted just now</char>, beloved, let us cleanse ourselves
        from all defilement of flesh (i.e., of carnality) and spirit<char style="sup">[A]</char>, while bringing
        holiness to perfection in the deep reverence—downright fear—of God.<verse eid="2CO 7:1" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 7:2" />Accomodate us: we haven’t wronged anyone, ruined anyone, or taken advantage of anyone. <verse eid="2CO 7:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 7:3" />I’m not pointing any fingers<char style="sup">[a]</char>; in fact I’ve stated before that you are in
        our hearts for the rest of our lives, until death do us part. <verse eid="2CO 7:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 7:4" />It’s a lot for me to be blunt with you, a lot for me to talk about you with pride. I’ve reached the point
        where I’m full of encouragement and comfort; I’m way overjoyed every time we’re faced with a really bad
        situation.<verse eid="2CO 7:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 7:5" />In fact, not once after arriving in Macedonia did our <char style="it">weary </char>bodies get a chance
        to rest, uh-uh…all kinds of pressure…on the<char style="it"> </char>outside <char style="it">we faced
        </char>conflict, on the inside fear. <verse eid="2CO 7:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 7:6" />In contrast, God was the One Who encouraged us the abased by <char style="it">having </char>Titus show
        up. <verse eid="2CO 7:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 7:7" />Not just <char style="it">by </char>him showing up, but by the encouragement, comfort, and advise he
        <char style="it">showered</char> on us, relaying to us your longing, your grieving, your fervency you
        have regarding me, resulting in it giving me all the more joy.<verse eid="2CO 7:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 7:8" />Even if I hurt you <char style="it">by</char> <char style="it">what I put </char>in the <char style="it">previous
        </char>letter, I have no regrets; even if I had regrets (for I see that that letter did cause you pain
        for <char style="it">some</char> time), <verse eid="2CO 7:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 7:9" />I’m glad now, not because you were <char style="it">simply </char>hurt, but rather that the pain that
        you suffered resulted in a change of heart and of actions<char style="sup">[b]</char>. In fact, you were
        hurt God’s way, so you suffered no loss <char style="it">in any area of your life</char>. <verse eid="2CO 7:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 7:10" />You see, being hurt (hurt intentionally in a way that you suffer pain) God’s way effects a change of
        heart and actions working towards the end goal of dodging a bullet<char style="sup">[c]</char> and having
        no regrets about <char style="it">what had to be done </char>to accomplish that; the pain that the world
        (i.e., those outside of Christ) experiences works in a way that, when it’s run its course, results in
        death (i.e., a stagnation of waste, joylessness, futility, destruction, and ultimately physical death).<verse eid="2CO 7:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 7:11" />While I’m on this topic, this very thing—being<char style="sup">[d]</char> hurt God’s way—look how much
        it accomplished in you and what a priority you made it. <char style="it">From where you were </char>instead
        is a rebuttal—instead <char style="it">you have </char>indignation, fear, longing, fervency, and self-vindication.
        In everything you demonstrated to everyone that you’re cleared of these matters<char style="sup">[e]</char>.<verse eid="2CO 7:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 7:12" />So now, that I’m even writing to you <char style="it">at all</char>, <char style="it">I’m not doing so</char>
        because of <char style="it">something you </char>did wrong or because of <char style="it">some </char>wrong
        done <char style="it">to us</char>, rather because of the priority and urgency at which you’ve made the
        things <char style="it">we confronted </char>you with before God materialize. <verse eid="2CO 7:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 7:13" />We’ve been encouraged by this.
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="2CO 7:13">On the subject of what’s been an encouragement to us, <char style="it">hearing the news </char>that Titus
        is happy gave me even more joy, since his spirit was refreshed by you all. <verse eid="2CO 7:13"/>
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 7:14" />I had told him a thing or two about you, telling him how proud I am of you, and I wasn’t disappointed
        or embarrassed. On the contrary—as we’ve always been truthful with you when we’ve talked to you, in the
        same vein our speaking with pride <char style="it">about you</char> to Titus turned out to be true as
        well. <verse eid="2CO 7:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 7:15" />The tender affection he has for you is that much more when recalling every time you did as you were told,
        as you received him with fear and trembling<char style="sup">[f]</char>. <verse eid="2CO 7:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 7:16" />I rejoice since I have confidence in you in every respect.<verse eid="2CO 7:16" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I’m not pointing any fingers</char>…Lit: <char style="it">I’m not saying condemnation</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a change of heart and of actions</char>…Lit: <char style="it">repentance</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">dodging a bullet</char>…Or: <char style="it">escaping calamity</char>…Lit: <char style="it">unto
        salvation</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">being</char>…Lit: <char style="it">to have been</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">you’re cleared of these matters</char>…Lit: <char style="it">you to be innocent to the
        matters</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">fear and trembling</char>…A biblical expression (Ps. 55:5; Eph. 6:5; Phil 2:12 for example)</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">cleanse yourselves from all defilement of flesh (i.e., carnal nature) and spirit</char>…A
        metaphor which compares the water purification rituals specified by the Law of Moses which the Jews had
        to do on a regular basis to a self-cleansing of the things inside a person which are not holy.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="2CO 7" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  8   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="2CO 8" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 8:1" />Just wanted you to know<char style="sup">[a]</char>, comrades<char style="sup">[b]</char>, <char style="it">about
        </char>the grace of God that’s been granted to the churches in Macedonia, <verse eid="2CO 8:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 8:2" />that in such a severe trial brought on by distress, the abundance of their joy and the vast extent of
        their poverty<char style="sup">[c]</char><char style="sup">[A]</char> amplified the richness of their
        generosity— <verse eid="2CO 8:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 8:3" />that according to their means—I swear—even beyond their means—<char style="it">and </char>of their own
        free accord— <verse eid="2CO 8:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 8:4" />with a good deal of explanations, assurances, and exhortation <char style="it">they were </char>asking
        us to do them a favor and <char style="it">allow them to </char>participate in ministering to the saints
        (i.e., their fellow believers).<verse eid="2CO 8:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 8:5" />And <char style="it">they didn’t </char>just <char style="it">do this </char>the way<char style="it">
        </char>we expected<char style="sup">[d]</char> <char style="it">they would</char>—no—by the will of God
        they first dedicated themselves to the Lord and to us, <verse eid="2CO 8:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 8:6" />resulting in us having encouraged Titus to finish off this favor, which is being done for you in a consistent
        manner to how he started it. <verse eid="2CO 8:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 8:7" />That aside, just as you continuously take everything to a new level<char style="sup">[e]</char>—faith,
        attestation<char style="sup">[f]</char>, knowledge and understanding, eager diligence, and the love which
        came out of us <char style="it">and was imparted </char>in you<char style="sup">[g]</char>—<char style="it">apply
        the same principles </char>so that you would take this act of charity to the next level as well.<verse eid="2CO 8:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 8:8" />What I’m saying shouldn’t be construed as an order, but certainly as a test<char style="sup">[h]</char>
        of the authenticity of your love by the zeal which motivates others. <verse eid="2CO 8:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 8:9" />In fact you know the act of charity of our Lord Jesus Christ, that he, being rich, became poor for your
        sake so that by that impoverishment you would become rich. <verse eid="2CO 8:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 8:10" />I’ll give you my opinion on this <char style="it">topic</char>: this benefits you, you the very ones
        who, beginning last year <char style="it">and continuing thenceforth</char>, didn’t just begin to tackle
        this but maintained the desire to do it.<verse eid="2CO 8:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 8:11" />But now complete the doing-part as well, so that just as the enthusiasm of the wanting-part <char style="it">was
        prevalent from the inception, </char>so the completion <char style="it">of the deed </char>from the what-do-we-possess-part
        is the <char style="it">natural</char> consequence <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">the wanting.</char><verse eid="2CO 8:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 8:12" />For if the enthusiasm’s in place, <char style="it">whatever gift a given person comes up with </char>is
        acceptable according to whatever wealth and belongings that person happens to possess, not according
        to what he doesn’t possess. <verse eid="2CO 8:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 8:13" />You see, this isn’t so that others can take it easy while you’re subjected to hardship, but <char style="it">it’s
        done </char>out of equality. <verse eid="2CO 8:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 8:14" />The way things stand at the moment, your abundance <char style="it">of material possessions is directed
        </char>towards their lack so that equality would take shape, <verse eid="2CO 8:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 8:15" />just as it’s written,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 8:15"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 8:15">He who has much didn’t have a surplus</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 8:15">And he who has a little didn’t lack<verse eid="2CO 8:15"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 8:16" />But God is so kind<char style="sup">[i]</char>: for our sake He’s putting the same eagerness <char style="it">to
        get the job done</char> in Titus’s heart, <verse eid="2CO 8:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 8:17" />since, while—yes—he took the counsel, advise, and encouragement that was given to him to heart, but,
        being more eager than ever, of his own volition he left on a trip to visit you. <verse eid="2CO 8:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CO 8:18" />We sent someone to go with him, the comrade who’s praised throughout all the churches in<char style="it">
        his preaching of </char>the Gospel— <verse eid="2CO 8:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CO 8:19" />not just <char style="it">to go along for the ride</char> but to be our travelling companion as well,
        hand-picked to be the churches’ attaché with respect to this act of charity, which is the service <char
        style="it">done </char>by us to the glory of the Lord and <char style="it">which is a token of </char>our
        enthusiasm.<verse eid="2CO 8:19" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CO 8:20" />The intention is that no one would find fault with us in our handling of this generous <char style="it">gift</char>.<verse eid="2CO 8:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CO 8:21" />In fact, we considered ahead of time what the decent thing to do would be, not just from the Lord’s perspective
        but also from the perspective of the average person. <verse eid="2CO 8:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CO 8:22" />We sent our comrade along with the others, he who at many times and in many ways has proven to be eager,
        diligent, and to get things done without dragging his feet, but now is even more eager because of the
        tremendous confidence <char style="it">he has </char>in you.<verse eid="2CO 8:22" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CO 8:23" />Whether <char style="it">I’m speaking </char>on behalf of Titus, my fellow worker and a mentor and assistant<char
        style="sup">[B]</char> for you, or whether <char style="it">I’m speaking on behalf of </char>our comrades
        the apostles of churches (i.e., those who are pioneers in founding churches; missionaries who establish
        churches), <char style="it">in either case the </char>glory <char style="it">goes to </char>Christ. <verse eid="2CO 8:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CO 8:24" />So the pointed demonstration of your love and of the tremendous things we tell them about you is taking
        place in full view of the churches.<verse eid="2CO 8:24" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">just wanted you to know</char>…Lit: <char style="it">we’re making known to you</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">in such a severe trial brought on by distress, the abundance of their joy and the vast
        extent of their poverty</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in much test of affliction the abundance of their
        joy and their poverty</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">expected</char>…Lit: <char style="it">hoped</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">take everything to a new level</char>…Lit: <char style="it">abound in all</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">attestation</char>…Lit: <char style="it">word</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">came out of us and was imparted in you</char>…The principle manuscripts are split here,
        with the others reading <char style="it">of you to us</char>.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">test</char>…Or: <char style="it">verification</char>; <char style="it">proof</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">God is so kind</char>…Lit: <char style="it">grace</char> <char style="it">with</char>
        [or <char style="it">to</char>] <char style="it">God</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">in such a severe trial brought on by distress, the abundance of their joy and the vast
        extent of their poverty</char>…There is some ambiguity whether <char style="it">their </char>refers to
        the Macedonians or to those whom they’re taking up a collection for.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">mentor and assistant</char>…Lit: <char style="it">fellow worker</char>. The two Gk.
        words for <char style="it">fellow worker, </char>namely <char style="it">koinonos </char>(κοινωνός /Strong’s
        2844)and <char style="it">sunergos </char><char style="w" strong="G04904">συνεργός</char>), are both
        used in this verse, and the distinction between these words is apparent by the usage here. This distinction
        is not found in the lexicons.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="2CO 8" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  9   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="2CO 9" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 9:1" />As a matter of fact, I sure do have more to write to you concerning this ministry-drive for the saints
        (i.e., our fellow believers). <verse eid="2CO 9:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 9:2" />You see, having observed you, I know your enthusiasm, an enthusiasm I speak proudly about to the Macedonians,
        <char style="it">namely</char> that Achaia started making preparations a year ago and that your passion
        <char style="it">for this project</char> motivated a great many people<char style="sup">[a]</char>there.<verse eid="2CO 9:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 9:3" />I dispatched the comrades<char style="sup">[b]</char> so that the tremendous things we say about you
        regarding this matter would not be for nothing, so that <char style="it">it would be </char>just like
        I kept saying over and over again that you were making preparations— <verse eid="2CO 9:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 9:4" /><char style="it">but it’s</char> not as though the Macedonians and I were going to somehow get together
        and go and catch you unprepared<char style="sup">[c]</char> and we—dare I say you too<char style="sup">[d]</char>—would
        be embarrassed at what’s behind it all<char style="sup">[e]</char>.<verse eid="2CO 9:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 9:5" />Anyways, to give the comrades encouragement was the most important thing to do, so that they would arrive
        in your locale ahead of time and put in order your pledged blessing (i.e., charitable contribution) ahead
        of time. These arrangements are <char style="it">thus</char> <char style="it">so that the entire affair
        is done</char> the way a blessing <char style="it">is done</char> and not the way a shakedown for money
        <char style="it">is done</char>.<verse eid="2CO 9:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 9:6" />Now <char style="it">onto </char>this: he who sows parsimoniously also reaps parsimoniously and he who
        sows with a mindset of blessing <char style="it">others </char>also reaps a blessing because of that
        mindset<char style="sup">[f]</char>. <verse eid="2CO 9:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 9:7" /><char style="it">Let</char> <char style="it">the offering</char> from each person <char style="it">be
        </char>according to what he decided in his heart beforehand, not out of an inner pain <char style="it">of</char>
        <char style="it">regret in having to part with one’s money </char>or out of compulsion, for God loves
        a cheerful, glad, happy, prompt-to-do giver. <verse eid="2CO 9:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 9:8" />In fact God is able to proliferate all <char style="it">kinds of </char>grace (i.e., good things, in
        terms of money and material goods) to us, so that in all <char style="it">situations</char> always having
        enough of everything you would exude any and every good work<char style="sup">[g]</char>, <verse eid="2CO 9:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 9:9" />just as it’s written:
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 9:9"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 9:9">He scattered, he gave to the needy</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 9:9">His righteousness remains <char style="it">in place </char>forever<verse eid="2CO 9:9"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 9:10" />Now He who supplies seed to the sower and bread for the food that you eat<char style="sup">[A]</char>
        will provide and multiply your seed and will cause the crop of your righteous endeavor to grow<char style="sup">[h]</char>,<verse eid="2CO 9:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 9:11" />being made rich in all <char style="it">respects,</char> towards an ends of complete simplicity (i.e.,
        a heart which has the single, simple motive of giving, and therefore has no ulterior motive, attaches
        no strings, and gives without any of the complications of guilt, remorse, etc.; does so under no threat,
        no compulsion, nor because of any rule, religious or otherwise), which through us works God’s praise
        to the nth degree, <verse eid="2CO 9:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 9:12" />because the ministry <char style="it">which consists</char> of this religious ritual, this act of worship,
        this service to God, is not simply the supplying of the saints’ needs but also the causing of a multiplication-effect
        through much praise to God— <verse eid="2CO 9:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 9:13" />Through the proof of this ministry, God has been glorified in the compliance with what you said you were
        going to do<char style="sup">[i]</char> for the Good News of Christ, the Gospel, and the simplicity of
        the act of sharing with them and with everyone, <verse eid="2CO 9:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 9:14" />and their prayer for you, longing for you on account of the exceeding grace of God <char style="it">which
        is</char> upon you.<verse eid="2CO 9:14" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 9:15" />God is so kind<char style="sup">[j]</char> with this indescribable gift of His!<verse eid="2CO 9:15" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a great many people</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the many</char> [<char style="it">majority</char>]</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">unprepared</char>…Or: <char style="it">off-guard</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">dare I say you too</char>…Lit: <char style="it">so that I wouldn’t say “you”</char>.
        The NASB renders this: <char style="it">not to mention you.</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">at what’s behind it all</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in this the substance</char> [or
        <char style="it">undergirding</char>; <char style="it">foundation</char>; <char style="it">core</char>].
        Appears to be an expression.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">he who sows with a mindset of blessing others also reaps a blessing because of that
        mindset</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the one sowing at</char> [i.e., <char style="it">at the exact location
        of; right over top of</char>] <char style="it">a blessing at a blessing reaps</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">exude any and every good work</char>…Lit: <char style="it">abound unto all good work</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">will cause the crop of your righteous endeavor to grow</char>…Lit: <char style="it">will
        grow the crop of your righteousness</char>. A metaphor comparing the doing of a righteous deed to growing
        a crop.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">what you said you were going to do</char>…Lit: <char style="it">your confession</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">God is so kind with this indescribable gift of His</char>…Lit: <char style="it">grace</char>
        <char style="it">with</char> [or <char style="it">to</char>] <char style="it">God at the indescribable
        gift of His</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">bread for the food that you eat</char>…Lit: <char style="it">bread for food</char>.
        the majority of one’s calories were derived from eating bread in ancient times. In the context of the
        writing of this epistle, therefore, bread was what people survived on (ref. Matt. 6:11). So saying that
        God will supply bread for food means that God will supply what you need to eat.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="2CO 9" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 10   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="2CO 10" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 10:1" />I, Paul, through the gentle restraint and kindness of Christ, who, <char style="it">when I was here on
        Earth</char> face-to-face with you was humble indeed, but audacious when away from you, beg you personally—<verse eid="2CO 10:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 10:2" />but with the infusion of audacity which comes from not being present—I ask with confidence, which I figure
        makes me brash enough to confront some people who suppose that we live day in, day out<char style="sup">[a]</char>
        according to the flesh (i.e. of our own ability apart from God; as though God doesn’t work through us).<verse eid="2CO 10:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 10:3" />You see, <char style="it">though</char> living day in, day out in flesh (i.e., in a physical body, one
        subject to human weaknesses), we don’t wage war according to the flesh: <verse eid="2CO 10:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 10:4" />our battle-gear isn’t fleshly (i.e., of a physical nature; of our own ability apart from God)—uh-uh,
        it’s quite capable in God of leveling heavily-fortified defenses—leveling schemes, machinations, detailed
        plans, <verse eid="2CO 10:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 10:5" />and every erected fortification or entrenched high-ground<char style="sup">[b]</char> which opposes the
        knowledge and understanding of God, and capturing every thought and making it a prisoner of the obedience
        of Christ<char style="sup">[A]</char>, <verse eid="2CO 10:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 10:6" />and of being prepared to avenge every disobedience, when your obedience happens to reach the tipping
        point.<verse eid="2CO 10:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 10:7" />You’re seeing things as they appear on the surface<char style="sup">[c]</char>. If a given person has
        convinced himself that he’s derived from Christ, let this fellow rethink the logic again as it applies
        to himself <char style="it">and let him come to the conclusion </char>that, just as he himself is derived
        from Christ, we also are <char style="it">derived from Christ </char>in the same way <char style="it">as
        he</char>. <verse eid="2CO 10:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 10:8" />So now, if I venture to say something even more cocky about our authority (an authority which the Lord
        gave for building you up and not for tearing you down, <char style="it">by the way</char>), I won’t embarrass
        myself and have to eat my words because I’ve failed in this regard<char style="sup">[d]</char>, <verse eid="2CO 10:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 10:9" /><char style="it">embarassed </char>so that I not revel in delight<char style="sup">[e]</char>, as you
        might be scared out of your wits by <char style="it">what I wrote in </char>the letters. <verse eid="2CO 10:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 10:10" />Since a few people say, “Sure—the letters cut to the bone and pack a punch<char style="sup">[f]</char>,
        but he comes across as weak when you see him in person and his speaking ability and rhetoric<char style="sup">[g]</char>
        is contemptuous,” <verse eid="2CO 10:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 10:11" />Let any such person <char style="it">who says that </char>think this over: what we are in writing through
        the mail when absent, such we are in what we do when present as well.<verse eid="2CO 10:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 10:12" />Furthermore, we dare not put ourselves in the same category as some of the self-promoters or compare
        ourselves to them—no—they get off to the side by themselves and rank themselves and do self-endorsements
        to one another<char style="sup">[h]</char>—they just don’t get it. <verse eid="2CO 10:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 10:13" />We’re not going to speak proudly or say tremendous things<char style="sup">[i]</char> about the things
        outside our sphere <char style="it">of ministry</char><char style="sup">[B]</char>—no—<char style="it">we’ll
        speak proudly about the things </char>within the sphere which the God of a limit <char style="it">to
        such spheres</char> assigned to us to envelop even you <char style="it">within that sphere</char>. <verse eid="2CO 10:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 10:14" />In fact, it’s not as though we don’t envelop you while extending our reach out to <char style="it">the
        perimeter of </char>our<char style="it"> sphere </char>and beyond; you see, in the course of enveloping
        you <char style="it">by our sphere,</char> we were the first to arrive in your locale with the Good News,
        the Gospel of Christ— <verse eid="2CO 10:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 10:15" /><char style="it">No, we </char>don’t speak proudly about things<char style="it"> </char>outside our sphere,
        <char style="it">namely </char>about the toils of others, but <char style="it">we’re </char>hoping, as
        your faith which is among you is being grown, to vastly enlarge our sphere, <verse eid="2CO 10:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 10:16" /><char style="it">that is </char>for places beyond you to be evangelized—<char style="it">and</char> not
        to speak proudly about <char style="it">the fruition of</char> somebody else’s long-term plans<char style="sup">[j]</char>
        taking place in his sphere, <verse eid="2CO 10:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 10:17" />but <char style="it">like it says, </char>”He who speaks proudly, let him speak proudly <char style="it">of
        what he does </char>in the Lord.”<verse eid="2CO 10:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CO 10:18" />You see, the person who promotes himself—that’s not the individual who obtains the approval <char style="it">of
        God</char>, rather the one whom the Lord speaks well of <char style="it">is the one</char> <char style="it">who
        gains the approval </char>instead.<verse eid="2CO 10:18" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">live day in, day out</char>…Lit: <char style="it">walk about</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">erected fortification or entrenched high-ground</char>…Lit: <char style="it">height
        lifted up</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">You’re seeing things as they appear on the surface</char>…Lit: <char style="it">You’re
        seeing according to face</char>. Note that the phrase <char style="it">according to face </char>is used
        in v. 1 (<char style="it">face-to-face</char>), although the meaning there appears to be different.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">embarrass myself and have to eat my words because I’ve failed in this regard</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">be put to shame</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">revel in delight</char>…Lit: <char style="it">glory</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">cut to the bone and pack a punch</char>…Lit: <char style="it">are weighty and strong</char>.
        The word <char style="it">weighty</char> also appears in Matt. 23:23, being used the same way there.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">speaking ability and rhetoric</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the word</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">they get off to the side by themselves and rank themselves and do self-endorsements
        to one another</char>…Lit: <char style="it">they themselves among themselves measure themselves and commend
        themselves</char>. The repetition of <char style="it">themselves </char>is a figure of speech.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">speak proudly or say tremendous things</char>…Also: <char style="it">boast</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the fruition of…long-term plans</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the preparations</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">capturing every thought and making it a prisoner of the obedience of Christ</char>…The
        passage of vv. 3–6 is a metaphor comparing the Christian struggles in their faith to the mechanics of
        waging war.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">sphere of ministry</char>…Lit: <char style="it">sphere</char>. It’s not exactly clear
        to me what Paul is talking about in this passage, the passage consisting of vv. 13–16. Certain words
        have vague definitions and aren’t clarified by usage in other parts of the NT.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="2CO 10" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 11   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="2CO 11" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 11:1" />If you would bear with me a bit while I act stupid—scratch that: you are<char style="it"> </char>bearing
        with me. <verse eid="2CO 11:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 11:2" />You see, I dote over you zealously<char style="sup">[a]</char> with a zealous doting that’s of God, for
        I’ve betrothed you to <char style="it">only </char>one man<char style="sup">[b]</char> <char style="it">in
        order </char>to present <char style="it">to this one man </char>a chaste virgin in Christ. <verse eid="2CO 11:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 11:3" />I fear that somehow that’s not the case—as the serpent deceived Eve with his cunning trickery, he would
        somehow seduce your minds <char style="it">and draw you </char>away from the simplicity<char style="sup">[c]</char>
        (i.e., straightforward, without conniving, ulterior motives, hidden agendas, or religious quid-pro-quo)
        and the purity which has Christ as its goal.<verse eid="2CO 11:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 11:4" />For indeed, if a passerby stops over and preaches <char style="it">that </char>another <char style="it">person
        is the real </char>Jesus, a person whom we didn’t preach <char style="it">as being the real Jesus</char>,
        or you receive (i.e., take to heart and wholeheartedly embrace) a different spirit which you didn’t receive
        <char style="it">before</char>, or you wholeheartedly embrace<char style="it"> </char>a different good-news-<char
        style="it">type</char> message that you didn’t receive<char style="sup">[d]</char>, you tolerate it with
        no qualms. <verse eid="2CO 11:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 11:5" />You see, the way I figure, we’re not inferior to these <char style="it">so-called</char> super-apostles
        in any category. <verse eid="2CO 11:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 11:6" />But even if I’m an amateur when it comes to speaking ability and rhetoric<char style="sup">[e]</char>,
        put that aside—<char style="it">I’m not an amateur</char> when it comes to knowledge and understanding—no—I’ve
        made that apparent to you in every possible way<char style="sup">[f]</char>.<verse eid="2CO 11:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 11:7" />Is it that I committed a sin in humbling and debasing myself so that you would be made to stand on two
        legs<char style="sup">[g]</char>, since I evangelized the good news of the Gospel to you sacrificially
        on my part and delivered it to you free of charge? <verse eid="2CO 11:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 11:8" />Scratch that—I robbed <char style="it">other </char>churches by drawing a wage <char style="it">from
        them </char>and applying it to your ministry. <verse eid="2CO 11:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 11:9" />Not only that, when I was staying with you and was in need, I wasn’t a burden to anyone: the comrades<char
        style="sup">[h]</char> who came from Macedonia provided what I needed. My living expenses weren’t a burden
        in any way to you, nor will they be. <verse eid="2CO 11:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 11:10" />Christ in me unequivocally indicates that this is true<char style="sup">[i]</char>: I won’t be denied
        the opportunity to speak with pride <char style="it">about what we will accomplish in the Lord </char>in
        the region of Achaia<char style="sup">[j]</char>. <verse eid="2CO 11:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 11:11" />Why would <char style="it">I be denied</char>? Because I don’t love you? God knows for a fact <char style="it">that
        I do</char>.<verse eid="2CO 11:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 11:12" />What I’m doing I’ll continue to do in order to nix the occasion <char style="it">for fault-finding </char>by
        those who are wanting <char style="it">to find such </char>an occasion, so that in <char style="it">the
        specific area </char>that they’re boasting of, everyone will come to the conclusion<char style="sup">[k]</char>
        that they’re also like us. <verse eid="2CO 11:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 11:13" />In fact, false apostles such as they, workers of deceit, are disguising themselves as apostles of Christ—<verse eid="2CO 11:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 11:14" />And it’s not surprising: Satan himself disguises himself as an angel of light. <verse eid="2CO 11:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 11:15" />So there’s not a huge <char style="it">difference</char> if his servants <char style="it">the false apostles</char>
        also disguise themselves as servants of righteousness. The way it ends for <char style="it">these false
        apostles </char>will be in step with their deeds.<char style="sup">[l]</char><verse eid="2CO 11:15" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 11:16" />Moving on to another topic.<char style="sup">[m]</char> Nobody should take me for a fool, but should
        it be otherwise, accept me even as a fool, so that even <char style="it">as a fool </char>I have some
        little thing <char style="it">or two</char> to say about my tremendous <char style="it">accomplishments</char>.<verse eid="2CO 11:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 11:17" />What I’m about to say isn’t in line with how the Lord speaks, but are words you’d expect to come out
        of one in <char style="it">the throes of </char>folly—the essence of the boasting <char style="it">you’re
        about to hear</char>.<verse eid="2CO 11:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CO 11:18" />Since many are talking up great things they’ve done according to flesh (i.e., from their own ability
        apart from God; taking credit for it personally and not giving God the credit), I’ll talk up my tremendous
        accomplishments too. <verse eid="2CO 11:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CO 11:19" />The fact of the matter is, you’re more than happy to tolerate what the fools spout off,<char style="it">
        </char>treating them like they’re<char style="it"> </char>sensible and wise<char style="sup">[A]</char>.<verse eid="2CO 11:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CO 11:20" />You put up with someone if he subjugates and oppresses you, if he cheats you out of house and home, if
        he sets you up to take advantage of you, if he lifts <char style="it">himself </char>up <char style="it">in
        arrogance</char>, if he slaps you upside the head<char style="sup">[B]</char>. <verse eid="2CO 11:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CO 11:21" />I’m ashamed to say it, <char style="it">but it’s </char>as though <char style="it">you disdain us</char>
        because we’ve become weak in what someone <char style="it">else</char> might dare <char style="it">speak
        proudly about</char>.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="2CO 11:21">I’m talking foolishly, but I’ll dare speak <char style="it">anyways</char>. <verse eid="2CO 11:21"/>
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CO 11:22" />Are they native-Hebrew speakers and live by the ancient Jewish culture?—So do I. Are they Israelites?—So
        am I. Are they father-to-son direct descendants and heirs of<char style="sup">[n]</char> Abraham?—So
        am I. <verse eid="2CO 11:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CO 11:23" />Are they Christ’s servants (I’m talking like a mad man)?—I’ll up them one: as far as hard labor goes,
        I’ve done more. I’ve spent more time in prison. I’ve received more beatings. I’ve had more near-death
        experiences: <verse eid="2CO 11:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CO 11:24" />I’ve received the thirty-nine lash <char style="it">punishment </char>by the Jews five times; <verse eid="2CO 11:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CO 11:25" />I’ve been beaten with staffs three times; I was stoned <char style="it">to death </char>once; I was shipwrecked
        three times; I spent twenty-four straight hours floundering out in the ocean<char style="sup">[o]</char>.<verse eid="2CO 11:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CO 11:26" />I’ve been on the road many a time <char style="it">walking great distances</char>; I’ve been in danger
        while travelling by river; in danger from robbers; in danger by my fellow countrymen; in danger by those
        in faraway countries; in danger in the city; in danger in the countryside; in danger on the high seas;
        in danger from phony comrades; <verse eid="2CO 11:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CO 11:27" />I worked hard, long hours and did heavy manual labor; had many a sleepless night; went long stretches
        with nothing to eat or nothing to drink; fasted many times; was cold because I had nothing to wear<char
        style="sup">[p]</char>— <verse eid="2CO 11:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CO 11:28" />Besides those external <char style="it">pressures</char>, <char style="it">there is </char>the <char
        style="it">pressure on the inside of me due to </char>the day-to-day responsibility for all the churches,
        worrying over them. <verse eid="2CO 11:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CO 11:29" />Who’s weak (i.e., sickly, frail, or simply unable to muster the strength to face life’s challenges),
        and I’m not weak <char style="it">along with them</char>? Who stumbles<char style="sup">[q]</char> (i.e.
        falls away from the walk of faith; falls into sin; is overcome by temptation; stops following God), and
        I’m not raving <char style="it">over it</char>?<verse eid="2CO 11:29" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CO 11:30" />If there has to be proud talk <char style="it">about tremendous things which have taken place</char>,
        I’ll speak proudly about things that have to do with my weakness (i.e., circumstances in which I lacked
        the power in my own self to overcome the difficulties I faced). <verse eid="2CO 11:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CO 11:31" />The God and Father of our Lord Jesus—He Who’s blessed forevermore—knows for a fact that I’m not lying—<verse eid="2CO 11:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CO 11:32" />In Damascus the governor under King Aretas kept the <char style="it">entire </char>city of Damascus on
        alert searching for me in order to arrest me, <verse eid="2CO 11:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CO 11:33" />and I was <char style="it">put </char>through<char style="it"> </char>a window in the <char style="it">city
        </char>wall and lowered to the ground in a basket and slipped out of his hands.<verse eid="2CO 11:33" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I dote over zealously</char>…Also<char style="it">: I’m jealous</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">man</char>…Also: <char style="it">husband</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">simplicity</char>…Same word used in 9:11; ref. back to that usage</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">receive</char>…Paul uses two different Gk. words for <char style="it">receive </char>[<char
        style="it">lambanō, </char><char style="w" strong="G02983">λαμβάνω</char>) and <char style="it">dechomai</char>,
        <char style="w" strong="G01209">δέχομαι</char>)] in this clause; the subtle distinction between the two
        can be gleaned from the usage here.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">speaking ability and rhetoric</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the word</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">in every possible way</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in every way in all things</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">made to stand on two legs</char>…Lit<char style="it">: be exalted</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Christ in me unequivocally indicates that this is true</char>…Lit: <char style="it">It
        is a truth of Christ in me</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I won’t be denied the opportunity to speak with pride about what we will accomplish
        in the Lord in the region of Achaia</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the very boast won’t be stifled to me
        in the region of Achaia</char>. Assumption is that the boasting Paul speaks of refers to 10:17.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">everyone will come to the conclusion</char>…Lit: <char style="it">it will be discovered</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">The way it ends for these false apostles will be in step with their deeds</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">To whom the end will be according to their works</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[m]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[m]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Moving on to another topic</char>…Lit: <char style="it">again I speak</char> [<char
        style="it">speak</char> so as to convey reasoning and logic]</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[n]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[n]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">father-to-son direct descendants and heirs of</char>…Lit: <char style="it">seed of</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[o]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[o]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">floundering out in the ocean</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in the deep</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[p]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[p]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">was cold because I had nothing to wear</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in cold and nakedness</char>.
        A hendiadys; ref. note of Matt. 3:11.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[q]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[q]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">stumbles</char>…Ref. note of Matt. 18:9</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">tolerate</char> <char style="it">what the fools spout off treating them like they’re
        sensible and wise</char>…Lit: <char style="it">tolerate the fools being sensible</char>. There’s ambiguity
        as to what the antecedent of the participle phrase <char style="it">being sensible </char>refers to.
        Who’s Paul saying is sensible, the Corinthians or the fools (the false apostles)? It appears the latter
        is the case. But this is not an isolated case in the NT where there’s such antecedent-ambiguity with
        a participle phrase (and participle phrases dangle by nature). English has this problem also, but it’s
        more acute in Gk.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">subjugates and oppresses you, if he cheats you out of house and home, if he sets you
        up to take advantage of you, if he lifts himself up in arrogance, if he slaps you upside the head</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">if someone enslaves; if someone devours </char>[<char style="it">ref. Mark 12:40</char>]<char
        style="it">; if someone catches </char>[<char style="it">like a hunter</char>]<char style="it">; if someone
        lifts up; if someone hits to the face</char>. These are hyperboles to a greater or lesser extent.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="2CO 11" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 12   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="2CO 12" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 12:1" />To talk with pride about <char style="it">some </char>spectacular things <char style="it">that have happened
        to me</char><char style="sup">[a]</char><char style="it"> </char>must <char style="it">be done</char>
        <char style="it">here</char>. While this won’t help anyone, I’ll jump into<char style="sup">[b]</char>
        visions and revelations of the Lord anyways. <verse eid="2CO 12:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 12:2" />From firsthand experience, I know <char style="it">of </char>a man in Christ fourteen years earlier,
        and said-person was seized and carried off (whether <char style="it">he was carried off </char>outside
        of the body <char style="it">or whether both his body and his spirit together were carried off, </char>I
        don’t know—<char style="it">only </char>God knows) until <char style="it">he reached</char> the third
        heaven<char style="sup">[A]</char> (i.e., went through the first and second heavens, which are the sky,
        the upper atmosphere, and outer space, into the spirit world: “paradise”). <verse eid="2CO 12:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 12:3" />And I know said-person (whether in the body or apart from the body, I don’t know—<char style="it">only
        </char>God knows), <verse eid="2CO 12:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 12:4" />that he was seized and carried off into paradise and heard remarks that must not be told, that are not
        allowed to be spoken to a person.<verse eid="2CO 12:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 12:5" />I’ll talk big on behalf of said-man and talk about the spectacular things <char style="it">that happened
        to him, </char>but I won’t talk big about myself except in the weaknesses <char style="it">I’m beset
        with</char>. <verse eid="2CO 12:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 12:6" />You see, if I were to want to talk big, I won’t be acting like a fool <char style="it">as I talk</char>:
        in fact, I’d be telling the truth. But I’ll spare you, lest someone make <char style="it">incorrect </char>assumptions<char
        style="sup">[c]</char> based on what he sees or hears that comes from me <verse eid="2CO 12:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 12:7" />and by means of the extraordinary nature of the revelations.
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="2CO 12:7">With this in mind, so that I not be lifted up and over<char style="sup">[B]</char> (i.e., leap over the
        hurdles of life), a “thorn in the flesh”<char style="sup">[C]</char> (<char style="it">an idiom referring
        to an antagonist which vexes and harasses continuously</char>) was given to me, an agent<char style="sup">[d]</char>
        of Satan, so that he would buffet me (i.e., strike me repeatedly and non-stop), so that I not be lifted
        up and over. <verse eid="2CO 12:7"/>
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 12:8" />Because of this I begged the Lord three times that it be taken away from me, <verse eid="2CO 12:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 12:9" />and he told me,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 12:9"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 12:9"><char style="wj">My grace </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">which I give </char></char><char style="wj">to
        you is sufficient,</char>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 12:9"><char style="wj">For the power </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">which accompanies it</char></char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 12:9"><char style="wj">Is brought to completion in weakness</char><char style="sup">[D]</char><verse eid="2CO 12:9"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 12:10" />In light of this, I’m content in weakness, with insults, in dire need, with persecutions, and in distress
        on behalf of Christ: for when I’m weak, then I’m powerful and capable.<verse eid="2CO 12:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 12:11" />I’ve turned into a fool; you drove me to it. The fact of the matter is that you ought to have a high
        opinion of me<char style="sup">[e]</char>. I’m not deficient in any category when compared to the apostles
        as a whole, you see, even though I’m nothing. <verse eid="2CO 12:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 12:12" />Indeed, the defining characteristics of an apostle<char style="sup">[E]</char> were thoroughly put into
        action among you with steadfastness and perseverance at every turn, and with signs and wonders (i.e.,
        spectacular, attention-getting miracles) and <char style="it">supernatural </char>power. <verse eid="2CO 12:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 12:13" />In fact how have you been treated worse than any of the other churches, except that I didn’t wear out
        my welcome<char style="sup">[f]</char> with you? Excuse this bad behavior on my part.<verse eid="2CO 12:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 12:14" />Hey, this is the third time I’ve made preparations to go visit you, and I’ll not wear out my welcome:
        I’m not trying to get your <char style="it">material possessions</char>, I’m trying to get you instead.
        You see, the children <char style="it">in the family </char>aren’t obligated to pay for<char style="sup">[g]</char>
        their parents <char style="it">when it comes to room, board, clothing, etc.</char>, but the parents are
        for their children. <verse eid="2CO 12:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 12:15" />I will most gladly spend on you—you who are vivacious in thought and emotion<char style="sup">[h]</char>—and
        be spent for you…although the more I love you, the less I’m loved.<verse eid="2CO 12:15" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 12:16" />But <char style="it">I’ll </char>let <char style="it">that</char> be. I wasn’t a burden to you; instead—the
        clever fellow that I am—I pulled a fast one on you<char style="sup">[i]</char>. <verse eid="2CO 12:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 12:17" />Of all the people I sent you, whom did <char style="it">I try to use </char>to take advantage of you
        with and milk you for gain? <verse eid="2CO 12:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CO 12:18" />I asked Titus <char style="it">to visit you </char>and the comrade <char style="it">who went with him
        </char>to accompany him—did Titus take advantage of you? Have we not conducted our lives in the same
        spirit (i.e., in the same attitude, led by the same prevailing demeanor)? Have we not followed in the
        same footsteps?<verse eid="2CO 12:18" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CO 12:19" />So far you think we’ve <char style="it">just </char>been telling you one excuse after another. <char
        style="it">But what we tell you, </char>we speak before God in Christ (i.e., knowing that God is listening
        closely, while relying on Christ to mediate); every last thing we do is for your edification, my dear
        <char style="it">comrades</char>. <verse eid="2CO 12:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CO 12:20" />The fact of the matters is that I’m afraid that somehow I’ll come <char style="it">visit you </char>and
        find that you’re not the way that I want and expect you to be, and vice-versa; that somehow <char style="it">I’ll
        find</char> there’s rivalry, jealousy, uncontrolled tempers, selfish ambition, bad-mouthing, gossip,
        arrogance, or havoc being wreaked. <verse eid="2CO 12:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CO 12:21" /><char style="it">I don’t want to have to </char>go there again and <char style="it">have</char> God humiliate
        me with you and <char style="it">cause me </char>to mourn much<char style="sup">[j]</char> (i.e., to
        pray deep, heart-felt prayers of grieving and sorrow; to be in a melancholy state of grief, pain, and
        sorrow) over sins you have previously committed and have no intention of asking God to forgive you of
        these things and quitting them—you have no intention of doing anything about them—when it comes to the
        uncleanness (i.e., lewd, crude, disgusting behavior), fornication (i.e., loose sexual morals), and licentiousness
        (i.e., unrestrained indulgence in immoral, physical pleasures) which you have practiced.<verse eid="2CO 12:21" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">To talk with pride about some of the spectacular things that have happened to me</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">to be boasting</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I’ll jump into</char>…Lit: <char style="it">I’ll come unto</char> [or <char style="it">into</char>].
        Appears to be an expression.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">make incorrect assumptions</char>…Lit: <char style="it">figure</char>; <char style="it">reckon;
        credit to someone</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">agent</char>…Also: <char style="it">angel</char>. See usage in Luke 9:52; Rev. 2:1.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a high opinion of me</char>…Lit: <char style="it">to be commend by you</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">wear out my welcome</char>…Lit: <char style="it">didn’t grow completely stiff or numb;
        wasn’t a burden</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">to pay for</char>…Lit: <char style="it">be storing provisions</char>. Like storing provisions
        in anticipation of winter.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">on you—you who are vivacious in thought and emotion</char>…Lit: <char style="it">on
        behalf of your souls</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the clever fellow that I am—I pulled a fast one on you</char>…Lit: <char style="it">being
        cunning, in deceit I have taken you</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">mourn much…</char>Ref. Matt. 5:4; 1 Cor. 5:2</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the third heaven</char>…The ancients had a different view of the universe than we do,
        and they assumed that the spiritual world, which includes heaven itself, is simply a layer on top of
        another layer. So the Gk. word<char style="it"> </char>for <char style="it">heaven </char>conflates a
        couple of concepts we do not. The first of the “heavens” is the sky above. The second heaven-layer, being
        above that of course, is where the sun, the moon, and the stars exist. We call it outer-space, but they
        assumed that these astronomical objects were closer to the earth than they actually are. They assumed
        that the sun travelled across the sky each day in the second “heaven.” So the third heaven is the layer
        above the second, but since the second includes all physical objects (and from our perspective extends
        to the far reaches of the universe), the third layer steps into the spirit-world. Now, is this spirit-world
        heaven as we know it? Paul calls it <char style="it">paradise </char>in v.4, so it may be. Ref. notes
        of John 3:3; 1 Pet. 1:5.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">be lifted up and over</char>…This is rendered word-for-word. It’s used as a metaphor.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft">”<char style="it">thorn in the flesh</char>”…This is an idiom from the OT, appearing in Num. 23:55; Josh.
        23:13; Judg. 2:3; Ezek. 28:24. Since it is an idiom, it should not be taken literally; and indeed, it
        is not used literally in any of the aforementioned references. This idiom was originally used to describe
        the vexation which came from the enemy nations which surrounded Israel. In fact, Paul goes on to state
        exactly what this idiom refers to in an appositive phrase a few words after: it is an “agent of Satan.”
        Furthermore, this verse doesn’t say that God gave Paul a thorn in the flesh, rather the passive voice
        of “was given” is used, thereby not specifying the subject, the one doing the giving.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[D]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[D]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">weakness</char>…Lit: <char style="it">asthenia</char> (the Gk. word for <char style="it">weakness</char>).<char
        style="it"> Asthenia </char><char style="w" strong="G00769">ἀσθένεια</char>)at times means sickness (Luke
        10:9 for example), but at other times means weakness as the English word suggests. When asthenia is used
        to mean sickness, it refers to a prolonged, undiagnosed ailment which lasts for a long time and causes
        a person to become weak. The context determines whether this refers to a physical ailment or not. In
        addition, asthenia is used a few times starting from the 10<char style="sup">th</char> chapter until
        this verse, and nowhere in those occurrences does it conclusively refer to a sickness of some sort. To
        cap it off, v. 10 says “for when I’m weak,” where “weak” summarizes the words before it, which are “insults,
        dire need, persecutions, and circumstances of distress”—none of which are a sickness of any sort. This
        implies that the insults, dire need, persecutions, and circumstances of distress are Paul’s weakness.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[E]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[E]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the defining characteristics of an apostle</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the signs of
        an apostle</char>. Although this translation often renders <char style="it">apostle </char>as <char style="it">missionary</char>,
        the complete definition of an apostle also includes what Paul says here, namely that a true apostle performs
        signs and wonders. Likewise, to be considered an evangelist according to the strictest biblical definition,
        one must perform miracles, healings, or something of a supernatural nature. This is because Philip (Acts
        21:8) is the only evangelist that the NT identifies by name, so his example must serve as the archetype
        for all evangelists. In other words, since Philip performed miracles, and Philip is the only evangelist
        in the Bible, all evangelists must perform miracles in order to conform to the strictest definition laid
        down by Acts 21.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="2CO 12" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 13   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="2CO 13" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 13:1" />This’ll be the third time I’ll visit you.
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 13:1"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 13:1"><char style="it">Based </char>upon <char style="it">what’s spoken from</char> the mouth</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 13:1">Of two or<char style="sup">[a]</char> <char style="it">better yet</char> three witnesses</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="2CO 13:1">Will every affair <char style="it">in question</char> be settled<char style="sup">[b]</char><verse eid="2CO 13:1"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 13:2" />I have said earlier and am telling those who’ve sinned up to now and everyone else for future reference
        (<char style="it">and telling them </char>as though <char style="it">I’m </char>present for the second
        time and leaving just now) that if I were to go <char style="it">see you </char>another time, I won’t
        hold anything back, <verse eid="2CO 13:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 13:3" />since you’re looking for proof of Christ speaking in me—<char style="it">Christ </char>who isn’t weak
        when it comes to you<char style="sup">[c]</char>, but rather is able, capable, and powerful in you. <verse eid="2CO 13:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 13:4" />The fact of the matter is, he was crucified out of weakness, but he lives out of power from God. The
        fact of the matter is, even we are weak in him, but we shall live jointly with him out of <char style="it">the</char>
        power of God <char style="it">granted </char>to you.<verse eid="2CO 13:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 13:5" />If you are in the Faith, test for yourselves—prove to yourselves <char style="it">this</char>: don’t
        you recognize as far as your own selves are concerned—don’t you know full-well that Christ Jesus <char
        style="it">is </char>in you and among you?—Unless of course you fail the test. <verse eid="2CO 13:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 13:6" />But I hope you’ll come to recognize that we don’t fail the test.<verse eid="2CO 13:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 13:7" />We pray to God for you to no longer do <char style="it">this or that thing which is</char> bad—not so
        that everyone would see that we were right all along, but that you would do what’s good instead. <verse eid="2CO 13:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 13:8" />You see, we don’t have the strength to do a thing contrary to the truth, but instead <char style="it">we
        only have the strength to do a thing </char>for the truth. <verse eid="2CO 13:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 13:9" />You see, we rejoice when we happen to be weak, but you happen to have strength. This is what we pray
        in addition: <char style="it">we pray </char>for you to reach maturity.<verse eid="2CO 13:9" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 13:10" />Because of this, I write these words while absent, so that when I get there and am staying with you,
        I won’t be using the authority which the Lord assigned to me in a harsh manner, <char style="it">an authority
        which is to be used </char>for edification and not <char style="it">is</char> <char style="it">to be
        used</char> destructively.<verse eid="2CO 13:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 13:11" />One last thing, comrades<char style="sup">[d]</char>: rejoice, mend your ways, be comforted and encouraged,
        stay in agreement<char style="sup">[e]</char>, live in peace, and the God of that wonderful, peaceful
        love<char style="sup">[f]</char> will be with you.<verse eid="2CO 13:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 13:12" />Give each other a holy hug<char style="sup">[g]</char> from me.
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="2CO 13:12">All the saints (i.e., your fellow believers in all the churches) greet you.<verse eid="2CO 13:12"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 13:13" />The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ, the love of God, and the fellowship of the Holy Spirit <char style="it">be
        </char>with you all.<verse eid="2CO 13:13" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">or</char>…Lit: <char style="it">and</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">settled</char>…Lit: <char style="it">established</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">isn’t weak when it comes to you</char>…Lit<char style="it">: isn’t weak unto you</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">stay in agreement</char>…Lit: <char style="it">be thinking the same thing</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">that wonderful, peaceful love</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the love and peace</char>.
        A hendiadys; ref. note of Matt. 3:11.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">holy hug</char>…Lit: <char style="it">holy kiss</char>. Liberties taken.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="2CO 13" />
</usx>
