<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- The Bernmeister's New Testament, Unabridged Edition -->
<!-- Copyright © 2024 Bernard M. Woodland -->
<!-- Version 1 -->
<!-- Public domain -->
<!-- The Bernmeister's NT, Unabridged Version 1 -->
<usx version="3.0">
  <!--   *******************   -->
  <!--   Titles and TOC Info   -->
  <!--   *******************   -->
  <book code="REV" style="id">The Bernmeister's NT, Unabridged</book>
  <para style="h">Revelation</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Book of Revelation</para>
  <para style="toc2">Revelation</para>
  <para style="toc3">Rev.</para>
  <para style="mt2">THE BOOK OF</para>
  <para style="mt1">REVELATION</para>
  <!--   ************   -->
  <!--   Introduction   -->
  <!--   ************   -->
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="ipi">The final piece of John’s portfolio of writings differs from the others. Revelation is a continuation
    of the prophesies in Genesis, Ezekiel, Daniel, and Zechariah, and the novice reader, lacking an overall
    view of the Bible, jumps into Revelation without first getting up to speed on those other books. This
    is explained in the author’s book <char style="it">A Path through Revelation.</char></para>
  <para style="ipi">There are, however, numerous grammatical mistakes in Revelation, and this leaves one to wonder what the
    cause of these mistakes is. Can we assume that John wrote the book with the help of a scribe?— Scribes
    normally edit out such errors. In addition, it appears that John jumbles verb tenses throughout. This
    might be him seeing a vision in the present of something that will happen in the future as though it
    happened already but as though he witnessed it in real-time. Some of these mistakes are probably John
    not remembering the form of a particular verb. He does have a mastery of what the forms do, but Greek
    is convoluted. Some of the “mistakes” can be chalked up to John’s writing style, his peculiar figures
    of speech. The long note in Rev. 8:3 captures an example of such grammatical errors.</para>
  <para style="ipi">Revelation does follow John’s propensity to utilize a smaller vocabulary than the likes of Paul, but
    the Greek text is both simple and complex at the same time. When translating it, one finds himself not
    so much following the literal meaning of the words and the nuances of the forms, but standing back and
    getting the gist of what’s being said and then putting that down. It’s as though one is listening closely
    to someone speaking to the broken-Greek, then putting the pieces together. At times, this becomes difficult
    because Revelation is so bizarre, and one doesn’t know if he’s encountering weirdness or John’s weakness
    in describing something. For example, Rev. 13:18, “it’s a man’s number”—not quite sure if that’s something
    ordinary that’s not explained well or if it’s yet another mystery of Revelation.</para>
  <para style="ipi">John’s final book complements his other writings since it differs in style from his gospel and his epistles.
    After a close reading of the Greek text, he appears to be a strong-willed person who does things his
    own way. He’s not as loud as Mark (and Peter by extension), but isn’t one who submits to accepted conventions
    of writing like Luke. To read John’s books is to enter his world and to go to him, for he will not go
    to you.</para>
  <para style="ib"></para>
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  1   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="REV 1" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 1:1" />A revelation—a revealing—by Jesus Christ <char style="it">of matters hidden</char>, <char style="it">a
        revelation</char> which God gave to him, to show his servants what must come to pass post-haste<char
        style="sup">[a]</char>. He transmitted what he saw through His angel to his servant John, <verse eid="REV 1:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 1:2" />who gave an official account of God’s discourse and of the statement<char style="sup">[b]</char> of Jesus
        Christ. <verse eid="REV 1:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 1:3" />Blessed be the one reading <char style="it">aloud to the congregation </char>and the listeners <char
        style="it">in the congregation </char>who hear the words of the prophecy and who keep what’s been written
        therein, for the time is near.<verse eid="REV 1:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 1:4" /><char style="it">From </char>John to the seven churches in the <char style="it">Roman province of </char>Asia:
        grace be to you and peace from He Who was, Who is, and Who is to come, and from the seven spirits that
        are right in front of His throne, <verse eid="REV 1:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 1:5" />and from Jesus Christ, the Faithful Witness, the first-born from the dead, and the ruler of the kings
        of the earth.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="REV 1:5">To him who loved us and who by his blood detached us from our sins, <verse eid="REV 1:5"/>
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 1:6" />and who made us <char style="it">into</char> a kingdom, <char style="it">into </char>personal attendants<char
        style="sup">[A]</char> to his Father-figure-God<char style="sup">[c]</char>—to him be the glory and the
        power forevermore. So be it<char style="sup">[d]</char>.<verse eid="REV 1:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 1:7" />Look!—he’s breaking through<char style="sup">[e]</char> the clouds
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 1:7">And every <char style="it">set of </char>eyes will see him,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 1:7">Even those who pierced him,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 1:7">And all the tribes of the earth<char style="sup">[B]</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 1:7">Upon <char style="it">seeing</char> him will thump <char style="it">their chests</char> <char style="it">in
        mourning</char>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 1:7"></para>
    <para style="m" vid="REV 1:7">…Yes, indeed. Let it be so<char style="sup">[d]</char>.<verse eid="REV 1:7"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 1:8" /><char style="wj">”I am the Alpha and the Omega…,” says the Lord God, “…the One Who exists, the One Who
        was, and the One Who’s coming: the Almighty.”</char><verse eid="REV 1:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 1:9" />I, John, your comrade<char style="sup">[f]</char> and co-worker in the tribulation, kingdom, and perseverance
        in Jesus, wound up on the island<char style="sup">[g]</char> of Patmos because of the word of God and
        the solemn declaration of <char style="it">things pertaining to</char> Jesus. <verse eid="REV 1:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 1:10" />I found myself in the Spirit<char style="sup">[C]</char> on a Sunday<char style="sup">[h]</char> and
        heard behind me a loud voice like a trumpet <char style="it">does when it sounds</char> <char style="it">an
        alert </char><verse eid="REV 1:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 1:11" />saying, <char style="wj">“Write down what you see in a scroll and send it to the seven churches: Ephesus,
        Smyrna, Pergamum, Thyatira, Sardis, Philadelphia, and Laodicea.”</char><verse eid="REV 1:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 1:12" />I turned <char style="it">around </char>so I could be facing the voice while it was speaking to me. Once
        I turned <char style="it">around</char> I saw seven golden lamps, <verse eid="REV 1:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 1:13" />and in the middle of the lamps I saw something equivalent to the ideal embodiment of a human being<char
        style="sup">[i]</char>, wearing a long robe that went down to his feet and wearing a golden sash around
        his chest. <verse eid="REV 1:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 1:14" />His head and his hair were as white as white wool—as <char style="it">white as </char>snow—and his eyes
        were like wheels of fire <char style="it">which turned around and around. </char><verse eid="REV 1:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 1:15" />His feet were the same as copper or bronze as it’s being melted in a furnace, and his voice is like a
        voice composed of a large volume of rushing water<char style="sup">[j]</char>. <verse eid="REV 1:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 1:16" />He had seven stars in his right hand, and from his mouth was a sharp, protruding, two-edged sword (a
        4 foot/120cm long Thracian sword), and his face shined like the sun when it’s at its maximum intensity.<verse eid="REV 1:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 1:17" />When I saw him, I fell at his feet as though I was dead. He put his right hand on me while saying, <char
        style="wj">“Don’t be afraid. I’m the first and the last </char><verse eid="REV 1:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 1:18" /><char style="wj">and the living one. I happened to die and—as you can see—I’m alive forever and ever,
        and I have the keys to the mysterious world of death</char><char style="sup">[D]</char><char style="wj">.
        </char><verse eid="REV 1:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 1:19" /><char style="wj">So write what you see and that which is and that which is going to come to pass after
        these things. </char><verse eid="REV 1:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 1:20" /><char style="it"><char style="wj">As far as </char></char><char style="wj">the mystery of the seven stars
        which are in my right hand and the seven golden lamps: the seven stars are </char><char style="it"><char
        style="wj">men who utter prophesies or deliver sermons </char></char><char style="wj">(agents or messengers)
        at the seven churches, and the lamps are the seven churches.”</char><verse eid="REV 1:20" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">post-haste</char>…Lit: <char style="it">quickly</char>. This doesn’t necessarily mean
        that he’s coming soon; it means that he’ll travel quickly when he does come, like a thief in the night.
        Ref. usage of <char style="it">quickly </char>with regard to travelling in 1 Cor. 4:19.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">statement of Jesus</char>…Lit: <char style="it">testimony of Jesus. </char>This phrase
        is repeated throughout Revelation.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Father-figure-God</char>…Lit: <char style="it">God and Father</char>. This is a hendiadys;
        ref. note of Matt. 3:11.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">so be it</char>…<char style="it">Let it be so…</char>Lit: <char style="it">amen. </char>Ref.
        note of Rev. 19:4.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">breaking through</char>…Lit: <char style="it">coming with</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrade</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brother</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">on the island</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in the island</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">on a Sunday</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in the Lord-day</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">ideal embodiment of a human being</char>…Lit: <char style="it">a son of man</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a large volume of rushing water</char>…Lit: <char style="it">many waters</char>. Like
        the sound a waterfall makes.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">personal attendants</char>…Lit: <char style="it">priests</char>. In this context, a
        priest is one who carries out the ritualistic duties demanded by the holy presence of the Almighty, similar
        to how priests in the OT had duties in the temple.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">tribes of the earth</char>…Using the word <char style="it">tribes</char> as a metonymy
        for the present-day ethnic groups and nations; the assumption being that all ethnic groups and nations
        were spawned by a single, specific tribe at their inception, in the same as is recorded in the OT, Gen.
        10 in particular.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">in the Spirit</char>…A strong presence of the Holy Spirit (1 Cor. 12:3) comes upon a
        person, often accompanied by some sort of prophetic utterance.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[D]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[D]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">mysterious world of death</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the death and the Hades</char>.
        A reference to death as alluded to in the OT and to death as portrayed by Greek mythology. As Christians,
        John and those who read the revelation will take this as a figure of speech, as they are taught in heaven
        vs. hell mythology (mythology meaning the understanding of the components in the unseen world, not a
        fictitious story).</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 1" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  2   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="REV 2" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 2:1" /><char style="wj">”Write the following to the agent in the Ephesus church:</char>
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="REV 2:1"><char style="wj">“The one who holds the seven stars in his right hand says, ‘</char><char style="it"><char
        style="wj">From</char></char><char style="wj"> the one who walks in the midst of the seven golden lamps:
        </char><verse eid="REV 2:1"/>
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 2:2" /><char style="wj">I know your deeds and </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">not just that but </char></char><char
        style="wj">your toil and perseverance, and the fact that you won’t tolerate evil men. You scrutinize
        and push back against those who call themselves apostles—but aren’t—and discover that they’re liars.
        </char><verse eid="REV 2:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 2:3" /><char style="wj">You have perseverance and endure on account of my reputation and everything I stand
        for</char><char style="sup">[a]</char><char style="wj">, and you haven’t become worn out </char><char
        style="it"><char style="wj">over it</char></char><char style="wj">. </char><verse eid="REV 2:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 2:4" /><char style="wj">That aside—I have an issue with you, that you’ve abandoned—divorced in fact—your Original
        Love. </char><verse eid="REV 2:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 2:5" /><char style="wj">So remember the place from where you’ve fallen, have a change of heart and of ways</char><char
        style="sup">[b]</char><char style="wj">, and act the way you used to. If you don’t, I’m </char><char
        style="it"><char style="wj">going to</char></char><char style="wj"> come to you and remove your lamp
        from its </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">normal resting </char></char><char style="wj">place—if
        you don’t have a change of heart and of ways.</char><verse eid="REV 2:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 2:6" /><char style="wj">”’That aside, you say this, that you hate what the Nicolaitans do; I hate what they
        do as well.’</char><verse eid="REV 2:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 2:7" /><char style="wj">”He says, ’If you’re able to listen </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">and take
        to heart what is said</char></char><char style="wj">, hear what</char><char style="sup">[c]</char><char
        style="wj"> the Spirit is saying to the churches: to him who overcomes I’ll grant that he eats from the
        tree of life, the one in God’s paradise.’”</char><verse eid="REV 2:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 2:8" /><char style="wj">”Write the following to the agent in the Smyrna church:</char>
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="REV 2:8"><char style="wj">“The first and the last, the one who appeared </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">back
        </char></char><char style="wj">from the dead and lived </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">again</char></char><char
        style="wj"> says, </char><verse eid="REV 2:8"/>
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 2:9" /><char style="wj">‘I know your ordeal and your poverty (no—you are rich) and the blasphemy from those
        who consider themselves to be Jews but aren’t but instead are a group from Satan</char><char style="sup">[d]</char><char
        style="wj">. </char><verse eid="REV 2:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 2:10" /><char style="wj">Don’t fear anything that you’re going to suffer. Look now—the devil is going to toss
        six of you in jail in order to put pressure on you to break you, and your ordeal will last for six days.
        Show yourself</char><char style="sup">[e]</char><char style="wj"> to be faithful to the point of death,
        and I’ll give you the victor’s wreath of life.</char><verse eid="REV 2:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 2:11" /><char style="wj">”’If you’re able to listen and take to heart what is said, hear what the Spirit is saying
        to the churches: there’s no way at all that the overcomer will be harmed by the Second Death.’”</char><verse eid="REV 2:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 2:12" /><char style="wj">”Write the following to the agent in the Pergamum church:</char>
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="REV 2:12"><char style="wj">“He who owns the sharp, two-edged Thracian sword</char><char style="sup">[f]</char><char
        style="wj"> says, </char><verse eid="REV 2:12"/>
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 2:13" /><char style="wj">’I know where you reside: </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">it’s </char></char><char
        style="wj">where the Citadel</char><char style="sup">[g]</char><char style="wj"> of Satan </char><char
        style="it"><char style="wj">is. </char></char><char style="wj">You hold fast to my reputation and everything
        I stand for and refused to deny my faith during the days of Antipas, my Faithful Witness, who was killed,
        taken from you, where Satan resides.</char><verse eid="REV 2:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 2:14" /><char style="wj">”’That aside, I have a bit of an issue with you, that you have some there who adhere
        to the doctrine of Balaam, who taught Balak to contrive and implement a plan that would attract and thereby
        lure the Israelites (and—boy—weren’t they your typical Israelites?) into sin</char><char style="sup">[h]</char><char
        style="wj">, </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">specifically </char></char><char style="wj">to
        eat food sacrificed to idols and to commit fornication. </char><verse eid="REV 2:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 2:15" /><char style="wj">In the same manner, you also have some there who likewise adhere to the doctrine of
        the Nicolaitans. </char><verse eid="REV 2:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 2:16" /><char style="wj">So have a change of heart and of ways. If you don’t, I’ll come in a hurry and engage
        you in combat using my mouth’s Thracian sword.</char><verse eid="REV 2:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 2:17" /><char style="wj">’”If you’re able to listen and take to heart what is said, hear what the Spirit is saying
        to the churches: I’ll give hidden manna (</char><char style="it"><char style="wj">i.e. the bread which
        God sent each day from the sky to feed Israel</char></char><char style="wj">) to the one who overcomes
        and will give him a voting ballot, one that casts a vote in his favor, and one that has a new name written
        on the ballot</char><char style="sup">[A]</char><char style="wj">, one which nobody knows except for
        the one receiving it.’”</char><verse eid="REV 2:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 2:18" /><char style="wj">”Write the following to the agent in the Thyatira church:</char>
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="REV 2:18"><char style="wj">“The Son of God, the one has eyes like wheels of fire </char><char style="it"><char
        style="wj">which turn around and around</char></char><char style="wj">, and whose feet are the same as
        bronze or copper melting in a furnace,</char><char style="it"><char style="wj"> </char></char><char style="wj">says,
        </char><verse eid="REV 2:18"/>
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 2:19" /><char style="wj">’I know your deeds, and the your love, your faith, that you do the right thing, and
        your perseverance, and that your deeds lately have been more abundant than the ones you did when first
        starting out. </char><verse eid="REV 2:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 2:20" /><char style="wj">That aside, I have something against you, that you allow the woman Jezebel, the one
        who calls herself a prophetess, </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">to do what she does. </char></char><char
        style="wj">She teaches, deceives, and leads astray My Servants, </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">enticing
        them</char></char><char style="wj"> to commit adultery and to eat food sacrificed to idols. </char><verse eid="REV 2:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="REV 2:21" /><char style="wj">I gave her a certain amount of time to have a change of heart and of ways, and she isn’t
        willing to change from her </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">ways of </char></char><char style="wj">fornication.
        </char><verse eid="REV 2:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="REV 2:22" /><char style="wj">See here—I’m going to cause her to be bedfast</char><char style="sup">[i]</char><char
        style="wj">, she and those committing adultery with her—I’ll cause them to undergo an extreme ordeal,
        if they choose not to change their ways. </char><verse eid="REV 2:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="REV 2:23" /><char style="wj">And her devotees</char><char style="sup">[j]</char><char style="wj">—I’ll cause them
        to die an awful, agonizing death</char><char style="sup">[k]</char><char style="wj">. And everyone in
        the church will put the pieces together and understand that I myself am the one who delves into and examines
        minds and hearts, and will pay each of you all commensurate with your deeds.</char><verse eid="REV 2:23" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="REV 2:24" /><char style="wj">”’Now I say to you others in Thyatira, those who don’t adhere to her teaching, those
        in particular who haven’t had close, intimate relations (as they say) with the deep things of Satan:
        I won’t burden you with anything more</char><char style="sup">[B]</char><char style="wj">. </char><verse eid="REV 2:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="REV 2:25" /><char style="wj">However, hold fast to what you have up until I happen to arrive. </char><verse eid="REV 2:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="REV 2:26" /><char style="wj">And he who overcomes and he who is diligent to put into practice my deeds until it’s
        all said-and-done…</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 2:26"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 2:26"><char style="wj">“’I’ll give him authority over the nations</char><verse eid="REV 2:26"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="REV 2:27" /><char style="wj">And will shepherd (rule) them with an iron staff</char>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 2:27"><char style="wj">As the clay pots are broken into pieces</char><verse eid="REV 2:27"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="REV 2:28" /><char style="wj">”’As I too have received from my Father, I will give him the Early Morning Star (</char><char
        style="it"><char style="wj">i.e. Venus as it appears at night</char></char><char style="wj">). </char><verse eid="REV 2:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="REV 2:29" /><char style="wj">If you’re able to hear and take to heart what is said, listen to what the Spirit is
        telling the churches.’”</char><verse eid="REV 2:29" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">my reputation and everything I stand for</char>…Lit: <char style="it">my name</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a change of heart and of ways</char>…Lit: <char style="it">repent</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">if you’re able to listen and take to heart what is said, hear what…</char>Lit: <char
        style="it">he who has ears to hear, let him hear</char>. Ref. Matt. 11:15.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a group from Satan</char>…Lit: <char style="it">a coming-together</char> [or, <char
        style="it">synagogue</char>] <char style="it">of Satan</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">show yourself</char>…Lit: <char style="it">become</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Thracian sword</char> …Ref. Rev. 1:16</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Citadel</char>…Lit: <char style="it">throne</char> </char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">to contrive and implement a plan that would attract and thereby lure the Israelites
        (and—boy—weren’t they your typical Israelites?) into sin</char>…Lit: <char style="it">cast a stumbling
        block before the sons of Israel</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">cause her to be bedfast</char>…Lit: <char style="it">cast her onto a bed</char>. An
        expression.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">her devotees</char>…Lit: <char style="it">her children</char>. It’s inferred from the
        use of the word <char style="it">children</char> in 1 John, 2 John, and 3 John that these are not her
        actual children.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I’ll cause them to die an awful, agonizing death</char>…Lit<char style="it">: I’ll kill
        using death</char>. A figure of speech.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a voting ballot, one that casts a vote in his favor, and one that has a new name written
        on the ballot</char>…Lit: <char style="it">a white pebble</char>…<char style="it">and upon the pebble
        a new name</char>. Liberties taken. The pebble referred to by John is a pebble used for voting; white
        is a vote for a candidate and black is a vote against a candidate.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I won’t burden you with anything more</char>…Lit: <char style="it">I won’t toss another
        burden upon you</char>. An expression, likely a metaphor which compares a person to a beast of burden,
        a pack animal which is already loaded with materials to carry and its master refuses to weigh it down
        with any more materials.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 2" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  3   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="REV 3" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 3:1" /><char style="wj">”Write the following to the agent in the Sardis church:</char>
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="REV 3:1"><char style="wj">“The one who has the seven Spirits of God and the seven stars says, ‘I know your deeds,
        that you have a reputation for being </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">spiritually</char></char><char
        style="wj"> alive, but </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">in fact</char></char><char style="wj">
        you’re </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">spiritually </char></char><char style="wj">dead</char><char
        style="sup">[a]</char><char style="wj">. </char><verse eid="REV 3:1"/>
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 3:2" /><char style="wj">Get ahold of yourself and stay focused, and reestablish what hasn’t been affected yet
        that’s in the process of dying out</char><char style="sup">[b]</char><char style="wj">; for I do not
        deem your works adequate to be presented before my God and undergo His intense scrutiny</char><char style="sup">[c]</char><char
        style="wj">. </char><verse eid="REV 3:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 3:3" /><char style="wj">So remember how it is you have come to receive </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">and
        take to heart the word of God</char></char><char style="wj">, and how you have heard and complied with
        it all, and have a change of heart and of ways</char><char style="sup">[d]</char><char style="wj">. So
        if you choose not to stay focused, I’ll come like a thief, and there’s no way at all you’ll be able to
        figure out what time I’ll burglarize</char><char style="sup">[e]</char><char style="wj"> you.</char><verse eid="REV 3:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 3:4" /><char style="wj">”’That aside, you have a few reputable people in Sardis who haven’t gotten their clothing
        dirty and will walk about with me in white clothing, because they’re worthy. </char><verse eid="REV 3:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 3:5" /><char style="wj">The one who overcomes in this way will be clothed in white, and there’s no way whatsoever
        that I’ll delete the name </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">of such a person</char></char><char
        style="wj"> from the Book of Life, and I’ll confess his name before the Father, in His very presence,
        and before His angels</char><char style="sup">[A]</char><char style="wj">.</char><verse eid="REV 3:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 3:6" /><char style="wj">”’If you’re able to hear and take to heart what is said, listen to what</char><char
        style="sup">[f]</char><char style="wj"> the Spirit is telling the churches.’”</char><verse eid="REV 3:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 3:7" /><char style="wj">”Write the following to the agent in the Philadelphia</char><char style="sup">[B]</char><char
        style="wj"> church:</char></para>
    <para style="p" vid="REV 3:7"><char style="wj">“The worthy one, the true one, the one who has the David-key, the one who opens </char><char
        style="it"><char style="wj">doors </char></char><char style="wj">and nobody shuts, and shuts and nobody
        opens, says, </char><verse eid="REV 3:7"/>
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 3:8" /><char style="wj">‘I know your works. Take a look—I’ve given you an open door and put it right in front
        of you, a door which no one can shut, since you have a little power and have kept my system of thought</char><char
        style="sup">[g]</char><char style="wj">, and have not denied what I stand for</char><char style="sup">[h]</char><char
        style="wj">.</char><verse eid="REV 3:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 3:9" /><char style="wj">Look now—I’m permitting—indeed, causing</char><char style="sup">[i]</char><char style="wj">—those
        from the synagogue of Satan (those who consider themselves to be Jews, but aren’t, but are liars instead)—look—I’ll
        make it so they’ll have to come and humble themselves before your feet, and they’ll understand that I
        love you. </char><verse eid="REV 3:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 3:10" /><char style="wj">Since you’ve adhered to </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">what </char></char><char
        style="wj">my idea of perseverance </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">is</char></char><char style="sup">[j]</char><char
        style="wj">, I too will keep you safe from the moment of trial, which will put the pressure on all those
        who inhabit the earth and reveal what comes out of them: good or bad. </char><verse eid="REV 3:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 3:11" /><char style="wj">I’m coming post-haste. Hold tight to what you have, so that nobody can take the victor’s
        trophy</char><char style="sup">[k]</char><char style="wj"> from you. </char><verse eid="REV 3:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 3:12" /><char style="wj">I’ll make him who overcomes a pillar in my God’s temple, and there’s no chance that
        he’ll ever again leave it </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">and be forced to stay</char></char><char
        style="wj"> outside. I’ll write my God’s name upon him</char><char style="sup">[C]</char><char style="wj">
        and the name of God’s city, the new Jerusalem, which is coming down out of the sky from my God, and will
        write my New Name.</char><verse eid="REV 3:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 3:13" /><char style="wj">”’If you’re able to hear and take to heart what is said, listen to what the Spirit is
        telling the churches.’”</char><verse eid="REV 3:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 3:14" /><char style="wj">”Write the following to the agent in the Laodicea church:</char>
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="REV 3:14"><char style="wj">“The so-be-it</char><char style="sup">[l]</char><char style="wj">, the Faithful and
        True Witness, the beginning of God’s creation says, </char><verse eid="REV 3:14"/>
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 3:15" /><char style="wj">’I know your works, that you’re neither cold nor hot. Oh, how I’d prefer that you were
        cold or hot, </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">one or the other</char></char><char style="wj">.
        </char><verse eid="REV 3:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 3:16" /><char style="wj">The way things are, that you’re neither cold nor hot—you’re lukewarm—I’m going to spit
        you out of my mouth, </char><verse eid="REV 3:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 3:17" /><char style="wj">because you say, “I’m rich, and I’ve reached the point where I’m rich enough that I
        don’t need anything.” But you don’t know that you’re wretched, pitiable, poor, blind, and naked. </char><verse eid="REV 3:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 3:18" /><char style="wj">I recommend that you buy gold from me</char><char style="sup">[D]</char><char style="wj">
        which has been purified by heating it up and melting it, buy white clothing from me so that you can cover
        your body with it, and the shame caused by your nakedness won’t be publicized, and buy eye ointment from
        me to rub on your eyes so you’ll be able to see. </char><verse eid="REV 3:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 3:19" /><char style="wj">As many as I happen to take a liking to, I point out their flaws and correct them the
        way a parent would a child. So be eager to have a change of heart and of ways. </char><verse eid="REV 3:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 3:20" /><char style="wj">See here—I’m standing at the door and knocking. If someone happens to hear my </char><char
        style="it"><char style="wj">knocking </char></char><char style="wj">sound and open the door, I’ll enter
        on into his home and have </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">an enjoyable </char></char><char style="wj">dinner
        with him, and he’ll </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">do the same</char></char><char style="wj">
        with me. </char><verse eid="REV 3:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="REV 3:21" /><char style="wj">To the overcomer I’ll grant that he be seated with me by my throne, as I too have conquered
        and have overcome and was seated with my Father by His throne.</char><verse eid="REV 3:21" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="REV 3:22" /><char style="wj">”’If you’re able to hear and take to heart what is said, listen to what the Spirit is
        telling the churches.’”</char><verse eid="REV 3:22" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">you have a reputation for being spiritually alive, but in fact you’re spiritually dead</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">you have a name that you live and you are dead</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Get ahold of yourself and stay focused, and reestablish what hasn’t been affected yet
        that’s in the process of dying out</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Become watchful and establish the remaining
        things that are going to die. </char>Ref. Matt 24:42 for similar rendering of word <char style="it">watchful</char>.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">for I do not deem your works adequate to be presented before my God and undergo His
        intense scrutiny</char>…Lit: <char style="it">I have not found your works fulfilled before my God</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a change of heart and of ways</char>…Lit: <char style="it">repent</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">burglarize you</char>…Lit: <char style="it">come upon you</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">if you’re able to hear and take to heart what is said, listen to what…</char>Lit: <char
        style="it">he who has ears to hear, let him hear</char>. Ref. Matt. 11:15.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">system of thought</char>…Lit: <char style="it">word</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">what I stand for</char>…Lit: <char style="it">my name</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">permitting—indeed, causing</char>…Lit: <char style="it">granting</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">my idea of what perseverance is</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the word of my perseverance</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">trophy</char>…Lit: <char style="it">wreath</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">so-be-it</char>…Lit: <char style="it">amen</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">his Angels</char>…Angels are affiliated with the holiness of God, and God uses them
        as attendants in the same way that priests used to attend to the temple in Jerusalem. They are bystanders,
        in other words, so they hear anything which is presented before God’s throne.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Philadelphia</char>…The Quakers named the city of Philadelphia in Pennsylvania after
        the city this church was in, as they aspired to emulate this church, since the church received all praise
        and no censure.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I’ll write my God’s name upon him</char>…The significance of writing a name on a person
        is that it puts a stamp of approval on a person, and additionally advertises that approval to everyone.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[D]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[D]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">buy gold from me</char>…An elaborate metaphor of buying purified gold, clothing, and
        eye ointment from Jesus. The buying aspect is to allow God to do His work in one’s life, rather than
        for a person to attempt it on his own. The purified gold represents trials which are allowed in one’s
        life, the purpose of which is, in the pressure exerted by them, to remove life’s impurities. White clothing
        represents righteousness that’s received by God and not a righteousness generated out of one’s own efforts.
        The eye ointment allows one to see plainly what the issues are in one’s life, seeing what should already
        be obvious.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 3" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  4   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="REV 4" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 4:1" />After all of this I looked, and—just like that—a door up in the sky had been opened, and the first voice
        I heard was speaking to me like a trumpet <char style="it">does when sounding an alert</char>, saying,
        “Come up here and I’ll show you what must come to pass after these things.” <verse eid="REV 4:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 4:2" />Immediately I wound up in <char style="it">the</char> Spirit and—just like that—a throne was situated
        there in the sky, and someone was sitting on the throne, <verse eid="REV 4:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 4:3" />and the one sitting looked like <char style="it">he was made of</char> stone, of jasper and sardius,
        and a rainbow that looked just like emerald went around the throne. <verse eid="REV 4:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 4:4" />And twenty-four <char style="it">smaller </char>thrones surrounded the <char style="it">one </char>throne,
        and upon the <char style="it">smaller </char>thrones were seated twenty-four elders<char style="sup">[A]</char>
        dressed in white and upon their heads were golden laurels, victors’ crowns. <verse eid="REV 4:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 4:5" />Out of the <char style="it">one</char> throne came thunder and lightning. Seven lamps of fire burned
        before the throne, and these are the seven Spirits of God. <verse eid="REV 4:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 4:6" />And before the throne there was a glass lake like crystal.
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="REV 4:6">In the midst of the throne and around the throne were four animal-like creatures, with eyes all over
        them on the front and on the back. <verse eid="REV 4:6"/>
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 4:7" />The first creature was like a lion, the second like a calf, the third had the face of a man, the fourth
        was like a flying eagle. <verse eid="REV 4:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 4:8" />And each one of the four creatures had six wings, and they were full of eyes around them and inside of
        them. Day and night they never stopped saying,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 4:8"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 4:8">Holy, holy, holy</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 4:8">Lord God Almighty</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 4:8">Who was, Who is, Who’s coming<verse eid="REV 4:8"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 4:9" />And when the creatures give glory, honor, and thanksgiving to the One seated on the throne, to the One
        who lives forever and ever, <verse eid="REV 4:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 4:10" />the twenty-four elders fall <char style="it">and prostrate themselves </char>before the One sitting on
        the throne and worship the One who lives forever and ever, and toss their wreaths before the throne saying,<verse eid="REV 4:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 4:11" />You are worthy, our Lord God
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 4:11">To receive the glory, the honor, and the power</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 4:11">Because You created all things</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 4:11">And by means of Your will</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 4:11">They were <char style="it">determined to be </char>and were created<verse eid="REV 4:11"/>
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">elders</char>…In the time of Jesus and for years prior to that, Israel had a national
        tribunal of judges known as the Sanhedrin over all of Israel, and there were lesser such tribunals that
        ruled over each city. This pattern of having a tribunal board is replicated in John’s vision.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 4" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  5   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="REV 5" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 5:1" />And I saw a scroll in the right hand of the of the One sitting on the throne, and the scroll <char style="it">was
        full of writing </char>on both the front and back sides and was sealed <char style="it">shut</char><char
        style="sup">[A]</char><char style="it"> </char>with seven seals. <verse eid="REV 5:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 5:2" />I saw a powerful angel proclaiming in a loud voice, “Who’s worthy to break the seals and open the scroll<char
        style="sup">[B]</char>?” <verse eid="REV 5:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 5:3" />They kept trying to find someone who was able to, and they couldn’t find anyone in heaven, on the earth,
        nor in the underworld <char style="it">of death</char><char style="sup">[a]</char><char style="it"> </char>to
        open the scroll or to <char style="it">even</char> look at it. <verse eid="REV 5:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 5:4" />They proceeded to weep intensely since nobody was found worthy enough to open the scroll or to <char
        style="it">even </char>look at it. <verse eid="REV 5:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 5:5" />But one of the elders <char style="it">then </char>tells me, “Don’t cry. Look here—the lion of the tribe
        of Judah, <char style="it">from </char>the shoot<char style="sup">[b]</char> of David, has prevailed
        <char style="it">in earning the right</char> to break the seven seals and open the scroll.”<verse eid="REV 5:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 5:6" />In the midst of the throne and the four creatures and in the midst of the elders, I saw a lamb standing
        there looking as though he had been slain, having seven horns seven eyes, which are the Seven Spirits
        of God which have been sent out all over the planet. <verse eid="REV 5:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 5:7" />He came and took what was in the right hand of the One sitting on the throne, <verse eid="REV 5:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 5:8" />and when he took the scroll, the four creatures and the twenty-four elders fell <char style="it">and
        prostrated themselves </char>before the lamb, each of them having a harp and a golden vial of incense,
        which are the prayers of those who are holy<char style="sup">[c]</char>. <verse eid="REV 5:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 5:9" />And they sing a new song saying <char style="it">in it</char>,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 5:9"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 5:9">You are worthy to take the scroll</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 5:9">And to break open its seals</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 5:9">Because you were slain and with your blood</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 5:9">Purchased for God those</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 5:9">From among every clan<char style="sup">[d]</char>, language, culture<char style="sup">[e]</char>, and
        ethnicity.<verse eid="REV 5:9"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 5:10" />And you made them into a priestly kingdom<char style="sup">[f]</char> for our God,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 5:10">And they will reign upon the earth.<verse eid="REV 5:10"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 5:11" />I looked and heard a sound of many angels surrounding the throne and of the creatures and elders. There
        were millions and millions and billions and billions<char style="sup">[C]</char> in number, <verse eid="REV 5:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 5:12" />all saying in a loud voice,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 5:12"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 5:12">Worthy is the slain lamb to receive</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 5:12">The power and wealth and wisdom and strength</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 5:12">And honor and glory and thanksgiving <char style="it">due him</char><verse eid="REV 5:12"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 5:13" />I heard all of creation that’s in the sky, on the earth, below the earth, on top of the sea, and beneath
        the sea saying,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 5:13"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 5:13">To the One sitting upon the throne and to the lamb</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 5:13"><char style="it">Be </char>the thanksgiving, honor, glory, might</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 5:13">Forever and ever<verse eid="REV 5:13"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 5:14" />The four creatures proceeded to say, “So be it<char style="sup">[g]</char>,” and the elders fell <char
        style="it">and prostrated themselves </char>and offered up worship.<verse eid="REV 5:14" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">in heaven, on the earth, nor in the underworld of death</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in
        the sky</char> [<char style="it">heaven</char>] <char style="it">upon the earth nor under the earth</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">shoot</char>…Lit: <char style="it">root</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">those who are holy</char>…Or: <char style="it">the saints</char>; <char style="it">those
        who’ve been set apart by God</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">clan</char>…Lit: <char style="it">tribe</char>. Ref. note of Rev. 1:7</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">culture</char>…Or: <char style="it">folk-people</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">priestly kingdom</char>…Lit: <char style="it">kingdom and priests</char>. A hendiadys.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">so be it</char>…Lit: <char style="it">amen</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">sealed shut</char>…The seals may have consisted of melted wax which was affixed to the
        scroll after it had been tightly rolled up. Before the wax cooled and hardened, the seal was stamped
        to give it an inscription. After the wax cooled, the scroll could not be unfurled, and the scroll thereby
        read, unless the wax was broken. Therefore, the seals served two purposes. First, they ensured that the
        scroll had never been read before. Second, the inscription was proof of the scroll was genuinely written
        by whomever claimed to have written it. Ref. note of 2 Cor. 1:22.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">break the seals and open the scroll</char>…Lit: <char style="it">open the scroll and
        break the seals</char>. The assumption is that the literal wording of opening the scroll and breaking
        the seal is backwards, being an expression of a sort, and that the reader at the time would take this
        for granted. This is analogous to us telling a child, “Put on your shoes and socks,” which we don’t mean
        for the child to do it in that order, but to put on the socks first before putting on the shoes.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">millions and millions and billions and billions</char>…Lit: <char style="it">ten-thousand
        ten-thousands and thousands of thousands</char>. This is more of an expression than a precise numbering.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 5" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  6   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="REV 6" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 6:1" />And I looked when the lamb broke<char style="sup">[a]</char><char style="it"> </char>one of the seven
        seals, and I heard one of the four creatures in a voice like thunder say, “Come!” <verse eid="REV 6:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 6:2" />…And I looked and—like that—a white horse <char style="it">appeared</char>, and the one mounted on it
        had a bow, and he had been given a victor’s wreath, and he went forth conquering and attempting to conquer.<verse eid="REV 6:2" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 6:3" />When he broke the second seal, from out of<char style="it"> </char>the second creature I heard, “Come!”<verse eid="REV 6:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 6:4" />…And another horse, a red one, <char style="it">appeared</char>, and the one mounted on it was granted
        to take the peace <char style="it">away </char>from the planet, so that people will kill each other,
        and he was given a large sword.<verse eid="REV 6:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 6:5" />When he broke the third seal, from out of the third creature I heard, “Come!” …And I looked and—like
        that—a black horse <char style="it">appeared</char>, and the one mounted on it had a scale in his hand.<verse eid="REV 6:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 6:6" />I heard a voice in the midst of the four creatures saying, “<char style="it">Set the price of</char>
        wheat at $100 per quart/950 ml and barley at $35 per quart<char style="sup">[A]</char>, and don’t tamper
        with <char style="it">the prices of olive </char>oil and wine.”<verse eid="REV 6:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 6:7" />When he opened the fourth seal, I heard the fourth creature’s voice say, “Come!” <verse eid="REV 6:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 6:8" />…And I looked and—like that—a pale horse <char style="it">appeared, </char>and the one mounted on it
        is named Death and trailing just behind him is Graveyard<char style="sup">[b]</char>. They were given
        control of one-quarter of the Earth, to kill it by sword, by famine, by the plague, and by indigenous
        wild animals.<verse eid="REV 6:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 6:9" />When the fifth seal was broken, I saw the lives of those who had been slain on account of the word of
        God and the profession of faith that they maintained, which was public knowledge<char style="sup">[c]</char>,
        under the altar. <verse eid="REV 6:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 6:10" />A loud voice cried out, “Just how long, Holy and True Master, will You continue to refrain from delivering
        a verdict that will vindicate and avenge our blood, taking it out on Earth’s <char style="it">current
        </char>inhabitants?” <verse eid="REV 6:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 6:11" />Each of them was given a white robe, and they were told that they’ll <char style="it">have to </char>wait
        a bit longer yet, until the quota is filled with their fellow-servants, their comrades, and those who
        are going to be killed like they too were.<verse eid="REV 6:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 6:12" />I looked when the sixth seal was broken, and a severe earthquake occurred, and the sun turned as black
        as burlap made out of hair, and the whole moon turned into something<char style="it"> </char>like <char
        style="it">the color of </char>blood, <verse eid="REV 6:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 6:13" />and the stars in the <char style="it">night </char>sky fell to the ground like a fig tree shedding its
        unripe figs when shaken by a strong wind, <verse eid="REV 6:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 6:14" />and the sky split apart like a scroll getting rolled up, and every mountain and every island in their
        vicinity was displaced. <verse eid="REV 6:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 6:15" />The kings of the Earth, the high-status noblemen, the generals, the wealthy, the mighty, the slaves and
        the free hid themselves in caves and in the rocks of the mountains. <verse eid="REV 6:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 6:16" />They <char style="it">then proceed to </char>say to the mountains and to the rocks, “Fall on us and hide
        us from the undivided attention<char style="sup">[d]</char> of the One sitting on the throne and from
        the wrath of the lamb, <verse eid="REV 6:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 6:17" />because the Great Day of their wrath has arrived, and who can withstand it?”<verse eid="REV 6:17" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">broke</char>…Lit: <char style="it">opened</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Graveyard</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Hades</char>. Some liberties taken.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the profession of faith that they maintained, which was public knowledge</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">their testimony</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">undivided attention</char>…Lit: <char style="it">face</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Set the price of</char> <char style="it">wheat at $100 per quart/950ml and barley at
        $35 per quart</char>…Lit: <char style="it">a quart of wheat for a denarius three quarts of barley for
        a denarius</char>. A denarius is a day’s wage and a quart of wheat is a day’s ration. Ref. note of Matt.
        18:28.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 6" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  7   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="REV 7" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 7:1" />After these things I saw four angels standing at the four corners of the earth, holding back the four
        winds of the earth, so that the winds couldn’t blow over the land, over the sea, or over any forest.<verse eid="REV 7:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 7:2" />And I saw another angel coming over from the East, where the sun rises, having the living God’s seal
        <char style="it">of approval</char>, and he shouted to the four angels in a loud voice, the angels who
        were granted to trash the land and the sea, <verse eid="REV 7:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 7:3" />“Don’t trash the land, the sea, or the forests until we get to put a seal <char style="it">of approval</char>
        upon the foreheads of God’s servants.” <verse eid="REV 7:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 7:4" />And I heard what the number of those who were sealed is—144,000—sealed from among all the sons of Israel:<verse eid="REV 7:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 7:5" />From the tribe of Judah: 12,000
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:5">From the tribe of Reuben: 12,000</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:5">From the tribe of Gad: 12,000<verse eid="REV 7:5"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 7:6" />From the tribe of Asher: 12,000
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:6">From the tribe of Naphtali: 12,000</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:6">From the tribe of Manasseh: 12,000<verse eid="REV 7:6"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 7:7" />From the tribe of Simeon: 12,000
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:7">From the tribe of Levi: 12,000</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:7">From the tribe of Issachar: 12,000<verse eid="REV 7:7"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 7:8" />From the tribe of Zebulon: 12,000
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:8">From the tribe of Joseph: 12,000</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:8">From the tribe of Benjamin: 12,000<verse eid="REV 7:8"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 7:9" />After these things I looked and—like that—a large crowd, the size of which is unknown, from every ethnicity,
        clan, culture, and language was brought to stand before the throne and before the lamb, and they were
        clothed in white robes and had palm branches in their hands, <verse eid="REV 7:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 7:10" />and were crying out in a loud voice,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:10"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:10">The protection <char style="it">we enjoy we attribute </char>to our God</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:10">Who’s seated upon the throne</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:10">And by the lamb<verse eid="REV 7:10"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 7:11" />And all the angels who were stood around the throne, the elders, and the four creatures fell on their
        faces before God and worshipped Him <verse eid="REV 7:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 7:12" />saying,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:12"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:12">We heartily agree:<char style="sup">[a]</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:12">The blessing, the glory, the wisdom, the thanksgiving,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:12">The honor, the power, and the might</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:12"><char style="it">We attribute </char>to our God forever and ever.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:12">So be it.<verse eid="REV 7:12"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 7:13" />One of the elders reflected upon this and said to me,
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="REV 7:13">“These people who are wearing the white robes—who are they and what are they all about<char style="sup">[b]</char>?”<verse eid="REV 7:13"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 7:14" />I told him, “My good fellow<char style="sup">[c]</char>, you know <char style="it">the answer</char>.”
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="REV 7:14">And he told me, “These are the ones coming out of the Great Tribulation and who have washed their robes
        by bleaching them in the blood of the lamb.”<verse eid="REV 7:14"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 7:15" />Because of this they are before God’s throne
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:15"><char style="it">In His very presence, the center of His attention</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:15">And perform a worship of religious service to Him</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:15">Day and night in His temple.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:15">And the one sitting on the throne</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:15">Will set up camp among them<char style="sup">[d]</char>.<verse eid="REV 7:15"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 7:16" />They will not ever again hunger or thirst,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:16">Nor will the sun beat down upon them</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:16">Nor any <char style="it">scorching</char> heat,<verse eid="REV 7:16"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 7:17" />Because the lamb on high in the midst of the throne
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:17">Shepherds them and will take them</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:17">Down a path to a spring of living water,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 7:17">And God has wiped every tear away from their eyes.<verse eid="REV 7:17"/>
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">we heartily agree</char>…Lit: <char style="it">amen. </char>Ref. note of 18:4.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">what are they all about</char>…Lit: <char style="it">whence they came</char>. Ref. note
        of Luke 13:25.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">my good fellow</char>…Lit: <char style="it">my lord</char>. Some liberties taken.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Will set up camp among them</char>…Lit: <char style="it">will pitch His tent</char>
        [<char style="it">will tabernacle</char>] <char style="it">upon them</char>. Some liberties taken.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 7" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  8   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="REV 8" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 8:1" />When he broke<char style="sup">[a]</char> the seventh seal, it became silent in heaven for about a half-hour.<verse eid="REV 8:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 8:2" />And I saw the seven angels who stand before God, and seven trumpets were given to them.<verse eid="REV 8:2" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 8:3" />Another angel who had in his possession a golden incense dispenser<char style="sup">[b]</char> came and
        was <char style="it">ushered over and </char>made to stand<char style="sup">[A]</char> upon<char style="sup">[c]</char>
        the altar. He was given a lot of incense so that he would offer up upon<char style="sup">[c]</char> the
        golden altar that is before God <char style="it">incense </char>in the form of the prayers of all the
        set-apart-people<char style="sup">[d]</char>. <verse eid="REV 8:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 8:4" />And the smoke of the incense which consists of the prayers of the set-apart-people went up from the hand
        of the angel who was before God. <verse eid="REV 8:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 8:5" />And the angel <char style="it">methodically and</char> <char style="it">deliberately</char> took the
        incense dispenser and filled it with some of the hot coals from the altar and flung it on the ground,
        and thunder and lightning, various sounds, and an earthquake occurred.<verse eid="REV 8:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 8:6" />The seven angels who have the seven trumpets got ready to sound alerts by blowing the trumpets. <verse eid="REV 8:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 8:7" />The first one blew his trumpet and it hailed, as fire mixed in with blood was hurled to the earth. A
        third of the trees were incinerated as well as all of the grass which was still growing<char style="sup">[e]</char>.<verse eid="REV 8:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 8:8" />The second angel blew his trumpet, and something like a huge mountain consisting of a burning coal was
        thrown into the sea, and a third of the sea turned into blood, <verse eid="REV 8:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 8:9" />and a third of the living creatures in the sea died, and a third of the ships were destroyed.<verse eid="REV 8:9" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 8:10" />The third angel blew his trumpet, and a huge star burning like a torch fell from the sky and onto a third
        of the rivers and upon the springs of waters. <verse eid="REV 8:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 8:11" />The star’s called Bitter-Flavoring<char style="sup">[f]</char>: a third of the water became bitter, and
        many people died from the water, because it became poisonous due to its having been made bitter.<verse eid="REV 8:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 8:12" />The fourth angel blew his trumpet, and a third of the sun, a third of the moon, and a third of the stars
        were struck, for the purpose of causing a third of them to go dark and causing no light to shine during
        the day a third of the time and likewise <char style="it">neither moonlight nor starlight a third of
        the time </char>at night.<verse eid="REV 8:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 8:13" />I looked, and I heard a certain vulture<char style="sup">[g]</char> flying very high up in the sky<char
        style="sup">[B]</char> saying in a loud voice, “Woe, woe, woe to the inhabitants of the Earth from the
        sounds of the remaining trumpets which the three angels are going to blow.<verse eid="REV 8:13" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">broke</char>…Lit: <char style="it">opened</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">incense dispenser</char>…Lit: <char style="it">censer</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">upon</char>…Or: <char style="it">at</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the set-apart-people</char>…Or: <char style="it">saints</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">grass which was still growing</char>…Lit: <char style="it">green grass</char>. <char
        style="it">Green</char> is rendered <char style="it">freshly-cut </char>in Luke 23:31.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Bitter-Flavoring</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Wormwood</char>. This is an actual plant.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">vulture</char>…Or: <char style="it">eagle</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">ushered over and made to stand</char>…Here in this passage are some of the brass tacks
        that Ray Summers in his book <char style="it">Worthy Is the Lamb</char> claimed were grammatical mistakes.
        The verb <char style="it">stand </char>here is in the passive voice but most translations, such as the
        NASB, translate it as active. The word <char style="it">give </char>in v. 3 translated <char style="it">offer
        up</char> is future tense but should be subjunctive. The words <char style="it">the prayers </char>is
        in the dative case, which is unexpected. In v. 5 the verb <char style="it">to take </char>is in the perfect
        tense, but is used like it’s aorist. Some observations on the claim that these are grammatical errors.
        First, looking at John’s contributions to the NT as a whole and not just at Revelation individually,
        Revelation is the only book with these kinds of errors. In the grammatical incidences enumerated from
        this passage, it’s hard to imagine that these would not have been mistakes caused by ignorance of the
        language. Now, grammatical mistakes are made when someone’s careless, perhaps writing while he’s tired
        or writing in too much of a hurry. And that may be the case. But inspecting a couple of the verb forms
        which are listed here, the passive form of <char style="it">to stand </char>and the perfect form of <char
        style="it">to take </char>are less common than the expected forms. Someone who’s sloppy, careless, or
        rushed would use the more common forms instead of the less common. So what’s the conclusion? Perhaps
        John couldn’t remember some of the forms of words and knew that the reader would be able to figure it
        out. Or he understood what he was writing and deliberately chose to write it and these are not mistakes.
        This leaves a translator with the task of figuring out what he meant on a case-by-case basis.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">very</char> <char style="it">high up in the sky</char>…Lit: <char style="it">mid-heaven</char>.
        In NT times, the sky and heaven as we know it were conflated into one, and there were multiple layers
        (many say there were seven). Progressing through these layers, one goes from the atmosphere surrounding
        us; to very high up in the sky; to where the sun and the stars are; then from there into the various
        layers of heaven, which presumably include paradise and the throne of God. According to such a gradation
        scheme, mid-heaven would be half-way through, and therefore very high up in the sky, perhaps even in
        their minds near where the stars are. Seeing that v. 13 mentions a vulture (or perhaps an eagle), vultures
        (and eagles for that matter) have been known to fly as high as 37,000 feet/11,275 meters). </char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 8" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  9   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="REV 9" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 9:1" />The fifth angel blew his horn, and I saw a star which had fallen and landed on the Earth, and he (<char
        style="it">the star</char>) was given the key to the bottomless pit. <verse eid="REV 9:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 9:2" />He opened the bottomless pit, and smoke came out of the pit, like smoke from a gigantic furnace. The
        sun was blotted out by the fumes from the smoke which came from the pit. <verse eid="REV 9:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 9:3" />From out of the smoke locusts went forth over the land, and they were granted capabilities that even
        scorpions don’t have. <verse eid="REV 9:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 9:4" />They were told not to harm the grass, nor any of the greenery, nor any of the trees—<char style="it">only
        to harm </char>the people who don’t have God’s seal upon their foreheads. <verse eid="REV 9:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 9:5" />They were not granted <char style="it">permission </char>to<char style="it"> </char>kill them, but instead
        <char style="it">were granted permission </char>to torment them for five months—and the pain<char style="sup">[a]</char>
        they inflict is like when a scorpion stings a person. <verse eid="REV 9:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 9:6" />When that time comes around, people will wish they were dead but will not be so lucky, and they’ll feel
        like they’re dying but death is nevertheless evading them.<char style="sup">[b]</char><verse eid="REV 9:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 9:7" />The locusts looked like horses dressed for battle. Upon their heads was something like a golden cap<char
        style="sup">[c]</char>; their faces were like the face of a person; <verse eid="REV 9:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 9:8" />they had hair like a woman’s hair; their teeth were like a lion’s teeth; <verse eid="REV 9:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 9:9" />and they had breastplates like iron. The sound they made when flying sounds like a multitude of horses
        charging into battle. <verse eid="REV 9:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 9:10" />They have tails like scorpions with stingers in them<char style="it">, </char>and they were given a mandate
        to hurt people with their tails for five months. <verse eid="REV 9:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 9:11" />A king rules over them, the angel of the abyss; his name in Hebrew is Abaddon and in Greek is Apollyon
        (<char style="it">i.e. Destruction</char>).<verse eid="REV 9:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 9:12" />The first woe is over; look out, there’s two more woes coming!<verse eid="REV 9:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 9:13" />The sixth angel blew his trumpet, and I heard a voice from the four horns of the golden altar which is
        before God <verse eid="REV 9:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 9:14" />say, “To the sixth angel who has the trumpet: release the four angels who are on top of<char style="sup">[d]</char>
        the Greater Euphrates River who’ve been restrained.” <verse eid="REV 9:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 9:15" />And the four angels who had been prepared for this very moment<char style="sup">[e]</char> to kill a
        third of mankind were released. <verse eid="REV 9:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 9:16" />The number of soldiers in the cavalry was two hundred million—that’s the number I heard. <verse eid="REV 9:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 9:17" />This is what the horses and the cavalry soldiers mounted on them looked like in the vision: they have
        red, purple, and yellow breastplates, and the horses’ hair is like a lion’s hair, and fire, smoke, and
        <char style="it">a sulfurous residue known as</char> brimstone comes out of their mouths.<verse eid="REV 9:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 9:18" />From these three curses one-third of mankind was killed—from the fire, smoke, and brimstone which comes
        out of their mouths; <verse eid="REV 9:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 9:19" />the fact is, the horses’ power is in their mouths and in their tails, seeing that their tails are like
        a snake having a head to inflict harm with. <verse eid="REV 9:19" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 9:20" />The remainder of mankind who weren’t killed by these curses didn’t repent either of the deeds of their
        hands, so that they wouldn’t worship demons and idols of gold, silver, and copper, those things that
        can neither see, hear, or walk around. <verse eid="REV 9:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="REV 9:21" />They wouldn’t repent of their murders, their recreational drug use<char style="sup">[f]</char>, their
        fornication, or their thievery.<verse eid="REV 9:21" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">pain</char>…Lit: <char style="it">torment</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">people will wish they were dead but will not be so lucky, and they’ll feel like they’re
        dying, but death is nevertheless evading them</char>…Lit: <char style="it">people will seek death and
        the will not find it, and they’ll feel like they’re dying and death flees from them</char>. Two similar
        expressions; the repetition of both is a figure of speech.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">caps</char>…Or: <char style="it">crowns; wreaths</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">on top of</char>…Or: <char style="it">at</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">this very moment</char>…Lit: <char style="it">hour and day and month</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">recreational drug use</char>…Also includes drug dealing; creating new kinds of illicit
        drugs; witchcraft; sorcery. Ref. note of Gal. 5:20.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 9" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 10   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="REV 10" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 10:1" />I saw another angel, a powerful one, coming down out of the sky with a cloud wrapped around him<char
        style="sup">[a]</char> and a rainbow on his head. His face was like the sun, and his feet were like pillars
        of fire. <verse eid="REV 10:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 10:2" />In his hand was a little scroll which had been opened. He put his right foot on the sea and his left
        on the land, <verse eid="REV 10:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 10:3" />and cried out in a loud voice just like a roaring lion. When he cried out, the seven thunders spoke their
        own voices. <verse eid="REV 10:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 10:4" />And when the seven thunders spoke, I was about to start writing <char style="it">it down</char>, and
        I heard a voice from the sky say, “Record the fact that what the seven thunders spoke is genuine<char
        style="sup">[b]</char>, but don’t write down <char style="it">what they said</char>.”<verse eid="REV 10:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 10:5" />The angel whom I saw standing on sea and land raised his right hand all the way up <verse eid="REV 10:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 10:6" />and swore an oath by Him who lives forever and ever, Who created the sky and the things in it, the land
        and the things in it, and the sea and the things in it, that there’ll be no further delay. <verse eid="REV 10:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 10:7" />To the contrary, <char style="it">it’ll take place </char>in the timeframe<char style="sup">[c]</char>
        of the voice of the seventh angel, when he’s about to blow his trumpet and God’s mystery will be concluded<char
        style="sup">[d]</char>, <char style="it">and it will turn out</char> the way He proclaimed the glowing
        details to His own servants the prophets.<verse eid="REV 10:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 10:8" />The voice which I heard from out of the sky proceeded to speak to me once again, “Go over and take the
        opened book which is in the hand of the angel standing on sea and land.” <verse eid="REV 10:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 10:9" />I left and went to the angel to tell him to give me the little scroll, and he <char style="it">then </char>says
        to me, “Take it and eat it. It will upset your stomach<char style="sup">[e]</char>, but will be as sweet
        as honey in your mouth.” <verse eid="REV 10:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 10:10" />I took the little scroll from the angel’s hand and ate it all up, and it was as sweet as honey in my
        mouth, but when I swallowed it, it upset my stomach. <verse eid="REV 10:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 10:11" />They <char style="it">then </char>tell me, “You must yet again prophesy in about many cultures, ethnicities,
        languages, and kings.”<verse eid="REV 10:11" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a cloud wrapped around him</char>…Or: <char style="it">clothed in a cloud</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Record the fact that what the seven thunders spoke is genuine</char>…Lit: <char style="it">seal
        that which the seven thunders spoke</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">timeframe</char>…Lit: <char style="it">days</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">will be concluded</char>…Lit: <char style="it">was concluded</char>. Unexpected use
        of a verb tense; ref. note o8:3.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">it will upset your stomach</char>…Lit: <char style="it">it makes bitter your stomach</char></char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 10" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 11   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="REV 11" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 11:1" />I was given a yardstick the size of a staff, while being told, “Get up and measure the temple of God,
        the altar, and the worshippers in it, <verse eid="REV 11:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 11:2" />but exclude the outer courtyard from the measurement, since it’s been given to the Gentiles<char style="sup">[A]</char>;
        the Holy City will be treated with utter contempt<char style="sup">[a]</char> for 42 months. <verse eid="REV 11:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 11:3" />And I will give the nod<char style="sup">[b]</char> to my two witnesses and they will prophesy for 1260
        days <char style="it">while</char> <char style="it">dressed</char> in burlap <char style="it">signifying
        mourning</char><char style="sup">[c]</char>.”<verse eid="REV 11:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 11:4" />These individuals are the two olive trees and the two lamps which stand before the Lord of the Earth.<verse eid="REV 11:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 11:5" />And if at any given moment someone wants to harm them, fire comes out of their mouths and devours their
        enemies. And if at any given moment someone would want to harm them, this someone must be killed in this
        manner.<char style="sup">[B]</char> <verse eid="REV 11:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 11:6" />These individuals have the authority to plug up the sky, so that it won’t rain over the timespan which
        they specify in prophesy, and they have authority over the waters to turn them into blood and <char style="it">over
        the land </char>to smite the land with any kind of calamity, should they so desire.<verse eid="REV 11:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 11:7" />When they do finish their public declaration<char style="sup">[d]</char>, the beasts which come up out
        of the abyss will wage war with them, defeat them, and kill them. <verse eid="REV 11:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 11:8" />Their corpses <char style="it">will be left lying </char>on the main boulevard of the Great City, which,
        from a spiritual perspective, is called That Worldly Land of Captivity Sodom<char style="sup">[e]</char>,
        also where the Lord was crucified. <verse eid="REV 11:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 11:9" />And <char style="it">various ones</char> from among the cultures, the clans, the languages, and the ethnicities
        <char style="it">will</char> <char style="it">then </char>see their corpses for three-and-a-half days
        and won’t be permitted to lay their bodies in a tomb. <verse eid="REV 11:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 11:10" />The inhabitants of the Earth will rejoice over them and be glad, and they’ll exchange gifts with one
        another, because this pair of prophets tormented the inhabitants of the Earth.<verse eid="REV 11:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 11:11" /><char style="it">I watched events unfold.</char><char style="sup">[C]</char><char style="it"> </char>After
        the three-and-a-half <char style="it">days</char>, a spirit of life<char style="sup">[D]</char> <char
        style="it">sent </char>from God entered them, and they stood on their feet, and a tremendous sort of
        fear fell upon those watching <char style="it">what was happening to </char>them. <verse eid="REV 11:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 11:12" />They heard a loud voice from out of the sky, originating from heaven, say to them, “Come up here,” and
        they went up into the sky in the cloud <char style="it">used to transport them</char>, and their enemies
        watched them. <verse eid="REV 11:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 11:13" />Just about then, a severe earthquake occurred, a tenth of the city collapsed<char style="sup">[f]</char>,
        seven thousand citizens<char style="sup">[g]</char> were killed by the earthquake, and the remainder
        became fearful and finally admitted to their guilt<char style="sup">[h]</char>.<verse eid="REV 11:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 11:14" />The second woe is over; look out—the third woe comes right on its heels!<verse eid="REV 11:14" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 11:15" />The seventh angel blew his trumpet, and loud voices started to be heard in heaven saying,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 11:15"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 11:15">The kingdom of the established order of our Lord</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 11:15">Has come to pass,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 11:15">And of His Messiah, the Christ.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 11:15">And He will reign forever and ever.<verse eid="REV 11:15"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 11:16" />The twenty-four elders who are seated upon their thrones before God fell on their faces and worshipped
        God <verse eid="REV 11:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 11:17" />saying,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 11:17"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 11:17">We thank you Lord God Almighty</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 11:17">Who is and Who was,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 11:17">Because You have taken your Great, Miraculous Power</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 11:17">And have <char style="it">begun to</char> reign <char style="it">with it.</char><verse eid="REV 11:17"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 11:18" />And the nations became enraged,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 11:18">And Your wrath came,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 11:18">And <char style="it">with it </char>the right time<char style="sup">[i]</char> for the dead to be judged</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 11:18">And to give to Your servants the prophets</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 11:18">The wage <char style="it">they earned</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 11:18">And to the set-apart-people<char style="sup">[j]</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 11:18">And to the nobodies<char style="sup">[l]</char> and the great</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 11:18">Who are awestruck by who You are<char style="sup">[k]</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 11:18">And to destroy those who are destroying the Earth.<verse eid="REV 11:18"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 11:19" />God’s heavenly temple was opened, the ark of His covenant was seen in His temple, and thunder and lightning,
        earthquakes, and hailstone occurred.<verse eid="REV 11:19" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">treated with utter contempt</char>…Lit: <char style="it">trampled under foot</char>.
        An expression. Ref. note of Matt. 5:13.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">give the nod</char>…Lit: <char style="it">grant</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">burlap signifying mourning</char>…Lit: <char style="it">sackcloth</char>. Ref. note
        of Matt. 11:21.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">public declaration</char>…Lit: <char style="it">witness</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">That Worldly Land of Captivity Sodom</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Sodom and Egypt</char>.
        A hendiadys.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a tenth of the city collapsed</char>…Lit:<char style="it"> a tenth of the city fell</char>.
        It’s unclear whether the city physically fell due to the earthquake or their inhabitants died—or both.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">citizens</char>…Lit: <char style="it">names of men</char>. Or, <char style="it">well-known
        individuals</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">finally admitted to their guilt</char>…Lit: <char style="it">gave glory to the God of
        heaven</char>. An idiom; ref. note of John 9:24.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">right time</char>…Lit: <char style="it">season</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the set-apart-people</char>…Or: <char style="it">the saints</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">by who You are</char>…Lit: <char style="it">of Your name</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">nobodies</char>…Lit: <char style="it">small</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">exclude the outer courtyard from the measurement, since it’s been given to the Gentiles</char>…The
        reason for measuring the temple is to confirm that it complies with God’s exacting standards of perfection,
        a prerequisite for His approval, and assuming it does, God will condescend to dwell in it. When God dwells
        in it, it will receive His protection. Now, the outer courtyard is not measured since God will not dwell
        in it, just as in the second temple at the time of Jesus Gentiles were allowed in that outer courtyard.
        Furthermore, the outer courtyard extends into the Holy City, which does not receive God’s protection.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">And if at any given moment someone wants to harm them, fire comes out of their mouth
        and devours their enemies. And if at any given moment someone would want to harm them, he must be killed
        in this manner</char>…Two consecutive conditional sentences, where the conditional clauses are almost
        identical. The conditional clauses differ in the verb tense for the verb <char style="it">to want. </char>The
        repetition of these clauses and sentences is a figure of speech used throughout the Bible. The shift
        in the verb tense of <char style="it">to want </char>is a figure of speech called a <char style="it">polyptoton</char>.
        The subtlety of this polyptoton is additional evidence that John’s weird use of verb tenses is idiomatic
        rather than the result of carelessness or neglect. Ref. note of 8:3.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I watched events unfold</char>…This interpolation was inserted for the benefit of the
        reader, as, generally speaking, the verbs in subsequent passage use the past tense, whereas in the previous
        they were using the future.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[D]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[D]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">spirit of life</char>…In this context, the word <char style="it">spirit </char>does
        not refer to an angelic spirit, but refers to a supernatural, physical refreshing. See usage of <char
        style="it">spirit </char>in other verses such as 1 Pet. 3:4.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 11" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 12   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="REV 12" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 12:1" />A great portent was seen in heaven: a woman clothed in the sun<char style="sup">[a]</char>, the moon
        under her feet, a crown with twelve stars on her head, <verse eid="REV 12:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 12:2" />and with a baby in her womb, screaming because of labor pains, the agony of giving birth. <verse eid="REV 12:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 12:3" />I saw another portent in heaven, and—out of nowhere—a huge red dragon with seven heads and ten horns
        and with ornamental headbands<char style="sup">[b]</char> on his head. <verse eid="REV 12:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 12:4" />His tail swept a third of the stars, dragging them <char style="it">until he’d completely gotten ahold
        of them</char><char style="sup">[A]</char>, and flung them to the Earth.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="REV 12:4">The dragon stood before the woman who was about to give birth, so that he could devour the child when
        she gives birth. <verse eid="REV 12:4"/>
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 12:5" />She gave birth to a son—a male<char style="it">-child</char>—who would <char style="it">some day </char>shepherd
        (rule) every nation with an iron staff<char style="sup">[B]</char>. Her child was snatched away from
        her <char style="it">and taken </char>to God and to His throne. <verse eid="REV 12:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 12:6" />The woman fled to the backcountry, where nobody was around, where, <char style="it">by God’s direction</char>,
        a place in it had been prepared for her, so that she would be taken care of<char style="sup">[c]</char>
        for 1260 days, allowing her to recuperate.<verse eid="REV 12:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 12:7" />A war occurred in heaven: Michael and his angels waged war with the dragon, and the dragon and his angels
        waged war <char style="it">against him. </char><verse eid="REV 12:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 12:8" />But he was not powerful enough, nor could he establish a foothold in heaven<char style="sup">[d]</char>,<verse eid="REV 12:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 12:9" />and the Great Dragon, the Ancient Serpent, the one called “Slanderer” (i.e. “the Devil”)—yes indeed:
        Satan—the one who deceives the entire inhabited world—he was driven to the Earth, and his angels too
        were driven out with him. <verse eid="REV 12:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 12:10" />I heard a loud voice in heaven saying,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 12:10"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 12:10">The end of our misery<char style="sup">[e]</char>, the security, the power,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 12:10">The kingdom of our God,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 12:10">And the authority of His Messiah, His Christ</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 12:10">Starts right now,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 12:10">Since our comrades’<char style="sup">[f]</char> accuser has been driven <char style="it">out,</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 12:10">The one who accuses them before our God day and night.<verse eid="REV 12:10"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 12:11" />And they defeated him by means of the lamb’s blood
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 12:11">And the logic of his solemn declaration<char style="sup">[g]</char>.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 12:11">They didn’t love their life</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 12:11"><char style="it">Even </char>to the point of death.<verse eid="REV 12:11"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 12:12" />On account of this be glad:
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 12:12"><char style="it">You </char>the sky, the atmosphere, outer space, and heaven</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 12:12">And those who are camped out<char style="sup">[h]</char> in you—</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 12:12">Woe to the land and sea</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 12:12">Because the devil’s <char style="it">headed</char> your way filled with rage,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 12:12">Knowing that he has <char style="it">only </char>a small window of time <char style="it">left</char>.<verse eid="REV 12:12"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 12:13" />And when the dragon saw that he was driven to the Earth, he pursued the woman who gave birth to the man-child.<verse eid="REV 12:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 12:14" />The woman was given a pair of giant vulture<char style="sup">[i]</char> wings, so that she could fly
        to the place set aside for her in the backcountry, where she is taken care of three-and-a-half years<char
        style="sup">[j]</char>, kept away from the serpent’s single-minded focus<char style="sup">[k]</char>.<verse eid="REV 12:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 12:15" />The serpent spewed water like a river from his mouth, going after the woman by making a torrent that
        would sweep her away; <verse eid="REV 12:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 12:16" />but the land came to the woman’s aid: the ground opened its mouth and drank the river up which the dragon
        spewed out of his mouth. <verse eid="REV 12:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 12:17" />The dragon became furious with the woman and went off to wage war with the remainder of her offspring,
        those who keep God’s commandments and who have something to attest to as far as Jesus is concerned<char
        style="sup">[l]</char>.<verse eid="REV 12:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 12:18" />And <char style="it">the dragon</char> stood on the seashore<char style="sup">[C]</char>…<verse eid="REV 12:18" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">clothed in the sun</char>…Or: <char style="it">with</char> <char style="it">the sun
        wrapped around her</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">ornamental headbands</char>…Or: <char style="it">diadems</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">she would be taken care of</char>…Lit: <char style="it">they would take care of her</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">nor could he establish a foothold in heaven</char>…Lit: <char style="it">nor was a place
        found for them in heaven</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the end of our misery, the security, and the power of his reign…</char>Lit: <char style="it">the
        salvation and the power</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the logic of his solemn declaration</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the word of his testimony</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">camped out</char>…Lit: <char style="it">setting up camp</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">giant vulture wings</char>…Or: <char style="it">wings of the Great Eagle</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">three-and-a-half years</char>…Lit: <char style="it">season and season and half-season</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">single-minded focus</char>…Lit: <char style="it">face</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">have something to attest to as far as Jesus is concerned</char>…Lit: <char style="it">have
        the testimony of Jesus</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">swept third of the stars, dragging them until he’d completely gotten ahold of them</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">drags a third of the stars</char>. Note the present tense <char style="it">drags </char>in
        the GT. Although <char style="it">drags </char>is present tense in form, it is past tense in meaning;
        this is a figure of speech. The interpolation <char style="it">until he’d completely gotten ahold of
        them </char>reflects the additional meaning that the figure of speech is communicating. Ref. note of
        John 1:5.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">shepherd every nation with an iron staff</char>…The metaphor of a shepherd is used throughout
        the Bible: a shepherd is a leader; someone who occupies a king-like position of authority. The staff
        being iron indicates the firmness and totality of the shepherd’s rule.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">stood on the seashore</char>…This is the starting sentence of the first paragraph of
        chapter 13</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 12" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 13   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="REV 13" />
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 13:1" />…<char style="sup">[A]</char>And I saw a beast come out of the sea, one who has ten horns, seven heads,
        and seven ornamental headbands<char style="sup">[a]</char> on his horns, and I saw the name “blasphemy”
        on his heads. <verse eid="REV 13:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 13:2" />The beast which I saw was like a leopard, his feet were like bear <char style="it">claws</char>, and
        his mouth was like a lion’s mouth. The dragon gave him his power, his throne, and extensive authority.<verse eid="REV 13:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 13:3" />One of his heads seemed to be mortally wounded<char style="it"> by having had its throat slit</char>,
        but his mortal wound had been successfully treated. The whole earth was in total awe of the beast<char
        style="sup">[b]</char>, <verse eid="REV 13:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 13:4" />and they worshipped the dragon because he gave the <char style="it">previously mentioned </char>authority
        to the beast, and they worshipped the beast saying, “Who can match the beast, and who can go to war with
        him <char style="it">and stand a chance against him</char>?”<verse eid="REV 13:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 13:5" />He was given a mouth to speak completely over-the-top blasphemies<char style="sup">[c]</char>, and he
        was given authority to act for forty-two months. <verse eid="REV 13:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 13:6" />He opened his mouth to blaspheme God, to blaspheme His reputation, everything He stands for, the place
        He calls home, and those who call heaven home<char style="sup">[d]</char>. <verse eid="REV 13:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 13:7" />He was granted to wage war with the set-apart-people<char style="sup">[e]</char> and to conquer them,
        and he was granted authority over every clan, every culture, those who share a common dialect, and every
        ethnic group. <verse eid="REV 13:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 13:8" />Everyone on the planet will worship him, <char style="it">that is </char>all those whose names haven’t
        been recorded in the Lamb’s Book of Life from day-one<char style="sup">[f]</char>, the lamb who was slain.<verse eid="REV 13:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 13:9" />A word to the wise is sufficient<char style="sup">[g]</char>:<verse eid="REV 13:9" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 13:10" />If someone <char style="it">is destined </char>to captivity,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 13:10">To captivity he heads.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 13:10">If someone <char style="it">is </char>to be killed by a sword,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 13:10">Killed by a sword <char style="it">he</char> <char style="it">will.</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 13:10"></para>
    <para style="m" vid="REV 13:10">There you have it: the perseverance and the faith of the set-apart-people.<verse eid="REV 13:10"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 13:11" />I saw another beast come out of the ground, and he had two horns like a lamb but talks like a dragon.<verse eid="REV 13:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 13:12" />He exercises all the first beast’s authority under his supervision<char style="sup">[h]</char>. He makes
        it so that the Earth and those who inhabit it would worship the First Beast, the one who was healed of
        his mortal wound. <verse eid="REV 13:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 13:13" />He performs spectacular miracles<char style="sup">[i]</char>, <char style="it">to the extent </char>that
        he can even make flames come down from out of the sky <char style="it">all the way</char> to the ground
        in front of people. <verse eid="REV 13:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 13:14" />And he deceives the inhabitants of the Earth by means of the miracles that were granted to him under
        the beast’s supervision, telling the inhabitants of the Earth to make a replica of the beast who had<char
        style="sup">[j]</char> the sword wound but lived through it.<verse eid="REV 13:14" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 13:15" />It was granted to him to give life-essence<char style="sup">[k]</char> to the beast’s replica, so that
        the replica could both talk and could cause those who choose not to worship the replica to be killed.<verse eid="REV 13:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 13:16" />And he makes everyone—the nobodies<char style="sup">[l]</char> and the great, the rich and the poor,
        the free and the slave—have a mark put on their right hand<char style="sup">[m]</char> or on their forehead,<verse eid="REV 13:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 13:17" />so that any given person won’t be able to make a purchase or be able to sell <char style="it">a thing</char>
        except if such person has the mark, <char style="it">specifically</char> the beast’s name or the number
        of his name. <verse eid="REV 13:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 13:18" />Here’s the tricky part<char style="sup">[n]</char>: let he who’s mentally proficient <char style="it">in
        dealing with large numbers</char> count the beast’s number, for it is a man’s number, and his number
        is 666<char style="sup">[B]</char>.<verse eid="REV 13:18" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">ornamental headbands</char>…Lit: <char style="it">diadems</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">was in total awe of the beast</char>…Lit: <char style="it">was amazed after the beast</char>.
        The unusual use of the word <char style="it">after </char>indicates that the combination of words is
        likely an expression.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">completely over-the-top blasphemies</char>…Lit: <char style="it">great and blasphemies</char>.
        A hendiadys; ref. note of Matt. 3:11.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">His reputation, everything He stands for, the place He calls home, and all those who
        call heaven home</char>…Lit: <char style="it">His name and His tabernacle and those who tabernacle in
        heaven</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the set-apart-people</char>…Or: <char style="it">the saints</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">day one</char>…Lit: <char style="it">from foundation of world</char>. An expression
        used throughout the NT.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a word to the wise is sufficient</char>…Lit: <char style="it">if someone has an ear,
        let him hear</char>. A favorite expression of Jesus.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">under his supervision</char>…Lit: <char style="it">before him</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">spectacular miracles</char>…Lit: <char style="it">signs</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">had</char>…Lit: <char style="it">has</char>. Ref. note of John 1:4.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">life-essence</char>…Lit: <char style="it">spirit</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">nobodies</char>…Lit: <char style="it">small</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[m]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[m]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">right hand</char>…Or: <char style="it">right wrist</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[n]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[n]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the tricky part</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the cunning-in-one’s-craft</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft">Paragraph begun in the last verse of chapter 12</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">666</char>..Some manuscripts have 616 instead of 666, but the weight of manuscript evidence
        and textual scholarship favors 666 over 616.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 13" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 14   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="REV 14" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 14:1" />I looked and—like that—the lamb was standing there at Mt. Zion and with him 144,000 who have his name
        and the name of his Father written upon their foreheads. <verse eid="REV 14:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 14:2" />I heard a voice from heaven, a voice like a large volume of rushing water<char style="sup">[a]</char>
        and like loud thunder. The voice I heard was like singing-harpists who are singing and playing their
        harps at the same time. <verse eid="REV 14:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 14:3" />They sing a new song before the throne and before the four creatures and the elders. No one was able
        to learn the song except for the 144,000, they who were purchased from the Earth. <verse eid="REV 14:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 14:4" />These are ones who haven’t defiled themselves with women, for they are virgins; these people follow the
        lamb wherever he goes; these people were purchased from mankind, cherry-picked from the pool of all humans
        and offered as the best-of-the-best<char style="sup">[b]</char> to God and to the lamb. <verse eid="REV 14:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 14:5" />No lie is to be found in their mouths; they are without blemish.<verse eid="REV 14:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 14:6" />I saw another angel flying way, way up in the sky<char style="sup">[c]</char> having an eternal proclamation
        of good news to deliver to those sitting on the Earth, to every ethnicity, clan, language, and culture,<verse eid="REV 14:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 14:7" />saying in a loud voice, “Fear God and come clean with Him<char style="sup">[d]</char>, since the time
        for His judgments has arrived. Worship the One who made the sky, the land, the sea, and the springs of
        water.”<verse eid="REV 14:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 14:8" />Another angel—a second one—trailed behind saying, “Fallen! Fallen! Babylon the Great—the one whom all
        nations have drunk from her supply of wine, drinking of the wine of the ferocity of her fornication.”<verse eid="REV 14:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 14:9" />Another angel—a third one—trailed them saying in a loud voice, “If one worships the beast and his replica
        and receives the mark on his forehead or on his hand, <verse eid="REV 14:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 14:10" />this very person drinks from out of the wine of the wrath of God, the undiluted mixture<char style="sup">[A]</char>
        <char style="it">of wine</char> which is in the cup of His wrath, and will be tormented by fire and brimstone
        under the scrutiny of<char style="sup">[e]</char> some holy angels and under the scrutiny of the lamb.<verse eid="REV 14:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 14:11" />The smoke of their torment billows up forever and ever, non-stop day and night, <char style="it">the
        torment of </char>they who worship the beast and his replica, and of any given person if he were to have
        received the mark of his name.”<verse eid="REV 14:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 14:12" />There you have it: the perseverance of the set-apart-people<char style="sup">[f]</char>, those who keep
        God’s commandments and the faith of Jesus.<verse eid="REV 14:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 14:13" />I heard a voice from out of the sky say, “Write <char style="it">this down</char>: ‘Blessed be the dead
        who believe in and serve the Lord<char style="sup">[g]</char> who are killed from here on out. Yes indeed,’
        says the Spirit, ‘so that they might rest from their toil. The fact is, as they parade in, their deeds
        are showcased.<char style="sup">[B]</char>’”<verse eid="REV 14:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 14:14" />I looked, and—out of nowhere—a white cloud <char style="it">appeared</char>, and seated on the cloud
        was someone <char style="it">who</char> <char style="it">looked</char> like a perfectly-proportioned
        man—the ideal man<char style="sup">[h]</char>—possessing a golden crown on his head and a sharp sickle
        in his hand. <verse eid="REV 14:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 14:15" />And another angel came out of the temple while crying out in a loud voice to the one sitting on the cloud,
        “Get out in the field and get to it with the sickle<char style="sup">[i]</char> and reap <char style="it">the
        entire field</char>, because the time has come to reap <char style="it">it entirely</char>, since the
        timing is perfect to reap the earth’s harvest<char style="sup">[C]</char>.” <verse eid="REV 14:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 14:16" />So the man sitting on the cloud took his sickle<char style="sup">[i]</char> <char style="it">down</char>
        to the Earth and reaped the Earth.<verse eid="REV 14:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 14:17" />Another angel came out of the heavenly temple, he too having a sharp sickle of his own. <verse eid="REV 14:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 14:18" />And another angel came out of the altar, the one in control of the flames <char style="it">of the altar</char>
        and in a loud voice hollered to one with the sharp sickle, “Get out there with your sharp sickle and
        gather the grapes from the vineyard of the Earth, because her grape clusters have ripened.” <verse eid="REV 14:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 14:19" />And the angel took his sickle to the Earth and gathered <char style="it">the grapes </char>from the Earth
        and took <char style="it">them</char> to the Great Winepress of God’s wrath. <verse eid="REV 14:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 14:20" />The winepress was tread outside the city<char style="sup">[D]</char>, and blood flowed out of the winepress
        <char style="it">creating a stream </char>about shoulder-high<char style="sup">[j]</char> and stretching
        out 200 miles/300 km<char style="sup">[k]</char>.<verse eid="REV 14:20" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a large volume of rushing water</char>…Lit: <char style="it">many waters</char>. Ref.
        note of 1:15</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">These people were purchased from mankind, cherry-picked from the pool of all humans
        and offered as the best-of-the-best</char>…Lit: <char style="it">These were purchased from mankind a
        first-fruit</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">way, way up in the sky</char>…Lit: <char style="it">mid-heaven</char>. Ref. note of
        8:13</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">come clean with Him</char>…Lit: <char style="it">give Him glory</char>. An expression;
        ref. note of John 9:24.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">under the scrutiny of</char>…Lit: <char style="it">before</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the set-apart-people</char>…Or: <char style="it">the saints</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">who believe in and serve the Lord</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in the Lord</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">someone who looked like a perfectly-proportioned man—the ideal man</char>…Lit: <char
        style="it">the same as a son of man</char>. Ref. note of Matt. 8:20.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Get out in the field and get to it with the sickle…took his sickle</char>…Lit: <char
        style="it">Send</char> <char style="it">your sickle </char>[into the field to work]…<char style="it">cast
        his sickle</char>. A figure of speech, as the sickle itself is not sent but the person swinging it is;
        the sickle is just a tool.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">shoulder-high</char>…Lit: <char style="it">up the horse’s bridle</char>. Liberties taken.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">200 miles/300 km</char>…Lit: <char style="it">1600 stadia</char>. Ref. note of Luke
        24:13.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">undiluted mixture</char>…In ancient times, wine was often times diluted with water.
        The metaphor has God’s wrath at maximum potency.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">The fact is, as they parade in, their deeds are showcased</char>…Lit: <char style="it">For
        their works follow after them</char>. A metaphor to the triumphal entry of a general into a city, with
        the spoils of war carried behind him. Same metaphor used in 1 Tim. 5:24.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">since the timing is perfect to reap the earth’s harvest</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the
        harvest of the earth has dried out</char>. Some liberties taken. The spring rain (the “latter rain”:
        ref. James 5:7, Joel 2:23, Jer. 5:24) arrives at the end of the growing season, and prepares the grain
        for harvest. After receiving the rain, the crop must dry out, otherwise it’ll get moldy. The moment it
        dries is the exact moment to harvest it.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[D]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[D]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the winepress was tread outside the city</char>…In those times, grape juice was extracted
        from grapes by putting the grapes in a vat and having the workers step on them, crushing them, causing
        the juice to seep out of the vat and into a pot or something. In the NT, something done <char style="it">outside
        the city </char>was something which was dirty, messy, or disgusting and consequently should be prevented
        from contaminating the city.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 14" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 15   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="REV 15" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 15:1" />I saw another portent in heaven, huge and quite a sight to see: seven angels with the last of the seven
        plagues, <char style="it">the last </char>because with them God’s wrath is complete.<verse eid="REV 15:1" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 15:2" />I saw something like a glass sea mixed with flames, and the ones who prevailed against the <char style="it">onslaught
        of the </char>beast, against his replica, and against the number of his name standing there at the glass
        sea, in possession of God’s harps. <verse eid="REV 15:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 15:3" />They sang the song of Moses, the servant of God, and the song of the lamb saying,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 15:3"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 15:3">Great and Marvelous <char style="it">are</char> Your works,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 15:3">Lord God Almighty,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 15:3">Righteous and true <char style="it">are</char> Your ways,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 15:3">King of the nations.<verse eid="REV 15:3"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 15:4" />Who does not fear and reverence You
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 15:4">To the utmost extent,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 15:4">To the point of fearing you, Lord?</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 15:4">Because You alone are pious</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 15:4">Since all the nations will come</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 15:4">And worship before You,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 15:4">Since Your righteousness has been made manifest.<verse eid="REV 15:4"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 15:5" />After these things, I looked and <char style="it">saw that </char>the temple housing the <char style="it">Great</char>
        Declaration<char style="sup">[a]</char> in heaven was opened, <verse eid="REV 15:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 15:6" />and the seven angels, the ones in possession of the seven plagues, left the temple clothed in clean,
        bright linen and with golden sashes wrapped around their chests. <verse eid="REV 15:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 15:7" />One of the four creatures gave the seven angels seven golden bowls that were filled to the brim, and
        the source they were filled from is the wrath of the God who lives forever and ever. <verse eid="REV 15:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 15:8" />The temple was filled up with smoke, and the source of the smoke is God’s glory and His power. No one
        was able to enter the temple until the seven plagues of the seven angels happened to finish.<verse eid="REV 15:8" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the temple housing the Great Declaration</char>…Lit<char style="it">: temple of the
        tabernacle of the witness</char></char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 15" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 16   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="REV 16" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 16:1" />I heard a loud voice coming out of the temple telling the angels, “Go forth and pour out the seven bowls
        of God’s wrath onto the Earth.”<verse eid="REV 16:1" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 16:2" />The first one departed and poured out his bowl onto the Earth, and a wicked-bad sore showed up on the
        people who have the mark of the beast and who worship his replica.<verse eid="REV 16:2" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 16:3" />The second one poured out his bowl onto the sea, and it turned into blood, the blood like a dead <char
        style="it">person has,</char> and all living beings in the sea died.<verse eid="REV 16:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 16:4" />The third one poured out his bowl on the rivers and on the springs of water, and <char style="it">the
        water</char> turned into blood. <verse eid="REV 16:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 16:5" />I heard the angel who affected the waters say,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 16:5"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 16:5">You are correct</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 16:5"><char style="it">You</char> Who is and Who was—<char style="it">You</char> Who are pious,<verse eid="REV 16:5"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 16:6" />Because saints’ and prophets’ blood has been spilled,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 16:6">And You’ve given them blood to drink up.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 16:6">They deserve it.<verse eid="REV 16:6"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 16:7" />And from the altar I heard <char style="it">someone</char> say,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 16:7"></para>
    <para style="p" vid="REV 16:7">Yes indeed, Lord God Almighty</para>
    <para style="p" vid="REV 16:7">True and correct <char style="it">are </char>Your judgments<verse eid="REV 16:7"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 16:8" />The fourth one poured his bowl out upon the sun, and it was granted <char style="it">the ability </char>to
        scorch mankind in flames, <verse eid="REV 16:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 16:9" />and mankind was scorched something fierce<char style="sup">[a]</char>. They blasphemed God’s reputation
        and everything He stands for<char style="sup">[b]</char>—He who has control over all these plagues—and
        they wouldn’t have a change of heart and come clean with Him<char style="sup">[c]</char>.<verse eid="REV 16:9" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 16:10" />The fifth one poured his bowl out upon the beast’s throne, and his kingdom <char style="it">suddenly
        </char>darkened, and they proceeded to bite their tongues as a result of the pain <char style="it">caused
        by the angel</char>. <verse eid="REV 16:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 16:11" />As a result of their pain and their sores, they blasphemed the God of heaven, but they wouldn’t stop
        doing the deeds they were doing.<verse eid="REV 16:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 16:12" />The sixth one poured out his bowl upon the Greater Euphrates River, and <char style="it">all </char>its
        water dried up, in order to form the road that the kings <char style="it">who come </char>from the East
        <char style="it">will use</char>. <verse eid="REV 16:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 16:13" />And I saw three harassing, demonic spirits like frogs <char style="it">come </char>out of the dragon’s
        mouth, the beast’s mouth, and the false prophet’s mouth; <verse eid="REV 16:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 16:14" />in fact, the demon spirits perform miracles<char style="sup">[d]</char> that go exactly to the kings
        of the entire inhabited world, to gather them to the war of the Great Day of God Almighty.<verse eid="REV 16:14" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 16:15" />See here now: I’m coming like a thief.
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 16:15">Blessed <char style="it">is</char> he who stays focused<char style="sup">[e]</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 16:15">And retains his clothing</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 16:15">So that he won’t walk about naked</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 16:15">And be exposed to ridicule<char style="sup">[f]</char>.<verse eid="REV 16:15"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 16:16" />And they were gathered to the place called “Armageddon” in Hebrew.<verse eid="REV 16:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 16:17" />The seventh <char style="it">angel</char> poured his bowl out upon the lower atmosphere, and a loud voice
        came out of the temple saying, “It has come into being<char style="sup">[g]</char>,” <verse eid="REV 16:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 16:18" />and thunder and lightning and <char style="it">strange </char>sounds occurred, plus an earthquake occurred—a
        big one—the likes of which have never happened on the Earth before since the beginning of the human race—that’s
        how enormous it was. <verse eid="REV 16:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 16:19" />The Great City split into three parts, and the <char style="it">major </char>cities of the nations fell.
        God wasn’t going to let Babylon the Great slip by and not dole out to her<char style="sup">[h]</char>
        the cup of the wine of his fierce wrath. <verse eid="REV 16:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 16:20" />Everyone living on an island fled, and nobody could be found up in the mountains<char style="sup">[i]</char>.<verse eid="REV 16:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="REV 16:21" />Huge hailstones that weighed about 75 lbs/34 kg<char style="sup">[j]</char> rained down from the sky
        upon mankind, and as a result of the plague of hail, the human race blasphemed God, since the plague
        in and of itself was severe—really severe.<verse eid="REV 16:21" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">mankind was scorched something fierce</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the men were scorched
        a great scorch</char>. The repetition of <char style="it">scorch </char>is a figure of speech, emphasizing
        the scorching.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">God’s reputation and everything He stands for</char>…Lit: <char style="it">His name</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">they wouldn’t have a change of heart and come clean with Him</char>…Lit: <char style="it">they
        wouldn’t repent to give him the glory</char>. <char style="it">Give him the glory</char>: an expression;
        ref. John 9:24 and note there.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">miracles</char>…Lit: <char style="it">signs</char>; <char style="it">omens</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">stays focused</char>…Lit: <char style="it">watches</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">and be exposed to ridicule</char>…Lit: <char style="it">and they’d see his shame. </char>Some
        liberties taken.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">it has come into being</char>…Same verb and same exact form of that verb is rendered
        <char style="it">come into being </char>in the phrase <char style="it">nothing which has come into being</char>
        in John 1:3.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">God wasn’t going to let Babylon the Great slip by and not dole out to her</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">Babylon the Great was remembered before God to give her</char>. A figure of speech.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Everyone living on any island fled, and nobody could be found up in the mountains</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">And all islands fled, and a mountain was not found</char>. Islands is a metonymy for
        those living on it; same for mountains.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">that weighed about 75 lbs./34 kg</char>…Lit: <char style="it">like a talent</char></char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 16" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 17   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="REV 17" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 17:1" />One of the seven angels who has the seven bowls came and spoke with me saying, “Come, I’ll show you the
        verdict rendered against the Great Harlot who sits upon many <char style="it">different </char>waters,<verse eid="REV 17:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 17:2" />she whom the kings of the Earth fornicated with, and she whom the inhabitants of the Earth got drunk
        off the wine of her fornication.” <verse eid="REV 17:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 17:3" />He took me up to an uninhabited, desolate place in the Spirit. I saw a woman sitting on a scarlet beast,
        a beast plastered with blasphemous names, <char style="it">a woman </char>who has seven heads and ten
        horns. <verse eid="REV 17:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 17:4" />The woman was clothed in <char style="it">the </char>purple clothing <char style="it">that the wealthy
        wear </char>and in <char style="it">luxurious </char>scarlet and was adorned in gold, gemstones, and
        pearls and had a golden cup in her hand filled with abominations and with the impurity and sacrilegious
        nature<char style="sup">[a]</char> of her fornication. <verse eid="REV 17:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 17:5" />There was a name written on her forehead—a mystery: “Babylon the Great, the mother of fornicators and
        prostitutes and of the abominations of the Earth.” <verse eid="REV 17:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 17:6" />I saw the woman intoxicated from <char style="it">drinking </char>the blood of the set-apart-people<char
        style="sup">[b]</char> and the blood of those who make statements about Jesus<char style="sup">[c]</char>.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="REV 17:6">Upon seeing her, I was stupefied gawking at her<char style="sup">[d]</char>. <verse eid="REV 17:6"/>
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 17:7" />The angel told me, “What are you gawking at? I’ll explain to you the mystery of the woman and the beast
        that’s bearing her, the one with the seven heads and the ten horns. <verse eid="REV 17:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 17:8" />The beast which you saw came up out of the abyss in the past, is not out of the abyss at the present,
        but is about to come up out of the abyss, and is headed to <char style="it">its own</char> demise<char
        style="sup">[e]</char>. The existing inhabitants of the Earth who don’t have their names written in the
        Book of Life from the beginning of time<char style="sup">[f]</char> seeing the beast will be amazed,
        because the beast came <char style="it">up out of the abyss</char> in the past, is not <char style="it">out
        of it</char> at present, but will be showing up some time in the future.<verse eid="REV 17:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 17:9" />Here’s <char style="it">something for</char> a person who has a mind for intrigue: the seven heads are
        mountains where the woman is sitting. These are seven kings. <verse eid="REV 17:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 17:10" />Five have fallen, one <char style="it">still </char>exists, the other hasn’t come <char style="it">into
        being </char>yet, but when he does in fact come <char style="it">into being</char>, he must remain a
        little while. <verse eid="REV 17:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 17:11" />The beast which came in the past and isn’t present now: it’s the eighth and <char style="it">comes</char>
        out of the seven, and is headed to <char style="it">its own </char>demise. <verse eid="REV 17:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 17:12" />The ten horns that you saw are ten kings who haven’t gotten a kingdom yet, but instead receive from the
        beast authority as kings for one hour. <verse eid="REV 17:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 17:13" />These guys have one purpose, and they give their power and authority to the beast. <verse eid="REV 17:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 17:14" />These guys will go to war with the lamb, and the lamb will conquer them, since <char style="it">he is
        </char>Lord of Lords and King of Kings, and <char style="it">so will </char>those with him: the called,
        the chosen, the faithful.<verse eid="REV 17:14" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 17:15" />He <char style="it">then </char>says to me, “The waters that you saw the harlot sitting on: they are
        cluster after cluster of folk-people<char style="sup">[g]</char>, are nations, and are those who share
        a common dialect. <verse eid="REV 17:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 17:16" />The ten horns which you saw, and the beast included: these guys hate the harlot and will strip her bare
        and have her for lunch<char style="sup">[h]</char>. <verse eid="REV 17:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 17:17" />The fact is, God will cause them to willingly do<char style="sup">[i]</char> His purpose, and that purpose
        is towards one goal <char style="it">only</char>: to give their kingdom to the beast, until <char style="it">such
        a time that</char> God’s ideas be completed. <verse eid="REV 17:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 17:18" />And the woman which you saw is the Great City which has a kingdom <char style="it">built </char>upon
        the kings of the Earth.<verse eid="REV 17:18" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">impurity and sacrilegious nature</char>…Lit: <char style="it">uncleanness</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the set-apart-people</char>…Or: <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">saints</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">those who make statements about Jesus</char>…Lit: <char style="it">witnesses of Jesus</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Seeing her, I was stupefied gawking at her</char>…Lit: <char style="it">I marveled seeing
        her a great marvel. </char>The repetition of marvel is a figure of speech.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">headed to its own demise</char>…Lit: <char style="it">headed to destruction</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">from the beginning of time…</char>Lit: <char style="it">from the foundation of the world</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">cluster after cluster of folk-people</char>…Lit: [<char style="it">folk</char>] <char
        style="it">people and crowds</char>. A hendiadys; ref. note of Matt. 3:11.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">they will strip her bare and have her for lunch</char>…Lit: <char style="it">they will
        make her desolate and naked too and they will eat her fleshes</char>. Two expressions.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">will</char> <char style="it">cause them to willingly do</char>…Lit: <char style="it">gave
        into their hearts to do. </char>Note the past form <char style="it">gave </char>is intended as future,
        not past.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">came up out of the abyss in the past, is not out of the abyss at the present, but is
        about to come up out of the abyss</char>…Lit: <char style="it">was and is not and is about to be coming
        up out of the abyss</char>. This appears to be more of the unpolished, error-ridden writing found throughout
        Revelation.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 17" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 18   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="REV 18" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 18:1" />After these things <char style="it">happened, </char>I saw another angel come down out of the sky, one
        who has great authority and power, and the Earth was illuminated by his majestic splendor<char style="sup">[a]</char>.<verse eid="REV 18:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 18:2" />He cried out in a loud voice,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:2"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:2">Fallen! Fallen is Babylon the Great!</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:2">She has become the haunt of harassing spirits<char style="sup">[b]</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:2">And a prison of all filthy, disgusting<char style="sup">[c]</char> spirits</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:2">And a prison of all filthy, disgusting birds</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:2">And a prison of all filthy, disgusting beasts</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:2">And of all things <char style="it">people </char>have come to hate,<verse eid="REV 18:2"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 18:3" />Because all the nations have gotten drunk
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:3">On the wine of her fornication,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:3">And the kings of the Earth have fornicated with her,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:3">And the merchants of the Earth have gotten rich</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:3">Off the powerful <char style="it">allure</char> of her revelry in luxury.<verse eid="REV 18:3"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 18:4" />And I heard another voice speaking from the sky,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:4"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:4">Come out, my people, from her</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:4">So that you don’t partner with her,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:4">Participating in her sins,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:4">And that you don’t receive a dose of her plagues,<verse eid="REV 18:4"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 18:5" />Because her sins have piled up
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:5"><char style="it">All the way</char> to the sky,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:5">And God has remembered her wrong-doings.<verse eid="REV 18:5"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 18:6" />Pay her back the way she dished it out to you,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:6">And up the ante<char style="sup">[d]</char> according to her deeds.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:6">Using the <char style="it">same </char>cup she did her<char style="it"> </char>mixing in,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:6">Mix a cocktail for her which is twice as concentrated<char style="sup">[A]</char>.<verse eid="REV 18:6"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 18:7" />So much as it glorified her
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:7">And made her revel in luxury,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:7">Give such torment and mourning as that to her.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:7"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:7">Because in her heart she tells herself,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:7">“I’ve been awarded the status of<char style="sup">[e]</char> queen</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:7">And am not a <char style="it">destitute </char>widow,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:7">There’s no way at all that I’ll experience mourning”—<verse eid="REV 18:7"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 18:8" />On account of this,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:8">Her plagues will arrive in one day:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:8">Death, mourning, and famine.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:8">She’ll be purged thoroughly by fire</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:8">Because the Lord God <char style="it">is </char>mighty</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:8">Who judges her.<verse eid="REV 18:8"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 18:9" />The kings of the Earth will weep and thump <char style="it">their chests in mourning</char> over her,
        those who fornicated with her and reveled in her luxury, when they eventually see the smoke of her conflagration,<verse eid="REV 18:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 18:10" />while standing far back because they’re terrified of her torment, saying,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:10"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:10">Woe! Woe <char style="it">to</char> the Great City!</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:10">The Mighty City Babylon—</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:10">Because your judgment arrived in one hour.<verse eid="REV 18:10"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 18:11" />The merchants of the Earth <char style="it">will then</char> cry and mourn over her, because no one <char
        style="it">will</char> buy their inventory<char style="sup">[f]</char> any longer, <verse eid="REV 18:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 18:12" />inventory of gold, of silver, of gemstones, of pearls, of fine linen, of purple, of scarlet, of the fruit
        of the citron tree, of all <char style="it">sorts of </char>chests made of ivory, of all <char style="it">sorts
        of </char>chests made of expensive wood, of copper, of iron, of marble… <verse eid="REV 18:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 18:13" />and cinnamon, exotic spice plants, incense, myrrh, frankincense, wine, olive oil, fine wheat flour, wheat,
        beasts of burden, sheep, horses, chariots, slaves who do manual labor, slaves in general<char style="sup">[g]</char>.<verse eid="REV 18:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 18:14" />And the <char style="it">large pieces of </char>fruit <char style="it">that come in</char> late-summer
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:14">Consisting of your soul’s desire</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:14">Departed from you,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:14">And all the sumptuous and splendid<char style="sup">[h]</char> things</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:14">Disintegrated right in front of you<char style="sup">[i]</char>.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:14">These things will no longer be found—</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:14">No—not a chance.<verse eid="REV 18:14"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 18:15" />Those who trade in these things, the merchants who got rich off her, will stand far back because they’re
        terrified of her torment, <verse eid="REV 18:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 18:16" />saying,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:16"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:16">Woe! Woe <char style="it">to</char> the Great City!</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:16">Clothed in fine linen, in <char style="it">luxurious </char>scarlet,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:16">In <char style="it">the </char>purple <char style="it">clothing that the wealthy wear,</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:16">And adorned in gold, in gemstones, and in pearls<verse eid="REV 18:16"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 18:17" />…Because in one hour such wealth will be wiped out. And every helmsmen and everyone who works the docks<char
        style="sup">[j]</char> and sailors and whoever works in the boating industry stood far back <verse eid="REV 18:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 18:18" />and, upon seeing the smoke of her conflagration, shouted, “<char style="it">Have you ever seen</char>
        anyone <char style="it">annihilated </char>the same way as the Great City <char style="it">was</char>?”<verse eid="REV 18:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 18:19" />Weeping and mourning, they poured dirt on their heads<char style="sup">[B]</char> and cried out,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:19"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:19">Woe! Woe <char style="it">to</char> the Great City!</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:19">Everyone who put ships out to sea got rich</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:19">Off her <char style="it">aggrandized</char> worth,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:19">Because in one hour she has been wiped out.<verse eid="REV 18:19"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 18:20" />Rejoice over her, sky and heaven
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:20">And saints, apostles, and prophets,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:20">Because the justice that we’re owed from her,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:20">God in His judgment has applied to her.<verse eid="REV 18:20"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="REV 18:21" />An angel who is strong took a stone the size of a large millstone and slammed it into the sea saying,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:21"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:21">In the same kind of swift, sudden, convulsive slam</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:21"><char style="it">As this stone was thrown</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:21">Babylon the Great City <char style="it">too </char>has been slammed</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:21">And has not yet been found—not a trace.<verse eid="REV 18:21"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="REV 18:22" />And any sound of harp players
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:22">And <char style="it">their accompanying band of </char>musicians</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:22">And flute players and trumpet players<char style="sup">[C]</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:22">And every artisan from every form of art</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:22">Could not be found—even a trace—</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:22">Still <char style="it">holding performances </char>in you,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:22">And the sound of any millstone still <char style="it">grinding</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:22">Could not be heard in you—not even a trace,<verse eid="REV 18:22"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="REV 18:23" />And a lamp’s light
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:23">Won’t shine yet again in you—</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:23">Not a chance,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:23">And the sound of a bride and groom <char style="it">together</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:23">Won’t be heard yet again in you—</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:23">Not a chance.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:23"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:23"><char style="it">And this </char>because your merchants were</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:23">The top deal-makers of the Earth,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:23">Because in your drug-induced sprees,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:23">All the nations have been deceived by you,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:23">And you have led them down the primrose path.<verse eid="REV 18:23"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="REV 18:24" />The prophets’ and saints’ blood
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:24">Has been found in her, and the blood</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 18:24">Of all those who’ve been slain upon the Earth.<verse eid="REV 18:24"/>
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">majestic splendor</char>…Lit: <char style="it">glory</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">harassing spirits</char>…Lit: <char style="it">demons</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">filthy, disgusting</char>…Lit: <char style="it">unclean</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">up the ante</char>…Lit: <char style="it">double the doubles</char>. An expression</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I’ve been awarded the status of</char>…Lit: <char style="it">I’ve been seated</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">inventory</char>…Lit: <char style="it">cargo and freight</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">slaves who do manual labor, slaves in generals</char>…Lit: <char style="it">bodies and
        lives of people</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the sumptuous and splendid</char>…Lit, in Gk: the <char style="it">lipara</char> [λιπαρὰ,
        from λιπαρός <char style="w" strong="G03045">λιπαρός</char>)]and the <char style="it">lampra </char>[λαμπρὰ,
        from λαμπρός <char style="w" strong="G02986">λαμπρός</char>)]. An alliteration, rhyme, assonance, or
        pun of a sort, evidence that this is an expression.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">disintegrated right in front of you</char>…Lit: <char style="it">perished from you</char>.
        Some liberties taken.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">works the docks</char>…Lit: <char style="it">at a sailing place</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Using the same cup she did her mixing in, mix a cocktail for her which is twice as concentrated</char>…The
        ancients mixed wine with spices and other flavorings similar to the way we mix cocktails. When hosting
        a dinner, they would prepare a special wine-based mix for the guests.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">poured dirt on their heads</char>…Lit: <char style="it">threw dust on their heads</char>.
        Attempt to emulate the ancient form of grief, mourning, or repentance, as it says in Job 42:6, “Wherefore
        I abhor myself and repent in dust and ashes.”</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">any sound of harp players and their accompanying band of musicians and flute players
        and trumpet players</char>…In ancient Rome, harps and flutes were the principal instruments played in
        amphitheaters in front of large crowds. To put this in perspective, harps and flutes were to them what
        electric guitars and keyboards are to rock bands. Famous performers—the pop stars of their day—went from
        city to city and played in front of large crowds, and all were enchanted by their music. Trumpets were
        third behind harps and flutes in popularity.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 18" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 19   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="REV 19" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 19:1" />After these things <char style="it">happened</char>, I heard what sounded like the voice of an enormous
        crowd in heaven saying,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:1"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:1">Hallelujah! (<char style="it">praise be to God</char>)</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:1"><char style="it">For </char>protecting us<char style="sup">[a]</char>,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:1"><char style="it">For </char>the glory and the power of our God,<verse eid="REV 19:1"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 19:2" />Because His judgments are absolutely correct in their truth<char style="sup">[b]</char>,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:2">Because He’s judged the Great Harlot</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:2">Who ruined the Earth</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:2">By polluting it with her fornication</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:2">And avenged the blood of His servants</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:2"><char style="it">Which was shed </char>by her hand.<verse eid="REV 19:2"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 19:3" />They completed what they had spoken by speaking a second time,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:3"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:3">Hallelujah!</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:3">Her smoke billows up and billows up forever and ever.<verse eid="REV 19:3"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 19:4" />And the twenty-four elders and the four creatures fell and worshiped the Almighty God who sits on the
        throne, saying,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:4"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:4">The end at last<char style="sup">[A]</char>: Hallelujah!<verse eid="REV 19:4"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 19:5" />And a voice issued forth from the throne saying,
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:5"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:5">Praise our God</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:5">All His servants</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:5">And all who reverence Him,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:5">The insignificant and the important<verse eid="REV 19:5"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 19:6" />And I heard the sound <char style="it">of something </char>like a large crowd and like the sound of a
        large volume of rushing water and like the sound of strong thunder saying,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:6"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:6">Hallelujah,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:6">Because our Lord God Almighty reigns.<verse eid="REV 19:6"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 19:7" />Let us rejoice and be glad
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:7">And give Him the glory,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:7">Because <char style="it">the time</char> has arrived for the lamb’s marriage,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:7">And his bride-to-be has prepared herself,<verse eid="REV 19:7"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 19:8" />And she was given bright, clean, fine linen to put on:
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:8">You see, the linen is the righteous deeds</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 19:8">Of the set-apart-people.<verse eid="REV 19:8"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 19:9" />He <char style="it">then </char>tells me, “Write <char style="it">this down</char>: Blessed are those
        who’ve been invited to the lamb’s marriage dinner.”</para>
    <para style="p" vid="REV 19:9">He continues, “These words are truly from God.”<verse eid="REV 19:9"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 19:10" />I fell before His feet to worship Him. He <char style="it">then </char>tells me, “Get ahold of yourself.<char
        style="sup">[c]</char> I’m a fellow-servant of yours and of your comrades who keep the statement of Jesus.
        Worship God, <char style="it">not me</char>. You see, the official statement about Jesus is the underlying
        impetus<char style="sup">[d]</char> of prophecy.”<verse eid="REV 19:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 19:11" />I saw the sky while it had been opened, and—like that—a white horse and mounted on it one called Ever
        True to His Faithful Nature<char style="sup">[e]</char>, and he judges and wages war righteously. <verse eid="REV 19:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 19:12" />His eyes are like wheels of fire, and upon his head are many ornamental headbands<char style="sup">[f]</char>,
        having names <char style="it">of his attributes, accomplishments, and titles </char>written on them which
        nobody knows except he himself, <verse eid="REV 19:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 19:13" />and clothed in clothing that has been soaked in blood, and the name that he goes by is the Word of God.<verse eid="REV 19:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 19:14" />The soldier-garrison in heaven followed him on white horses, clothed in clean, fine white linen. <verse eid="REV 19:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 19:15" />Out of his mouth protrudes a sharp Thracian sword, <char style="it">and it’s there</char> so that he
        can strike the nations, and he personally shepherds (rules) them with a staff of iron. He himself treads
        the winepress of the wine of the ferocious wrath of God Almighty. <verse eid="REV 19:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 19:16" />He has a name written on his outer garment and on his thigh: King of Kings and Lord of Lords.<verse eid="REV 19:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 19:17" />I saw an angel up in the upper atmosphere blocking the sun<char style="sup">[B]</char>. He shouted in
        a loud voice telling any bird that’s <char style="it">capable of </char>flying at a high altitude<char
        style="sup">[C]</char>, “Come gather <char style="it">yourselves </char>for God’s Great Dinner, <verse eid="REV 19:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 19:18" />so that you get the chance to eat the meat of kings, of commanders, of mighty people, of horses and those
        mounted on them, of free men and not just them but of slaves, of the insignificant, and of the great.”<verse eid="REV 19:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 19:19" />And I saw the beast and the kings of the Earth and their soldiers gathered for the purpose of waging
        war against the one mounted on the horse and his troops.<verse eid="REV 19:19" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 19:20" />And the beast was seized and with him the false prophet too, the one who performs miracles under his
        supervision, by <char style="it">such miracles</char> he’s deceived those who’ve received the mark of
        the beast and those who worship his replica—the pair were thrown alive into the Lake of Fire, the lake
        burning in brimstone. <verse eid="REV 19:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="REV 19:21" />The remainder were killed by the Thracian sword that comes out of the mouth of the one mounted on the
        horse, and all of the <char style="it">previously mentioned </char>birds ate their flesh until they were
        too full to eat anymore.<verse eid="REV 19:21" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">protecting us</char>…Lit: <char style="it">salvation</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">absolutely correct in their truth</char>…Lit: <char style="it">true and correct</char>.
        A sort of hendiadys; ref. note of Matt. 3:11.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Get ahold of yourself</char>…Or: <char style="it">see to it that you don’t</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">underlying impetus</char>…Lit: <char style="it">spirit</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Ever True to His Faithful Nature</char>…Lit: <char style="it">faithful and true</char>.
        A hendiadys.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">ornamental headbands</char>…Lit: <char style="it">diadems</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the end at last</char>…Lit: <char style="it">amen</char>. This well-known Hebrew word
        which, depending on the context, has one or more of the following meanings: <char style="it">the end
        at last</char>;<char style="it"> that is so true</char>; <char style="it">that is the last of it</char>;
        <char style="it">let it be so</char>; <char style="it">so be it</char>; <char style="it">the final word
        has been spoken</char>; <char style="it">I/we affirm what you just said/did; the end</char>; <char style="it">the
        end at last</char>.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">up in the upper atmosphere blocking the sun</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in the sun</char>.
        The ancients’ perception of the sun is that it was a lot closer to the Earth than it actually is. Consequently,
        a liberty taken to adapt the wording in a way that fits the modern perspective of astronomy.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">any bird that’s capable of flying at a high altitude</char>…Lit: <char style="it">all
        birds the ones that fly in mid-heaven</char> In regard to <char style="it">mid-heaven</char>, ref. note
        of 8:13. Birds which are “capable of flying at a high altitude” refers to eagles and vultures and perhaps
        a few other carrion-eating types of birds. In any case, what’s referred to is birds which pick at dead
        carcasses and tear their flesh off.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 19" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 20   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="REV 20" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 20:1" />I saw an angel come down out of the sky with the key to the abyss on him and with a huge chain in his
        hand, <verse eid="REV 20:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 20:2" />and he grabbed the dragon, the Ancient Serpent who is a slanderer<char style="sup">[a]</char>—yes, Satan—tied
        him up <char style="it">with the chain </char>for a thousand years, <verse eid="REV 20:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 20:3" />tossed him into the abyss, locked it, and covered the top over and secured it<char style="sup">[b]</char>
        so that he couldn’t deceive the nations anymore until the thousand years were up. After that, he must
        be set free for a little while.<verse eid="REV 20:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 20:4" />I saw some thrones, and <char style="it">I saw </char>those who were seated on them. They were assigned
        the task of presiding in judgment <char style="it">over the crimes perpetrated against</char> the lives
        of those who had been beheaded on account of the statement of Jesus and the word of God and <char style="it">perpetrated</char>
        <char style="it">against </char>whoever wouldn’t worship the beast or his replica and wouldn’t receive
        the mark upon their foreheads and their hands. And they lived and reigned with the Messiah (the Christ)
        a thousand years. <verse eid="REV 20:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 20:5" />The rest of the dead weren’t brought back to life<char style="sup">[c]</char> until the thousand years
        was over. That’s the First Life-after-Death Epoch<char style="sup">[d]</char>. <verse eid="REV 20:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 20:6" />The person who takes part in the First Life-after-Death Epoch is blessed and holy; the second change
        of bodily state of being<char style="sup">[e]</char> has no power over these people, but instead they’ll
        be personal attendants<char style="sup">[f]</char> of God and of the Messiah, and they will reign with
        him for a thousand years.<verse eid="REV 20:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 20:7" />But when the thousand years finally does end, Satan will be let out of jail. <verse eid="REV 20:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 20:8" />He’ll be set free to commit an act of deception upon the nations <char style="it">even to </char>the
        farthest reach of the planet<char style="sup">[A]</char>—all the way to Timbuktu<char style="sup">[B]</char>—to
        gather them together for the War. There were <char style="it">gathered </char>as many as the number of
        grains of sand on a typical seashore. <verse eid="REV 20:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 20:9" /><char style="it">As an army </char>they<char style="it"> </char>deployed themselves in such a way as
        to occupy and control all the key territory<char style="sup">[g]</char> and surrounded the saints’ home
        base<char style="sup">[h]</char>, which is the Beloved City—And flames came down from out of the sky
        and devoured them. <verse eid="REV 20:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 20:10" />“The Slanderer”—the Devil, the one deceiving them—was thrown into the lake of fire and brimstone, where
        the beast and the false prophet <char style="it">are</char> too, and they will be tormented day and night
        forever and ever.<verse eid="REV 20:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 20:11" />I saw a great white throne and the One seated on it, <char style="it">One</char> whom the Earth fled
        from <char style="it">the fierceness and intensity of</char> His undivided attention<char style="sup">[i]</char>—and
        they found no place <char style="it">to escape it</char>. <verse eid="REV 20:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 20:12" />I saw the <char style="it">spiritually </char>dead <char style="it">who had died previously</char>, the
        insignificant and the important, made to stand before the throne, and <char style="it">many </char>books
        were opened, and apart from them another book was opened, which is <char style="it">called </char>the
        <char style="it">Book of </char>Life. And the dead were judged from what had been written in the <char
        style="it">many </char>books, <char style="it">judged, that is,</char> according to the deeds they had
        committed. <verse eid="REV 20:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 20:13" />The graveyard<char style="sup">[C]</char> coughed up its dead—the Grim Reaper returned his dead indeed<char
        style="sup">[j]</char>—and each was judged according to his deeds. <verse eid="REV 20:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 20:14" />And the Grim Reaper was thrown into the Lake of Fire. <verse eid="REV 20:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 20:15" />And if any given person’s name wasn’t found written in the Book of Life, he was thrown into the Lake
        of Fire.<verse eid="REV 20:15" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">slanderer</char>…Or: <char style="it">the Devil</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">covered the top over and secured it</char>…Lit: <char style="it">sealed it shut above
        him</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">weren’t brought back to life</char>…Lit: <char style="it">didn’t live</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the First Life after Death Epoch</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the First Resurrection</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">second change of bodily state of being</char>…Lit: <char style="it">second death</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">personal attendants</char>…Lit: <char style="it">priests</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">they deployed themselves in such a way as to occupy and control all the key territory</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">they went up upon the breadth of the Earth</char>. An expression.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">home base</char>…Lit: <char style="it">encampment</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">undivided attention</char>…Lit: <char style="it">face</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the Grim Reaper returned his dead indeed</char>…Lit: <char style="it">and Death and
        Hades gave their dead</char>. An expression; some liberties taken.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the farthest reach of the planet</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the four corners of the
        Earth</char>. This is an expression. Though the ancient Greeks knew that the world was round, expressions
        continued to be circulated describing it as though it were flat and had four corners.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">all the way to Timbuktu</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the Gog and Magog</char>. Gog and
        Magog are used as a metonymy for any nation of peoples who settled at an extreme distance from the center
        of civilization and over the centuries their whereabouts and any contact with them or knowledge of them
        had been lost.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the graveyard</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the sea</char>. Some liberties taken. The
        sea is used symbolically in the Bible to represent the masses of humanity.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 20" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 21   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="REV 21" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 21:1" />I saw brand-new sky and brand-new ground, seeing that the original sky and the original ground had disappeared
        and that the sea didn’t exist anymore. <verse eid="REV 21:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 21:2" />I saw the Holy City of Jerusalem—a brand-new one—coming down out of the sky, coming from heaven, from
        God, gotten ready like a bride <char style="it">who put on her best dress along with her best jewelry,
        her best face, and arranged her hair in the best way </char>in preparation of being joined to her husband<char
        style="it">-to-be</char>. <verse eid="REV 21:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 21:3" />I heard a loud voice from the throne saying, “Look—God’s setting up camp with mankind<char style="sup">[a]</char>.
        He will camp out with them, and they will be His very own people, <verse eid="REV 21:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 21:4" />and He’ll wipe every tear from their eyes, and Death will not exist, nor will mourning, nor the screaming
        <char style="it">of anguish</char>, nor will the pains of labor exist: the original stuff is gone.<verse eid="REV 21:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 21:5" />The One seated on the throne said, “See here—I’m remaking and redoing everything.” He continued, “Write
        <char style="it">this down</char>, since these very words are ever true in their faithfulness<char style="sup">[b]</char>.”<verse eid="REV 21:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 21:6" />He told me, “It has come into being.<char style="sup">[c]</char> I am the A-to-Z<char style="sup">[d]</char>,
        the beginning and the end. To him who thirsts, I allow to drink from the spring of the water of life,
        no strings attached. <verse eid="REV 21:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 21:7" />The one who triumphs in perseverance will inherit these things. I will be a god-figure<char style="sup">[A]</char>
        to him and he will be a son to me. <verse eid="REV 21:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 21:8" />Now as far as the cowardly, the worthless, the detestable, the murderers, the fornicators, the recreational
        drug-users, the idolaters, and all liars are concerned, they wind up in the lake which burns with fire
        and brimstone, which is the Second Death, <char style="it">the second bodily transformation of the disobedient</char>.<verse eid="REV 21:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 21:9" />One of the seven angels (the angels who have the seven bowls filled with the final seven plagues) came
        and conversed with me saying, “Come and I’ll show you the lamb’s wife<char style="it">-to-be</char>,
        his bride.” <verse eid="REV 21:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 21:10" />In the Spirit he took me and put me on a huge, tall mountain and showed me the holy city Jerusalem coming
        down out of heaven from God, <verse eid="REV 21:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 21:11" />having God’s glory. It was glimmering and radiating light like a gemstone does, like crystal-clear jasper,<verse eid="REV 21:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 21:12" />and had large, tall walls, twelve gates and twelve angels at each gate, and names inscribed <char style="it">on
        the gates </char>that are from the twelve tribes of the sons of Israel. <verse eid="REV 21:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 21:13" />Three gates face east, three face north, three face south, and three face west. <verse eid="REV 21:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 21:14" />The city wall has twelve <char style="it">underlying bands of enormous stones which serve as its</char>
        foundations, and upon them are the names of the twelve apostles of the lamb.<verse eid="REV 21:14" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 21:15" />The <char style="it">angel </char>who was conversing with me had a golden measuring stick, so that he
        could measure<char style="sup">[B]</char> the city, its gates, and its walls. <verse eid="REV 21:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 21:16" />The city is laid in a square, and its length and width are the same. Using the measuring stick, he measured
        the city to be 1500 miles/2400 km<char style="sup">[e]</char> long, and the width and the height are
        the same as the length. <verse eid="REV 21:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 21:17" />He measured its wall to be 215 ft/66 m high<char style="sup">[C]</char>, in terms of human <char style="it">units
        of measurement</char>, which is the same <char style="it">units</char> that angels use. <verse eid="REV 21:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 21:18" />Its surrounding wall is jasper, and the city is pure gold like a clear glass. <verse eid="REV 21:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 21:19" />The foundation of the city walls is decorated with every kind of precious stone and gemstone <char style="it">imaginable.
        </char>The first foundation is jasper, the second is sapphire, the third is agate, the fourth is emerald,<verse eid="REV 21:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 21:20" />the fifth is onyx, the sixth is ruby, the seventh is chrysolite, the eighth is beryl, the ninth is topaz,
        the tenth is turquoise, the eleventh is jacinth, the twelfth is amethyst. <verse eid="REV 21:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="REV 21:21" />The twelve gates are twelve pearls, and each gate is <char style="it">made out of </char>a single pearl.
        The <char style="it">main </char>street of the city is pure gold like transparent glass.<verse eid="REV 21:21" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="REV 21:22" />I saw that there was no temple in it, since the Lord God Almighty is its temple, and so is the lamb.<verse eid="REV 21:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="REV 21:23" />The city has no need to be illuminated by the light of the sun and the moon, since God’s glory shines
        on it and illuminates it, and the lamb is its lamp. <verse eid="REV 21:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="REV 21:24" />The nations will <char style="it">be able to see clearly to </char>walk about as a result of the city’s
        light, and the kings of the Earth bring their glory to it, <char style="it">contributing their very best
        to it</char>. <verse eid="REV 21:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="REV 21:25" />Its gates will never, ever shut because it’ll be daytime all the time<char style="sup">[D]</char>, seeing
        that there will be no nighttime, <verse eid="REV 21:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="REV 21:26" />and they will bring the very best things nations possess and their valuable artifacts into it. <verse eid="REV 21:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="REV 21:27" />And there’s no way whatsoever that any sort of base, degenerate <char style="it">being </char>will enter,
        nor will any being who lies about doing detestable things<char style="sup">[f]</char>—only those who’ve
        been written in the lamb’s Book of Life <char style="it">may enter</char>.<verse eid="REV 21:27" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">God’s setting up camp with mankind</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the tabernacle of God
        with the men</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">ever true in their faithfulness</char>…Lit: <char style="it">faithful and true</char>.
        A hendiadys.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">It has come into being</char>…Almost the same word and almost the same inflected form
        as used in 16:17; ref. note for that verse.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the A-to-Z</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the Alpha and the Omega</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">1500 miles/2400 km</char>…Lit: <char style="it">12,000 stadia</char>. Ref. note of Luke
        24:13 for conversion of units.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">being who lies about doing detestable things</char>…Lit: <char style="it">that doing
        detestable and a liar</char>. A hendiadys.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">god-figure</char>…The word <char style="it">God </char>in the GT of the NT is usually
        preceded with a definite article; this occurrence is not. This is not to say that God is simply a god-figure
        and not God. A god-figure is one who supplies what is necessary for survival. Pagans, in fact, view their
        idols as god-figures and credit them with providing what is needed for their survival. In the OT, the
        Jehovah-names for God do, for the most part, describe God as the ultimate god-figure, the one who promises
        to supply our survival needs. Hence, Jehovah Jireh (the Lord our Provider), Jehova Rapha (the Lord our
        Healer), Jehovah Nissi (the Lord our Banner), Jehovah Rohi (the Lord our Shepherd), etc.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">measure</char>…Measuring the city verifies that it is perfect, in the same way that
        exact dimensions of the tabernacle are specified in the Torah. The act of measuring confirms that it
        perfectly complies with God’s exacting standards; in this context, that it is made by God and not by
        man. Also, ref. note of Rev. 11:2.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">215 ft/ 66 meters high</char>…Lit: <char style="it">144 cubits</char>. A cubit is approximately
        18 inches/450 millimeters.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[D]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[D]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">daytime all the time</char>…Gates in ancient cities were normally kept open during the
        day but shut at night, as to protect against bands of marauders who roamed the night and other such threats.
        With there being no night, there is no need to ever shut the gates.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 21" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 22   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="REV 22" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 22:1" />He <char style="it">then </char>showed me a river of living water as clear as crystal, pouring out of
        God’s throne and out of the lamb <verse eid="REV 22:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 22:2" />and into the middle of the <char style="it">city’s</char> main street. The tree of life yields fruit
        on either side of the river twelve <char style="it">times a year, </char>each month, and the tree’s leaves
        are destined for the treatment and healing of the nations. <verse eid="REV 22:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 22:3" />No kind of curse (<char style="it">bad things which happen to people</char>) will exist anymore. God’s
        throne will be in <char style="it">the city</char>, and so will the lamb, and His servants will ritualistically
        offer up a service of worship to Him. <verse eid="REV 22:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 22:4" />His face will be visible, and His name <char style="it">will be seen </char>upon their foreheads. <verse eid="REV 22:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 22:5" />There will no longer be any night, and there won’t be any need for lamplight and sunlight, because the
        Lord God will provide illumination for them and will reign forever and ever.<verse eid="REV 22:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 22:6" />He told me, “These here words are ever true in their faithfulness<char style="sup">[a]</char>.”
    </para>
    <para style="p" vid="REV 22:6">The Lord, the God of the prophetic utterances of the prophets<char style="sup">[A]</char>, sent His angel
        to show His servants what must come to pass post-haste.<verse eid="REV 22:6"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 22:7" /><char style="wj">See here—I’m coming post-haste. Blessed is the one who keeps the words of the prophecy
        in this scroll.</char><verse eid="REV 22:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 22:8" />And, I, John, the one who’s listening to and watching <char style="it">all</char> these things—when I
        heard and saw <char style="it">this</char>, I fell <char style="it">on my face </char>before the feet
        of the angel who’s showing me these things to worship <char style="it">him</char>. <verse eid="REV 22:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 22:9" />He <char style="it">then </char>tells me, “Get ahold of yourself. I’m a fellow-servant of yours, of your
        comrades the prophets, and of those adhering to the words in this scroll. Worship God<char style="it">,
        not me.</char>”<char style="it"> </char><verse eid="REV 22:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 22:10" />He <char style="it">then </char>tells me, “Don’t deny access to<char style="sup">[b]</char> the prophetic
        words in this scroll, seeing that the time is near. <verse eid="REV 22:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 22:11" />Let he who behaves in a worthless manner yet continue in his worthlessness, let he who is foul yet continue
        to be foul and filthy, let he who’s righteous yet continue to act righteously, and he who’s holy yet
        continue to act like a saint.<verse eid="REV 22:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 22:12" /><char style="wj">See here—I’m coming post-haste. I have cash on hand to pay each person according to
        the work he’s done </char><char style="it"><char style="wj">for the day</char></char><char style="wj">.</char><char
        style="sup">[B]</char><char style="wj"> </char><verse eid="REV 22:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 22:13" /><char style="wj">I am the A-Z, the first and the last, beginning and the end.</char><verse eid="REV 22:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 22:14" />Blessed are those who wash their robes, so they have the right<char style="sup">[c]</char> to the tree
        of life; and when they perchance desire to enter the city, they <char style="it">are permitted to </char>use
        the gates. <verse eid="REV 22:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 22:15" />Outside <char style="it">the city</char><char style="sup">[d]</char><char style="it"> </char>are the
        dogs, the recreational drug users, the fornicators, the murderers, the idolaters, and everyone who is
        quite fond of lying and lies <char style="it">all the time</char><char style="sup">[e]</char>.<verse eid="REV 22:15" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 22:16" /><char style="wj">I, Jesus, dispatched my agent to declare these things to you in the churches. I am the
        direct-descendant</char><char style="sup">[f]</char><char style="wj"> of David, the Bright Morning Star.
        </char><verse eid="REV 22:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 22:17" />And the Spirit and the bride<char style="it">-to-be</char> say, “Come!” And let the one who thirsts come,
        and let the one who <char style="it">so </char>desires freely partake of the water of life.<verse eid="REV 22:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 22:18" />I confirm<char style="sup">[g]</char> that I’ve heard all the prophetic words which are in this scroll.
        If anyone chooses to add to them, God will add all the plagues that are written in this scroll to his
        life. <verse eid="REV 22:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 22:19" />And if anyone chooses to delete words from this prophetic scroll, God will delete his access to the tree
        of life and to the holy city, which has been written about in this scroll.<verse eid="REV 22:19" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 22:20" />He who confirms these things says:
    </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 22:20"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 22:20"><char style="wj">“Yes indeed, I’m coming post-haste.”</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="REV 22:20"></para>
    <para style="p" vid="REV 22:20">Let it be so<char style="sup">[h]</char>. Come Lord Jesus.<verse eid="REV 22:20"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="REV 22:21" />May the grace of the Lord Jesus be with everyone.<verse eid="REV 22:21" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">ever true in their faithfulness</char>…Lit: <char style="it">faithful and true</char>.
        A hendiadys. Same phrase used in Rev. 21:5.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">deny access to</char>…Lit: <char style="it">seal</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">right</char>…Lit: <char style="it">authority</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">outside the city</char>…Lit: <char style="it">outside</char>. Ref. note of 14:20</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">quite fond of lying and lies all the time</char>…Lit: <char style="it">all loving</char>
        [<char style="it">phileō, </char><char style="w" strong="G05368">φιλέω</char>)] <char style="it">and
        practicing a lie</char>. The awkward wording is a figure of speech.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the direct-descendant</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the stock</char> [<char style="it">root</char>]
        <char style="it">and the lineage</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">confirm</char>…Lit: <char style="it">testify</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">let it be so</char>…Lit: <char style="it">amen</char>. Ref. note of 19:4.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">God of the prophetic utterances of the prophets</char>…Lit: <char style="it">God of
        the spirits of the prophets</char>…The phrase <char style="it">spirits of the prophets </char>is an idiom.
        It also appears in 1 Cor. 14:32. These two passages qualify the idiom’s meaning.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="REV 22" />
</usx>
