<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- The Bernmeister's New Testament, Unabridged Edition -->
<!-- Copyright © 2024 Bernard M. Woodland -->
<!-- Version 2 -->
<!-- Public domain -->
<!-- The Bernmeister's NT, Unabridged Version 2 -->
<usx version="3.0">
  <!--   *******************   -->
  <!--   Titles and TOC Info   -->
  <!--   *******************   -->
  <book code="ROM" style="id">The Bernmeister's NT, Unabridged</book>
  <para style="h">Romans</para>
  <para style="toc1">The Epistle of Romans</para>
  <para style="toc2">Romans</para>
  <para style="toc3">Rom.</para>
  <para style="mt2">THE EPISTLE OF</para>
  <para style="mt1">ROMANS</para>
  <!--   ************   -->
  <!--   Introduction   -->
  <!--   ************   -->
  <para style="imt">Introduction</para>
  <para style="ipi">Paul, the great pioneer of Christianity, the great theologian of Christian doctrine, makes a treatise
    out of the first half of this long letter to the Romans. </para>
  <para style="ipi">The combination of Paul’s mastery of Greek., the customizing of his writing to a non-Jewish audience,
    and his lucid prose make it easy on the translator, as his works can be translated nearly word-for-word
    and the result be intelligible enough to serve as the final rendering. Therefore, if one compares various
    works of translations, even the ones which deviate from the traditional, literal rendering, one finds
    that the translations are similar. Paul uses his powerful vocabulary and understanding of the grammar
    to pack nuances into a pithy text, rather than relying on figures of speech like a few of the other NT
    writers do.</para>
  <para style="ipi">Reasoning, philosophy, and the ability to look at various aspects of difficult questions are Paul’s bread
    &amp; butter. Whereas Jesus’s teachings are remarkably insightful, Paul’s teachings are remarkably philosophical—and
    the first half of Romans is the pinnacle of this. Paul takes the reader on a long, single thread until
    the ninth chapter, when he finally segues to another.</para>
  <para style="ipi">Since Romans delves into such thought-provoking theological and philosophical topics, the approach in
    translation is akin to the Amplified Bible, a compromise between preserving the literal wording and clarifying
    the end-result. As an analogy, scholars say that the writings of the philosopher Immanuel Kant should
    not be read directly by someone unschooled in the philosophical terminology Kant uses, as they will not
    understand it. This is partly the case with Romans also, as Paul’s multi-faceted meaning of his use of,
    for example, the word <char style="it">law </char>in conjunction with his inclusion or omission of the
    definite article is over the head of the unschooled reader, compounded by the fact that most translations
    don’t propagate through to the rendered version the inclusion or exclusion the definite article on a
    word-for-word basis anyways, as the final product in English would be awkward at best.</para>
  <para style="ipi">To ameliorate this, I’ve preferred a word-for-word rendering of the definite article before <char style="it">law
    </char>and <char style="it">sin </char>in particular and before other words as well because I believe
    that this is valuable information that Paul is communicating, that it has a large impact on what he’s
    trying to convey, and that it’s essential that the reader get this “unfiltered.” But by doing so, I must
    sacrifice some readability for clarity. To compensate and to fully explain the meaning of the preceding
    word in conjunction with its optionally-included article, immediately following, I add an explanation
    inside of parenthesis and set off by <char style="it">i.e</char>. Generally speaking, if the next occurrence
    of the word in the same chapter merits the same explanatory phrase, I omit the parenthetical note for
    brevity’s sake, assuming that the reader will understand that it’s the same as the previous.</para>
  <para style="ib"></para>
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  1   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="ROM 1" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 1:1" />Paul, servant of Christ Jesus, called as a missionary<char style="sup">[a]</char>, designated to God’s
        good news—the Gospel, <verse eid="ROM 1:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 1:2" />what He promised before over and over through His prophets in the Old Testament<char style="sup">[b]</char><verse eid="ROM 1:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 1:3" />about His son, who—physically speaking—came into being through the lineage of David, <verse eid="ROM 1:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 1:4" />who was declared in a powerful way to be God’s son according to the Holy Spirit due to the resurrection
        from the dead, <char style="it">namely</char> Jesus Christ our Lord, <verse eid="ROM 1:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 1:5" />through whom we’ve received grace and have received a missionary assignment that has the end-goal of
        obedience—a consequence of faith—among all the Gentiles and the far-off nations on behalf of all he stands
        for<char style="sup">[c]</char>, <verse eid="ROM 1:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 1:6" />by which you too are called by Jesus Christ:<verse eid="ROM 1:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 1:7" />To God’s beloved who are holy and called <char style="it">of God </char>who are in Rome: Grace <char
        style="it">be </char>to you—and peace—from the Father-God and the Lord Jesus Christ.<verse eid="ROM 1:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 1:8" />First and foremost, concerning you I thank my God through Jesus Christ, that the word is being spread
        about your faith throughout the entire world. <verse eid="ROM 1:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 1:9" />In fact, God is my witness, whom I offer a service of worship to in my spirit in the evangelization of
        his son, as I’m constantly making mention of you <verse eid="ROM 1:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 1:10" />every time I offer up prayers, asking if somehow, sometime, I will have succeeded by the will of God
        in visiting you. <verse eid="ROM 1:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 1:11" />The fact of the matter is that I long to see you so that I might bestow on you a spiritual gift, a gift
        whose goal is to establish you. <verse eid="ROM 1:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 1:12" />This <char style="it">bestowing of a spiritual gift </char>is <char style="it">done </char>to take comfort
        together with you through the faith shared between you and me.<verse eid="ROM 1:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 1:13" />I don’t want you to be left in the dark, comrades<char style="sup">[d]</char>, that I purposed many times
        to come to you, but I was prevented <char style="it">from doing so </char>up until now, so that I would
        <char style="it">have the opportunity in the meantime </char>to observe the germination and growth of
        tangible signs of maturity<char style="sup">[e]</char> among you as well just I observed it in the other
        Gentiles— <verse eid="ROM 1:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 1:14" />I’m in debt not just to the civilized but to the uncivilized<char style="sup">[f]</char> also, to not
        just the wise but to the foolish also. <verse eid="ROM 1:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 1:15" />This is what motivates me to evangelize to you too who are in Rome.<verse eid="ROM 1:15" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 1:16" />The fact of the matter is, I’m not ashamed of the Gospel, for it’s God’s power in all those who believe
        for them to end up with salvation (i.e., the state of being kept from from spiritual, moral, mental,
        and physical calamity)—and not just the Jews but the non-Jewish Westerners<char style="sup">[g]</char>
        as well. <verse eid="ROM 1:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 1:17" />For in <char style="it">the Gospel </char>God’s righteousness (i.e., God’s requirements of how a person
        must lead his life in order to please Him and be approved by Him) is revealed out of faith and <char
        style="it">back</char> into faith, just as it’s been written <char style="it">in the Old Testament, </char>“The
        one who’s righteous (i.e., the one whose life is to be approved by God) shall live out of faith.”<verse eid="ROM 1:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 1:18" />You see, God’s wrath is unfurled from up in the sky, up in heaven, upon ungodliness and unrighteousness
        <char style="it">inherent in </char>people who withhold the truth in and by their unrighteousness, <verse eid="ROM 1:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 1:19" /><char style="it">and it is unfurled </char>because the knowledge of God has appeared and been made known
        to them. <verse eid="ROM 1:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 1:20" />To this point, from the inception of human society, His invisible aspects (that is, His everlasting power
        and divine nature) have been clearly seen and understood by means of the things which were created, resulting
        in <char style="it">all humans </char>being without excuse. <verse eid="ROM 1:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 1:21" />Therefore, while knowing and understanding God, they didn’t glorify or thank <char style="it">Him </char>as
        God, but became empty-headed in their reasonings instead, and their non-understanding heart darkened.<verse eid="ROM 1:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 1:22" />Asserting to be wise, they became idiots <verse eid="ROM 1:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 1:23" />and exchanged the glory of the Immortal God for the facsimile of a Mortal Human and of animals<char style="sup">[h]</char>.<verse eid="ROM 1:23" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 1:24" />So for the aforementioned reasons, <char style="it">as they were wallowing </char>in the desires of their
        hearts, God handed them over to dirty and disgusting unholy things<char style="sup">[i]</char> in dishonoring
        and disgracing their bodies among themselves, <verse eid="ROM 1:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 1:25" />the very people who, <char style="it">as they were wallowing </char>in the <char style="it">aforementioned
        </char>lie, swapped the truth of God and worshipped and held religious services for the creature, circumventing
        the Creator, the One who is forever blessed (and let us pause a moment for that to sink in<char style="sup">[j]</char>).<verse eid="ROM 1:25" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 1:26" />On account of this, God handed them over to an unnatural, disgraceful, excruciating passion <char style="it">of
        lust. </char>In this regard, both the women<char style="sup">[A]</char> swapped the Natural Function
        for that which circumvents what comes naturally; <verse eid="ROM 1:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 1:27" />and the men<char style="sup">[A]</char> too—and in the same manner—leaving the Natural Function of the
        woman, burning in their longing for one another, men perpetrating the disgraceful deed with<char style="sup">[k]</char>
        men and receiving the corresponding reward which they have coming to them and which they were bound to
        receive due to their error, <char style="it">an error</char> <char style="it">which they adhered to</char>
        among themselves.<verse eid="ROM 1:27" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 1:28" />And just as they did not approve of retaining the accumulated knowledge and understanding of God, God
        handed them over to an unapproved mind, to do what is not fitting to do, <verse eid="ROM 1:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 1:29" />having been filled to the brim with every kind of unrighteousness: with wickedness, greed, malice, <char
        style="it">they are</char> full of envy, murder, strife, Machiavellian-styled rivalry, malevolence; <char
        style="it">they’re </char>gossips and slanderers, <verse eid="ROM 1:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ROM 1:30" />trash-talkers, God-haters; <char style="it">they’re </char>insolent people, <char style="it">they’re
        </char>arrogant, <char style="it">they’re </char>braggarts, <char style="it">they </char>dream up evil,
        <char style="it">they </char>rebel against <char style="it">their </char>parents, <verse eid="ROM 1:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ROM 1:31" /><char style="it">they’re </char>dull-witted, treacherous, without the natural affection one has for parents,
        children, nation, etc.; <char style="it">they’re</char> unmerciful— <verse eid="ROM 1:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ROM 1:32" />The very people who know and understand God’s righteous precepts exactly, that those who practice such
        things deserve to die—not only do they do these things, but they’re in lockstep-agreement and think highly
        of those who practice them.<verse eid="ROM 1:32" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">missionary</char>…Lit: <char style="it">apostle</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Old Testament</char>…Lit: <char style="it">holy scriptures</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">all he stands for</char>…Lit: <char style="it">his name</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">would have the opportunity in the meantime to observe the germination and growth of
        tangible signs of maturity</char>…Lit: <char style="it">could have some fruit</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the civilized but to the uncivilized</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the Greeks but to
        the Barbarians</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">non-Jewish Westerners</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Greeks</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">animals</char>…Lit: <char style="it">birds, four-legged creatures, and reptiles</char>.
        The NT writers enumerated categories that we simply place under the umbrella of <char style="it">animals.</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">dirty and disgusting unholy things</char>…Lit: <char style="it">uncleanness</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">and let us pause a moment for that to sink in</char>…Lit: <char style="it">amen. </char>Ref.
        note of Rev. 19:4.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">with</char>…Also: <char style="it">in</char>. The word ordering was also moved, as the
        GT reads <char style="it">men with men </char>or <char style="it">men in men.</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">women</char>…<char style="it">men</char>…In the GT, Paul uses the archaic versions of
        these words, the versions found in the LXX quotation of Gen. 5:2, “He made them man and woman, husband
        and wife.” These are the same words used in the embedded Gen. 5:2 quotations in Matt. 19:4 an Mark 6:6.
        By selecting the same words as found in Gen. 5:2, instead of choosing the more commonly used Gk. words
        for <char style="it">men</char> and <char style="it">women</char>, Paul is signaling that the statements
        he makes in vv. 26,27 are based on Gen. 5:2.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="ROM 1" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  2   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="ROM 2" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 2:1" />…Which leads to this: who do you think you are, you who<char style="sup">[a]</char> pronounces judgment
        <char style="it">over others</char> (i.e., draws conclusions about others for the purpose of writing
        them off)<char style="sup">[b]</char>?—There’s no excuse <char style="it">for this</char>. The fact is,
        in the <char style="it">area</char> in which you judge another, you condemn yourself, for the one who’s
        doing the judging practices the same thing<char style="sup">[A]</char>. <verse eid="ROM 2:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 2:2" />Now we know for a fact that God renders a <char style="it">guilty</char> verdict in line with the truth
        against those who practice such things. <verse eid="ROM 2:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 2:3" />You rascal<char style="sup">[c]</char>, you who commits <char style="it">such sins</char> and practices
        such things—do you figure that you’ll evade God’s judgment? <verse eid="ROM 2:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 2:4" />Or while despising the riches of His goodness, forbearance and patience, you’re unaware that the goodness
        of God leads one to repentance (i.e., to change one’s heart and one’s ways)? <verse eid="ROM 2:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 2:5" />But in accordance with your hard—<char style="it">downright</char> unrepentant—heart, you’re accumulating
        your own <char style="it">individualized</char>-wrath <char style="it">to be regurgitated</char> on that
        date when wrath is unveiled and readily distributed, the day of God’s righteous judgment, <verse eid="ROM 2:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 2:6" />Who “will repay every person according to what that person’s done.” <verse eid="ROM 2:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 2:7" />On the one hand to those who, in accordance with a consistent pattern of good works, seek after glory,
        honor, and immortality, <char style="it">the repayment will be </char>eternal life. <verse eid="ROM 2:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 2:8" />But on the other hand, to those who, out of <char style="it">an</char> <char style="it">attempt </char>to<char
        style="it"> </char>promote themselves by buying influence <char style="it">with God </char>and out of
        not being persuaded and being disobedience to the Truth but are convinced <char style="it">that doing
        </char>unrighteousness <char style="it">is alright</char>, <char style="it">the repayment will be </char>wrath
        and an outburst of rage— <verse eid="ROM 2:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 2:9" />Distress and anguish for every last person<char style="sup">[d]</char> who leads a life of evil, Jews
        at a higher level and non-Jewish Westerners <char style="it">at a level below them</char>.<char style="sup">[B]</char><verse eid="ROM 2:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 2:10" />But glory, honor, and peace to all who lead a life of good, Jews at a higher level and Westerners <char
        style="it">at a level below them</char>. <verse eid="ROM 2:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 2:11" />The fact of the matter is that God shows no favoritism.<verse eid="ROM 2:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 2:12" />You see, anyone at all<char style="sup">[e]</char> who sinned without the benefit of possessing a law
        (i.e., a list of God’s rules) will perish; and anyone at all who sins while <char style="it">immersed</char>
        in a law will be judged by <char style="it">that </char>law. <verse eid="ROM 2:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 2:13" />To be clear, it’s not the ones who have heard a law <char style="it">and can spout off what it says </char>who
        are right with God, but the ones who put a law into practice will be pronounced righteous <char style="it">by
        God</char>.<verse eid="ROM 2:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 2:14" />To this point, when the Gentiles who don’t have a law (i.e., a list of God’s rules) instinctively do
        the things of the Law<char style="it"> </char>(i.e., the definitive, comprehensive list of God’s rules,
        which is the Law of Moses), they, <char style="it">though </char>not possessing the Law, are a law (i.e.,
        a set of God-given rules) for<char style="sup">[f]</char> themselves. <verse eid="ROM 2:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 2:15" />These particular people point out what the law written in their hearts (i.e., their particular list of
        God’s rules written in their hearts) has accomplished—<char style="it">and</char> while <char style="it">pointing
        this out </char>their consciences join in and testify even <char style="it">to the extent of arbitrating
        </char>between the various differing rationales condemning or defending— <verse eid="ROM 2:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 2:16" />on whatever day it happens to be when God judges the hidden things of mankind through Christ Jesus according
        to my positive message—my Gospel.<verse eid="ROM 2:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 2:17" />Now if you call yourself a Jew and are fixated on law (i.e., mankind possessing and putting into practice
        the definitive list of God’s rules), boast over (i.e., take pride in; swagger over; loudly extol the
        virtues of; defend vociferously) <char style="it">the things of </char>God, <verse eid="ROM 2:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 2:18" />know the will <char style="it">of God</char>,<char style="it"> </char>and accept or reject the differing
        oral traditions <char style="it">of interpretation which are derived </char>from<char style="it"> </char>the
        Law <char style="it">of Moses</char><char style="sup">[C]</char>— <verse eid="ROM 2:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 2:19" />and all these to the extent that you’ve convinced yourself that you’ve reached the point where you’re
        a guide to the blind, a light in darkness, <verse eid="ROM 2:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 2:20" />a trainer to the foolish, a teacher to the young, possessing in the Law <char style="it">of Moses</char>
        the embodiment of the knowledge and the truth <char style="it">of God</char>— <verse eid="ROM 2:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 2:21" />so now, does the one who’s teaching someone else teach himself <char style="it">anything</char>? Does
        the one who preaches <char style="it">to others </char>not to steal steal <char style="it">himself</char>?<verse eid="ROM 2:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 2:22" />Does the one who says “don’t commit adultery” commit adultery? Is the one who abhors idols a temple robber?<verse eid="ROM 2:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 2:23" />Does the one who boasts in law (i.e., takes pride in—to the point of bragging about—his ability to follow
        the list of God’s rules) dishonor God by the transgression of the Law <char style="it">of Moses</char>?<verse eid="ROM 2:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 2:24" />In fact, “God’s reputation<char style="sup">[g]</char> is slandered among the Gentiles because of you,”
        like it says in the Bible<char style="sup">[h]</char>.<verse eid="ROM 2:24" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 2:25" />The fact of the matter is that—yes—circumcision (i.e., committing one’s life to following the Law of
        Moses) is beneficial if one were to put <char style="it">the edicts of</char> the Law <char style="it">of
        Moses </char>into practice, but if one were to transgress the Law, his circumcision will have become
        uncircumcision (i.e., as though he never committed himself to follow the Law of Moses). <verse eid="ROM 2:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 2:26" />So if the <char style="it">archetypical </char>circumcised man were to keep the edicts of the Law <char
        style="it">of Moses</char>, wouldn’t his uncircumcision count as circumcision? <verse eid="ROM 2:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 2:27" />And the physically-uncircumcised man who satisfies <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">requirements
        of </char>the Law <char style="it">of Moses </char>will judge you, the <char style="it">quintessential</char>
        transgressor of law (i.e., one who doesn’t fulfill the requirements of the list of edicts given by God),
        a transgressor in the midst of having a verbatim copy of God’s edicts and by having signed up to comply
        with those edicts<char style="sup">[i]</char>.<verse eid="ROM 2:27" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 2:28" />You see, a person is not Jewish because he appears Jewish on the outside, nor is circumcision a physical
        characteristic, <verse eid="ROM 2:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 2:29" />but rather one is Jewish by virtue of what’s on the inside, and circumcision is of the heart <char style="it">done
        </char>by <char style="it">the </char>Spirit not by the letter (i.e., by the rigid interpretation and
        application of God’s edicts); that person’s praise is not from people but from God.<verse eid="ROM 2:29" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">who do you think you are, you who</char>…Lit: <char style="it">oh man all who</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">pronounces judgment over others (i.e., draws conclusions about others for the purpose
        of writing them off)</char>…Also: <char style="it">decides</char>…Lit: <char style="it">judges</char>.
        Ref. note of Matt. 7:1.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">you rascal</char>…Lit: <char style="it">oh man</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">for every last person</char>…Lit: <char style="it">upon all soul </char>[<char style="it">person</char>]<char
        style="it"> of man</char>. The word <char style="it">soul </char>means <char style="it">person </char>in
        this context.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">anyone at all</char>…In the GT this is actually plural, not singular</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">for</char>…Or: <char style="it">in</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">God’s reputation</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the name of God</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">like it says in the Bible</char>…Lit: <char style="it">according what’s been written</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">in the midst of having a verbatim copy of God’s edicts and by having signed up to comply
        with those edicts</char>…Lit: <char style="it">through letter and circumcision</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the one who’s doing the judging practices the same thing</char>…Paul’s referring to
        a curious psychological condition I’ll call “The Jimmy Swaggert Phenomenon.” The TV evangelist in his
        heyday in the ‘80’s was calling out other ministers for their sexual sins while at the same time visiting
        prostitutes. What Paul is saying here is that, generally speaking, people tend to judge others in the
        same areas they are guilty of themselves.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Jews at a higher level and non-Jewish Westerners</char> <char style="it">at a level
        below them</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Jew first and Greek</char>. Since Jews were God’s chosen people
        and since they were given the word of God, Paul’s saying that judgment will be harsher on them. But on
        the flip side, v. 10 says that Jews will receive a higher level of glory, honor, and peace for the same
        reason.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">oral traditions of interpretation which are derived from the Law of Moses</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">taught-by-word-of-mouth out of the Law</char>. This might be a reference to the Oral
        Torah, which evolved into the Mishnah.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="ROM 2" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  3   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="ROM 3" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 3:1" />So what’s so much better about being Jewish? Put another way,<char style="it"> </char>what’s the advantage
        of being circumcised (i.e., being in a covenant to obey the Law of Moses)? <verse eid="ROM 3:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 3:2" />Much and in many ways. First—certainly first—is that they were entrusted with <char style="it">the safekeeping
        and preservation of </char>God’s words<char style="sup">[A]</char>. <verse eid="ROM 3:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 3:3" />So now, what if some of them refused to have faith and believe? Does their refusal to believe cancel
        God’s faithfulness?— <verse eid="ROM 3:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 3:4" />Don’t even think about it; think this instead<char style="sup">[B]</char>: God is true, but every person
        is a liar, just like it’s written,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 3:4"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 3:4">…So You’d be absolutely right in Your words</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 3:4">And come out on top in Your judgments<verse eid="ROM 3:4"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 3:5" />Now if our unrighteousness causes us to become aligned with the righteousness of God, what’s the takeaway<char
        style="sup">[a]</char>? It isn’t that God, Who brings the wrath <char style="it">which</char> <char style="it">He’s
        deemed justifiable </char>upon <char style="it">select individuals</char>,<char style="it"> </char>is
        unfair? (I’m talking <char style="it">about “unfair”</char> in terms of human standards <char style="it">of
        fair and unfair</char>.<char style="sup">[b]</char>) <verse eid="ROM 3:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 3:6" />Don’t even think about it<char style="sup">[c]</char>—otherwise, how will God judge the world (i.e.,
        those who are a part of the ungodly society which mankind formed)? <verse eid="ROM 3:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 3:7" />But if in the My Fraud Falsehood the truth of God proliferates to His glory, why am I still being judged
        like <char style="it">I’m</char> a sinner, <verse eid="ROM 3:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 3:8" />and not <char style="it">being judged </char>according to the way in which we’re being slandered, in
        which some people are saying that our position is: let’s do these things here which are<char style="it">
        </char>evil<char style="sup">[d]</char> in order that these things here which are good will come? Their
        condemnation <char style="it">of our so-called position</char> is justified.<verse eid="ROM 3:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 3:9" />What then? Do we have an advantage? Not entirely. The fact is, we Jews—and throw in all Westerners<char
        style="sup">[e]</char> too—have been pre-indicted<char style="sup">[f]</char> for being dominated<char
        style="sup">[g]</char> by sin, <verse eid="ROM 3:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 3:10" />just like it’s recorded in Scripture:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 3:10"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 3:10">There is no person who’s righteous—not one.<verse eid="ROM 3:10"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 3:11" />There’s no person who understands.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 3:11">No one seeks out God.<verse eid="ROM 3:11"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 3:12" />All of them veered off <char style="it">in a bad direction</char>;</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 3:12">The whole lot of them is useless.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 3:12">There’s no one who does good</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 3:12">—Not even a single person.<verse eid="ROM 3:12"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 3:13" />Their throat is an open grave.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 3:13">They deceive <char style="it">others </char>with their tongues.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 3:13">Cobra venom is under their lips, <char style="it">under the lips of those</char><verse eid="ROM 3:13"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 3:14" />Whose mouth cusses and has a bitter taste in it.<verse eid="ROM 3:14" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 3:15" />Their feet are keen to shed blood</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 3:15">(i.e., they are acutely prone to shed blood).<verse eid="ROM 3:15"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 3:16" />Ruin and misery is in their paths</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 3:16">(i.e., for them, ruin and misery is inevitable and unavoidable),<verse eid="ROM 3:16"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 3:17" />And they haven’t discerned a path of peace,<verse eid="ROM 3:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 3:18" />There is no fear of God directly in front of their eyes</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 3:18">(i.e., their hearts’ desire is not fascinated</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 3:18">by a deep reverence for God).<verse eid="ROM 3:18"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 3:19" />Now we know that, to the extent to which the Law <char style="it">of Moses </char>touches on points,
        it addresses those who’re <char style="it">up to their neck </char>in the Law, so that everyone would
        be left with nothing to say<char style="sup">[h]</char> and the entire world (i.e., the entire established
        order of humanity) would become accountable to God. <verse eid="ROM 3:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 3:20" />Therefore, what comes out of works of law (i.e., an attempt to perform the deeds which satisfy the requirements
        mandated by a list of God-given rules) is that not a single living being<char style="sup">[i]</char>
        will be justified before Him (i.e., declared “not guilty” in a court of law presided over by God as judge);
        the fact is, through law comes a<char style="it"> </char>recognition and a precise knowledge and understanding
        of sin.<verse eid="ROM 3:20" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 3:21" />But as it turns out, righteousness of God (i.e., a venue whereby God will approve of how one conducts
        his life) has been manifested apart from law (i.e., the reliance on pleasing God solely based on obeying
        His list of rules), <char style="it">as it </char>is showcased<char style="sup">[j]</char> by the Old
        Testament<char style="sup">[k]</char>, <verse eid="ROM 3:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 3:22" />a righteousness of God through Jesus Christ-faith to all who believe: there is no distinction, you see:<verse eid="ROM 3:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 3:23" />For all have sinned and come up short of the glory of God, <verse eid="ROM 3:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 3:24" />while <char style="it">at the same time being offered</char> a gift of being justified by His grace through
        the redemption (i.e., the restoring of a person to his original, proper, and designated place) in Christ
        Jesus, <verse eid="ROM 3:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 3:25" />whom God determined before it all started to be a propitiation (i.e., a means of redemption) through
        faith in his blood resulting in a demonstration of His righteousness by the overlooking of the previously-committed
        sins <verse eid="ROM 3:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 3:26" />by the forbearance of God coupled with the demonstration of His righteousness in the present time, resulting
        in Him being just and justifying a given person out of and as a byproduct of Jesus-faith.<verse eid="ROM 3:26" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 3:27" />So where is the boaster (i.e., the one who brags about his own accomplishments)?—he’s been shut out.
        Through what sort of law (i.e., method of attaining righteousness with God)? <char style="it">Through</char>
        the works<char style="it">-method</char>?—No, but rather through a law (i.e. method) of faith. <verse eid="ROM 3:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 3:28" />You see, we figure that a person’s justified by faith apart from works of law (i.e. a method of works).<verse eid="ROM 3:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 3:29" />Is God the Jews’ God only? Isn’t He the Gentiles’ God too—Yes, <char style="it">He’s </char>the Gentiles’
        God too, <verse eid="ROM 3:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ROM 3:30" />if one assumes that there is only one true God and that this God is of one mind and has His own will,
        and there is no other being comparable to Him<char style="sup">[l]</char>, a God who will justify a circumcised
        man (i.e., a person who’s in a covenant to obey the Law of Moses) as a result of<char style="sup">[m]</char>
        faith and an uncircumcised man by means of the <char style="it">same </char>faith. <verse eid="ROM 3:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ROM 3:31" />Is law (i.e., the expectation of having to obey the list of God’s rules) preempted through faith? Don’t
        even think about it—on the contrary: law is established.<verse eid="ROM 3:31" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">what’s the takeaway</char>…Lit: <char style="it">what shall we say</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I’m talking about “unfair” in terms of human standards of fair and unfair…</char>Lit:
        <char style="it">I speak according to man</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Don’t even think about it</char>…Ref. note of v. 4</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">this thing here which is evil/this thing here which is good</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the
        evil/the good</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">all Westerners</char>…Lit: all <char style="it">Greeks</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">pre-indicted</char>…Lit: <char style="it">accused beforehand</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">dominated</char>…Lit: <char style="it">under</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">everyone would be left with nothing to say</char>…Lit: <char style="it">every mouth
        would close</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">not a single living being…</char>Lit: <char style="it">all flesh</char>. A figure of
        speech. Also used in Matt. 24:22.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">showcased</char>…Lit: <char style="it">witnessed</char> </char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the Old Testament</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the Law and the Prophets</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">there is only one true God and that this God is of one mind and has His own will, and
        there is no other being comparable to Him</char>…Lit: <char style="it">God is One</char>. Ref. note of
        James 2:19.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[m]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[m]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">as a result of</char>…Lit: <char style="it">out of</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">they were entrusted with the safekeeping and preservation of God’s words</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">they were entrusted the words of God</char>. For all the sins of nation of Israel that
        we read about in the OT, they got a couple of things right, one of which is the Masoretic Text—the culmination
        of their careful keeping of God’s words.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Don’t even think about it; think this instead</char>…Lit: <char style="it">may it never
        come-into-being; but let God come-into-being true</char>. Paul’s uses the Gk. verb <char style="it">ginomai
        </char><char style="w" strong="G01096">γίνομαι</char>) [<char style="it">come-into-being</char>] twice
        here. The first usage is in an expression (“may it never <char style="it">come-into-being</char>”); the
        second usage (“but let God <char style="it">come-into-being</char> true”) is a play on that expression.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="ROM 3" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  4   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="ROM 4" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 4:1" />So what’ll we say about what we’ve discovered about Abraham, our forefather physically-speaking<char
        style="sup">[A]</char>? <verse eid="ROM 4:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 4:2" />You see, if Abraham was justified (i.e., examined by a judge and declared to be in the right) by<char
        style="sup">[a]</char> works, he has bragging-rights (i.e., he has the right to be proud of and brag
        about his personal achievements); but no—not with God. <verse eid="ROM 4:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 4:3" />Taking a closer look, what does the Scripture say?</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 4:3"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 4:3">Abraham had faith in God<char style="sup">[B]</char>, and it was credited to him as righteousness<verse eid="ROM 4:3"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 4:4" />The agreed-upon pay which the average worker earns is not awarded to him as a favor or as a gift to charity
        but as a debt which is owed and which he must be compensated for. <verse eid="ROM 4:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 4:5" />Contrast that to the average worker who instead <char style="it">of being owed a wage of righteousness
        </char>believes in the justification of the ungodly <char style="it">and relies on this justification
        instead</char>: his faith is credited to him as righteousness, <verse eid="ROM 4:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 4:6" />just as David too describes the blessings on the person whom God credits righteousness independent of
        works:<verse eid="ROM 4:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 4:7" />Blessed are they whose lawless deeds have been forgiven</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 4:7">And whose sins have been covered over.<verse eid="ROM 4:7"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 4:8" />Blessed is a man to whom the Lord</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 4:8">Will definitely not impute sin.<verse eid="ROM 4:8"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 4:9" />So is this blessing upon the circumcised (i.e., those who’ve made a covenant to obey the Law of Moses)
        or the uncircumcised? The fact of the matter is that we say, “The faith <char style="it">peculiar to
        Abraham </char>was credited to him as righteousness.” <verse eid="ROM 4:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 4:10" />So how was it credited? While circumcised or uncircumcised? No—not while circumcised but while uncircumcised,<verse eid="ROM 4:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 4:11" />and <char style="it">after being credited with righteous</char>, he had the actual circumcision operation
        done to him<char style="sup">[b]</char>, a certification of the righteousness of the faith which he had
        while uncircumcised, resulting in him being the progenitor of every believer who traverses from uncircumcision
        (i.e., them being Gentiles and consequently having no covenant with God) to their being credited with
        righteous, <verse eid="ROM 4:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 4:12" />and a progenitor of a circumcised person (i.e., a person who’s Jewish and consequently follows the Law
        of Moses) <char style="it">whose righteousness</char> is not derived from circumcision alone but is a
        result of following in the footsteps of the faith that our patriarch Abraham had while uncircumcised.<verse eid="ROM 4:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 4:13" />You see, the promise to Abraham or to his offspring, the promise to be the world’s heir, was not by means
        of law (i.e., a method where one follows a list of rules, with the implication of obtaining righteousness
        from it) but rather through faith-<char style="it">based</char>-righteousness. <verse eid="ROM 4:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 4:14" />To that point, if a law-based methodology is the means by which one lays claim <char style="it">to righteousness
        </char>and takes possession of it, faith has been made null and void, and the promise <char style="it">that
        was given to Abraham </char>has been nullified. <verse eid="ROM 4:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 4:15" />The Law <char style="it">of Moses</char> brings about wrath, you see, but where there is no law (i.e.,
        God-originated list of right and wrong), there’s no transgression <char style="it">of that law </char>either.<verse eid="ROM 4:15" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 4:16" />By this<char style="it"> method, righteousness </char>comes out of faith, so that <char style="it">it
        would be dispensed </char>in accordance to grace, resulting in the certainty of the promise to all the
        descendants <char style="it">of Abraham</char>, not only to those who are based out of the Law <char
        style="it">of Moses </char>but also to those who are based out of Abraham’s faith, who is the progenitor
        of us all, <verse eid="ROM 4:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 4:17" />just like it’s written in Scripture, “I have positioned you to be a father (i.e., patriarch, progenitor)
        of every nation and of all Gentiles”…<char style="it">positioning him </char>in plain sight of (<char
        style="it">and therefore getting the full attention of</char>)<char style="it"> </char>the One whom he
        believed: God, the One who makes the dead alive and calls things which be not as being. <verse eid="ROM 4:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 4:18" />Contrary to hope <char style="it">but resting </char>upon hope<char style="sup">[c]</char>, Abraham believed,
        resulting in him becoming “a father of many nations” according to the quotation, “This is the way your
        offspring will be.” <verse eid="ROM 4:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 4:19" />Not weakened in faith after fully noticing his own already-lifeless<char style="sup">[d]</char> body,
        which <char style="it">by that time </char>had existed for a hundred years or so, and the lifelessness<char
        style="sup">[d]</char> of Sarah’s womb, <verse eid="ROM 4:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 4:20" />he didn’t doubt the promise<char style="sup">[e]</char> of God by <char style="it">being in </char>unbelief
        but was strengthened in faith instead, after giving glory to God, <verse eid="ROM 4:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 4:21" />convinced that He who promised is able also to do <char style="it">what He promised</char>. <verse eid="ROM 4:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 4:22" />This is why “it was credited to him as righteousness.” <verse eid="ROM 4:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 4:23" />Now <char style="it">what Scripture says</char>—that <char style="it">righteousness </char>was credited
        to him—was not written for his sake only, <verse eid="ROM 4:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 4:24" />but for our sake too, those to whom it’s going to be credited, <char style="it">namely </char>to those
        believing and laying their trust upon the resurrected-Jesus—our Lord raised from the dead, <verse eid="ROM 4:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 4:25" />who was handed over and delivered <char style="it">to</char> <char style="it">those who killed him </char>by
        our sins and was raised by our justification (i.e., the process of getting us to where we are acquitted
        of our sins before God).<verse eid="ROM 4:25" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">by</char>…Lit: <char style="it">out of</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">he had the actual circumcision operation done to him</char>…Lit: <char style="it">he
        received a sign-type of circumcision</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Contrary to hope but resting upon hope</char>…Lit: <char style="it">against hope upon
        hope. </char>Contrary to any hope in the natural world but resting on hope in the promise of God.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">lifeless</char>…<char style="it">lifelessness</char>…Lit: <char style="it">dead</char>…<char
        style="it">deadness</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the promise</char>…Lit: <char style="it">at the promise</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">discovered about Abraham, our forefather physically-speaking</char>…Or: <char style="it">discovered
        about Abraham, our forefather, according to flesh</char> [<char style="it">i.e., according to his attempts
        to please God through works</char>]. The text is ambiguous.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">had faith in God</char>…Lit: <char style="it">believed in God</char>. Paul, quoting
        from the LXX, uses the dative case for the word <char style="it">God, </char>and the dative case when
        applied to a person after the verb <char style="it">to believe </char>is rendered <char style="it">to
        believe in</char>; a few examples of this are Matt. 21:25; 21:32; Mark 11:31; Luke 20:5. The literal
        rendering, though correct, is misleading and doesn’t agree with the rendering from Hebrew of Gen. 15:4.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="ROM 4" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  5   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="ROM 5" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 5:1" />So having been justified (i.e., examined by God the judge and declared to be righteous) as a result of
        faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ, <verse eid="ROM 5:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 5:2" />through whom we’ve also arrived at the point where we have the access by faith to this grace in which
        we’ve come to stand and boast (i.e., take pride, bask, exult) in a hope<char style="sup">[a]</char> of
        the glory of God.<verse eid="ROM 5:2" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 5:3" />Not only that, but we also boast in our affliction, knowing that the affliction <char style="it">we experience
        </char>accomplishes perseverance, <verse eid="ROM 5:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 5:4" />the<char style="it"> ensuing</char> perseverance approval (i.e., deemed sound as a result of having passed
        tests), the <char style="it">ensuing </char>approval hope, <verse eid="ROM 5:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 5:5" />and the <char style="it">ensuing </char>hope won’t disappoint<char style="sup">[b]</char>, since the
        love of God has been poured out in our hearts through the Holy Spirit who was given to us.<verse eid="ROM 5:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 5:6" />You see, while we were still weak, even still at the appointed time Christ died on behalf of ungodly
        people. <verse eid="ROM 5:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 5:7" />You see, there’s hardly a person who will die on behalf of a person who’s righteous; and maybe someone
        will muster the courage to die on behalf of a good person. <verse eid="ROM 5:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 5:8" />But God’s own love is endorsed to us<char style="sup">[c]</char> <char style="it">by virtue of the fact</char>
        that Christ died on our behalf while we were still sinners. <verse eid="ROM 5:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 5:9" />So now that we’ve been justified by his blood, we’ll all the more be spared from the wrath <char style="it">which
        is due us </char>through him. <verse eid="ROM 5:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 5:10" />You see, if we were reconciled to God through the death of His son while we were enemies, now that we’ve
        been reconciled, we’ll all the more be spared, preserved, and kept intact by his life. <verse eid="ROM 5:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 5:11" />Not only that but we’ll also boast (i.e., take pride, bask, exult) in God through our Lord Jesus Christ,
        through whom we at this time have received the <char style="it">previously stated </char>reconciliation.<verse eid="ROM 5:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 5:12" />Throughout this <char style="it">all</char>, just as sin entered the world through one man and death
        (i.e., stagnation of waste, joylessness, futility, and destruction) through the sin <char style="it">which
        entered</char>, and in this way death propagated to all men, seeing that<char style="sup">[d]</char>
        everybody has sinned— <verse eid="ROM 5:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 5:13" />the fact is, up until law (i.e., an enumeration of God’s commandments) <char style="it">was given, </char>sin
        was in the world (i.e., the established order of human beings), but sin is not transacted and counted
        against a person<char style="sup">[A]</char> when law doesn’t exist. <verse eid="ROM 5:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 5:14" />That aside, death reigned from Adam until Moses<char style="sup">[B]</char> and <char style="it">it also
        reigned </char>over those who didn’t sin by committing the same transgression that Adam committed, who
        is a prototype of and symbolic of <char style="it">all </char>human beings who come after him.<verse eid="ROM 5:14" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 5:15" />But put that aside. The gift <char style="it">of</char> <char style="it">grace </char>doesn’t operate
        the same way as the <char style="it">initial </char>transgression: for if the many died (i.e., were transformed
        into a state of spiritual death, resulting in their lives becoming a stagnation of waste, joylessness,
        futility, and destruction—culminating in physical death itself) by the single transgression, all the
        more did the grace of God and the unrequited-gift overflow<char style="sup">[e]</char> to the many by
        grace, by the one man Jesus Christ. <verse eid="ROM 5:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 5:16" />But the unrequited-gift doesn’t operate the same way as <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">affair
        with </char>the lone person who sinned: on the one hand the judicial review which came out of <char style="it">an
        incident involving </char>a single person resulted in condemnation, but on the other hand the grace<char
        style="it"> which </char>came out of many transgressions resulted in an act of righteousness.<verse eid="ROM 5:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 5:17" />Put another way, if by the transgression of the singular person death reigned through the singular person,
        all the more will they who receive the abundance of the grace <char style="it">of God </char>and the
        gift of righteousness reign in life through the singular person Jesus Christ. <verse eid="ROM 5:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 5:18" />So then, just as condemnation came to every person as the result of one transgression, in the same way
        one act of righteousness resulted in making available to every person the <char style="it">ability of</char>
        to have the slate of his <char style="it">entire</char> life wiped clean<char style="sup">[f]</char>.<verse eid="ROM 5:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 5:19" />For just as through the disobedience of the singular person the many were declared by imposition to be
        sinners, in the same way too through the obedience of the singular person the many are declared by imposition
        to be righteous. <verse eid="ROM 5:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 5:20" />But law (i.e., the expectation of living up to the standards imposed by a list of right and wrong) slipped
        in, sneaking in unplanned as though crashing a party, in order that the transgression <char style="it">seeded
        by Adam and propagated to the entire human race</char> would multiply; but if the sin <char style="it">which
        was seeded </char>multiplied, grace multiplied even more so, <verse eid="ROM 5:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 5:21" />so that just as the sin <char style="it">which was seeded </char>reigned by the death <char style="it">that
        it spawned</char>, in the same way grace would reign through righteousness resulting in eternal life
        (i.e., that special fullness of life, one which begins in this lifetime) through our Lord Jesus Christ.<verse eid="ROM 5:21" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">boast (i.e., take pride, bask, exult) in a hope</char>…Lit: <char style="it">boast upon
        hope</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">won’t disappoint</char>…Lit: <char style="it">won’t be ashamed</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">God’s own love is endorsed to us</char>…Lit: <char style="it">God commends His love
        to us</char>. The Gk. word for <char style="it">commend </char>was in ancient times used when someone
        introduced a person whom he recommends to someone else, with the intention of the two becoming friends
        or joining together in a common cause.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">seeing that</char>…Lit: <char style="it">at which</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">overflow</char>…Also: <char style="it">abound</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">to have the slate of his entire life wiped clean</char>…Lit: <char style="it">justification
        of life</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">transacted and counted against a person</char>…Lit: <char style="it">charged to one’s
        account; imputed</char>. Paul says here and elsewhere that sin cannot take place without God having published
        a list of His commandments. God doesn’t count deeds done in ignorance as sin. This is why when toddlers
        die, they don’t face condemnation: toddlers aren’t old enough to comprehend the commandments. It also
        explains Gen. 4:15, where God didn’t kill Cain for killing Abel but said he’d kill anyone who killed
        Cain.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">death reigned from Adam until Moses</char>…Paul is referring to the timeframe before
        the ultimate law, the Law of Moses, was delivered to the people. Even without the Law, which is the ultimate,
        definitive list compiled by God of what sin is, sin managed to wreak its devastation (i.e., death) during
        that time. Paul said a verse earlier that sin is not transacted (imputed) where law doesn’t exist; but
        he’s clarifying that remark by saying that sin indeed reigned in spite of the Law of Moses not existing.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="ROM 5" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  6   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="ROM 6" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 6:1" />So what’s there to say about this<char style="sup">[a]</char>? Shall we dwell in the sin <char style="it">inherent
        in all humans </char>so that more and more grace <char style="it">will come of it</char>?— <verse eid="ROM 6:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 6:2" />Don’t even think about it<char style="sup">[b]</char>. We—the very people who died (i.e., were transformed
        into a state of spiritual death, resulting in our lives becoming a stagnation of waste, joylessness,
        futility, and destruction) in the sin<char style="sup">[c]</char> <char style="it">inherited by all humans</char>—how
        will we live in it still? <verse eid="ROM 6:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 6:3" />Or are you ignorant <char style="it">of the fact </char>that any person at all who was baptized into
        Christ Jesus (i.e., was initiated into a total dedication to Christ Jesus) was baptized (i.e. was initiated)
        into his death? <verse eid="ROM 6:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 6:4" />So we were buried together with him through the baptism <char style="it">ritual symbolic of a total dedication
        to Christ </char>resulting in death, in order that, just as Christ was raised from the dead through the
        glory of the Father, we too in like fashion would go about in a brand-newness of life. <verse eid="ROM 6:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 6:5" />You see, if we’ve become united together in a way which replicates his death<char style="sup">[d]</char>,
        then certainly we will also be <char style="it">a product </char>of the resurrection, <verse eid="ROM 6:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 6:6" />knowing this: that our old-self<char style="sup">[e]</char> was jointly-crucified, so that the body of
        sin (i.e., the sinful propensity incumbent to our human nature<char style="sup">[A]</char>) would be
        done away with, done away with in respect to us slaving in the sin<char style="sup">[c]</char> <char
        style="it">inherited by all humans</char>: <verse eid="ROM 6:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 6:7" />for he who’s died has been justified from (i.e., cleared of; absolved of) the sin.<verse eid="ROM 6:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 6:8" />Now if we jointly-died with Christ, we believe that we’ll also jointly-live with him, <verse eid="ROM 6:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 6:9" />knowing for a fact that, now that he’s been raised from the dead, Christ won’t die anymore<char style="sup">[f]</char>:
        death no longer has control over him. <verse eid="ROM 6:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 6:10" />The fact is, what<char style="sup">[g]</char> died died once and for all in the sin <char style="it">inherited
        by all humans</char>; what lives lives in God. <verse eid="ROM 6:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 6:11" />In the same way we also consider ourselves to be, on the one hand, dead in the sin, but on the other
        hand living in Christ Jesus.<verse eid="ROM 6:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 6:12" />So don’t keep on letting sin reign in your mortal bodies (i.e., the part of you which hosts carnal desires
        during your life here on Earth) to where you obey its <char style="it">sinful</char> desire, <verse eid="ROM 6:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 6:13" />nor put your body parts (i.e., your physical body parts, each part being a metonymy for various activities
        one engages in. In this case, each part is a metonymy for this or that sin, the whole comprising your
        personal carnal signature) in a place where they’re available to be used as tools, mechanisms, or weapons
        of unrighteousness in the sin <char style="it">inherent in all humans</char>, but instead put yourselves
        in a place where you’re made available in God as alive from the dead and your body parts as tools, mechanisms,
        and weapons of righteousness in God. <verse eid="ROM 6:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 6:14" />To this point, sin will not control you; you see, you’re not under <char style="it">the jurisdiction
        of </char>law (i.e., your life is decided by a list of do’s-and-dont’s) but under <char style="it">the
        jurisdiction of </char>grace instead.<verse eid="ROM 6:14" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 6:15" />So now<char style="sup">[h]</char>…shall we sin since we’re not under <char style="it">the jurisdiction
        of </char>law but under <char style="it">the jurisdiction of </char>grace instead?—Don’t even think about
        it<char style="sup">[i]</char>. <verse eid="ROM 6:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 6:16" />You ought to know<char style="sup">[j]</char> that whatever thing you make yourself available to be used
        by—used to the point of being obedient to—you’re enslaved to, <char style="it">a slave </char>of either
        sin culminating in death or obedience culminating in righteousness. <verse eid="ROM 6:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 6:17" />God is so good<char style="sup">[k]</char>:<char style="it"> </char>you were slaves of sin, but you whole-heartedly
        obeyed what was presented to you in a clear, orderly, and systematic way<char style="sup">[l]</char>:
        the <char style="it">particular</char> kind of instruction <char style="it">which has you walking in
        the righteousness of faith rather than just following a set of rules</char>; <verse eid="ROM 6:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 6:18" />having been freed from the sin <char style="it">inherent in all humans</char>, you were enslaved by righteousness.<verse eid="ROM 6:18" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 6:19" />The subject I’m talking about is the human condition and human experience on account of the weakness
        of your flesh (i.e., of your lack of self-ability apart from God; of that part of you which has carnal
        desires; of that part of you which fails to live up to God’s standards). You see, just as you made your
        <char style="it">body </char>parts available to be used as slaves in the filth and degradation<char style="sup">[m]</char>
        <char style="it">of carnality </char>and in <char style="it">an artifact of sin, </char>namely the refusal
        to be restrained by any laws, rules, or codes of conduct, which leads to even more of the same<char style="sup">[n]</char>,
        in like fashion make your <char style="it">body </char>parts available at this time to be used as slaves
        by the righteousness <char style="it">which is a consequence of faith </char>which leads to holiness<char
        style="sup">[o]</char>. <verse eid="ROM 6:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 6:20" />The fact is, when you were yet slaves of sin, you were free <char style="it">with respect to</char> <char
        style="it">living </char>in righteousness.<verse eid="ROM 6:20" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 6:21" />So what final result did you obtain back then, based on the things which you’re now ashamed of? The fact
        of the matter is that those things end in death. <verse eid="ROM 6:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 6:22" />But as things stand now, <char style="it">on the one hand </char>having been freed from the sin <char
        style="it">inherent in all humans </char>but <char style="it">on the other hand </char>having become
        slaves in God, you’re getting holiness as your final result <char style="it">on the one hand</char>,
        but you end up with eternal life (i.e., that special fullness of life) <char style="it">on the other</char>.<verse eid="ROM 6:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 6:23" />For the wages of the sin <char style="it">inherent in all humans is</char> death, but the gift of God
        <char style="it">is </char>that special fullness of life (eternal life) in Christ Jesus our Lord.<verse eid="ROM 6:23" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">what’s there to say about this</char>…Lit: <char style="it">what shall we say</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">don’t even think about it</char>…Lit: <char style="it">may it not be</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">in the sin</char>…Or: <char style="it">to the sin</char>. Literal rendering is <char
        style="it">in </char>[or perhaps<char style="it"> by </char>or <char style="it">with</char>]<char style="it">
        the sin </char>not <char style="it">to the sin.</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">in a way which replicates his death</char>…Lit<char style="it">: in the likeness of
        his death</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">old-self</char>…Lit: <char style="it">old man</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">won’t die anymore</char>…Lit<char style="it">: dies no longer</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">what</char>…Lit<char style="it">: that which</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">So now</char>…Lit: <char style="it">So what?</char> Or: <char style="it">What then?</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Don’t even think about it</char>…Lit: <char style="it">may it not be</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">You ought to know</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Don’t you know</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">God is so good</char>…Lit: <char style="it">grace</char> [<char style="it">kindness</char>,
        <char style="it">mercy</char>, <char style="it">benevolence</char>] <char style="it">with</char> [also
        <char style="it">to</char>] <char style="it">God</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">presented to you in a clear, orderly, and systematic way</char>…Lit: <char style="it">put
        in your custody</char>. A metaphor of a sort which compares the communication of a teaching to the transfer
        of the custody of a prisoner from one party to another.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[m]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[m]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">filth and degradation</char>…Lit: <char style="it">uncleanness</char>. Rooted in the
        uncleanness defined by the Law of Moses.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[n]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[n]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">in an artifact of sin the refusal to be restrained by any laws, rules, or codes of conduct,
        which leads to even more of the same</char>…Lit: <char style="it">in the lawlessness unto the lawlessness</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[o]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[o]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">by the righteousness which is a consequence of faith which leads to holiness</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">in the righteousness unto holiness</char>. This is a parallel construct to the previous
        phrase <char style="it">in the lawlessness unto the lawlessness.</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the sinful propensity incumbent to our human nature</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the
        body of sin</char>. The perspective which comes out of the NT is that the carnal nature present in all
        people is a component of the physical body; therefore, the words <char style="it">body </char>and <char
        style="it">flesh </char>can or will, depending on the context, refer to the carnal nature, rather than
        the physical body itself. The words <char style="it">body </char>and <char style="it">flesh </char>are
        used this way throughout the chapter.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="ROM 6" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  7   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="ROM 7" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 7:1" />Or are you unaware, comrades<char style="sup">[a]</char> (<char style="it">and </char>I’m speaking to
        those <char style="it">of you </char>who’re familiar with the operative details of a law-code), that
        the Law <char style="it">of Moses </char>exercises control over a person <char style="it">only </char>during
        that person’s lifetime? <verse eid="ROM 7:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 7:2" />To this point, a married woman<char style="sup">[A]</char> (<char style="it">who owing to marriage laws
        is under the authority of her husband, who has the legal right to initiate a divorce—but not she</char>)
        is legally bound to her husband while he’s alive. If the husband were to die, <char style="it">then-and-only-then
        </char>will she be released<char style="sup">[b]</char> from her legal constraint to her<char style="it">
        </char>husband. <verse eid="ROM 7:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 7:3" />So then, while her husband’s still alive, she’d be officially labeled an adulteress if she were to get
        <char style="it">married (and therefore under the authority of and bound to) </char>to<char style="it">
        </char>another man<char style="sup">[c]</char>.<verse eid="ROM 7:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 7:4" />In the same way, my <char style="it">fellow </char>comrades, through the body of Christ you too have
        been put to death in relation to the Law <char style="it">of Moses </char>resulting in you having come
        into being <char style="it">under the authority of and bound </char>to another—to him who’s been raised
        from the dead—in order that you would produce aftereffects<char style="sup">[d]</char> in God. <verse eid="ROM 7:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 7:5" />You see, when you were in the flesh (i.e., trying in and of yourself to live up to God’s rules while
        at the same time beholden to your carnal nature), the passions of the sins <char style="it">pervasive
        to mankind</char>, those things that, on account of the Law, were repeatedly at work in our body parts
        (i.e., your personal carnal signature) resulting in the production of aftereffects in death (i.e., in
        a stagnation of waste, joylessness, futility, and destruction).<verse eid="ROM 7:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 7:6" />But as things stand now, we’ve been released<char style="sup">[e]</char> from the Law <char style="it">of
        Moses</char>, having died to that which kept holding us down, so that we serve in newness of spirit<char
        style="sup">[B]</char> (i.e. walking in line with and dominated by a regenerated human spirit, which
        is in communion with the Holy Spirit) and not oldness of letter (i.e., a strict, literal, exacting interpretation
        of the verbatim Law of Moses, along with a grueling, rigid adherence done the “old way”—out of a person’s
        self-ability).<verse eid="ROM 7:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 7:7" />So what’s there to say about this<char style="sup">[f]</char>? <char style="it">Are we to conclude that
        </char>the Law <char style="it">of Moses</char> <char style="it">is characteristic of and has the quality
        and nature of </char>sin?—Don’t even think about it<char style="sup">[g]</char>—on the contrary I would
        not have come to know, recognize, and understand the sin <char style="it">pervasive to mankind </char>if
        not through law (i.e., by conducting my life under the weight of a long list of God-ordained rules);
        for indeed I would’ve come to know <char style="it">this </char>first-hand had not the Law <char style="it">of
        Moses </char>kept on telling <char style="it">me</char> over and over<char style="sup">[C]</char>, “Thou
        shalt not covet <char style="it">such-and-such</char><char style="sup">[D]</char>.” <verse eid="ROM 7:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 7:8" />Sin took advantage of the situation through the commandment “<char style="it">thou shalt not covet</char>”
        and worked utterly in me every sort of coveting imaginable<char style="sup">[h]</char>: you see, apart
        from law (i.e., being forced to obey a list of rules) sin <char style="it">is </char>dead. <verse eid="ROM 7:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 7:9" />In the past I was alive and living apart from law; but the commandment came and the sin <char style="it">of
        coveting which I just mentioned </char>sprang to life; <verse eid="ROM 7:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 7:10" />I died. It became evident in me that the commandment—the same one <char style="it">leading</char> to
        life—<char style="it">was leading</char> to death. <verse eid="ROM 7:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 7:11" />To be more specific, the sin <char style="it">of coveting </char>through the commandment took advantage
        of the situation, fooled me completely, and killed me (i.e., caused me to die spiritually) by this. <verse eid="ROM 7:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 7:12" />Consequently, the Law <char style="it">of Moses is</char> indeed holy, and the commandment “<char style="it">thou
        shalt not covet</char>” <char style="it">is </char>holy and just and good.<verse eid="ROM 7:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 7:13" />So the thing which is good became <char style="it">a mechanism of </char>death in me, <char style="it">right</char>?<char
        style="sup">[E]</char>—Don’t even think about it<char style="sup">[g]</char>; on the contrary, in order
        that <char style="it">the nature and devastation of </char>sin would become apparent, sin utterly worked
        death through the good in me, so that the sin <char style="it">of coveting </char>would reach its maximal
        efficacy<char style="sup">[i]</char> through the commandment “<char style="it">thou shalt not covet.</char>”<verse eid="ROM 7:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 7:14" />You see, we know for a fact that the Law is intrinsically spiritual; I am fleshly (i.e., the nature of
        my physical body is that it is susceptible to carnal temptations, and that part of me does not want to
        serve God), having been sold by the sin <char style="it">pervasive to mankind</char>: <verse eid="ROM 7:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 7:15" />I don’t understand nor do I recognize what it is that I’m getting done; the fact of the matter is, I’m
        not putting into practice what I want—I’m doing what I hate instead. <verse eid="ROM 7:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 7:16" />But if I’m doing what I don’t want to, I concur with the Law <char style="it">of Moses, </char>concurring
        that it’s good. <verse eid="ROM 7:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 7:17" />At this point, though, it’s no longer me personally accomplishing this but rather the sin which inhabits
        me.<verse eid="ROM 7:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 7:18" />You see, I know for a fact that good does not inhabit me, that is, in my flesh (i.e. in my human, carnal
        nature); for the wanting is present in me, at hand ready to jump in, but getting the good done is not
        happening. <verse eid="ROM 7:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 7:19" />In fact, I’m not doing the good that I want to do, but instead, I’m doing the bad which I don’t want
        to do and doing it on a day-to-day basis. <verse eid="ROM 7:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 7:20" />Now if what I don’t want to do is the thing that I’m doing, It’s no longer me producing the finished
        product but the sin which inhabits me <char style="it">is producing it </char>instead. <verse eid="ROM 7:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 7:21" />I’m discovering the Law <char style="it">of God </char>(i.e., the principle that one should do right
        and live according to God’s will), then, with the wanting in me to do the good, because the bad is present
        in me, <char style="it">ready to rear its ugly head</char>; <verse eid="ROM 7:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 7:22" />you see, I delight in the Law of God with respect to the inner-person, <verse eid="ROM 7:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 7:23" />but I see another law (i.e., a different principle) in my body parts (i.e., in my unique carnal signature)
        waging war against the law of my mind (i.e. against the principles by which my mind operate), <char style="it">defeating
        me </char>and making me a prisoner of the sin which exists in my body parts. <verse eid="ROM 7:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 7:24" /><char style="it">What </char>a miserable person I am: who’ll rescue me from this body <char style="it">which
        is rooted in </char>death?— <verse eid="ROM 7:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 7:25" />God is so good<char style="sup">[j]</char> through Jesus Christ our Lord!—So then me—on the one hand
        I’m enslaved in mind to a law of God (i.e., to a principle set in place by God), but on the other hand
        <char style="it">I’m enslaved </char>in flesh to a law of sin (i.e., to a principle of sin caused by
        carnality).<verse eid="ROM 7:25" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">then-and-only-then will she be released</char>…Lit: <char style="it">she has been released</char>.
        The perfect tense is the reason for the extrapolation <char style="it">then-and-only-then.</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">bound to a different man</char>…Lit: [<char style="it">with</char>] <char style="it">a
        different man</char>. The dative case of <char style="it">different man </char>is same case as <char
        style="it">to her husband </char>in v. 2, and refers to the same thing; hence the interpolation.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">produce aftereffects</char>…Lit: <char style="it">bear fruit</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">released</char>…As this is the same word used in v. 2, Paul is connecting the analogy
        of a wife who’s released from her marriage to us being released from the Law.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">what’s there to say about this</char>…Lit: <char style="it">what shall we say</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">don’t even think about it</char>…Lit: <char style="it">may it not be. </char>Ref. note
        of Rom. 3:4.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">every sort of coveting imaginable</char>…Lit: <char style="it">all covetings</char>.
        A figure of speech. </char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">would reach its maximal efficacy</char>…Lit: <char style="it">would become exceedingly
        sinful</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">God is so good</char>…Lit: <char style="it">grace</char> [<char style="it">kindness</char>,
        <char style="it">mercy</char>, <char style="it">benevolence</char>] <char style="it">with</char> [also
        <char style="it">to</char>] <char style="it">God</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">married woman</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the under-man woman</char>. The GT is saying
        that she’s under the power of a man. According to the Law of Moses, only a man could initiate a divorce.
        Ref. note of Matt. 5:31.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">newness of spirit</char>…Paul’s intentional omission of the definite article before
        <char style="it">spirit </char>(and for that matter, before <char style="it">law</char>) refers to the
        way in which a believer conducts his life. It does not specifically refer to the Holy Spirit per se,
        but instead refers to a lifestyle where one walks with the Holy Spirit. Some translations assume that
        the definite article is implied (which there are plenty of examples of such implied definite articles
        in other NT prepositional phrases), and therefore <char style="it">spirit </char>here refers to <char
        style="it">the </char>[<char style="it">Holy</char>]<char style="it"> </char>Spirit. They point to 2
        Cor. 3:6 as corroborating evidence. I disagree; Paul is consistent and precise in his inclusion or exclusion
        of definite articles in the preceding chapters of Romans, and he would’ve explicitly added one to specify
        Holy Spirit for the purpose of resolving the ambiguity he most certainly would’ve foreseen.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the Law of Moses kept on telling me over and over</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the Law
        was saying (</char>where<char style="it"> was saying </char>is an imperfect verb tense<char style="it">)</char>.
        Unlike other NT writers (Mark comes to mind), and also because his epistles are treatises and not story-narratives
        like the Gospels, Paul uses the imperfect tense sparingly. This usage here feels as though Paul is being
        reminded of this over and over in his head, rather than seeing it appear over and over again in the Law.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[D]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[D]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Thou shalt not covet such-and-such</char>…Lit: <char style="it">you shall not long for</char>.
        The word <char style="it">long for </char>comes straight out of Exod. 20:17 in the LXX, so a reader in
        ancient times who was familiar with the LXX OT would immediately recognize this reference to the Ten
        Commandments.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[E]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[E]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">So the thing which is good became a mechanism of death in me, right?</char>…Or: <char
        style="it">So death became something which is good in me</char>, <char style="it">right?</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">So death became good in</char> [or: <char style="it">with</char>; <char style="it">to</char>]
        <char style="it">me</char>. The word <char style="it">death </char>is in the nominative case and <char
        style="it">good </char>is either nominative or accusative, and for the GT to fit into a strict grammar
        parsing, the English translation must put <char style="it">death </char>as the subject and assume <char
        style="it">good </char>is accusative rather than nominative, meaning that <char style="it">good </char>takes
        the predicate rather than the subject. The rendering with <char style="it">death </char>as the subject
        and <char style="it">good </char>as the predicate doesn’t make sense, hence other translations (NASB
        translates this, “that which is <char style="it">good </char>became a cause of death for me”), change
        this according to the context. This means Paul made a mistake when he wrote this—a single-letter slipup,
        as <char style="it">thanatos </char>(death, θάνατος/Strong’s 2288) need only be changed to <char style="it">thanaton
        </char>(θάνατόν). On a side note, J.B. Phillips believed that Paul made a mistake in 1 Cor. 14:22a (ref.
        note).</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="ROM 7" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  8   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="ROM 8" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 8:1" />Therefore, there’s nothing <char style="it">of</char> condemnation now with those in Christ Jesus: <verse eid="ROM 8:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 8:2" />The law of the spirit of life (i.e., the principle of living a spiritual life in communion with the Holy
        Spirit) set you free from the law of the sin <char style="it">which afflicts mankind </char>and the <char
        style="it">ensuing </char>death (i.e. the principle of sin coming about due to our human nature and the
        resulting stagnation of waste, joylessness, futility, and destruction). <verse eid="ROM 8:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 8:3" />You see, the inability of the Law <char style="it">of Moses </char>in that it was continually weak through
        the flesh (i.e., through human ability alone apart from God and aggravated by human carnality), God sent
        His very-own son in sinful-flesh form and, in regard to sin, condemned the sin in the flesh, <verse eid="ROM 8:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 8:4" />so that the decrees of the Law <char style="it">of Moses </char>would be fulfilled in us, in those who’re
        not going about their day-to-day business according to flesh (i.e., according to their own ability apart
        from God and according to their carnal nature) but rather according to spirit (i.e., according to a spiritual
        life, a life in communion with the Holy Spirit). <verse eid="ROM 8:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 8:5" />For those whose existence is in accordance with the nature of the flesh think about the things of the
        flesh; those <char style="it">whose existence is in accordance with </char>spirit (i.e. with living a
        spiritual life) <char style="it">think about </char>the things of the Spirit. <verse eid="ROM 8:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 8:6" />The fact of the matter is that the flesh-mindset<char style="it"> is </char>death; the mindset of the
        spirit <char style="it">is </char>life and peace. <verse eid="ROM 8:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 8:7" />Therefore, the mindset of the flesh is an enemy to God; for it doesn’t submit to the Law of God; in fact,
        it can’t do so: <verse eid="ROM 8:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 8:8" />Those existing in flesh can’t please God.<verse eid="ROM 8:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 8:9" />You aren’t in flesh (i.e., live out of your natural ability and through your carnal nature) but in spirit
        (i.e., live out of a regenerated human spirit in communion with the Holy Spirit), if God’s Spirit in
        fact dwells in you. (If a given person doesn’t have Christ’s Spirit, that person’s not <char style="it">a
        part</char> <char style="it">of him and </char>from him<char style="sup">[A]</char>.) <verse eid="ROM 8:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 8:10" />Now if Christ is in you—yes—the body is dead through sin, but the spirit has life and is alive through
        righteousness. <verse eid="ROM 8:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 8:11" />If the Spirit of the One who raised Jesus from the dead dwells in you all, He who raised Jesus from the
        dead will also invigorate<char style="sup">[a]</char> your mortal bodies through the Indwelling Spirit
        in you.<verse eid="ROM 8:11" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 8:12" />So then, comrades<char style="sup">[b]</char>, we have an obligation—<char style="it">but</char> not
        to the flesh—<char style="it">we’re not</char> to live according to flesh. <verse eid="ROM 8:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 8:13" />If you live according to flesh, you’re going to die (i.e., experience spiritual death), you see; but
        if by spirit you put to death the practices of the body, you’re going to live. <verse eid="ROM 8:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 8:14" />The fact is, any people—any people at all—who’re led by the Spirit of God: these <char style="it">people</char>
        are sons of God. <verse eid="ROM 8:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 8:15" />In fact, you have not received a spirit (i.e., a prevailing disposition) of slavery resulting in fear
        again; instead, you’ve received a spirit of adoption, one with which we cry out, “Papa<char style="sup">[c]</char>!
        Father!” <verse eid="ROM 8:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 8:16" />The Spirit himself in conjunction with our spirit<char style="sup">[B]</char> jointly declares that we
        are children of God. <verse eid="ROM 8:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 8:17" />If children, heirs too—heirs of God indeed; joint-heirs of Christ’s <char style="it">inheritance</char>,
        if indeed we jointly-suffer <char style="it">with him </char>in order that we too would be jointly-glorified.<verse eid="ROM 8:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 8:18" />Regarding this point, I figure that the present-day sufferings aren’t even in the same ballpark as the
        glory that’s going to be revealed to us. <verse eid="ROM 8:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 8:19" />In fact, the creation is in suspense waiting for the sons of God to break onto the scene<char style="sup">[d]</char>.<verse eid="ROM 8:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 8:20" />You see, the creation was subjected to futility—not willingly <char style="it">of course</char>—no—it
        <char style="it">was subjected</char> on account of whoever or whatever subjected it, <char style="it">resting
        </char>upon hope<char style="sup">[e]</char> <verse eid="ROM 8:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 8:21" />that the creation itself will be set free from the slavery of corruption (a corruption like decomposing
        organic matter) over to the freedom of the sons of God. <verse eid="ROM 8:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 8:22" />Regarding this, we know from first-hand experience that every bit of the creation moans and groans in
        unison and is in agony in unison <char style="it">from the time it was first corrupted </char>up to now.<verse eid="ROM 8:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 8:23" />Not only <char style="it">does the creation moan, groan, and agonize </char>but so do those who have
        a token sample of celebration<char style="sup">[C]</char> of the Spirit—namely us—we too moan and groan
        within ourselves in suspense waiting for an adoption, the redemption of our body (i.e., the restoration
        of the body to its original purpose and function and the elimination of the carnal nature). <verse eid="ROM 8:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 8:24" />In fact, we were saved by hope; hope which is seen (i.e., is of something which verifiably exists in
        the physical world) isn’t hope—just who hopes for what he sees? <verse eid="ROM 8:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 8:25" />Now if we hope for what we don’t see, we’re in suspense awaiting it, exercising perseverance throughout.<verse eid="ROM 8:25" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 8:26" />In the same way, the Spirit helps us (i.e., he gets ahold of something in unison with us against that
        something) with our weakness: you see, we don’t know how we must pray or what we must pray; instead <char
        style="it">of us being constrained by that limitation</char>, when he intercedes on behalf of others<char
        style="sup">[D]</char>, the Spirit himself intercedes (i.e., he personally acts on another’s behalf by
        joining up with him in order to obtain a goal, to hit the mark like an arrow hitting its target, <char
        style="it">like a baseball player who gets a good solid hit on a ball putting it in the spot he’s chosen</char>)
        with moans and groans which can’t be put into speech. <verse eid="ROM 8:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 8:27" />The one who searches the hearts knows for a fact the thoughts, opinions, and intentions of the Spirit,
        since he intercedes on behalf of<char style="sup">[D]</char> people set apart for God<char style="sup">[f]</char>.<verse eid="ROM 8:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 8:28" />We know for a fact that God works all things in unison<char style="sup">[E]</char> towards a good goal
        for them who love God, those who exist as the according-to-purpose called-ones, <verse eid="ROM 8:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 8:29" />since they whom He foreknew (i.e., knew one’s individual personality, nature, and spiritual acuity before
        it became apparent), he foreordained<char style="sup">[F]</char> to conform to the image of His son,
        resulting in him being firstborn among many comrades and brothers. <verse eid="ROM 8:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ROM 8:30" />Those whom He foreordained, He also called (i.e., summoned to believe in Him). And those He called, He
        also justified (i.e., declared “not guilty”); those He justified, He also glorified.<verse eid="ROM 8:30" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ROM 8:31" />So what’s the takeaway?<char style="sup">[g]</char>—If God’s on our side<char style="sup">[h]</char>,
        who’s on the opposing team? <verse eid="ROM 8:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ROM 8:32" />He who certainly didn’t spare His own son, but surrendered him <char style="it">to crucifixion</char>
        on behalf of us all, how will He not freely and willingly give us all things? <verse eid="ROM 8:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ROM 8:33" />Who will press charges against those chosen by God, those in God’s church? God’s doing the justifying
        (i.e., God’s the one Who’s issuing the “not guilty” verdicts); <verse eid="ROM 8:33" />
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ROM 8:34" />who’s issuing the guilty verdicts? <char style="it">Is the person who’s issuing the guilty verdicts </char>Christ
        Jesus, the <char style="it">fellow </char>who died, but—beyond that—was resurrected? <char style="it">The
        fellow </char>who’s also God’s chief executive<char style="sup">[i]</char>, <char style="it">the fellow</char>
        who also intercedes on our behalf? <verse eid="ROM 8:34" />
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ROM 8:35" />What<char style="sup">[G]</char> will separate us from the love of Christ—tribulation…distress…persecution…famine…nakedness…danger…sword
        (i.e., another’s imposition of brute force upon you even to the threat of death)? <verse eid="ROM 8:35" />
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ROM 8:36" />Just as it’s written:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 8:36"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 8:36">We’re being put to death all day long for Your sake</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 8:36">We’ve been slated <char style="it">for slaughter </char>as though <char style="it">we’re </char>sheep
        of slaughter<verse eid="ROM 8:36"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="37" style="v" sid="ROM 8:37" />No—in all these things we come out on top conquering through the one who loved us. <verse eid="ROM 8:37" />
      <verse number="38" style="v" sid="ROM 8:38" />In fact, I’ve reached the point where I’m persuaded that neither death nor life nor <char style="it">Satan’s</char>
        agents nor <char style="it">demon</char>-chieftains<char style="sup">[H]</char> nor present-events nor
        future-events nor unexplainable, supernatural, or miraculous powers<char style="sup">[H]</char>, <verse eid="ROM 8:38" />
      <verse number="39" style="v" sid="ROM 8:39" />nor heights (i.e., high highs) nor depths (i.e., depths of despair) nor some other creature will be able
        to separate us from the love of God, love which is in Christ Jesus our Lord.<verse eid="ROM 8:39" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">invigorate</char>…Lit: <char style="it">make alive</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Papa</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Abba</char>. The Aramaic word for <char style="it">father</char>.
        The Roman Gentiles, the audience of this epistle, must’ve not only known this word but appreciated the
        intimacy it conveyed.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">In fact, the creation is in suspense waiting for the sons of God to break onto the scene</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">For the eager expectation of the creation eagerly awaits the revelation of the sons
        of God</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">resting upon hope</char>…Lit: <char style="it">upon hope</char>. Repetition of <char
        style="it">upon hope </char>in Rom 4:18, <char style="it">against hope upon hope</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">people set apart to God</char>…Lit: <char style="it">saints</char>. <char style="it">Holy
        people </char>is what <char style="it">saints </char>means literally. <char style="it">Holy </char>also
        means <char style="it">set apart. </char>The saints are God’s people, those who obey Him, those who walk
        in His ways.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">So what’s the takeaway?</char>…Lit: <char style="it">So what shall we say?</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">on our side</char>…Lit: <char style="it">on our behalf</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">God’s chief executive</char>…Lit: <char style="it">at the right hand of God</char>.
        Ref. notes of Matt. 22:24, 26:64.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a part of him and from him</char>…Lit: <char style="it">of him</char>. Any person who
        has the Holy Spirit in them is a believer.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">The Spirit himself in conjunction with our spirit</char>…A clear summary of Paul’s usage
        of the word spirit in this chapter and in his other epistles. As the GT doesn’t use capital letters,
        it isn’t always obvious whether Paul is referring to the Holy Spirit or to the regenerated human spirit—or
        to both. The context in addition to the inclusion or omission of the definite article (in line with rules
        for definite articles) is the only way of deciding.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a token sample of celebration</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the first-fruits</char>.
        The Gk. word <char style="it">aparchā </char><char style="w" strong="G00536">ἀπαρχή</char>). Also used
        in Jam. 1:18. While the word <char style="it">aparchā </char>refers to the classical Gk. pagan offering
        of the first produce of the harvest, we assume Paul and James are referring to the wave offering of Lev.
        23:9–11. In both cases, a first-fruit offering is a small sample of the year’s harvest—the most excellent
        sample obtainable—a token which is offered at harvest time to God (or the god) from whom is credited
        for causing the bountiful harvest. The first-fruits is the following: (a) a recognition and remembrance
        that God’s blessing, and not simply man’s labor, is the reason the crops grew and that there is a harvest;
        (b) a celebration of the harvest; (c) a time of thankfulness like the Thanksgiving holiday in the US;
        (d) a holiday which marks a change in the calendar year; (e) the end of a season of work and an acknowledgement
        of the work done during that season; (f) the very best of the best. When the word <char style="it">aparchā
        </char>is used in the NT, it refers to one, to several, or to all of these.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[D]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[D]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">intercedes on behalf of others</char>…<char style="it">intercedes on behalf of</char>…In
        the GT, the word <char style="it">intercedes </char>in v.26 begins with the preposition <char style="it">huper
        </char><char style="w" strong="G05228">ὑπέρ</char>) used as a prefix. In v. 27, <char style="it">intercede
        </char>does not begin with <char style="it">huper</char>; instead <char style="it">huper</char> is used
        right after <char style="it">intercede </char>as an ordinary preposition, rendered <char style="it">on
        behalf of</char>. This is why <char style="it">intercedes on behalf of others</char> was added to v.
        26: it captures the differences between <char style="it">intercedes </char>as they appear in vv. 27,28.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[E]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[E]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">God works all things in unison</char>…Or: <char style="it">all things work in unison</char>.
        The principal manuscripts are split fairly evenly between these two renderings, with the two oldest ones
        favoring <char style="it">God works everything in unison. </char>Some claim that this verse says that
        God is the instigator of bad things, causing them to happen so that He can work them to do good; this
        may have been the reason why manuscripts were altered centuries ago. This verse does not say what the
        cause of bad things is; it simply says that if and when things occur—bad things included—God then works
        them for good. Since v. 31 says “if God’s on our side,” then it stands to reason that God is not the
        cause of bringing bad things into believers’ lives, otherwise, that would constitute Him being against
        them rather than for them.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[F]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[F]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">foreordained</char>…The word’s Gk. root means: to mark out the boundaries; to lay down;
        to mark out; to determine; to appoint; to settle; to assign. The prefix means <char style="it">ahead
        of time. </char>Concatenating the meanings of the prefix and the root gives one a clearer idea of what
        <char style="it">foreordain </char>means. </char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[G]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[G]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">what</char>…Lit: <char style="it">who</char>. Paul’s using a figure of speech, a personification,
        to refer to the items which he proceeds to list, as though each item is a person. The items listed are
        delimited by ellipses in an effort to convey this figure of speech to the reader.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[H]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[H]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Satan’s agents nor demon-chieftains</char>…<char style="it">unexplainable, supernatural,
        or miraculous powers</char>…Lit: <char style="it">angels</char> [<char style="it">messengers</char>;
        <char style="it">agents</char>] <char style="it">nor rulers</char>…<char style="it">powers</char>. All
        the items in the list are of incorporeal things. It can be understood with no doubt that the word <char
        style="it">angel </char>here refers to demonic agents; ref. 2 Cor. 12:7 for confirmation. As the introductory
        word <char style="it">angel </char>speaks of demonic forces, it’s safe to assume that <char style="it">rulers</char>
        refers to demonic forces as well. This is also confirmed by the word’s usage in Eph. 6:12 and Col. 2:15.
        The justification of adding the descriptive words <char style="it">unexplainable, supernatural, or miraculous</char>
        before the word <char style="it">powers </char>is (in addition to the other items being incorporeal)
        the way <char style="it">powers </char>is used in Matt. 4:12; Mark 6:2; 9:39 to refer to miracles, and
        in Matt. 24:29 to refer to the stars. </char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="ROM 8" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter  9   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="ROM 9" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 9:1" />Truthfully, I’m telling you in Christ—I’m not lying—my conscience attests <char style="it">to the fact</char>
        in conjunction with the Holy Spirit <verse eid="ROM 9:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 9:2" />that I have tremendous sorrow and incessant pain in my heart: <verse eid="ROM 9:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 9:3" /><char style="it">that is, </char>that I would be granted this request<char style="sup">[a]</char>, that
        I—even I—be accursed and shunned by the Messiah, the Christ, for the sake of my brethren<char style="sup">[b]</char>,
        my flesh &amp; blood relatives <verse eid="ROM 9:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 9:4" />(the ones <char style="it">I’m </char>referring to<char style="it"> </char>are the Israelites), they
        who have the Lineal Descent Selection<char style="sup">[c]</char>; the <char style="it">Shekhinah</char>-Glory<char
        style="sup">[A]</char> (i.e., God manifesting Himself in His glory, such as in the burning bush); the
        Covenants (i.e., the Abrahamic, Mosaic, and Davidic covenants); the Enactment of the Law <char style="it">of
        Moses</char><char style="sup">[d]</char>; the Religious Service (i.e., the temple rituals, sacrificial
        system, priestly traditions, etc.); the Promises— <verse eid="ROM 9:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 9:5" />who are <char style="it">the descendants</char> of the patriarchs, and from whom the Messiah <char style="it">came</char>,
        physically speaking, who is over all, God <char style="it">be </char>blessed forevermore. Let us pause
        a moment for that to sink in.<char style="sup">[e]</char><verse eid="ROM 9:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 9:6" />It’s not as though the word of God has been ineffectual. The fact of the matter is, Israel doesn’t consist
        solely of everyone who was spawned from the nation of Israel<char style="sup">[f]</char>, <verse eid="ROM 9:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 9:7" />nor are all of Abraham’s children (i.e., his sons, grandsons, etc.) his seed (i.e., his true father-to-son
        lineal descendants and progeny); rather, “Your seed shall be in <char style="it">and through</char> Isaac.”<verse eid="ROM 9:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 9:8" />In other words<char style="sup">[g]</char>, the children of the flesh (i.e., the biological offsprings)
        are not the ones who’re the children of God<char style="sup">[B]</char>, rather the children of promise
        are regarded as being the seed. <verse eid="ROM 9:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 9:9" />In fact, this statement <char style="it">from the Old Testament </char>is based on promise, “I’ll come
        at the right time<char style="sup">[h]</char>, and Sarah will have a son<char style="sup">[i]</char>.”<verse eid="ROM 9:9" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 9:10" />Not just that but Rebekah too, while doing on the marriage bed what married couples do, <char style="it">was
        impregnated</char><char style="sup">[j]</char> from <char style="it">what came</char> out of one man,
        from Isaac, one of our patriarchs. <verse eid="ROM 9:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 9:11" />You see, while they had not been born yet and committed any good or bad deed, in order that freedom of
        choice in God’s purpose would persist— <verse eid="ROM 9:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 9:12" />not as a works-outcome but rather as a calling<char style="it">-</char>outcome, <char style="it">the
        free choice of </char>the One Who calls<char style="sup">[C]</char>—she was told that, “the <char style="it">older</char>
        <char style="it">and therefore </char>superior<char style="it"> </char>one shall serve the younger,”<verse eid="ROM 9:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 9:13" />as it’s written:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:13"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:13">I loved Isaac;</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:13">I hated (i.e., despised; had contempt for; loathed) Esau<verse eid="ROM 9:13"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 9:14" />What’s the takeaway<char style="sup">[k]</char>? Not that God’s unfair, right?—Don’t even think about
        it.<char style="sup">[l]</char> <verse eid="ROM 9:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 9:15" />Furthermore, he tells Moses:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:15"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:15">I’ll have mercy on whom I so happen to show mercy to</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:15">And have pity on whom I so happen to have pity on<verse eid="ROM 9:15"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 9:16" />So then it’s not <char style="it">based on </char>the person desiring this or that or the one pursuing
        this or that, but rather it’s a product of the mercy of God. <verse eid="ROM 9:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 9:17" />In fact, in regard to Pharaoh the Old Testament<char style="sup">[m]</char> says:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:17"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:17">I brought you to prominence for this:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:17">In order to demonstrate in you My power</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:17">And in order to make My reputation<char style="sup">[n]</char> known</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:17">To everyone throughout all the land <verse eid="ROM 9:17"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 9:18" />So then, He shows mercy to whom He pleases; He hardens <char style="it">the heart of </char>whom He pleases.<verse eid="ROM 9:18" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 9:19" />I know what you’re going to say now<char style="sup">[o]</char>: how <char style="it">can</char> He blame
        <char style="it">anyone for anything </char>anymore? In this regard, who has arrived at a point where
        he’s<char style="it"> successfully </char>resisted His will? <verse eid="ROM 9:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 9:20" />Wow—aren’t you something?<char style="sup">[p]</char>—no, on the contrary who do you think you are<char
        style="sup">[q]</char>, you who responds to <char style="it">an assertion that </char>God<char style="it">
        has made </char>with a contradictory reply? Shall the thing created tell <char style="it">its </char>creator,
        “Why’d you make me this way?” <verse eid="ROM 9:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 9:21" />Doesn’t the potter have the right to make vessels from the same lump of clay that are intended for dishonorable
        <char style="it">use</char> (i.e., dirty water basins or chamber pots) on the one hand but for honorable
        <char style="it">use</char> (i.e., best dinnerware pieces or decorative pots) on the other<char style="sup">[r]</char>?<verse eid="ROM 9:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 9:22" /><char style="it">What </char>if God, wanting to demonstrate His wrath in a particular situation and make
        His capabilities known <char style="it">near and far </char>in the same<char style="it">,</char> while
        exercising a good deal of patience took vessels of wrath along for a ride<char style="sup">[s]</char>,
        preparing <char style="it">them</char> for an ends of destruction? <verse eid="ROM 9:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 9:23" />And <char style="it">what if He</char>, in order that the riches of His glory be made known, <char style="it">wanted
        to demonstrate His kindness </char>upon vessels of mercy, ones that have been prepared beforehand for
        an ends of glory, <verse eid="ROM 9:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 9:24" />even us, whom He called, not only from among the Jews but from among the Gentiles as well? <verse eid="ROM 9:24" />
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 9:25" />Also, like in <char style="it">the Book of </char>Hosea:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:25"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:25">I will call the people who aren’t My people “My people,”</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:25">And <char style="it">the </char>unloved <char style="it">woman</char> “beloved.”<verse eid="ROM 9:25"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 9:26" />And it will come to pass that in the place</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:26">Where they were told “You are not My people,”</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:26">There they’ll be called “sons of the Living God.”<verse eid="ROM 9:26"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 9:27" />Now while representing Israel, Isaiah cried out, </para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:27"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:27">Even if the descendants of Israel happened to be</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:27">As numerous<char style="it"> </char>as the grains of sand on the seashore,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:27"><char style="it">Only </char>a select few will be spared from calamity<char style="sup">[D]</char><verse eid="ROM 9:27"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 9:28" />Furthermore <char style="it">Isaiah said</char>:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:28"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:28">Wrap it up lickety-split<char style="sup">[E]</char>—</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:28"><char style="it">That’s what </char>the Lord will do upon the earth<verse eid="ROM 9:28"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 9:29" />And just as Isaiah said before the fact:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:29"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:29">Had not the Army Commander-in-Chief<char style="sup">[t]</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:29">Left behind seed (i.e., progeny; heirs) for us,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:29">We would’ve become like Sodom,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:29">And we would’ve duplicated Gomorrah.<verse eid="ROM 9:29"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ROM 9:30" />So what’s the takeaway<char style="sup">[u]</char>? That the Gentiles—they who aren’t pursuing righteousness—cornered
        and subdued righteousness (a righteousness which came out of faith)? <verse eid="ROM 9:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ROM 9:31" />But Israel, pursuing a law of righteousness (i.e., a system of rules of right conduct), didn’t attain
        law (i.e., didn’t live up to the standards of those rules)? <verse eid="ROM 9:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ROM 9:32" />Because of what? Because <char style="it">their pursuit of righteousness</char> wasn’t from <char style="it">a
        standpoint of </char>faith but was <char style="it">pursued </char>as though <char style="it">it</char>
        <char style="it">could be attained</char> from <char style="it">a standpoint of</char> works. They crashed
        into the collision-stone, <verse eid="ROM 9:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ROM 9:33" />just like it’s written:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:33"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:33">Look here! I’m laying a collision-stone</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:33">In Zion<char style="sup">[v]</char> (i.e., in My yet-to-come relationship with mankind)</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:33">And a problem-causing rock<char style="sup">[F]</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:33">And he who believes and trusts in it/him<char style="sup">[G]</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 9:33">Won’t have any regrets<verse eid="ROM 9:33"/>
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">that I would be granted this request</char>…Lit: <char style="it">I would pray</char>.
        Quoting Max &amp; Mary, “in Hellenistic Greek, the imperfect verb tense takes the place of potential
        optative”; this is the case here.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">brethren</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the Lineal Descent Selection</char>…Lit<char style="it">: the adoption</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the Enactment of the Law of Moses</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the legislation</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Let us pause a moment for that to sink in</char>…Lit: <char style="it">amen</char>.
        Ref. Rom. 1:25; Rev. 19:4.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Israel doesn’t consist solely of everyone who was spawned from the nation of Israel</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">not all they out of Israel, these are Israel</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">In other words</char>…Lit: <char style="it">that is</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">at the right time</char>…Lit: <char style="it">according to the season</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Sarah will have a son</char>…Lit: <char style="it">a son will be with</char> [or <char
        style="it">in</char>] <char style="it">Sarah</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">while doing on the marriage bed what married couples do,</char> <char style="it">was
        impregnated</char> …Lit: [<char style="it">she</char>] <char style="it">having bed</char>. The bed is
        a synecdoche for having ongoing sexual relations (ref. Heb. 13:4). That she conceived as a result is
        a synecdoche.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">what’s the takeaway</char>…Lit: <char style="it">what shall we say</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Don’t even think about it</char>…Lit: <char style="it">may it not come into being</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[m]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[m]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Old Testament</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Scripture</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[n]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[n]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">reputation</char>…Lit: <char style="it">name</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[o]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[o]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I know what you’re going to say now</char>…Lit: <char style="it">So then will you say
        to me</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[p]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[p]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Wow—aren’t you something</char>…Lit: <char style="it">oh man</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[q]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[q]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">who do you think you are</char>…Lit: <char style="it">who are you</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[r]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[r]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">vessels from the same lump of clay that are intended for dishonorable use (i.e., dirty
        water basins or chamber pots) on the one hand but for honorable use (i.e., best dinnerware pieces or
        decorative pots) on the other</char>…Lit: <char style="it">on the one hand it, a vessel, unto honor,
        but on the other hand it unto dishonor</char>. Same wording used in. 2 Tim. 2:20,21.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[s]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[s]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">took</char>…<char style="it">along</char> <char style="it">for a ride</char>…Lit: <char
        style="it">brought</char>; <char style="it">carried</char> . Somewhat of a figure of speech.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[t]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[t]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Army Commander-in-Chief</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Lord of Sabaoth</char> [<char style="it">Hosts</char>].
        <char style="it">Sabaoth </char>is Hebrew for HeH<char style="it">Hosts</char>.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[u]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[u]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">what’s the takeaway</char>…Lit: <char style="it">what shall we say</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[v]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[v]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Zion</char>…Ref. note of John 12:14</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the Shekhinah-Glory</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the</char> <char style="it">glory</char>.
        Episodes in the OT where God’s glory was present: Moses and the burning bush; the cloud on Mt. Sinai;
        Solomon’s dedication of the temple; etc.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the children of the flesh are not the ones who’re the children of God</char>…Lit: <char
        style="it">not the children of flesh</char>, <char style="it">these</char> [<char style="it">are</char>]
        <char style="it">children of God</char>. The phrase <char style="it">these are children of God </char>is
        a parallel construct to the literal rendering in v. 6, <char style="it">these are Israel. </char>The
        use of the word <char style="it">this </char>or <char style="it">these </char>in this way is a figure
        of speech (also appears in John 1:2/<char style="it">this person</char>), one which is also used in English
        with the near and far demonstrative pronouns. In the NT, the use of <char style="it">this </char>or <char
        style="it">that </char>as a figure of speech, like in <char style="it">this person</char> or <char style="it">those
        people</char> means that the writer is spotlighting a person while presenting him to the reader; is emphasizing
        the distinction between one person and another (this is the case in chapter nine here).</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">not as a works-outcome but rather as a calling-outcome, the free choice of the One Who
        calls</char>…(Ref. note of Acts 13:46 also.)This verse and the surrounding passage was a bedrock of Calvin’s
        teaching on predestination, and along with him most who taught and teach predestination. The question
        is not whether God chooses ahead of time or capriciously (or both), but how He so chooses. Although God
        reserves the right to choose irrespective of what man does, on the other hand He has given us promises
        whereby a person can be sure that if he acts on such a promise, God will fulfill his promise. There are
        thousands of promises in the Bible, and these are given for our benefit, to know that God has guaranteed
        something. On the other extreme is 1 Cor. 12:18, where God places each believer in Christ’s body capriciously.
        In the case of Jacob and Esau, where God chose Jacob and rejected Esau, reading into the story, God’s
        choice was not arbitrary, but was based on the heart of Jacob and of Esau. Furthermore, Jacob’s and Esau’s
        hearts were fixated while they were still in Rebekah’s womb—which is unusual. While, certainly, God chose
        Jacob over Esau before they were born and had “committed any good or bad deed” (v. 11), God saw their
        hearts before they were born and decided based on what was in them. When says in v. 15 that God will
        have mercy on whomever He chooses, it implies that no one is in a position to come to God and demand
        something by means of justice (ref. 3:19,20); this excludes God from being “unfair” (v. 14). </char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[D]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[D]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">only a select few will be spared from calamity</char>…Lit: <char style="it">a remnant
        shall be saved</char>. The concept of the remnant is understood by studying its usage in the OT.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[E]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[E]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">wrap it up lickety-split</char>…Also: <char style="it">shutting a piece of business
        down and wrapping it up quickly</char>…Lit: <char style="it">finishing an affair off and cutting it short</char>.
        [very Lit: <char style="it">for a word finishing and cutting</char>]. The two Gk. words for <char style="it">finishing
        </char>and <char style="it">cutting </char>rhyme; this is likely a paronomasia (pun) of a sort. The use
        of this figure of speech explains the abrupt transition to the sentence which follows.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[F]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[F]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">problem-causing rock</char>…Lit: <char style="it">a stone of stumbling</char> [<char
        style="it">Skandalon, </char><char style="w" strong="G04625">σκάνδαλον</char>)]. The word <char style="it">skandalon
        </char>is used in the LXX to refer to the hostile nations which surrounded Israel and harassed her; its
        meaning is based on this usage. Ref. note of Matt. 18:6.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[G]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[G]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">it/him</char>…It can mean either or both, as the GT is ambiguous. Perhaps when the OT
        was written, it was taken to mean <char style="it">it</char>, as the antecedent <char style="it">it </char>is
        <char style="it">stone</char>, an inanimate object. But as Paul’s writing in the time of fulfillment
        of this prophecy, it’s known that the rock is a <char style="it">he, </char>namely Christ. So Paul may
        have been intentionally putting this ambiguity to good use.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="ROM 9" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 10   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="ROM 10" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 10:1" />Comrades<char style="sup">[a]</char>, my heart’s good intentions <char style="it">towards my fellow Israelites
        </char>and my prayer to God when I pray for them are targeted towards <char style="it">their </char>salvation
        (i.e., their being rescued from spiritual, moral, mental, and physical calamity). <verse eid="ROM 10:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 10:2" />Furthermore, I do declare that they have a zeal for God, but not <char style="it">a zeal </char>in which
        they arrive at an understanding of what they’re doing<char style="sup">[b]</char>. <verse eid="ROM 10:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 10:3" />For while being ignorant of the righteousness of God and while seeking to erect their own righteousness,
        they didn’t put themselves in subjection to the righteousness of God. <verse eid="ROM 10:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 10:4" />You see, for all those who have faith and believe, Christ puts an end to<char style="sup">[c]</char>
        law (i.e., the method of living by God’s list of rules) whose end-goal is righteousness.<verse eid="ROM 10:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 10:5" />In fact, Moses writes <char style="it">about </char>the righteousness which comes out of law, <char style="it">stating</char>
        that, “Those things which a person has done, he’ll stake his life on them<char style="sup">[d]</char>.”<verse eid="ROM 10:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 10:6" />But the righteousness which comes from <char style="it">the perspective of </char>faith puts things this
        way: Don’t say in your heart, “Who will ascend into heaven” (that is, to bring Christ down), or, <verse eid="ROM 10:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 10:7" />“Who will descend into the abyss (i.e., the world of the dead; the place of eternal identity-loss)” (that
        is, to bring Christ up out of the world of the dead)<char style="sup">[A]</char>; <verse eid="ROM 10:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 10:8" />Rather, what <char style="it">does</char> <char style="it">the Old Testament</char> say? <char style="it">It
        says</char>:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:8"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:8">The spoken-word<char style="sup">[B]</char> is near you,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:8">In your mouth and in your heart</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:8"></para>
    <para style="m" vid="ROM 10:8">…That is, <char style="it">the</char> “<char style="it">spoken-word which is near you” is </char>the
        word of faith<char style="sup">[C]</char> which we preach, <verse eid="ROM 10:8"/>
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 10:9" />that if you were to confess with your mouth <char style="it">the </char>Lord Jesus and believe with your
        heart that God raised him from the dead, you will be saved (i.e., rescued from spiritual, moral, mental,
        and physical calamity). <verse eid="ROM 10:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 10:10" />You see, <char style="it">the word </char>is believed with <char style="it">the</char> heart, and the
        end-result is righteousness; <char style="it">the word </char>is confessed with <char style="it">the</char>
        mouth, and the end-result is salvation (i.e., the state of being saved). <verse eid="ROM 10:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 10:11" />To this point, the Old Testament<char style="sup">[e]</char> says:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:11"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:11">He who trusts and believes in it<char style="sup">[f]</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:11">Won’t have any regrets<verse eid="ROM 10:11"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 10:12" />In fact, there’s no distinction made between Jews and non-Jewish Westerners<char style="sup">[g]</char>;
        for the same <char style="it">Lord </char>is everyone’s Lord, enriching all who call upon him: <verse eid="ROM 10:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 10:13" />“Everyone who ventures to call upon the Lord’s authority and reputation <char style="it">for</char> <char
        style="it">being favorably inclined</char><char style="sup">[h]</char><char style="it"> </char>will be
        saved.”<verse eid="ROM 10:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 10:14" />So how could they call upon him whom they haven’t believed in? How could they believe in a person they
        haven’t heard of? Apart from <char style="it">people </char>preaching <char style="it">to them</char>,
        how could they hear <char style="it">about him</char>? <verse eid="ROM 10:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 10:15" />How could <char style="it">these people</char> preach if they haven’t been sent out? As it’s written:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:15"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:15">Oh, how beautiful are the feet (i.e., the course and direction of the lives)</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:15">Of those<char style="sup">[D]</char> evangelizing the good things <char style="it">of God</char><verse eid="ROM 10:15"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 10:16" />No, not everyone obeyed the Good News, the Gospel. You see, Isaiah says, “Lord who believed our message?”<verse eid="ROM 10:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 10:17" />Therefore, the faith <char style="it">that I’m talking about </char>comes out of hearing a message (i.e.,
        listening intently to a message and letting it sink into your heart and not just pass through your head);
        the hearing <char style="it">I’m talking about comes </char>through a spoken-word of Christ<char style="sup">[E]</char>.<verse eid="ROM 10:17" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 10:18" />That aside, I’ll tell <char style="it">you</char> <char style="it">this</char>: It’s not as though they
        haven’t heard <char style="it">the message yet</char>, is it? On the contrary:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:18"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:18">The sound of their voice went out to the entire earth</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:18">And to the far reaches of the civilized world<char style="sup">[i]</char><verse eid="ROM 10:18"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 10:19" />No, I’ll<char style="it"> one-up that and </char>say <char style="it">this</char>:<char style="it"> </char>It’s
        not that Israel hasn’t understood <char style="it">the message</char>, is it? Right out of the gate Moses
        says,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:19"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:19">I’ll make you jealous over<char style="sup">[j]</char> a people;</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:19">I’ll enrage you over a people who are clueless<verse eid="ROM 10:19"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 10:20" />And Isaiah takes it to another level and says:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:20"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:20">I was discovered by those not seeking Me;</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:20">I became manifest to those not inquiring of Me<verse eid="ROM 10:20"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 10:21" />But to Israel it says:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:21"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:21">All day long I’ve had My arms stretched out</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 10:21">To a disobedient and contrary folk<verse eid="ROM 10:21"/>
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">in which they arrive at an understanding of what they’re doing</char>…Lit: <char style="it">according
        to an arrived-at understanding</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">puts an end to</char>…Lit: <char style="it">is an end of</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">he’ll stake his life on them</char>…Or: <char style="it">he’ll be consumed by obeying
        them</char>; <char style="it">he’ll suffer the consequences of them</char>. Lit: <char style="it">he
        shall live with them</char>. An idiom, the meaning of which isn’t entirely certain.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Old Testament</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Scripture</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">in it</char>…Or: <char style="it">in him</char>. Ref. note of 9:33.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">non-Jewish Westerners</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Greeks</char>. Ref. note of 2:9.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the Lord’s authority and reputation for</char> <char style="it">being favorably inclined</char>
        …Lit: <char style="it">the name of the Lord</char>. The “name of the Lord” is a biblical idiom.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">civilized world</char>…Lit<char style="it">: inhabited world</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">over</char>…Lit: <char style="it">at</char></char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Don’t say in your heart, “Who will ascend into heaven” (that is, to bring Christ down),
        or, “Who will descend into the abyss (i.e., the world of the dead; the place of eternal identity-loss)”
        (that is, to bring Christ up out of the world of the dead)</char>…This summarizes the two principal heresies
        of Christ: the first is “who will ascend into heaven to bring Christ down.” This is the view that Christ
        never became flesh and blood; that he is God’s son, but he’s always been up in heaven and always will
        be. Though he’s the son of God, he’s inaccessible to us; too high up for us; not able to and never has
        come down to our level. The second is “who will descend into the abyss to bring Christ up out of it.”
        This view says that Jesus was a man, but was subject to the same demise of any other human being. Although
        he lived an inspiring life, he’s dead now like any other person is. Essentially, he’s no use to anyone
        anymore since he was mortal like us, but now he’s dead and can’t help anyone anymore.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">spoken-word</char>…Gk: <char style="it">rhema </char><char style="w" strong="G04487">ῥῆμα</char>).
        <char style="it">Rhema </char>is a form of the Gk. word <char style="it">logos </char><char style="w"
        strong="G03056">λόγος</char>)<char style="it">; </char>it appears to be derived from an aorist participle
        from the verb form of <char style="it">logos, </char>which is <char style="it">legō </char><char style="w"
        strong="G03004">λέγω</char>)<char style="it">. </char>The lexicon definition of <char style="it">rhema
        </char>is “that which is or has been uttered by the living voice; the thing spoken” (Thayer’s); “that
        which is said, word, statement, expression, or statement of any kind” (Danker &amp; Bauer). To add to
        the note of John 1:1, a note which explains the meaning of <char style="it">logos, </char>it can be viewed
        as the comprehensive body of thought on a subject matter the ancient Greeks captured in a book (a scroll).
        Thus, the great philosophers wrote treatises on everything from science to politics. These treatises
        were the logos for a subject, the written word on that subject. On the other hand, a rhema is a spoken
        word on a subject, as indicated by its usage in Heb. 12:20. Since it’s spoken and not written, one infers
        a few things about it. First, it isn’t a comprehensive erudition on a subject. For this reason, John
        called Jesus the Logos and not the Rhema. Second, since it’s spoken, it’s applied to a particular situation
        at a particular point in time; it’s the logos applied in real-time; it’s a specific application of the
        logos. Third, the rhema spoken about in v. 8 the “word of faith” is the word which is “in your mouth
        and in your heart” and is spoken out “of faith.” Rhema is the logos, the written word, planted in one’s
        heart and spoken out of one’s mouth. The promise given in v. 9 is that anyone who speaks such a rhema
        about Jesus being Lord and God raising him from the dead is guaranteed to receive the promise, in this
        passage, to be saved.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">word of faith</char>…This phrase in v. 8 is where the Word of Faith movement gets its
        name from. The Word of Faith movement says that this passage here in Rom. 10 is a general principle of
        faith—an important one—one which applies not only to being saved (v. 9), but to any and all promise in
        the Bible.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[D]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[D]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Oh, how beautiful are the feet (i.e., the course and direction of the lives) of those</char>…Feet
        in the Bible are a metonymy for the direction one’s life is headed in; his decision to follow a certain
        path; his tendency to do so; his consistency in sticking to it.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[E]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[E]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">word of Christ</char>…The Textus Receptus and other manuscripts say <char style="it">word
        of God</char>, but the manuscript support for <char style="it">word of Christ </char>is stronger than
        for <char style="it">word of God. </char>The Gk. word <char style="it">rhema </char><char style="w" strong="G04487">ῥῆμα</char>)is
        used for <char style="it">word </char>here and throughout the chapter. By using <char style="it">rhema
        </char>repeatedly, Paul refers to the same concept throughout the chapter. Also, Paul writes <char style="it">the
        faith </char>at the beginning of v. 17 rather than simply <char style="it">faith </char>(no definite
        article). The use of the definite article before <char style="it">faith </char>means that Paul’s continuing
        his train of thought and referring to the same principle of faith and the word that he started in v.
        8.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="ROM 10" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 11   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="ROM 11" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 11:1" />So, I’ll say <char style="it">this</char>: God hasn’t rejected His people, has He?—Not a chance.<char
        style="sup">[a]</char> The fact of the matter is that I myself am an Israelite, from Abraham’s seed (i.e.
        lineal descent; progeny; great-great-etc. grandson), the tribe of Benjamin— <verse eid="ROM 11:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 11:2" />God hasn’t rejected His people, those whom He foreknew (i.e., knew their individual personalities, nature,
        and spiritual acuity before it became apparent). Or don’t you know what the Old Testament<char style="sup">[b]</char>
        says about Elijah? As he intercedes with God against Israel:<verse eid="ROM 11:2" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 11:3" />Lord, they killed Your prophets, they tore down Your altars,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:3">And I’m the only survivor, and they’re out to get me<char style="sup">[c]</char><verse eid="ROM 11:3"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 11:4" />What does <char style="it">God’s</char> Divine Answer<char style="sup">[d]</char> tell him instead?</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:4"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:4">I’ve kept at My disposal seven-thousand men,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:4">Those individuals in particular</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:4">Who haven’t kowtowed<char style="sup">[e]</char> to Baal<verse eid="ROM 11:4"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 11:5" />So in the same way in this day-and-age also, a remnant (i.e., the select few who’ve stayed the course)
        freely chosen by grace has emerged. <verse eid="ROM 11:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 11:6" />Now if <char style="it">the choice </char>is by grace, it’s no longer a product of works, since grace
        <char style="it">of this sort</char> would no longer qualify as being grace. <verse eid="ROM 11:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 11:7" />What then? What Israel sought after, that’s what it didn’t obtain; it obtained the free choice <char
        style="it">by grace</char>, but the rest <char style="it">who weren’t part of the remnant </char>were
        hardened <char style="it">on the inside</char> <verse eid="ROM 11:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 11:8" />just as it’s written:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:8"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:8">God gave them a deep, intense mindset<char style="sup">[f]</char> of stupefaction,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:8">Eyes incapable of sight and ears incapable of hearing,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:8">Continuing<char style="it"> </char>up to the present day<verse eid="ROM 11:8"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 11:9" />And <char style="it">in the Old Testament </char>David says:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:9"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:9">Let their sustenance, provision, relaxation, and merriment<char style="sup">[g]</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:9">Turn into a snare and into a net</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:9">And into a cause of vexation<char style="sup">[h]</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:9">And into a tit-for-tat payback meted out to them.<verse eid="ROM 11:9"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 11:10" />Let their vision deteriorate to the point where they can’t see,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:10">And throughout all of this <char style="it">let </char>their back <char style="it">be</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:10">Thrown out and mangled up, leaving them hunched over.<verse eid="ROM 11:10"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 11:11" />I’m saying that they haven’t careened off the road to where they’re stuck in a ditch<char style="sup">[i]</char>,
        have they?—Don’t even think about it.<char style="sup">[j]</char> Instead, by their transgressions the
        salvation <char style="it">which is in Jesus in one fell swoop</char><char style="sup">[k]</char><char
        style="it"> has been made available to the Gentiles </char>in order to provoke <char style="it">my fellow
        countrymen </char>to imitation because of envy<char style="sup">[A]</char>. <verse eid="ROM 11:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 11:12" />Now if their transgression is a bonanza for the world, and their failure a bonanza for the Gentiles,
        how much more <char style="it">of a bonanza would </char>their saturation <char style="it">in</char>
        <char style="it">the faith be</char>?<verse eid="ROM 11:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 11:13" />I’m addressing you Gentiles. Insofar as I have indeed been sent as a missionary—an apostle—to the Gentiles—I’m
        putting my ministry on center stage<char style="sup">[l]</char>, <verse eid="ROM 11:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 11:14" />if somehow I might provoke my kinsmen to imitation because of envy and <char style="it">thereby </char>save
        (i.e., rescue) some of them. <verse eid="ROM 11:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 11:15" />You see, if their rejection <char style="it">of Jesus</char> <char style="it">be </char>the world’s reconciliation,
        what can <char style="it">their</char> acceptance <char style="it">of Jesus</char> <char style="it">be</char>
        if not life from the dead? <verse eid="ROM 11:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 11:16" />If the early sample<char style="sup">[m]</char> of the harvest is consecrated <char style="it">to God</char>,
        the bulk of the harvest is consecrated as well; if the root’s consecrated, the branches are too.<verse eid="ROM 11:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 11:17" />Now if some of the branches were chopped off, you—the wild olive branch—were grafted into them and became
        joint-partakers of the Olive Tree’s Root of Faith, <verse eid="ROM 11:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 11:18" />no boasting from the <char style="it">wild </char>branches <char style="it">about how you supplanted
        the natural branches</char>. But if you intend to adopt a condescending attitude, <char style="it">keep
        in mind that </char>you don’t support the root, but the root supports you. <verse eid="ROM 11:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 11:19" />So if you’re going to say, “Branches were chopped off so that I could be grafted in”… <verse eid="ROM 11:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 11:20" />that’s all well and good: they were broken off due to their refusal to believe<char style="sup">[n]</char>;
        you’ve come to stand due to faith. Don’t think highly <char style="it">of yourselves</char>, but <char
        style="it">adopt an attitude of </char>fear: <verse eid="ROM 11:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 11:21" />if God didn’t spare the natural branches, I don’t see any way around Him not sparing you either.<verse eid="ROM 11:21" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 11:22" />Ah<char style="sup">[o]</char>, God’s kindness and severity. On the one hand, severity <char style="it">will
        be lavished </char>upon those who’ve wound up in a ditch by their own doing<char style="sup">[p]</char>,
        but on the other hand God’s kindness <char style="it">will be lavished </char>upon you, if you were to
        continue doing what you’re doing in<char style="sup">[q]</char> <char style="it">this </char>kindness;
        otherwise, you’ll be “chopped off” <char style="it">so to speak</char> too. <verse eid="ROM 11:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 11:23" />And they too—if they were to not continue in their refusal to believe, they’ll be grafted in: the fact
        is, God is able to graft them back in again. <verse eid="ROM 11:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 11:24" />You see, if you were chopped off a wild olive tree and grafted into a cultivated olive tree, how much
        more will these natural branches be grafted back into their own olive tree?<verse eid="ROM 11:24" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 11:25" />The fact of the matter is that I don’t want you to continue in ignorance, comrades<char style="sup">[r]</char>,
        over this mystery, so that you wouldn’t be forming within yourselves thoughts and ideas which haven’t
        been carefully considered or well thought-through, since, to a large extent a hardness has occurred to
        Israel until the fullness of the Gentiles enters in, <verse eid="ROM 11:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 11:26" />and in this way all Israel shall be saved (i.e., rescued from spiritual, moral, mental, and physical
        calamity), just like it’s been recorded in Scripture:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:26"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:26">The Deliverer will come out of Zion</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:26">(i.e., out of the manifestation of God’s ultimate plan)—</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:26">He’ll repel ungodliness from Israel.<verse eid="ROM 11:26"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 11:27" />And this is the Covenant from Me to them,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:27">That I’ll take away their sins<char style="sup">[s]</char>.<verse eid="ROM 11:27"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 11:28" />Yes, <char style="it">they are</char> enemies of the Good News, the Gospel, on account of you, but <char
        style="it">are </char>beloved according to the Selection on account of the patriarchs <char style="it">of
        Israel</char>: <verse eid="ROM 11:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 11:29" />the gifts <char style="it">that were given by the grace of God</char>, <char style="it">not earned by
        the recipients,</char> and the calling of God (i.e., God’s selection to be one of His people) are irrevocable,
        you see. <verse eid="ROM 11:29" />
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ROM 11:30" />Just as you were disobedient <char style="it">to God </char>and unconvinced <char style="it">that you
        should believe in Him</char> a while ago, you have now received mercy on account of their disobedience
        and unbelief. <verse eid="ROM 11:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ROM 11:31" />In the same way, at the present moment these people too are disobedient to and unconvinced by your mercy
        to the effect that they would receive mercy. <verse eid="ROM 11:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ROM 11:32" />For God consigned them all<char style="sup">[t]</char> to disobedience so that they all would receive
        mercy.<verse eid="ROM 11:32" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ROM 11:33" />Oh, the depth of the riches, the wisdom, and the understanding of God—as His decisions evade analysis
        and the path that He’s taken cannot be traced<char style="sup">[u]</char>!…<verse eid="ROM 11:33" />
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="34" style="v" sid="ROM 11:34" />In fact, who knew what was on the Lord’s mind?</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:34">Or who became His decision-making advisor?<verse eid="ROM 11:34"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi">
      <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ROM 11:35" />Or who’s loaned him anything</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 11:35">That He’ll have to pay back?<verse eid="ROM 11:35"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ROM 11:36" />…Because from Him and through Him and to Him are all things—to Him <char style="it">be </char>the Glory
        forever and ever. And let us pause for a moment to let that sink in<char style="sup">[v]</char>.<verse eid="ROM 11:36" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Not a chance</char>…Lit: <char style="it">may</char> [<char style="it">it</char>] <char
        style="it">not become</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Old Testament</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the Scripture</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">out to get me</char>…Lit: <char style="it">seeking my soul</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">God’s Divine Answer</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the oracle</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">kowtowed</char>…Lit: <char style="it">bent a knee</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">deep, intense mindset</char>…Lit: <char style="it">a spirit</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">sustenance, provision, relaxation, and merriment</char>…Lit: <char style="it">table</char>.
        <char style="it">Table </char>is a biblical synecdoche.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">a cause of vexation</char>…Lit: <char style="it">a stumbling block</char>. Ref. note
        of Matt. 18:6.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">careened off the road to where they’re stuck in a ditch</char>…Lit: <char style="it">tripped
        in order that they would fall</char>. The words <char style="it">tripped </char>and <char style="it">fall
        </char>refer to the word stumbling block in v. 9. The implication is that they’ve fallen into sin.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Don’t even think about it</char>…Lit: <char style="it">may it never come-into-being</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">in one fell swoop</char>…This interpolation is an insinuation of the aorist tense of
        the Gk. verb <char style="it">to provoke (etc.)</char>.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">putting my ministry on center stage</char>…Lit: <char style="it">glorifying my ministry</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[m]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[m]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">early sample</char>…Lit: <char style="it">first fruit</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[n]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[n]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">refusal to believe</char>…Lit: <char style="it">unbelief</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[o]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[o]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">ah</char>…Lit: <char style="it">behold</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[p]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[p]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">wound up in a ditch by their own doing</char>…Lit: <char style="it">fallen</char>. Refers
        to the word <char style="it">ditch </char>used in v. 11, which refers to the stumbling block. In the
        NT, stumbling blocks are often the result of hard-headed recalcitrance.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[q]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[q]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">in</char>…Or: <char style="it">by</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[r]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[r]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[s]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[s]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">That I’ll take away their sins</char>…Lit: <char style="it">When I’ll take away their
        sins</char>. A figure of speech.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[t]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[t]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">consigned them all</char>…Lit: <char style="it">shut them all up in unison</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[u]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[u]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">As His decisions evade analysis and the path that He’s taken cannot be traced</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">how inscrutable are His judgments and untraceable are His ways</char>. The Gk. words
        for <char style="it">inscrutable </char>and <char style="it">untraceable </char>are <char style="it">anekseraunata
        </char>(ἀνεξεραύνητος /Strong’s 419)and <char style="it">aneksixniastoi </char><char style="w" strong="G00421">ἀνεξιχνίαστος</char>).
        These two words appear to be an alliteration/assonance; perhaps Paul was using an expression here.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[v]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[v]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">and let us pause a moment for that to sink in</char>…Lit: <char style="it">amen. </char>Ref.
        note of Rev. 19:4.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">by their transgressions the salvation which is in Jesus in one fell swoop has been made
        available to the Gentiles in order to provoke my fellow countrymen to imitation because of envy</char>…Or:
        <char style="it">by their transgressions they in one fell swoop provoked the Gentiles to become intensely
        interested in the salvation which is in Jesus and to emulate it</char>. Whichever of the two rendering
        is the correct rendering is ambiguous, hinging on what the antecedent of the word <char style="it">them
        </char>is and compounded by Paul’s insistence that the reader supply the interpolated words<char style="it">.
        </char>The ambiguity of <char style="it">them </char>is resolved by the way that the same verb <char
        style="it">to provoke to jealousy </char>is used again in v. 14.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="ROM 11" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 12   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="ROM 12" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 12:1" />On account of the mercies of God, I beseech you, comrades<char style="sup">[a]</char>, to present your
        bodies an alive, holy, and acceptable (“<char style="it">acceptable” as though it complies with something
        analogous to the requirements in the Old Testament for the animals to be sacrificed</char>) sacrifice
        (<char style="it">like a sacrificial animal</char>) to God, performing your religious ritual, one which
        constitutes worship. <verse eid="ROM 12:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 12:2" />And be not conformed to <char style="it">the lifestyle of </char>this age, but be transformed on the
        outside by what’s on the inside by the renewing of the mind instead, resulting in you continuously approving
        as the result of examination what the will of God is, the good <char style="it">will of God</char>, the
        acceptable<char style="sup">[A]</char> <char style="it">will of God</char>, and the perfect <char style="it">will
        of God</char>.<verse eid="ROM 12:2" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 12:3" />In addition, through the grace given to me I’m telling every one of you all not to let your minds stray
        and be thinking loftier thoughts, thoughts where you think more highly of yourself, than you ought be
        thinking<char style="sup">[b]</char>, but be sound-minded (i.e., come down to earth, straighten your
        head out, and get rid of those lofty thoughts) instead, as God has allocated an area of responsibility
        for every person<char style="sup">[B]</char>. <verse eid="ROM 12:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 12:4" />You see, just as there’re many parts to any given body, but all the parts don’t serve the same purpose,<verse eid="ROM 12:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 12:5" />similarly, we the many <char style="it">parts </char>are one body in Christ, and a member of one another
        from an individual perspective.<verse eid="ROM 12:5" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 12:6" />Now having gifts<char style="sup">[C]</char> according to the grace (i.e., the giver giving not based
        on the receiver meriting it but based on the giver’s generosity; giving with no expectation of receiving
        anything in return; giving something freely and therefore irrevocably) given to us diversely, whether
        <char style="it">the gift be </char>prophecy (i.e., speaking the utterances of God) <char style="it">let
        the prophesying be done </char>according to the allocation of responsibility<char style="sup">[c]</char>;<verse eid="ROM 12:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 12:7" />whether being in charge of a particular area of ministry<char style="it"> </char>and serving in that
        area<char style="sup">[d]</char>, <char style="it">let</char> <char style="it">the same be applied </char>to
        the service; whether teaching, <char style="it">let the same be applied </char>to the teaching; <verse eid="ROM 12:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 12:8" />whether assistance, advocacy, counseling, and encouraging<char style="sup">[e]</char>, <char style="it">let
        the same be applied </char>to the assistance, etc.; whether giving<char style="sup">[f]</char>, <char
        style="it">let the same be applied </char>in singleness (i.e., in simplicity: straightforward, without
        hesitancy, hidden agendas, or internal conflicts); whether taking the lead, <char style="it">let the
        same be applied</char> with pep, diligence, and self-motivation; whether being merciful, <char style="it">let
        the same be applied</char> in cheerfulness.<verse eid="ROM 12:8" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 12:9" /><char style="it">Let </char>the love <char style="it">you have be</char> genuine and without hypocrisy.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ROM 12:9">Hate the evil <char style="it">that’s in the world</char>, adhere to the good.<verse eid="ROM 12:9"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 12:10" />With a close comradeship, <char style="it">engage in</char> close friendships formed out of natural affection.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ROM 12:10">In the high value <char style="it">with which you esteem others</char>, put each other ahead of yourselves.<verse eid="ROM 12:10"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 12:11" />Using pep, diligence, and self-motivation, don’t be lazy.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ROM 12:11">In the Spirit <char style="it">be</char> zealous<char style="sup">[g]</char>.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ROM 12:11">Serve in the Lord.<verse eid="ROM 12:11"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 12:12" />In good times, rejoice; in bad times, persevere<char style="sup">[h]</char>.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ROM 12:12">Pray constantly—continuously.<verse eid="ROM 12:12"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 12:13" />Be intimately familiar with the needs of the saints, your fellow believers.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ROM 12:13">Reach out to those who are new or who are different—make this your pastime.<char style="sup">[i]</char><verse eid="ROM 12:13"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 12:14" />Have a good word to say about those who persecute <char style="it">others</char>.<char style="sup">[j]</char></para>
    <para style="p" vid="ROM 12:14">Bless and don’t curse.<verse eid="ROM 12:14"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 12:15" />Rejoice with those who’re rejoicing.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ROM 12:15">Weep with those who’re weeping.<verse eid="ROM 12:15"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 12:16" />Maintain the same mindset towards each individual: don’t think you’re better than anyone else<char style="sup">[k]</char>
        but associate with those who’ve been humbled by circumstances or by their station in life (i.e., those
        on the lowest wrungs of society; those who aren’t the brightest and best). Don’t become too big for your
        britches/too big for your boots<char style="sup">[l]</char>.<verse eid="ROM 12:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 12:17" /><char style="it">When anyone does something bad to you, </char>don’t do something bad to them in return.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ROM 12:17">Have respect for what people generally regard as beautiful and what they hold in high esteem.<verse eid="ROM 12:17"/>
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 12:18" />If at all possible, for your own part, be at peace with everyone.<verse eid="ROM 12:18" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 12:19" />Don’t take your own revenge, beloved, but leave room for the wrath <char style="it">of God</char>. You
        see, it’s written:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 12:19"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 12:19">“Vengeance is for Me <char style="it">to do</char>, I’ll pay <char style="it">them </char>back,” says
        the Lord<verse eid="ROM 12:19"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 12:20" />Instead <char style="it">of taking revenge</char>:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 12:20"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 12:20">If your enemy happens to be hungry, give him something to eat.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 12:20">If he happens to be thirsty, give him some water.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 12:20">You see, by doing this you make him stew in his own juice<char style="sup">[m]</char>.<verse eid="ROM 12:20"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 12:21" />Don’t be defeated by the bad <char style="it">things people do to you</char>, but defeat bad things with
        good things.<verse eid="ROM 12:21" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">let your minds stray and be thinking loftier thoughts than you ought be thinking</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">be thinking beyond that which you must be thinking</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">responsibility</char>….The same Gk. word <char style="it">pistis </char><char style="w"
        strong="G04102">πίστις</char>) as was used in v. 3. It has the same meaning as its usage in v. 3 (ref.
        note of v. 3).</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">being in charge of a particular area of ministry or serving in that area</char>…The
        Gk. word used here is from the same root as the word <char style="it">deacon; r</char>ef. note of Acts
        6:3.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">assistance, advocacy, counseling, and encouraging</char>…Same word used in Acts 11:36;
        ref. note there.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">giving</char>…Lit: <char style="it">giving a portion of what one has</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">In the Spirit be zealous</char>…Or: <char style="it">With spirit</char> [<char style="it">deep,
        prevailing demeanor</char>] <char style="it">be zealous</char>. The word <char style="it">spirit </char>used
        here is somewhat ambiguous.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">In good times, rejoice; in bad times, persevere</char>…Lit: <char style="it">In</char>
        [<char style="it">times of</char>] <char style="it">hope rejoice in</char> [<char style="it">times of</char>]
        <char style="it">tribulation persevere</char>. Note that <char style="it">times of </char>is an interpolation.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Reach out to those who are new—make this your pastime</char>…Lit: <char style="it">pursue
        the hospitality</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Have a good word to say about those who persecute others</char>…Lit: <char style="it">bless
        those persecuting</char> [<char style="it">you</char>]. The word <char style="it">you </char>appears
        in some of the principle manuscripts but does not appear in the others.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">don’t think you’re better than anyone else</char>…Lit: <char style="it">don’t think
        the high things</char>. This appears to be an idiom. Also, the word <char style="it">think </char>in
        this context (and it’s used three times in v. 16) refers to thoughts and attitudes you have towards other
        people.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">Don’t become too big for your britches/too big for your boots</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Don’t
        become thinking with yourselves</char>. This appears to be an idiom. The word <char style="it">thinking
        </char>refers to the opinion you have of others (see previous note).The phrase <char style="it">with
        yourselves</char> is also used in Rom. 11:25.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[m]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[m]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">stew in his own juice</char>…Lit: <char style="it">heap coals of fire on his head</char>.
        An idiom.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">acceptable</char>…Since the same Gk. word for <char style="it">acceptable </char>is
        used in here in v. 2 as was used in v. 1, the meaning of <char style="it">acceptable </char>as it appears
        in v. 2 takes on the same meaning as was used in v. 1, where in that verse it refers to the requirements
        specified in the Law of Moses for the sacrificial animal to be offered at the temple. The acceptable
        will of God is therefore one which meets the set of minimum requirements.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">God has allocated an area of responsibility for every person</char>…Lit: <char style="it">God
        as apportioned to each person a portion of trust</char>. The Gk. word for <char style="it">faith</char>
        [<char style="it">pistis</char>, <char style="w" strong="G04102">πίστις</char>)] also means <char style="it">trust</char>.
        A similar word <char style="it">pistos </char>means <char style="it">faithful </char>or <char style="it">trustworthy.</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[C]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[C]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">gifts</char>…There’s more than one NT Gk. word rendered <char style="it">gift</char>;<char
        style="it"> </char>the one used in this verse is <char style="it">charisma, </char>which is obviously
        derived from the word <char style="it">charis </char>[<char style="it">grace,</char><char style="w" strong="G05485">χάρις</char>)];
        Paul uses both here, exemplifying and reinforcing the relationship between the two. To quote Max &amp;
        Mary, a <char style="it">charisma </char>is “a gift of God’s grace, for the benefit of the community.”
        A charisma is a gift that’s given by the grace of the giver (also, ref. note of Acts 8:20). It’s given
        irrevocably. The recipient did not and cannot earn it. The Greek word <char style="it">dōron </char><char
        style="w" strong="G01435">δῶρον</char>)<char style="it">, </char>which in general means <char style="it">gift
        </char>as we know the word in English<char style="it">, </char>is also used when describing the gift
        offerings given to God; the implication is that the gift is given based on the worthiness of the recipient;
        the obligation to give.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="ROM 12" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 13   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="ROM 13" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 13:1" />Let all people from all walks of life<char style="sup">[a]</char> submit to the overarching authorities<char
        style="sup">[A]</char>; the fact is, there’s no authority-structure except <char style="it">what’s been
        put there </char>by God, and those that exist have been arranged, organized, and put into place by God
        into the state in which they exist, <verse eid="ROM 13:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 13:2" />so that any given person who opposes the authority <char style="it">that’s in place </char>has taken
        a stand against the way that God decides to organize and arrange things; the ones who’ve taken a stand
        in opposition <char style="it">to the authorities in place </char>will be judged (i.e., arrested, prosecuted,
        convicted, and incarcerated by the criminal justice system) for doing so. <verse eid="ROM 13:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 13:3" />You see, those who do good have no need to be afraid of rulers; but those who do bad <char style="it">need
        to be afraid</char>. Do you want to have no fear of the authorities?—do good,<char style="it"> </char>and
        you’ll be applauded by them: <verse eid="ROM 13:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 13:4" />the <char style="it">person in authority </char>is God’s servant for you in a positive way. But if you
        were to live the life of crime, be afraid: <char style="it">the authorities</char> have the wherewithal
        to forcibly and violently impose their will upon you—and won’t hesitate to use it<char style="sup">[B]</char>.
        In fact, <char style="it">the authorities </char>are God’s servants to dole out wrath upon the <char
        style="it">stereotypical </char>criminal.<verse eid="ROM 13:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 13:5" />Putting it all together, you’ve got to submit <char style="it">to the authorities, </char>not just because
        of the wrath <char style="it">they could potentially inflict </char>but also because <char style="it">you
        should be</char> <char style="it">keeping a clean</char> conscience<char style="sup">[b]</char>. <verse eid="ROM 13:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 13:6" />In fact, this is also a reason why you pay taxes: they’re ministers (i.e., officers, constables, judges,
        etc.) of God employed full-time at this, <char style="it">and their salary is paid out of tax revenue</char>.<verse eid="ROM 13:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 13:7" />Pay all <char style="it">the taxes </char>that you’re on the hook to pay: tax to the taxman, tolls at
        the tollgate, customs at the customhouse, reverence—fear even—to the one who instills fear, honor to
        the one who should be honored.<verse eid="ROM 13:7" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 13:8" />Don’t owe anyone anything<char style="sup">[c]</char> except to love one another: he who loves another
        person has fulfilled law (i.e., has satisfied the mandates of any list of godly rules). <verse eid="ROM 13:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 13:9" />To this end, the <char style="it">commandments</char>, “Thou shalt not commit adultery,” “Thou shalt
        not murder,” “Thou shalt not steal,” “Thou shalt not covet,” and if there’s any other commandment <char
        style="it">I should’ve included</char>, it’s summed up by one statement, “Thou shalt love thy neighbor
        as thyself.” <verse eid="ROM 13:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 13:10" />The love <char style="it">that you show </char>to the typical neighbor doesn’t do anything bad; so then,
        love is a fulfillment of law.<verse eid="ROM 13:10" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 13:11" /><char style="it">I’ll </char>add<char style="it"> </char>this <char style="it">to what I’ve said</char>.
        You know what time it is, that it’s time for us to wake up, for now our salvation is closer than when
        we <char style="it">first </char>became believers. <verse eid="ROM 13:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 13:12" />The night wanes, daylight approaches, so put away the deeds of darkness; put on the armor of the light.<verse eid="ROM 13:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 13:13" />Like <char style="it">the way people carry themselves </char>during the day, go about behaving appropriately
        and properly, not with loud partying, drunkenness, or sleeping around and unrestrained indulgence in
        immoral, physical pleasures, nor strife, discord, contention and the ensuing passions. <verse eid="ROM 13:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 13:14" />Instead, clothe yourselves in the Lord Jesus Christ and make no provision to indulge the desires of the
        flesh (i.e., one’s carnal nature).<verse eid="ROM 13:14" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">all people from all walks of life</char>…Lit: <char style="it">every soul</char>. In
        the NT, <char style="it">soul </char>is used from time to time as a synecdoche for <char style="it">person</char>,
        emphasizing what’s in the mind of that person, the uniqueness and individuality of him.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">because you should be keeping a clean conscience</char>…Lit: <char style="it">on account
        of conscience</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">anyone anything</char>…Similar to <char style="it">anyone anything</char>, the GT here
        also has an alliteration/assonance, <char style="it">mādeni māden </char>(Μηδενὶ μηδὲν).</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">overarching authorities</char>…The overarching authorities are a synecdoche for the
        entire authority structure from the top on down.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[B]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[B]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the wherewithal to forcibly and violently impose their will upon you—and won’t hesitate
        to use it</char>…Lit: <char style="it">don’t bear the sword in vain</char>. <char style="it">The sword</char>
        is a metonymy for the arms that the law enforcement agencies use, and also includes their coordinated
        efforts when using them. This is not only the use of violence to arrest criminals but to imprison them
        as well. Furthermore, that the violence is deadly violence: this verse says that law enforcement agents
        and the criminal justice system have the right, the ability, and the responsibility to inflict deadly
        violence up to the point of killing a criminal, not only while arresting him but as the sentence for
        the crime committed. </char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="ROM 13" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 14   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="ROM 14" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 14:1" />Accept the person who’s struggling in the Faith <char style="it">the way he is</char> without resolving
        the disagreements <char style="it">over what he should or shouldn’t believe</char>. <verse eid="ROM 14:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 14:2" />On the one hand a given person who believes <char style="it">that he’s permitted to eat any kind of food
        </char>eats every <char style="it">kind of food</char>, but on the other hand a given person who’s struggling<char
        style="sup">[a]</char> with his faith is a vegetarian. <verse eid="ROM 14:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 14:3" />Don’t let the one who <char style="it">believes he’s permitted </char>to eat anything<char style="it">
        </char>despise the one who doesn’t, and don’t let the one who won’t eat everything judge the one who
        does; you see, God has accepted <char style="it">this person</char>.<verse eid="ROM 14:3" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 14:4" />Who <char style="it">do you think</char> you are, you who judges another man’s butler?—<char style="it">The
        butler </char>will stand or fall (i.e., get the nod of approval to continue doing what he’s doing or
        be reprimanded and forced to amend his behavior) by his own boss. And stand he will, for the boss—the
        Lord—is able to <char style="it">pick him up off the ground and</char> stand him <char style="it">to
        his feet</char><char style="sup">[b]</char>.<verse eid="ROM 14:4" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 14:5" />In fact, one person decides that one day stands out above the other days <char style="it">as being a
        special holy day</char>; another person decides that all days are the same <char style="it">and so none
        stands out above the others</char>—let each person work it all out in his own mind. <verse eid="ROM 14:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 14:6" />The one who thinks <char style="it">about what days should be considered holy</char> thinks the day <char
        style="it">he has in mind should be dedicated </char>to the Lord; the one who’ll eat <char style="it">anything</char>
        eats to the Lord; you see <char style="it">while eating these items </char>he’s giving thanksgiving to
        God; and the one who won’t eat <char style="it">everything</char> abstains from eating <char style="it">certain
        foods</char> to the Lord, and <char style="it">while not eating these items </char>he’s thanking God.<verse eid="ROM 14:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 14:7" />The fact of the matter is that not a one of us lives for himself, and not a one <char style="it">of us
        </char>dies for himself. <verse eid="ROM 14:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 14:8" />If we so happen to live, we live in the Lord; and if we so happen to die, we die in the Lord. And so,
        if we so happen to live and so happen to die, we are of the Lord (i.e., we are a part of, are derived
        from, the Lord). <verse eid="ROM 14:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 14:9" />You see, Christ died and came back to life again<char style="sup">[c]</char> to arrive at this point:
        in order to assume lordship over both <char style="it">the</char> dead and <char style="it">the</char>
        living.<verse eid="ROM 14:9" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 14:10" />Who <char style="it">do you think </char>you<char style="it"> </char>are,<char style="it"> </char>you
        who judges your fellow comrade<char style="sup">[d]</char>? Or <char style="it">I can</char> also say,
        who <char style="it">do you think</char> you are to despise your comrade? You see, we’ll all have to
        stand in the courtroom before God the judge, <verse eid="ROM 14:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 14:11" />seeing that it’s written:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 14:11"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 14:11">“<char style="it">As surely as </char>I live,” says the Lord, “<char style="it">I swear</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 14:11">That everyone <char style="it">willingly or not</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 14:11">Will be on their knees before Me <char style="it">paying homage,</char></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 14:11">And <char style="it">that</char> every tongue will confess out loud</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 14:11"><char style="it">In homage </char>to God.”<verse eid="ROM 14:11"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 14:12" />So then each of you will deliver a <char style="it">written </char>report<char style="sup">[e]</char>
        to God concerning himself <char style="it">while he stands before Him in judgment, and God will go over
        that report with him</char>.<verse eid="ROM 14:12" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 14:13" />So no longer judge one another, but become all the more determined to not do something in particular
        that your fellow comrade believes is sinful or that causes your fellow comrade to regress into sin<char
        style="sup">[f]</char>— <verse eid="ROM 14:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 14:14" />I know for a fact and have reached the point where I’m persuaded in the Lord Jesus that nothing <char
        style="it">I’ve written about here </char>is forbidden to partake of, participant in, or consume<char
        style="sup">[A]</char> in <char style="it">and of</char> itself, except by someone who reckons that it’s
        forbidden—to that person, it’s forbidden. <verse eid="ROM 14:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 14:15" />In fact, if your comrade is being hurt <char style="it">by you </char>because of food, you’re no longer
        walking in love. Don’t destroy he whom Christ died for with your food <char style="it">convictions</char>.<verse eid="ROM 14:15" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 14:16" />So don’t let your good <char style="it">behavior </char>be spoken of disparagingly. <verse eid="ROM 14:16" />
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 14:17" />The kingdom of God (i.e., God’s involvement with mankind) does not <char style="it">chiefly concern itself
        with </char>food and drink<char style="sup">[g]</char> you see, but rather <char style="it">with </char>righteousness,
        peace, and joy in the Holy Spirit. <verse eid="ROM 14:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 14:18" />In fact, the one who’s serving—slaving away—in Christ in <char style="it">doing</char> this is well-pleasing
        to God and spoken well of by the people around him<char style="sup">[h]</char>. <verse eid="ROM 14:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 14:19" />So then pursue those things pertaining to peace and to each other’s edification. <verse eid="ROM 14:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 14:20" />Don’t dismantle the work of God because of an issue over food. Yes, all <char style="it">foods</char>
        can be consumed<char style="sup">[i]</char>, but’s it’s wrong for the person who sees <char style="it">a
        particular food</char> as an item of temptation and as something that is sinful to eat<char style="sup">[j]</char>.<verse eid="ROM 14:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 14:21" />The practice of not eating meat, drinking wine, or indulging in something which your fellow comrade believes
        to be sinful is laudable. <verse eid="ROM 14:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 14:22" />Keep your personal beliefs between you and God. Blessed is he who’s not having to decide for himself
        one way or the other <char style="it">in the moment </char>what he’s OK with. <verse eid="ROM 14:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 14:23" />But he who’s weighing point and counterpoint deciding if he’d chance eating <char style="it">some food
        </char>has already reached the point where he’s condemned (i.e., objectively guilty of wrong-doing),
        since that’s not a product of faith. Anything which is not a product of faith is a sin.<verse eid="ROM 14:23" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">struggling</char>…Lit: <char style="it">weak</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">able to pick him up off the ground and stand him to his feet</char>…Lit: <char style="it">to
        stand</char>. The interpolation is suggested by the aorist tense of the infinitive <char style="it">stand.</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">came back to life again</char>…Lit: <char style="it">lived</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">fellow comrade</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brother</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">deliver a written report</char>…Lit: <char style="it">give a word</char>. The interpolation
        <char style="it">written </char>is implied by the use of the Gk. word <char style="it">logos </char><char
        style="w" strong="G03056">λόγος</char>)instead of <char style="it">rhema </char><char style="w" strong="G04487">ῥῆμα</char>)<char
        style="it">.</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">something in particular that your comrade believes is sinful or that causes your comrade
        to regress into sin</char>…Lit: <char style="it">place an occasion for stumbling to the brother or a
        stumbling block</char>. Ref. note of Matt. 18:6.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">does not chiefly concern itself with food and drink</char>…Lit: <char style="it">is
        not food and drink</char>. The Gk. words for <char style="it">food</char> and <char style="it">drink</char>
        (<char style="it">brōsis</char> and <char style="it">posis, </char><char style="w" strong="G01035">βρῶσις</char>),
        <char style="w" strong="G04213">πόσις</char>)) rhyme, making them a figure of speech (alliteration/assonance).</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">spoken well of by the people around him</char>…Lit: <char style="it">approved by men</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">can be consumed</char>…Lit<char style="it">: are clean</char>. This is the opposite
        of <char style="it">unclean </char>used in v. 14.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the person who sees a particular food as a source of temptation and something that is
        sinful to eat</char>…Lit: <char style="it">the man who eats on account of an occasion for stumbling</char>.
        <char style="it">Occasion for stumbling</char> is the same word used in v. 13; ref. note there, and ultimately
        Matt. 18:6. Also, the interpolations <char style="it">a particular food </char>and <char style="it">that
        food </char>are simple inferences, as without them, Paul would be permitting everything.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">nothing I’ve written about here is forbidden to partake of, participant in, or consume</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">nothing</char> [<char style="it">is</char>] <char style="it">unclean</char>. The word
        <char style="it">unclean </char>is the Gk. word <char style="it">koinos </char><char style="w" strong="G02839">κοινός</char>)<char
        style="it">, </char>which, incidentally, is also the root from which we get the word <char style="it">fellowship.
        </char>Ref. Acts 10:14 with regard to <char style="it">koinos.</char></char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="ROM 14" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 15   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="ROM 15" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 15:1" />We who are capable ought to bear the struggles<char style="sup">[a]</char> of those who are incapable
        and not <char style="it">just </char>please ourselves (i.e., not just make ourselves happy). <verse eid="ROM 15:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 15:2" />Let each of us please the neighbor <char style="it">at hand </char>for his betterment. <verse eid="ROM 15:2" />
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 15:3" />You see, Christ didn’t go around pleasing himself either, but <char style="it">led a life</char> according
        to this verse instead:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:3"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:3">The reproaches of those who reproach You fell upon me<verse eid="ROM 15:3"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 15:4" />To this point, all the many things which were written <char style="it">in the</char> <char style="it">Old
        Testament</char> were put there ahead of time for our instruction, so that we would have hope through
        the endurance (i.e., never-failing consistency and persistency in spite of all things to the contrary—in
        this case, the consistency and persistency of the Old Testament’s themes) and through the advice, encouragement,
        and guidance of the Scriptures. <verse eid="ROM 15:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 15:5" />May the God of endurance and of advice, encouragement, and guidance grant that you think along the same
        lines <char style="it">while </char>among one another <char style="it">in a way which is </char>consistent
        with Christ Jesus, <verse eid="ROM 15:5" />
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 15:6" />so that speaking the same thing in unison<char style="sup">[b]</char> you would glorify the God and Father
        of our Lord Jesus Christ.<verse eid="ROM 15:6" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 15:7" />Therefore take each other into your circles<char style="sup">[c]</char>, just as, to God’s glory, Christ
        also took us in. <verse eid="ROM 15:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 15:8" />In fact, I’m saying that Christ has <char style="it">already</char> become a minister of circumcision
        (i.e., a minister to those following the Law of Moses) on behalf of the truth of God arriving at a place
        where he proved that the promises of the patriarchs are reliable, <verse eid="ROM 15:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 15:9" />but <char style="it">became a servant to </char>the Gentiles on behalf of mercies which glorified God,
        as it’s written:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:9"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:9">On account of this, <char style="it">while </char>among Gentiles</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:9">I will confess <char style="it">praises </char>to<char style="it"> </char>You out loud,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:9">And I’ll sing as one authorized by You to do so<char style="sup">[d]</char><verse eid="ROM 15:9"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 15:10" />And another <char style="it">verse</char> says:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:10"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:10">Rejoice, Gentiles, with His folk-people<verse eid="ROM 15:10"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 15:11" />And another:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:11"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:11">All you Gentiles praise the Lord,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:11">And have all the folk-people praise Him<verse eid="ROM 15:11"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="m">
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 15:12" />And another verse from Isaiah says:</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:12"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:12">There’ll be a root <char style="it">planted </char>from out of<char style="it"> David’s father </char>Jesse,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:12">And the offshoot <char style="it">produced from it will be </char>ruling Gentiles.</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:12">The Gentiles will <char style="it">set their </char>hope upon it.<verse eid="ROM 15:12"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 15:13" />Would that the God of hope fill you with every kind of joy and peace imaginable<char style="sup">[e]</char>
        in the Faith to the point of you overflowing in the hope—in the power—of the Holy Spirit.<verse eid="ROM 15:13" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 15:14" />Concerning you, I’ve been convinced, my <char style="it">dear fellow </char>comrades<char style="sup">[f]</char>—even
        I personally <char style="it">have been</char>—that you—yes, you—are full of goodness, having reached
        a point where you’re filled with knowledge of all sorts <char style="it">and are</char> able to admonish
        one another too. <verse eid="ROM 15:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 15:15" />But occasionally I didn’t hold back any punches when I wrote to you, as I would remind you through the
        God-given grace that was given to me <verse eid="ROM 15:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 15:16" />for me to be a minister of Christ Jesus to the Gentiles, treating <char style="it">my</char> <char style="it">ministry
        of </char>the good news, the Gospel, of God as a holy, priestly duty, in order that the sacrificial offering
        <char style="it">so to speak </char>of the Gentiles would become <char style="it">something </char>acceptable,
        being made holy by the Holy Spirit.<verse eid="ROM 15:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 15:17" />I have something I’m excited to tell you about<char style="sup">[g]</char>, something that has to do
        with the things of<char style="sup">[h]</char> God in Christ Jesus. <verse eid="ROM 15:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 15:18" />You see, I dare not talk about something which Christ didn’t accomplish through me towards the goal of
        the Gentile’s obedience in word and deed, <verse eid="ROM 15:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 15:19" /><char style="it">accomplished </char>by the <char style="it">supernatural</char> power of the miraculous<char
        style="sup">[i]</char>, <char style="it">that is </char>by the <char style="it">supernatural </char>power
        of the Spirit of God, so much so that the fulfillment of the spreading of the good news of Christ <char
        style="it">took </char>me from Jerusalem and its surrounding area all the way to Illyricum, <verse eid="ROM 15:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 15:20" />but <char style="it">took me </char>in such a way <char style="it">as to travel from Jerusalem to Illyricum</char>
        <char style="it">with</char> the aspiration of evangelizing in places where nobody knows for certain
        what Christ is all about<char style="sup">[j]</char>, in order that I not build a building upon someone
        else’s foundation, <verse eid="ROM 15:20" />
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 15:21" />but instead that <char style="it">the evangelization would be </char>according to what<char style="it">
        </char>was<char style="it"> </char>written <char style="it">in the Old Testament</char>,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:21"></para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:21">The announcement about Him will be</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:21">To those who haven’t seen Him,</para>
    <para style="pi" vid="ROM 15:21">And they who haven’t heard will understand<verse eid="ROM 15:21"/>
    </para>
    <para style="pi" />    <!-- Spacer line. No verse associated with it. -->
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 15:22" />For reasons which are obvious, there’ve been so many obstacles in getting to go and visit you, <verse eid="ROM 15:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 15:23" />but as things stand now I no longer have any options left<char style="sup">[k]</char> in these regions
        and have been having a desire for a good many years now to go visit you, <verse eid="ROM 15:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 15:24" />as I might walk to Spain. Specifically, while walking through <char style="it">that part of the empire,</char>
        I hope to see you up close and have you send me on my way from there <char style="it">refreshed, resupplied,
        and ready for the journey</char>, if I <char style="it">could </char>first of all <char style="it">ask
        you </char>to take care of some of my provisions. <verse eid="ROM 15:24" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 15:25" />But I’m going to Jerusalem now <char style="it">in my</char> serving the saints, our fellow-believers.<verse eid="ROM 15:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 15:26" />The fact of the matter is that Macedonia and Achaia have been enthusiastic about making a tangible contribution
        to the saints in Jerusalem who are poor. <verse eid="ROM 15:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 15:27" />They have been enthusiastic, you see, and are indebted to them: for if <char style="it">the believers
        in Jerusalem</char> made tangible contributions to the Gentiles by means of their Holy Spirit-generated
        gifts, ministries, and manifestations of the Holy Spirit<char style="sup">[l]</char>, <char style="it">the
        Gentiles</char> too ought to serve them in the form of offerings made by means of their own physical
        abilities. <verse eid="ROM 15:27" />
      <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 15:28" />So now that I’m finished with this <char style="it">offering</char>, signed, sealed, and delivered,<char
        style="sup">[m]</char> I’ll depart and cross through your area on my way to Spain. <verse eid="ROM 15:28" />
      <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 15:29" />I know for a fact that I’m headed your way, going in the fullness of the blessings of Christ.<verse eid="ROM 15:29" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ROM 15:30" />I beseech you, comrades, through our Lord Jesus Christ and through the love of the Spirit, <char style="it">for
        you </char>to come together and help me out in your prayers to God for me, <verse eid="ROM 15:30" />
      <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ROM 15:31" />so that I’d be protected from and delivered out of the disobedience and incredulity <char style="it">pervasive
        </char>among the Judeans, and that my ministry inside of Jerusalem would be accepted by the saints <char
        style="it">there</char>, <verse eid="ROM 15:31" />
      <verse number="32" style="v" sid="ROM 15:32" />so that I could head your way with joy through the will of God to take some time off and relax when you
        and I are together. <verse eid="ROM 15:32" />
      <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ROM 15:33" /><char style="it">May</char> the God of peace <char style="it">be </char>with you all. So be it.<char
        style="sup">[n]</char><verse eid="ROM 15:33" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">struggles</char>…Lit: <char style="it">weaknesses</char>. Ref. 14:1.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">speaking the same thing in unison…Lit: in one accord with one mouth</char>. <char style="it">Mouth
        </char>is a synecdoche.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">take each other into your circles</char>…Lit: <char style="it">receive to yourselves</char>
        [<char style="it">accept</char>] <char style="it">one another</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">sing as one authorized by You to do so</char>…Lit: <char style="it">sing in Your name</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">every kind of joy and peace imaginable</char>…Lit: <char style="it">of all joy and peace</char>.
        A figure of speech.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">comrades</char>…Lit: <char style="it">brothers</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">I have something I’m excited to tell you about</char>…Lit: <char style="it">I have a
        bragging-point</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">of</char>…Lit: <char style="it">with</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">the supernatural power of the miraculous</char>…Lit: [<char style="it">the</char>]<char
        style="it">power of signs and wonders</char>. Signs and wonders is a biblical expression.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[j]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[j]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">nobody knows for certain what Christ is all about</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Christ
        was not named</char>. Note that <char style="it">being</char> <char style="it">named </char>refers to
        knowing one’s reputation.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[k]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[k]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">any options left</char>…Also: <char style="it">opportunities</char>…Lit: <char style="it">a
        place</char>. Usage for the word <char style="it">place </char>is same as in Eph. 4:27.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[l]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[l]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">their Holy Spirit-generated gifts, ministries, and manifestations of the Holy Spirit</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">their spirituals</char>. Same Gk. word <char style="it">spirituals </char>used in 1
        Cor. 12:1; ref. note there.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[m]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[m]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">So now that I’m finished with this offering, signed, sealed, and delivered</char>…Lit:
        <char style="it">So having done this and having sealed to them this fruit</char>. The phrase <char style="it">having
        sealed to them this fruit</char> appears to be a metaphor, an expression, or something along those lines.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[n]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[n]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">So be it</char>…Lit: <char style="it">Amen. </char>Ref. note of Rev. 19:4.</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="ROM 15" />
  <!--   **********   -->
  <!--   Chapter 16   -->
  <!--   **********   -->
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="ROM 16" />
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 16:1" />I endorse our sister-comrade<char style="sup">[a]</char> Phoebe, who’s in charge of an area of ministry<char
        style="sup">[b]</char> at the church in Cenchreae, <verse eid="ROM 16:1" />
      <verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 16:2" /><char style="it">endorsing her </char>so that you’ll make her a part of your inner circle in the Lord,
        as she’s earned respect among her fellow-believers the saints<char style="sup">[c]</char>. Extend a helping-hand
        to her in whatever ways she needs; she’s been a great help to many people—including me—you see.<verse eid="ROM 16:2" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 16:3" />Say hello to Priscilla and Aquila for me, my coworkers in Christ Jesus, <verse eid="ROM 16:3" />
      <verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 16:4" />the very people who stuck their necks out for me, putting their life on the line—It’s not just me who’s
        thankful for them but all the Gentile churches are too. <verse eid="ROM 16:4" />
      <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 16:5" />Say hello to everyone who attends her house-church too.</para>
    <para style="p" vid="ROM 16:5">Say hello to my good friend Epenetus, who was the first one to receive Christ in the <char style="it">Roman
        </char>province of Asia. <verse eid="ROM 16:5"/>
      <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 16:6" />Say hello to Mary, who worked her tail off for you. <verse eid="ROM 16:6" />
      <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 16:7" />Say hello to my fellow-Israelis Andronicus and Junia, who did time in prison with me. They’re outstanding
        missionaries<char style="sup">[d]</char>, and they became <char style="it">believers </char>in Christ
        before I did. <verse eid="ROM 16:7" />
      <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 16:8" />Say hello to Ampliatus, my dear <char style="it">friend</char> in the Lord. <verse eid="ROM 16:8" />
      <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 16:9" />Say hello to Urbanus, our co-worker in Christ, and my dear friend Stachys. <verse eid="ROM 16:9" />
      <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 16:10" />Say hello to Apelles, who in Christ has withstood everything thrown at him. Say hello to Aristobulus’s
        household (i.e., his family and his household servants). <verse eid="ROM 16:10" />
      <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 16:11" />Say hello to Herodion, my distant relative. Say hello to those in the Narcissus‘s household who are in
        the Lord (i.e., who are Christians). <verse eid="ROM 16:11" />
      <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 16:12" />Say hello to Tryphena and Tryphosa, who work their tails off in the Lord. Say hello to my dear friend
        Persis, another woman who’s a hard worker in the Lord. <verse eid="ROM 16:12" />
      <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 16:13" />Say hello to Rufus, a person chosen in the Lord (i.e., a person who’s special or unusual in his relationship
        with the Lord), and to his mother—and who’s my mother too. <verse eid="ROM 16:13" />
      <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 16:14" />Say hello to Asyncritus, Phlegon, Hermes, Patrobas, Hermas and the comrades who hang out with them. <verse eid="ROM 16:14" />
      <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 16:15" />Say hello to Philologus, Julia, Nereus and his sister, and Olympas and all the saints who hang out with
        them. <verse eid="ROM 16:15" />
      <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 16:16" />Greet each other with a holy hug<char style="sup">[e]</char>. All the churches of Christ send their greetings.<verse eid="ROM 16:16" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 16:17" />Comrades, I beg you to keep an eye out for those who cause dissensions and cause problems by introducing
        specific items that oppose the instruction you’ve learned. Stay away from them; <verse eid="ROM 16:17" />
      <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 16:18" />you see, those sort of people don’t serve our Lord Christ, but <char style="it">serve </char>their own
        appetite<char style="sup">[f]</char> instead. By smooth, believable talk and by their positivity<char
        style="sup">[g]</char>, they deceive the hearts of the naive. <verse eid="ROM 16:18" />
      <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 16:19" />Your reputation for obedience has spread far and wide to where everyone has heard about it—I’m thrilled
        about you—but I want you to be wise to <char style="it">where</char> <char style="it">you do</char> the
        good, and innocent to <char style="it">where</char> <char style="it">you don’t do</char> the evil. <verse eid="ROM 16:19" />
      <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 16:20" />Soon now, the God of peace will crush Satan and subjugate him to you<char style="sup">[h]</char>. The
        grace of our Lord Jesus be with you.<verse eid="ROM 16:20" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 16:21" />My coworker Timothy sends his greetings to you, and so do my distant relatives Lucius, Jason, and Sosipater.<verse eid="ROM 16:21" />
      <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 16:22" />I, Tertius, who did the actual writing of this letter <char style="it">for Paul</char>, personally extend
        my greetings in the Lord. <verse eid="ROM 16:22" />
      <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 16:23" />Gaius, who’s outgoing and welcoming and who’s congenial to me and to the entire church, sends his greetings.
        The city treasurer Erastus and our comrade Quartus send you their greetings too. <verse eid="ROM 16:23" />
      <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 16:24" /><char style="sup">[A]</char><verse eid="ROM 16:24" />
    </para>
    <para style="p">
      <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 16:25" />Now to Him who is able to stand you up and keep you standing consistent with and in relation to<char
        style="it"> the teachings of</char> my Gospel, my good-news message of Jesus Christ, consistent with
        the revelation of the mystery which has been kept silent for ages and ages, <verse eid="ROM 16:25" />
      <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 16:26" />but has now been made manifest <char style="it">through the proclamation of the Gospel </char>and through
        the prophetic Scriptures by the command of the eternal God, with the goal of being made known to the
        Gentiles resulting in their obedience, the consequence of their faith, <verse eid="ROM 16:26" />
      <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 16:27" />to the One Wise God be glory through Jesus Christ forever. And with that I conclude<char style="sup">[i]</char>.<verse eid="ROM 16:27" />
    </para>
  <!--   .........   -->
  <!--   Footnotes   -->
  <!--   .........   -->
    <note caller="[a]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[a]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">sister-comrade</char>…Lit: <char style="it">sister</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[b]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[b]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">who’s in charge of an area of ministry</char>…Lit: <char style="it">deacon</char>. Ref.
        note of Acts 6:3.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[c]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[c]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">earned respect among her fellow-believers the saints</char>…Lit: <char style="it">worthy
        of the saints</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[d]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[d]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">outstanding missionaries</char>…Lit: <char style="it">outstanding among the apostles</char></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[e]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[e]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">holy hug</char>…Lit: <char style="it">holy kiss</char>. Liberties taken.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[f]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[f]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">appetite</char>…Lit: <char style="it">stomachs</char>. Both a synecdoche and a metaphor.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[g]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[g]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">positivity</char>…Also: <char style="it">flattery. </char>The Gk. word used here is
        the word usually rendered <char style="it">blessing</char>, and the root literally means <char style="it">well-speaking</char>.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[h]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[h]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">subjugate him to you</char>…Lit: <char style="it">under your feet</char>. A biblical
        expression.</char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[i]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[i]</char>
      <char style="ft"><char style="it">and with that I conclude</char>…Lit: <char style="it">amen. </char>Ref. note of Rev.
        19:4.</char>
      <char style="fp"></char>
    </note>
    <note caller="[A]" style="f">
      <char style="fk">[A]</char>
      <char style="ft">Verse 24 omitted from the best manuscripts</char>
    </note>
  <chapter eid="ROM 16" />
</usx>
